<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC3826980
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Progranulin Directly Binds to the CRD 2 and CRD3 of TNFR Extracellular Domains
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     We previously reported that PGRN directly bound to TNF receptors (TNFR) in vitro and in chondrocytes (Tang, et al,
     <em>
      Science
     </em>
     , 2011). Here we report that PGRN also associated with TNFR in splenocytes, and inhibited the binding of TNFα to immune cells. Proper folding of PGRN is essential for its binding to TNFR, as DTT treatment abolished its binding to TNFR. In contrast, the binding of PGRN to Sortilin was enhanced by DTT. Protein interaction assays with mutants of the TNFR extracellular domain demonstrated that CRD2 and CRD3 of TNFR are important for the interaction with PGRN, similar to the binding to TNFα. Taken together, these findings provide the molecular basis underlying PGRN/TNFR interaction and PGRN-mediated anti-inflammatory activity in various autoimmune diseases and conditions.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     PGRN, TNFα, TNFR, Sortilin, protein interaction
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Progranulin (PGRN) also known as granulin–epithelin precursor (GEP) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     1
    </xref>
    ], proepithelin (PEPI) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     2
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    ], acrogranin [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    ], and PC-cell derived growth factor (PCDGF) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    ], is a growth factor containing seven and half cysteine-rich granulin domains in the order of P–G–F–B–A–C–D–E, where A–G are full repeats and P is the half-motif [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ]. Progranulin has multiple biological functions including anti-inflammation and immune regulations [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN acts as a neurotrophic growth factor and stimulates neurite growth [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ]. Mutations of the
    <em>
     GRN
    </em>
    gene are known to lead to the development of frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     10
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN expression is elevated in activated microglia in many neurodegenerative diseases including Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, motor neuron disease, multiple sclerosis and Alzheimer’s disease [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     11
    </xref>
    –
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     14
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    Growing evidences indicate that PGRN plays its neuroprotective role through the modulation of neuroinflammation. PGRN-deficient mice have increased susceptibility to neuroinflammation and neuron loss following toxin–induced injury [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    ], whereas mice overexpressing PGRN exhibit a neuro-protective role by decreased pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-1β, IL-6, and TNFα, and increased anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 in glial cells [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN insufficiency in some autism patients results in reduced neurotropic support together with cumulative damage in association with dysregulated inflammation [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ]. Loss of function mutations in the
    <em>
     GRN
    </em>
    gene are related to pro-inflammatory cytokine dysregulation in FTLD patients [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     18
    </xref>
    ]. In addition, mutations in
    <em>
     GRN
    </em>
    are also associated with increased prevalence of specific and related autoimmune diseases, including inflammatory arthritis [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    ] [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    PGRN binding receptors and signaling in mediating its anti-inflammatory functions in neurons still remain elusive. Sortilin has been shown to bind to PGRN via its last three amino acid residues and mediate the endocytosis of PGRN in neurons [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     22
    </xref>
    ]. However, PGRN was found to bind to
    <em>
     Sort1
    </em>
    −/− neurons [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    ], and to regulate neuronal outgrowth independent of Sortilin [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     23
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN-mediated neurotrophic properties depend on the granulin E domain but do not require Sortilin binding [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     24
    </xref>
    ], which indicates that Sortilin is not the only neuronal PGRN receptor. Indeed, it was found that PGRN bound directly to TNFR, and inhibited the TNFα-mediated respiratory burst in neutrophils [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     25
    </xref>
    ] and inflammatory diseases in mice [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ], suggesting that PGRN/TNFR interactions may contribute to PGRN-mediated neuroinflammation. The importance of PGRN/TNFR interactions in regulating neuroinflammation was further supported by several recent reports. For instance, PGRN attenuated neuronal injury induced by cerebral ischemia-reperfusion through the suppression of neutrophil recruitment and inflammation [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN was found to directly inhibit
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-labeled TNF-α binding to the neutrophil surface, and in turn suppressed TNF-α induced neutrophil chemotaxis [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ]. Additionally, PGRN treatment inhibited the TNFa-induced expression of ICAM-1 in human brain microvascular endothelial cells [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ]. Furthermore, PGRN was also reported to suppress TNF-a-induced expression of ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 in a dose-dependent manner in human umbilical vein endothelial cells, and PGRN deficiency promotes inflammation in the aortas of ApoE KO mice [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    ], indicating that PGRN also plays a direct protective role in endothelial cells and could be a promising pharmacological target molecule in the treatment of cardiovascular diseases.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although it has been established that three middle regions (granulin F, A and C as well as linker regions involved) of PGRN, which are separated by other non-binding regions, are required for interacting with TNFR, the selection of appropriate reagents and experimental procedures was found to be important for demonstrating the sophisticated physical interaction of PGRN/TNFR. Application of improperly folded PGRN, a highly cysteine-rich protein with extensive tertiary structure known to be critically linked to function, and selection of inappropriate chips can lead to the failure to demonstrate interactions between PGRN and TNFR, as reflected in Chen’s paper [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     29
    </xref>
    ]. In this study, we extend the previous discovery by demonstrating that PGRN also interacts with TNFR in immune system cells, examine the effects of PGRN folding on its binding to receptors by comparing the binding of PGRN to TNFR and Sortilin under various conditions, and provide information for recapitulating the high-affinity binding of PGRN to TNFR. Importantly, we also dissect and identify the domains of TNFR responsible for binding to PGRN.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Materials and Methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Reagents
    </title>
    <p>
     Human TNFα biotinylated fluorokine Kit (Cat. No. NFTA0), human Sortilin (Cat. No. 3154-ST), and human rTNFα (Cat. No. 210-TA) were purchased from R&amp;D System. Human PGRN used in Surface Plasmon Resonance was purchased from Adipogen, San Diego, CA (Cat. No. AG-40A-0188). Recombinant human TNFR2 were purchased from Invitrogen (Cat. No. PHR3025). RIPA lysis buffer, Protein A/G agarose beads, and antibodies against PGRN (SC-28928) and TNFR2 (SC-7862) were ordered from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. Jurkat cell, T cell leukemia cell line, was purchased from ATCC.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Preparation of recombinant proteins
    </title>
    <p>
     PGRN from our lab was purified from conditioned medium of HEK-EBNA cells, which were stably transfected with human PGRN with C-terminal His-tags as described previously [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ]. Briefly, cells were cultured with serum-free medium for 3 days, and the medium was then collected for PGRN purification with the ProBond Purification System (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). The protein purity was determined with SDS-PAGE, and activity was measured with a TNFα blocking assay.
    </p>
    <p>
     Recombinant CRD2CRD3 domain of TNFR1 (R1/C2C3) and TNFR2 (R2/C2C3) were expressed as GST fusion proteins in corresponding expression plasmids based on pGEX-3X vectors in E. coli DH5α (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) under the induction of 0.25 mM IPTG. Fusion proteins were affinity-purified on glutathione-agarose beads as described previously [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ]. Factor Xa (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA) was used to release R1/C2C3 or R2/C2C3, respectively, from the fusion proteins. After digestion, the enzyme was removed with the Xa removal resin (Qiagen Valencia, CA).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Co-Immunoprecipitation (Co-IP)
    </title>
    <p>
     Mouse splenocytes were isolated, and treated with either PGRN (100ng/ml) or TNFα (100ng/ml) for 2 min or 10 min. The cells were lysed in modified RIPA lysis buffer containing 1 fold proteinase inhibitors, PMSF, and sodium orthovanadate (from Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Then cell lysates were briefly sonicated to further disrupt the membrane structure. 1 mg protein was used for immunoprecipitation for each sample. 2μg/ml of control IgG and 20μl of protein A/G beads were added into the cell lysis mixture to pre-clear the non-specific binding proteins. After centrifuging, 2μg/ml of control IgG or TNFR2 antibody was added to the supernatant respectively, and the mixture was incubated for 1 hour at 4 degree. Then 20 μl of protein A/G beads were added and incubated overnight. The beads were washed with lysis buffer for 6–8 times, and the protein complex was separated by SDS-PAGE. The presence of PGRN and TNFR2 was detected by probing with their respective antibodies.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Surface Plasmon Resonance (SPR)
    </title>
    <p>
     The Biacore experiments were conducted at the core facility of Tufts University on CM5 chip. The SensiQ experiments were performed by SensiQ Technologies, Inc., and both COOHV and COOH1 chips were used to measure the binding between TNFR with PGRN [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     SDS-PAGE and western blotting
    </title>
    <p>
     Protein samples from immunoprecipitation or from protein purifications were separated by SDS-PAGE. For protein purification, the gel was stained with Coomassie Blue for 30 min after electrophoresis, and de-stained for several hours so the target band could be visualized. For immunoprecipitation, the samples were transferred to a nylon membrane after electrophoresis. The membrane was probed with the primary antibody overnight at 4°C, and with the secondary antibody for 2 hours at room temperature. The bands were developed on the film using ECL Prime Western Blotting Detection Reagent (Amersham Pittsburgh, PA).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     TNFα blocking assay
    </title>
    <p>
     This experiment mainly followed the protocol of the manufacturer (Cat. No. NFTA0 R&amp;D System). Jurkat cells were suspended in 0.4% BSA PBS buffer. The cells were pre-treated with BSA or PGRN (1, 5, 10 μg) for 15 min. Biotinylated TNFα was added for 1 hour, then FITC-labeled streptavidin was added. In another tube, anti-TNFα antibody was added as a positive control for inhibition of TNFα binding. The staining was measured by flow cytometry at the NYU core facility.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Solid phase binding assay
    </title>
    <p>
     Various doses of PGRN or BSA were coated to an ELISA plate overnight. After blocking, biotin-labeled TNFR was added and the plate was incubated for 2 hours. Finally streptavidin-conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) was added and the binding between PGRN and TNFR2 was detected by incubation of the substrate of HRP. In other experiments plates were coated overnight with different doses of R1/C2C3 or R2/C2C3. Then biotin-labeled PGRN was added followed by HRP-conjugated streptavidin in the plate. The interactions between PGRN and R1/C2C3, or R2/C2C3 were detected as described above.
    </p>
    <p>
     In another experiment, plates were coated overnight with various doses of PGRN in PBS buffer in the presence or absence of 10mM DTT. After blocking, biotin-labeled TNFR2 or Sortilin was added to each well. The bound protein from the liquid phase was then detected by HRP-conjugated streptavidin.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     The yeast two-hybrid system
    </title>
    <p>
     Full-length pDB-TNFR1 and pDB-TNFR2 plasmids were used as templates to amplify fragments of the cysteine-rich domains (CRD). Every CRD and combination of CRDs of TNFR1 was produced and ligated to a pDB-leu vector with SalI and NotI. CRDs of TNFR2 went through the same procedure except that they were digested with NcoI and NotI. PGRN gene was cloned into the pPC86 vector. The same strategy was used as the discovery of PGRN-TNFR interaction, referred to as a modified yeast-two-hybrid (Y2H) system in previous reports [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ]. Positive interactions between the bait and prey protein couples were displayed as blue dots on the membrane.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     GST Pull-Down Assay
    </title>
    <p>
     GST-fusion proteins, R1/C2C3 and R2/C2C3, were conjugated to Glutathione-Sepharose beads, which were further incubated with purified PGRN at 4°C overnight. GST-conjugated beads were incubated with the same amount of PGRN as a control. Bound proteins were resolved by 10% SDS-PAGE and detected by western blotting with anti-PGRN antibody.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     PGRN binds to TNFR2 in splenocytes and inhibits the binding of TNFα to immune cells
    </title>
    <p>
     Our previous study found that PGRN bound to TNFR in chondrocytes and that the administration of PGRN could prevent TNFα-induced inflammatory arthritis [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
     ]. Attempting to apply our discovery to the immune system, we performed co-immunoprecipitation to study the interaction between PGRN and TNFR2 in splenocytes. Splenocytes were isolated from mice and treated with PGRN or TNFα for 2 and 10 minutes. The cell lysates were used in the immunoprecipitation with anti-TNFR2 antibody. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1A
     </xref>
     , PGRN and TNFR2 are detectable in the immunoprecipitated complexes from splenocytes, and the signaling was enhanced by PGRN and TNFα treatment. In addition, PGRN inhibited the binding of TNFα to Jurkat cells in a dose-dependent manner (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1B
     </xref>
     ). These results show that PGRN binds to TNFR and prevents TNFα binding to membrane receptors not only in chondrocytes [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ], but also in the immune system [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       PGRN interacts with TNFR in immune cells
      </strong>
      <p>
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       PGRN binds with TNFR2 in mouse splenocytes. Splenocytes were isolated from WT mouse and treated with PGRN (100 ng/ml) and TNFα. (100 ng/ml) for 2 min and 10 min, respectively. The cells were lysed and membrane was further broken by brief sonication. The TNFR2 antibody was used to precipitate TNFR2-associated proteins. The presence of PGRN and TNFR2 in the immunoprecipitated complex was examined using westernblotting with corresponding antibodies. Rabbit IgG (RIgG) serves as a negative control and is indicated.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       PGRN inhibits the binding of TNFα to cell surface in Jurkat cells. Jurkat cells, a T cell leukemia cell line, were pretreated with various amounts of PGRN, as indicated, followed by incubation with biotinylated-TNFα. The binding of biotinylated-TNFα to cells was examined with FACS.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Selection of appropriate chips in surface Plasmon resonance is important for demonstrating the binding of PGRN to TNFR
    </title>
    <p>
     We previously reported that PGRN from our lab binds to TNFR1 and TNFR2 with the K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     of 1.8 and 1.5 nM, respectively [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ]. This finding was confirmed by Atreaon Inc. through independently contracted services (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2A and C
     </xref>
     , TNFα binds to TNFR on COOH1 and COOHV chips in SensiQ methods. When tested on the COOH1 chip, the same chip used in our previous study [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ], PGRN from Adipogen shows high binding affinity to both TNFR1 and TNFR2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2D
     </xref>
     ). Consistent with our previous study [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ], PGRN shows selectively higher binding affinity to TNFR2 than to TNFR1. However, when switched to COOHV chip, PGRN fails to bind to TFNR (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2B
     </xref>
     ). These data were repeated in three individual experiments. Furthermore PGRN fails to bind to TNFR1 and TNFR2 in CM5 chips in Biacore, which is the same chip used in Chen’s study [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     ]. As summarized in
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     , the successful demonstration of the binding of PGRN to TNFR1 and TNFR2 in surface plasmon resonance is highly dependent upon the chips used.
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       PGRN binds to TNFR on COOH1 chip, but not on COOHV chip in SensiQ surface plasmon resonance assay
      </strong>
      <p>
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       TNF binds to TNFR1 (red line) and TNFR2 (blue line) in SensiQ COOHV chip.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       PGRN fails to bind to both TNFR1 (red line) and TNFR2 (blue line) on COOHV chip.
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       TNFα binds to TNFR1 (red line) and TNFR2 (blue line) on COOH1 chip.
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       PGRN from adipogen binds to both TNFR1 (red line) and TNFR2 on COOH1 (blue line) chip.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Summary of K
        <sub>
         D
        </sub>
        results from SPR
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Proper folding of PGRN is critical for its binding to TNFR, but not to Sortilin
    </title>
    <p>
     The Grn F, A, and C domains are required for PGRN to bind to TNFR [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ], whereas only the C-terminus of Grn E, particularly the last three amino acids QLL, is required for the binding of [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      22
     </xref>
     ]. We hypothesize that the binding of PGRN to TNFR requires proper folding of PGRN so that all three regions required for TNFR binding can form a trimer-like structure and are accessible to TNFR. To test this hypothesis, PGRN was pretreated with 10mM DTT, which is known to disturb the formation of disulfide bonds in PGRN and in turn affects its folding, and then the binding of PGRN to TNFR2 and Sortilin were measured using solid phase binding. DTT treatment completely abolished the binding of PGRN to TNFR2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     ). In marked contrast, the binding of PGRN to Sortilin was significantly enhanced by DTT treatment (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3B
     </xref>
     ). This result clearly shows that proper folding and conformation of PGRN are required for binding to TNFR, but not to Sortilin. Thus, use of Sortilin binding activity to validate the biological and TNFR-binding activities of PGRN, as in Chen’s paper [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     ], is inappropriate.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       DTT treatment of PGRN abolishes its binding to TNFR, whereas enhances its binding to Sortilin
      </strong>
      <p>
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       Schematic diagram of PGRN structure and its domain/motifs required for binding to TNFR and Sortilin.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       DTT treatment disrupts the direct binding between PGRN and TNFR2. PGRN from our lab was pretreated with or without 10 mM DTT, and various amounts of PGRN, as indicated, were coated on the plate. Binding to TNFR2 was measured as described above.
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       DTT treatment enhances the binding of PGRN to Sortilin. Similar to Fig. 3B, same dosages of PGRN from our lab were pretreated with or without 10mM DTT, the binding to Sortilin was measured.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     CRD2 and CRD3 of TNFR are responsible for the binding of PGRN
    </title>
    <p>
     We reported that three middle regions (granulin F, A and C as well as linker regions involved) of PGRN are required for interaction with TNFR [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ]. However it was still unclear which domain(s) of TNFR are responsible for binding to PGRN. The extracellular domains of both TNFR1 and TNFR2 contain the similar structure of four cysteine-rich domains (CRD), including the well-organized CRD1, CRD2, and CRD3 domains and the less regular CRD4 domain, which is head-to-tail ligated with little overlap [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      31
     </xref>
     ]. To identify the domains of TNFR important for PGRN binding, we generated various combinations of CRD1-4 domains of both TNFR1 and TNFR2. The interactions between PGRN and CRD1-4 domains of TNFR1 and TNFR2 were tested in yeast two hybrid systems as reported previously [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
     ]. As expected, PGRN showed clear binding affinity for CRD1-4 of TNFR1 extracellular domain. Both CRD1-4 and CRD1-3 of TNFR1 showed strong binding to PGRN, and the binding was completely lost after further deletion of the CRD3 domain of TNFR1, indicating that the CRD3 domain of TNFR1 is essential for binding to PGRN. Single CRD3 domain only exhibited weak binding, and CRD2 and CRD3 domain (C2C3) displayed comparable binding with PGRN as the full-length extracellular domain of TNFR1 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4A
     </xref>
     ). This result revealed that in the interaction between PGRN and TNFR1, the CRD3 domain of TNFR1 was the determinant for the binding, whereas CRD2 played an important role in enhancing this binding to a substantial degree.
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       CRD2 and CRD3 domains of TNFR are important for binding to PGRN
      </strong>
      <p>
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       PGRN binds with CRD2 and CRD3 domains of TNFR1 in yeast two-hybrid system. Different combinations of TNFR1 CRD domains were generated on the left, and their binding to PGRN was detected by X-gal activity as shown on the right.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       PGRN binds to CRD2 and CRD3 domains of TNFR2 in yeast two-hybrid system. Similar truncations of TNFR2 CRD domains were indicated on the left, and their binding to PGRN was detected by X-gal activity as shown on the right.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Similar to TNFR1, the CRD3 domain of TNFR2 is also essential for binding to PGRN. However, unlike in TNFR1, CRD3 alone of TNFR2 showed strong binding to PGRN, and the CRD1-CRD2 also displayed weaker binding to PGRN (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4B
     </xref>
     ). This discrepancy may explain why PGRN shows higher binding affinity to TNFR2 than to TNFR1 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
    <p>
     CRD2 and CRD3 of TNFR are known to be required for binding TNFα [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      32
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      33
     </xref>
     ] , and yeast two hybrid (Y2H) system also demonstrated that they are important for binding PGRN. To further verify the binding discovered in Y2H, the GST-pull down assay was performed. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5A
     </xref>
     , PGRN was pulled-down by both GST-fused CRD2CRD3 domain of both TNFR1 and TNFR2, but not by GST control. To eliminate the potential effect by GST, GST moiety from GST-R1C2C3 and GST-R2/C2C3 was cleaved by Xa factor and the untagged CRD2 CRD3 of TNFR1 (R1/C2/D3) and TNFR2 (R2/C2C3) were purified. The direct binding to PGRN was measured by solid phase assay. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figs. 5B and 5C
     </xref>
     , both R1/C2C3 and R2/C2C3 proteins showed dose-dependent binding activity to PGRN.
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 5
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Direct Binding of PGRN to CRD2CRD3 of TNFR
       <em>
        in vitro
       </em>
      </strong>
      <p>
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       GST pull-down assay. GST (serves as a negative control) or GST fused CRD2CRD3 of TNFR1 (R1/C2C3) and TNFR2 (R2/C2C3) fusion protein immobilized on glutathione-Sepharose beads were incubated with recombinant PGRN. PGRN trapped was examined by immunoblotting with anti-PGRN antibodies
       <em>
        (left panel);
       </em>
       Coomassie blue staining shows that the comparable fusion proteins were used in this experiment (
       <em>
        right panel)
       </em>
       . GST (lane 1) and GST fused CRD2CRD3 of TNFR1 (lane 2) and CRD2CRD3 of TNFR2 (lane 3) are indicated with arrows as GST and C2C3, respectively.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       Recombinant CRD2CRD3 of TNFR1 (TNFR1/C2C3) binds to PGRN. Purified R1/C2C3 protein was obtained after cleavage of GST moiety, and was used to bind to PGRN in a solid phase assay as described above.
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       Recombinant CRD2CRD3 of TNFR2 (TNFR2/C2C3) binds to PGRN. Similar to R1/C2C3, R2/C2C3 were also obtained after removal of GST moiety, and further used in a solid phase binding assay.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    PGRN-mediated inhibition of TNFα activity has been well established [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     25
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     34
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     35
    </xref>
    ]. For instance, incubation of human neutrophils with PGRN diminishes the production of reactive oxygen species (i.e., the oxidative burst), which is triggered when cells are exposed to TNFα [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     25
    </xref>
    ]. Moreover, this effect of PGRN is enhanced by the presence of a serine protease inhibitor that protects PGRN from degradation. We reported previously that PGRN bound directly to TNFR and inhibited the binding of TNFα to TNFR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ], which is consistent with these earlier findings and provides a molecular basis underlying PGRN-mediated anti-TNFα activity. Recent experimental and epidemiological evidence from several laboratories also supports the importance of PGRN/TNFR interaction in inflammatory diseases and conditions. It was found that PGRN protected lung inflammation in vivo and the PGRN-mediated protective effect depended on PGRN/TNFR2 interaction [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     34
    </xref>
    ]. Enhanced neuroinflammation was observed in PGRN-deficient mice [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    ], whereas mice overexpressing PGRN exhibit neuroprotective role by decreased pro-inflammatory cytokines [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN was also reported to ameliorate ischemia-reperfusion induced neuronal injury, and this ameliorative effect resulted from the suppression of neutrophil recruitment and inflammation by PGRN [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ], since PGRN was found to directly inhibit the binding of TNF-α to the neutrophil surface, and in turn, to suppress TNF-α induced neutrophil chemotaxis. Additionally, PGRN also plays a protective role in atherosclerosis, as PGRN suppresses TNFa-induced expression of ICAM-1 and VCAM-1 in umbilical vein endothelial cells, and PGRN deficiency exacerbates inflammation and atherosclerosis[
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    ]. Furthermore, mutations in
    <em>
     GRN
    </em>
    were associated with an increased prevalence of specific and related autoimmune diseases, including inflammatory arthritis [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    ] [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    We have shown that PGRN associated with TNFR in chondrocytes and was therapeutic in inflammatory arthritis [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ]. In the present study we present further evidence in a Co-Immunoprecipitation (Co-IP) assay demonstrating that PGRN interacts with TNFR in immune cells as well. This finding provides the molecular and cellular mechanism by which PGRN mediates anti-inflammation in various kinds of autoimmune diseases, including rheumatoid arthritis. Although Co-IP assay is known to be an important tool for detecting the in vivo interactions of endogenous proteins, the procedure is technically challenging when handling low abundance membrane proteins. The key is the selection of an appropriate detergent to efficiently release the proteins from the lipid bilayer membrane without disturbing the protein complexes. Any inappropriate concentrations/procedures may lead to negative results. The inability to detect Co-IP of endogenous TNFR and PGRN in neuroblastoma was reported by Chen et al [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     29
    </xref>
    ], but it is unclear whether the TNFR complexes were extracted from the membrane successfully, as data validating the experimental approach was not shown, for instance, whether TNFR antibodies could precipitate the known components of TNFR complexes. Additionally, the abundance of the proteins of interest in the membrane is also important for successfully demonstrating the interactions. As shown in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1A
    </xref>
    , PGRN precipitated by anti-TNFR2 antibody was clearly enhanced when splenocytes were treated with either PGRN or TNFα, which are known to upregulate the expression of TNFR2 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     36
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    PGRN is a highly cysteine-rich glycoprotein, and contains numerous internal disulfide bonds, which are critical for maintaining the proper folding and conformation of this protein [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    ]. Tolkatchev [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     38
    </xref>
    ] showed that of the 7 ½ individual granulin domains that comprise PGRN, only granulins A, F and C contain well-defined three-dimensional structures consisting of a complex laddering of disulfide bonds. Importantly, our work also demonstrated that it is these same three granulin units – F, A and C, that are required for binding TNFR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ]. Proper folding of PGRN is critical for its binding to TNFR, as three middle granulin domains F, A, and C of PGRN are separated by other non-binding regions, and are required for interacting with TNFR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ]. Indeed, DTT treatment, which is known to disturb the formation of disulfide bonds and in turn affecting protein folding, completely abolished binding of PGRN to TNFR (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3
    </xref>
    ). In marked contrast, the binding of PGRN to Sortilin was actually enhanced by DTT treatment. This finding is probably due to the fact that the very last C-terminal three amino acids (QLL) of PGRN, known to be required for Sortilin binding [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     22
    </xref>
    ], are exposed in the unfolded PGRN and become more easily accessible to Sortilin. Thus, because the conformational requirements for the binding of PGRN to Sortilin are substantially less stringent than those for binding to TNFR, demonstration of binding to Sortilin is an inappropriate litmus test for documenting that the recombinant PGRN is properly folded and thereby capable of interacting with TNFR.
   </p>
   <p>
    Posttranslational modifications of PGRN, including glycosylation, could be another important factor affecting its binding to TNFR. PGRN is composed of 593 amino acids but displays an apparent molecular weight of approximately 90 kDa, which indicates that PGRN contains post-translational modifications, including glycosylation [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     39
    </xref>
    ]. PGRN is known to possess multiple N-glycosylation sites, and treatment of N-glycosidase F decreased the molecular weight of PGRN from 88kDa to 68 kDa [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    ]. Recombinant PGRN produced from a HEK-EBAN stable line and PGRN purchased from R&amp;D Systems exhibited a slight difference in gel mobility assay (data not shown), indicating that they may not contain the similar modifications and in turn conformation and TNFR binding activity accordingly. We reported earlier that some batches of PGRN purchased from R&amp;D Systems did not show clear binding affinity to TNFR in the solid phase binding assay [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. Variations in TNFR binding and biological activities among purification batches of PGRNs from various sources are quite similar to the discrepancy between different purifications of perlecan, a PGRN-binding glycoprotein [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     40
    </xref>
    ]. Perlecans purified from different cell types or the same cell type with different expression systems have been shown to have the potential for significant variation in glycosylation and function, and can vary dramatically in FGF receptor-based assays or in growth factor binding assays [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     41
    </xref>
    –
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     43
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    Surface plasmon resonance (SPR) assay is a widely used approach to demonstrate the direct interactions among macromolecules [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     44
    </xref>
    ]. The type of equipment and the selection of the chip are critical in general[
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     45
    </xref>
    ] as well as in the stoichiometry of TNF binding to TNFR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     46
    </xref>
    ], and also appear to be important for detecting the binding of PGRN to TNFR. We have reported previously the binding of PGRN from our lab to TNFR using the COOH1 chip, a planar PEG-based chip, at SensiQ [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ]; this finding has now been repeated with PGRN from Adipogen. However, no binding was observed using the COOHV chip, a 3D Dextran chip. In addition, CM5 chip in a Biacore (used in Chen’s paper [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     29
    </xref>
    ]) did not detect the binding of PGRN to TNFR, either. As described in the letter-to-editor concerning Chen’s paper [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     29
    </xref>
    ] (
    <a>
     http://www.jneurosci.org/content/33/21/9202/reply#jneuro_el_111445
    </a>
    ), the demonstration of delicate interactions of PGRN/TNFR with SPR is highly dependent upon the type of chip used as well as the source of the recombinant PGRNs, and changes of chips or sources of recombinant proteins, etc, may lead to negative results. Matrix coated on the chips, such as Dextran on COOHV chip, appears to interfere with binding of PGRN to TNFR1 and TNFR2, but does not affect the binding of TNFα to TNFR (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2
    </xref>
    ). Failure of the CM5 and COOHV chips may be also related to their high immobilization capacity, whereas low capacity is preferable for kinetic experiments (Biacore, Gedig, and Van der Merwe).
   </p>
   <p>
    The yeast two-hybrid system, followed by confirmation with GST pull-down and solid phase binding assays, revealed that PGRN interacted with the CRD2 and CRD3 of TNFR. The interaction between TNFα and TNFR has been reported to be via these same CRDs [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     32
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     33
    </xref>
    ]. CRD3 was the essential domain for the binding to PGRN, whereas CRD2 enhanced it to a large scale (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figs. 4
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). This finding is in accordance with the report that CRD3 is “an ideal candidate for binding specificity control” and serves as the determinant, whereas CRD2 plays a modulation function during interactions [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     47
    </xref>
    ]. Collectively, our results establish that CRD2 and CRD3 extracellular domains of TNFR are important for mediating the interactions between TNFR and PGRN. Dissection and identification of domains of TNFR responsible for PGRN binding provide the molecular basis underlying the PGRN/TNFR interaction and the PGRN-mediated anti-TNF activity in various kinds of diseases and conditions.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <sec>
    <sec>
     <table>
      <tbody>
       <tr>
        <td>
         PGRN
        </td>
        <td>
         progranulin
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         TNFR
        </td>
        <td>
         tumor-necrotizing factor receptor
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         CRD
        </td>
        <td>
         cysteine-rich domains
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         BMDM
        </td>
        <td>
         bone marrow-derived macrophages
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         SPR
        </td>
        <td>
         Surface plasmon resonance
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         FTLD
        </td>
        <td>
         frontotemporal lobar degeneration
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         Y2H
        </td>
        <td>
         yeast two-hybrid
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         HRP
        </td>
        <td>
         horseradish peroxidase
        </td>
       </tr>
      </tbody>
     </table>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>