<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.str.2006.09.014
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structural Insights into the Specific Binding of Huntingtin Proline-Rich Region with the SH3 and WW Domains
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Author Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      MOLNEURO
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      PROTEINS
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Huntington's disease (HD) is a dominant neurodegenerative disorder characterized by movement abnormalities, cognitive impairment, and psychiatric disturbances due to neuronal cell loss, especially in the basal ganglia and the cerebral cortex (
    <a>
     Martin and Gusella, 1986
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Vonsattel et al., 1985
    </a>
    ). Accumulating evidence supports the finding that a polyglutamine (polyQ) expansion tract in huntingtin (Htt), a ubiquitously expressed protein of yet unknown function, is the cause of this disease (
    <a>
     MacDonald et al., 1993
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     DiFiglia et al., 1995
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Human Htt is a large multidomain protein of 3144 amino acid residues with a polyQ domain at the N terminus (
    <a>
     MacDonald et al., 1993
    </a>
    ). The polyQ domain ranges from 11 to 34 glutamine residues in unaffected individuals, whereas that of HD patients extends to 37 or more glutamine residues (
    <a>
     Bates et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). A proline-rich region (PRR) containing 40 residues (normally residues 41–80) directly follows the polyQ domain in sequence (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The N-Terminal, Central, and C-Terminal Portions of Htt PRR Have Different ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (238 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Recently, many investigations revealed that mutant Htt with expanded polyQ impairs the normal interactions of several proteins involved in gene transcription, trafficking, endocytosis, and cell signaling (
    <a>
     Goehler et al., 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Harjes and Wanker, 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Li and Li, 2004
    </a>
    ). Thus, it is speculative that HD neuropathology is related to the interference of the normal function of cellular proteins by the aberrant Htt protein (
    <a>
     Landles and Bates, 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Li et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Li and Li, 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    There are many Htt-interacting partners identified; some contain Src homology 3 (SH3) or tryptophan (WW) domains, such as SH3GL3/endophilin3 (
    <a>
     Sittler et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), protein kinase C and casein kinase substrate in neurons 1 (PACSIN1/syndapin) (
    <a>
     Modregger et al., 2002
    </a>
    ), HYPA/FBP11 (
    <a>
     Faber et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), PSD-95 (
    <a>
     Sun et al., 2001
    </a>
    ), RasGAP (
    <a>
     Liu et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), and CA150 (
    <a>
     Holbert et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). Among them, SH3GL3 is reported to be preferentially expressed in human brain and testis, and its C-terminal SH3 domain is essential for the interaction with Htt PRR (
    <a>
     Sittler et al., 1998
    </a>
    ). The characteristics of the interaction between SH3GL3 and Htt and the colocalization of these two proteins suggest that SH3GL3 could be involved in the selective neuronal cell death in HD (
    <a>
     Sittler et al., 1998
    </a>
    ). SH3GL3 was also found to bind to the shell of the Htt body, suggesting that the SH3GL3-associated HD pathology may be caused by sequestering the Htt inclusion bodies (
    <a>
     Qin et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). PACSIN1 has been implicated in clathrin-mediated endocytosis (
    <a>
     DiProspero et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), and its abnormal binding behavior and altered intracellular distribution in pathological tissues suggest that it plays a role during the early stages of the selective neuropathology of HD (
    <a>
     DiProspero et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Modregger et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Human HYPA interacts with the N-terminal region of Htt protein through its tandem WW domains, as identified by yeast two-hybrid assay (
    <a>
     Faber et al., 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Passani et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). FBP11, the murine ortholog of human HYPA, is one of the several proteins that bind with formins involved in murine limb and kidney development (
    <a>
     Bedford, et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). FBP11 also participates in pre-mRNA splicing (
    <a>
     Lin et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) and regulation of N-WASP localization (
    <a>
     Mizutani et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The involvement of PRR in the pathological process of HD can also be observed from the fact that MW7 scFv, a monoclonal antibody recognizing Htt PRR, significantly inhibits aggregation as well as the cell death induced by mutant Htt protein (
    <a>
     Khoshnan et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Another observation indicates that removal of a series of prolines adjacent to the polyQ tract in Htt blocks formation of the shell of the Htt body and redistributes sequestration of many vesicle-associated proteins, a process that may be related to neuronal dysfunction (
    <a>
     Qin et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    The typical PRR segment recognized by SH3 or WW domains contains less than 10 amino acid residues (
    <a>
     Kay et al., 2000
    </a>
    ), and the molecular mechanism underlying the specific recognition has been elucidated and reviewed (
    <a>
     Ilsley et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Musacchio, 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sudol, 1996
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zarrinpar et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). However, many proteins, such as Htt, formin (
    <a>
     Bedford et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), and N-WASP (
    <a>
     Bompard and Caron, 2004
    </a>
    ), contain PRR far longer than 10 residues. How these long PRRs recognize various SH3 and WW domains remains largely unknown. Obtaining the structural knowledge of the interaction between Htt PRR and the SH3 or WW domain will be the first step toward understanding how the abnormally expanded polyQ tract interferes with the normal function of cellular proteins that contain the SH3 or WW domain.
   </p>
   <p>
    We have determined the solution structure of the SH3 domain of SH3GL3 and have assigned the backbone resonances of the WW domain pair of HYPA by heteronuclear NMR. Based on the structure, the binding specificities between Htt PRR and these domains have been elucidated in detail. This study reveals that Htt PRR recognizes the SH3 domain and the WW domain pair with high specificities, but with different mechanisms.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    The Three Portions of Htt PRR Have Different Preferences for the SH3 and WW Domains
   </title>
   <p>
    To identify which portion of the Htt PRR region (residues 41–80) is responsible for the interaction with the SH3 or WW domain, we subdivided the region into three peptide parts, corresponding to the N-terminal (Pept-1), central (Pept-2), and C-terminal (Pept-3) portions of Htt PRR, respectively (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). The three segmental sequences were cloned and expressed as GST fusion proteins for a pull-down assay.
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B suggests that SH3GL3-SH3 and PACSIN1-SH3 only bind to Pept-2, not to Pept-1 or Pept-3, while HYPA-WW1-2 (the tandem domains of HYPA) binds to Pept-1 and Pept-3, but not to Pept-2. This is consistent with the previous study that an expanded Pept-2 specifically binds with PACSIN1-SH3 (
    <a>
     Modregger et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). The results imply that the three portions of Htt PRR have different binding affinities for the SH3 domain of SH3GL3 or PACSIN1 and the tandem WW domains of HYPA.
   </p>
   <title>
    Solution Structure of the SH3GL3-SH3 Domain
   </title>
   <p>
    To study the interaction between SH3GL3-SH3 and Htt PRR in detail, we solved the structure of the SH3 domain in solution by heteronuclear multidimensional NMR techniques. A summary of the NMR experimental restraints for structure calculation and statistics is presented in
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    (see the
    <a>
     Supplemental Data
    </a>
    available with this article online). All ten of the lowest-energy final structures converge with an NOE or dihedral angle violation no greater than 0.3 Å or 5°, respectively. The average root-mean-square deviations (rmsds) for the ten structures for backbone and all heavy atoms are 0.64 and 1.76 Å, respectively.
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A depicts a superimposition of the ten lowest-energy structures and a ribbon representation of one of the ten NMR structures. The solution structure of SH3GL3-SH3 maintains a typical SH3 fold containing five β strands organized in an antiparallel β barrel structure with a short 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix between the last two β strands (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B). Similar to most SH3 fold domains (
    <a>
     Dalgarno et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), this structure also contains two characteristic loops, namely, the RT loop between β
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and β
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and the n-Src loop between β
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and β
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    . There is also a broad pocket called the specificity pocket between these two loops. The canonical PxxP-binding pocket is located on the hydrophobic patch that contains a cluster of conserved aromatic residues (Tyr10, Phe12, Trp38, and Tyr54) that are arranged adjacent each other in a nearly parallel manner.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="3D Solution Structure of the SH3 Domain from SH3GL3(A) Backbone atom ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (167 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Binding Specificity of SH3GL3-SH3 with Htt PRR
   </title>
   <p>
    To elucidate the binding specificity of SH3GL3-SH3 with Htt PRR, several truncated peptides of Htt PRR (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A) were tested for interaction with the SH3 domain by using the chemical shift perturbation method.
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    shows the chemical shift mapping on the SH3 domain upon binding with various peptides. The effects on some residues, such as Glu15 and Phe49, which have amide resonances largely affected by the addition of Pept-1 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A), Pept-2 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B), or Pept-3 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C), are very similar. The significant residues for these three titrations are mapped on the domain structure (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G), in which the significantly perturbed residues are located in the RT loop of the SH3 domain. The residues mostly affected by the addition of Pept-1-2 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D) cover the canonical PxxP-binding site and the specificity pocket between the RT loop and the n-Src loop of SH3GL3-SH3 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    H). Moreover, Pept-2-3 also exhibits similar binding properties with Pept-1-2 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    E and 3I), though it possesses a different peptide sequence. The result that the three nonapeptides, though having different sequences, bind to the SH3 domain with similar binding behavior suggests that their binding abilities may originate from prolines, but not from the nonproline residues. A similar result is also obtained from the binding of two double-portion peptides (Pept-1-2 and Pept-2-3). It is likely that Pept-1-2 and Pept-2-3 bind to the SH3 domain with similar binding sites, but with different orientations. In addition, binding of these short peptides, whether single portion or double portions, to the SH3 domain is relatively weak, whereas binding of Pept-2 to the SH3 domain is a little stronger than that of Pept-1 and Pept-3 (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). This may explain why only the binding of Pept-2 with the SH3 domain has been identified by the less sensitive experiment of pull-down assay (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B). These results are consistent with the studies that recognition of the SH3 domain by most short proline-rich peptides is moderately weak and poorly selective, and that the specificity pocket of the SH3 domain is favorable to proline-rich peptide recognition (
    <a>
     Santamaria et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). For this reason, we speculate that the binding of these short peptides to the SH3 domain is less specific, and that it is the proline residue that contributes to the binding.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Summary of the Chemical Shift Perturbations and Surface Mapping for Interactions ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (512 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    As for the full-length PRR (Pept-1-2-3), its binding causes perturbation on some additional residues, such as Lys23, Glu24, and Asp26 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    F), which reside on the opposite surface of the PxxP-binding pocket on the SH3GL3-SH3 domain. Thus, the binding sites on the domain structure cover the entire canonical PxxP-binding site and the specificity pocket and perhaps its opposite surface (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    J). The saturation curves for the chemical shift changes of three representative residues in <span id="7162977" source="intactdb" intactdbid="17161366" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="Q99963" type="participant">SH3GL3-SH3</span> upon titration with <span id="7162977" source="intactdb" intactdbid="17161366" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="P42858" type="participant">Pept-1-2-3</span> are well fitted with a 1:1 stoichiometry (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    K) and give a dissociation constant (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    ) of <span id="7162977" source="intactdb" intactdbid="17161366" annotator="elias" type="value">∼0.68</span><span id="7162977" source="intactdb" intactdbid="17161366" annotator="elias" type="unit">mM</span>. Mutation of Gln17 to Ala, which is located in the crucial RT loop, causes the binding ability to be reduced by ∼3-fold (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 2.2 mM). Taken together, the chemical shift perturbation experiments indicate that the entire Pept-1-2-3 is necessary for its specific binding to the SH3 domain. When it is shortened, it would loss its binding affinity (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ) and specificity (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    ). This binding specificity of Htt PRR for the SH3 domain might be required for regulating SH3-mediated interactions (
    <a>
     Li, 2005
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Orientation of Htt PRR Binding on the SH3 Domain
   </title>
   <p>
    A spin-labeling NMR method (
    <a>
     Mahoney et al., 2000
    </a>
    ) was applied to identify the orientation of Htt PRR binding on the surface of the SH3 domain. For ensuring that the binding sites on the SH3 domain are affected by the spin-labeled compound, we produced a pair of 22 residue peptides, which contain not only the entire central portion of Htt PRR, but also its several flanking amino acids (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A), that were spin labeled with MTSSL in either the N or C terminus. When the N-terminally labeled peptide Pept-22-N-MTSSL binds to the SH3 domain, two crosspeaks in the HSQC spectrum corresponding to Asp11 and Glu13 are nearly completely eliminated (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B), indicating that the N terminus of the peptide sterically contacts the SH3 domain near the Asp11 and Glu13 residues. As for Pept-22-C-MTSSL binding, many resonances, even including those of Asp11 and Glu13, are significantly affected by the spin label, but most of the residues are located in the proximity of the specificity pocket of the SH3 domain (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). This observation demonstrates that the C terminus of the peptide contacts the SH3 domain near the specificity pocket (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D). Taken together, these findings indicate that Htt PRR exhibits a preferred binding mode on the SH3 domain (also see
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    A), and that the orientation of PRR is consistent with that of the Class II SH3 ligand (
    <a>
     Mayer, 2001
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Effects of the Spin-Labeled Peptides on the Backbone Amide Resonances of the SH3 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (291 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Evidence for the Specific Binding from Intermolecular NOEs
   </title>
   <p>
    On the basis of filtered-NOESY analysis on the SH3GL3-SH3/Pept-1-2-3 complex (molar ratio of 1:1) (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A), several NOE peaks from 7 residues in the SH3 domain interacting with Pept-1-2-3 were unambiguously identified and assigned on the SH3 domain. Among the residues interacting with Pept-1-2-3 (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B), Gly8 and Asn53 are located in the typical PxxP-binding site, while Gln17 and Trp38 flank the specificity pocket. Surprisingly, the residues Cys6, Ile28, and Val59 have also been found to interact with Pept-1-2-3. These residues are located on a concave surface corresponding to the binding surface of Pex5p on the Pex13p-SH3 domain (
    <a>
     Douangamath et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kami et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). There is a possibility that the extended residues in Pept-1-2-3 also contact the opposite surface of the SH3 domain when it specifically binds to the PxxP-binding site and the specificity pocket.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Intermolecular NOEs of the SH3GL3-SH3/Pept-1-2-3 Complex(A) Selected portion of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (228 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Backbone Dynamics of the HYPA WW Domain Pair
   </title>
   <p>
    Since Htt PRR binds to the WW domain pair of HYPA, it will be interesting to study how Htt PRR interacts with this domain pair. The structure of the FBP11-WW1 domain has been elucidated (
    <a>
     Pires, et al., 2005
    </a>
    ), but that of WW2 and the domain orientation in the domain pair remain unsolved. To explore whether these small WW domains are orientationally flexible with respect to each other in the WW domain pair of HYPA, we determined the relaxation rates (R
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and R
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) and {
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H}-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N NOEs for the WW1-2 domain pair (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    ). Generally, large NOE values (&gt;0.7) reflect slow internal motion, whereas small values indicate substantial internal motion and negative values are indicative of fully disordered regions (
    <a>
     Bruschweiler, 2003
    </a>
    ). The average NOE value of WW1 (residues 13–42) is ∼0.52, suggesting that WW1 in the free state is marginally stable, which has been proved by the following titration experiments. WW2 (residues 54–83) is more poorly folded than WW1, as indicated by its smaller NOE values (an average of 0.45). Moreover, the single WW1 domain is structured, as the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N HSQC spectrum shows wide dispersion; however, the single WW2 is fully disordered, as indicated by severe line broadening and peak overlapping (data not shown). The linker region (residues 43–53) exhibits even faster internal motions than both domains, and the average NOE value is only 0.33. A similar result can also be obtained from the relaxation data of the R
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    :R
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    ratio (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    ). The different dynamics of WW1 and WW2 in the domain pair infers that they have different properties for binding with PRR-containing partners.
   </p>
   <title>
    Binding Specificity of the WW Domain Pair with Htt PRR
   </title>
   <p>
    To understand the binding properties of the HYPA WW domain pair with Htt PRR in detail, we studied binding of the three nonapeptides and Pept-1-2-3 from Htt PRR as well as peptide PPTPPPLPP from the PRR of formin (
    <a>
     Bedford et al., 1997
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pires et al., 2005
    </a>
    ) by using the chemical shift perturbation method. The plots of the chemical shift changes versus residue number of the WW domain pair upon titration of various peptides at a peptide:protein molar ratio of 8:1 are displayed in
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    . The addition of increasing amounts of the peptide ligand PPTPPPLPP results in chemical shift changes of a number of residues dispersed in both the WW1 and WW2 domains (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A). During titration, the amide resonances of some residues exhibit a little broadening in the line widths. This line broadening may be due to the chemical exchange at an intermediate time regime between the ligand-free and -bound states. Notably, the chemical shift changes for the residues in WW1 are in some aspects similar to those for the corresponding residues in WW2 at every titration point. This indicates that both WW domains have similar binding capabilities for peptide PPTPPPLPP. In other words, the two WW domains have no selectivity for the peptide from formin, which is consistent with the previous alanine-scanning mutagenesis analysis (
    <a>
     Bedford et al., 1997
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Chemical Shift Perturbation of the HYPA WW Domain Pair upon Titration of Various ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (359 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    As for the peptides from Htt PRR, titration of Pept-1 causes chemical shift changes of a number of residues in both domains, but more prominently in the WW1 domain (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B). During titration, the amide resonances in WW1 exhibits large chemical shift changes with slight line broadening, in contrast to the large broadenings observed for the corresponding resonances in WW2 (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A). In particular, some amide resonances in WW2, such as Ser61, Asp62, Tyr69, and Arg77, rapidly disappear from the spectrum at the first titration point and reappear at a peptide:protein ratio higher than 4:1. Titration of Pept-2 results in only small or no chemical shift changes of the residues in both domains, even at a Pept-2:WW1-2 ratio of 8:1 (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C). There is no substantial line broadening in any of the resonances either (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    B). This indicates that Pept-2 has no or very weak interaction with the WW1-2 domain pair, which is consistent with the result from the pull-down experiment (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B). Titration of Pept-3 also causes chemical shift changes of many residues in both domains (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D). During titration, some resonances in WW2, such as Ser61 and Tyr69, exhibit increased peak intensities (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    C), whereas the corresponding resonances (Ser20 and Tyr28) in WW1 show no intensity change. Interestingly, titration of Pept-1-2-3 causes significant chemical shift changes of many resonances in both domains (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    E). The resonances of these residues in both domains rapidly disappear from the spectrum at a peptide:protein ratio below 1:1 and reappear at a ratio higher than 4:1 (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    D). The intensities of these reappeared peaks at the last titration are significantly enhanced compared to the peaks in the ligand-free form. This indicates that binding of Pept-1-2-3 leads WW1-2, especially the WW2 part, to achieve a well-folded structure in the complex.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Summary of the Spectral Perturbations for Interactions between the HYPA WW ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (514 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Upon binding with Pept-1, a number of resonances (e.g., Thr16, Ser20, and Tyr28) in WW1 experience an intermediate chemical exchange on the NMR timescale, while the corresponding resonances undergo fast exchange upon binding with Pept-3 (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    A and 7C). As a rough approximation, tight binding might correlate with slow ligand exchange, and weak binding might correlate with fast exchange (
    <a>
     Fielding, 2003
    </a>
    ). Moreover, the chemical shift changes of WW1 caused by Pept-1 binding are large, in contrast to the small chemical shift changes caused by Pept-3 binding in each titration step (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    E). The titration curves of WW1 caused by Pept-1 binding show that the binding tends to reach saturation at a lower Pept-1 concentration than the concentration of Pept-3 in the curves of WW1 caused by Pept-3 binding. Collectively, these results demonstrate that Pept-1 binds to WW1 more tightly than Pept-3. Since WW2 is not as stable in the ligand-free state as WW1, which is indicated by the dynamics analysis (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    ), it is possible that WW2 undergoes conformational exchange on the NMR timescale even in the ligand-free state. Upon peptide binding, the chemical exchange between the ligand-bound and -free states makes it complicated to compare how WW2 binds to Pept-1 and Pept-3. Upon addition of Pept-1, a number of resonances in WW2 undergo chemical shift change and line broadening (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A). Some of them (e.g., Ser61 and Asp62) disappear and finally reappear at the later titrations; some (e.g., Tyr69 and Glu83) do not reappear even at the last titration point (peptide:protein ratio of 8:1). However, upon addition of Pept-3, the corresponding peaks in WW2 do not disappear, but their chemical shifts do change (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    C). Interestingly, the intensities of these peaks increase considerably upon binding. This indicates that, in contrast to Pept-1, a small amount of Pept-3 could transform WW2 from a relatively unstable state to the rather stable bound state. From this aspect, Pept-3 is a preferential ligand for WW2 binding. The titration curves for chemical shift changes of WW2 upon addition of Pept-2 or Pept-3 clearly indicate that WW2 preferentially binds to Pept-3, not Pept-2 (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F). Taken together, these findings show that WW2 in the ligand-free state is less stable than WW1 in the form of tandem domains. Pept-1 is preferential to WW1 binding, while Pept-3 is preferential to WW2 binding; however, Pept-2 has no or very weak binding capability for both WW1 and WW2. Thus, Pept-1-2-3 should exhibit a preferred binding mode on the HYPA WW domain pair (also see
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Schematic Representation of the Specific Interactions of Htt PRR with the SH3 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr8.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr8.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr8.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212606004035-gr8.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig8" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (89 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <title>
    Multiple Binding Sites of the SH3GL3-SH3 Domain
   </title>
   <p>
    Currently, three different ligand-binding sites on diverse SH3 domains have been identified. The first is the canonical PxxP-binding site that is constructed by the conserved aromatic residues. The second is the specificity pocket between the RT loop and the n-Src loop, such as the binding site of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    SH3(C) for the α-helical portion of the p47
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    tail peptide (
    <a>
     Kami et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). The third site, analogous to the binding site of Pex5p on the Pex13p-SH3 domain, is located on the opposite concave surface of the specificity pocket consisting of the β1 and β2 strands and the C terminus (
    <a>
     Barnett et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Douangamath et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kami et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Our data provide convincing evidence to support that Htt PRR specifically binds to the SH3 domain, and that the binding sites include the canonical PxxP-binding site and the specificity pocket (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    A). Since the PRR chain is much longer than the canonical SH3 ligands, it is likely that it can contact the SH3 domain on the third site, as indicated by the results of the intermolecular NOE experiment. The C terminus of PRR orients to the specificity pocket, whereas the N terminus orients to the PxxP-binding site, which is consistent with what is observed in the Class II SH3 ligand (
    <a>
     Mayer, 2001
    </a>
    ). This kind of binding mode may allow PRR motifs (generally in the PPII helix) to bind with various SH3 domains that are more diverse and selective.
   </p>
   <title>
    Characteristics of the Interaction of the HYPA WW Domain Pair
   </title>
   <p>
    Many proteins possess arrays of multiple WW domains; it is likely that the tandem WW domains cooperate with each other to achieve further specific recognition. To our knowledge, Htt PRR is the first example reported as a ligand for binding of the WW domain pair. The N-terminal portion of Htt PRR preferentially binds to WW1, while the C-terminal portion binds to WW2; however, the central portion remains unoccupied (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    B). Up to date, only two structures of the tandem WW domain pair, Prp40 (
    <a>
     Wiesner et al., 2002
    </a>
    ) and Su(dx) (
    <a>
     Fedoroff et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), have been solved. In the case of HYPA, both WW domains are marginally folded, as indicated by the wide dispersion of amide resonances in the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N HSQC spectrum. These domains, especially WW2, are not as stable as those in the ligand-bound states. The current study also provides insights into the dynamics and ligand recognition of the WW domain pair.
   </p>
   <title>
    Alteration of the Interactions Involving PRR Has Implications for the HD Pathology
   </title>
   <p>
    Since the aberrant interactions involved in Htt PRR and its SH3 domain- or WW domain-containing partners might be associated with the pathology of HD, it is interesting to know how the polyQ tract alters the normal interaction between Htt PRR and the SH3 or WW domain. Our current result showing that the N terminus of Htt PRR, occurring after the polyQ domain, is critical for binding to the SH3 domain and the WW domain pair implies that the specific interactions are susceptible to the length of the polyQ tract. In the Htt-interacting partners, all of the SH3 domain- or WW domain-containing partners, except PSD-95, bind more tightly to Htt with elongated polyQ stretch (
    <a>
     Li and Li, 2004
    </a>
    ). It is possible that the elongated polyQ stretch makes the entire PRR region more accessible to these SH3 domain- or WW domain-containing partners and thus enhances their binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    Since Htt PRR is proximal to the polyQ tract, it is likely that alteration of the interactions involving PRR is associated with the HD pathology. The expanded polyQ tract makes the PRR region more available to the WW-containing proteins or to MW7, a monoclonal antibody recognizing Htt PRR, and significantly inhibits aggregation as well as the cell death induced by the mutant Htt protein (
    <a>
     Khoshnan et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). In addition, removal of a series of prolines adjacent to the polyQ region in Htt blocks formation of the shell of the Htt body and redistributes the sequestration of many vesicle-associated proteins, a process that may be related to neuronal dysfunction (
    <a>
     Qin et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Considering that interactions involving Htt PRR are susceptible to polyQ length (
    <a>
     Feany and La Spada, 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Li et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Sugars and Rubinsztein, 2003
    </a>
    ), we speculate that the alteration of these specific interactions is one of the substantial causes for HD pathology.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Protein Expression and Purification
   </title>
   <p>
    The encoding sequence for the SH3GL3-SH3 domain, corresponding to residues 285–344 of SH3GL3, was amplified via PCR and was cloned into the pET-22b expression plasmid by using the NdeI/XhoI cloning sites. The SH3 sequence was renumbered from 285–344 to 1–60, which is hereinafter used for describing the SH3 domain. The plasmid was transformed into
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    BL21 (DE3). Cells harboring the plasmid were grown at 37°C. When OD
    <sub>
     600
    </sub>
    reached ∼0.6, SH3GL3-SH3 expression was induced by adding IPTG to a final concentration of 0.1 mM. The culture was then shaken for 10 hr at 25°C. After cell lysis, the protein was purified through a nickel-NTA column (QIAGEN), followed by a 16/40 Superose 12 column (Amersham Pharmacia).
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N- and
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N/
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C-labeled SH3GL3-SH3 proteins were prepared by using the M9 minimal medium containing
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    NH
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    Cl and/or
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -D-glucose as the sole nitrogen and/or carbon resource, respectively.
   </p>
   <p>
    The encoding sequence of the WW1-2 domain, corresponding to residues 136–224 of HYPA/FBP11, was amplified via PCR and was cloned into the pET-3a plasmid by using the NdeI/BamHI sites. The WW1-2 sequence was renumbered from 136–224 to 1–89, which is hereinafter used for describing the HYPA-WW1-2 domain. The plasmid was transformed into
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    BL21 (DE3). Cells containing the plasmid were grown at 37°C until an OD
    <sub>
     600
    </sub>
    of ∼0.8 was reached. Expression was induced by adding IPTG to a final concentration of 0.1 mM. The culture was then shaken for 10 hr at 25°C. The protein was purified sequentially by heat denaturation, ion-exchange chromatography on a Q-Sepharose Fast Flow column and gel filtration on a 16/60 Superdex 75 column (Amersham Pharmacia). The encoding sequences of the WW1 and WW2 domains, corresponding to residues 10–42 and 51–83 of WW1-2, respectively, were amplified via PCR and were cloned into the pGBTNH plasmid by using the BamHI/XhoI cloning sites (
    <a>
     Bao et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). The respective plasmid was transformed into
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    BL21 (DE3). Cells harboring each plasmid were grown at 37°C. When OD
    <sub>
     600
    </sub>
    reached ∼0.8, WW1 or WW2 expression was induced by adding IPTG. After cell lysis, the supernatant was loaded onto a nickel-NTA column (QIAGEN). After washing, followed by on-column thrombin cleavage for removing the GB1 tag, the protein was eluted and subjected to chromatography on a 16/40 Superose 12 column (Amersham Pharmacia).
   </p>
   <title>
    Synthesis of Proline-Rich Peptides
   </title>
   <p>
    The peptides (PPTPPPLPP, Pept-1, Pept-2, Pept-3, Pept-1-2, Pept-2-3, and Pept-1-2-3) were obtained from automatic solid-phase peptide synthesis on 2-Cl-Trt resin by using the FMOC strategy. The N-terminal amino group and the C-terminal carboxyl group of the peptides were retained unmodified. After release of the peptides from the resin by using AcOH/TFE/DCM, the peptides were purified by reverse-phase HPLC by following standard protocols involving a water/acetonitrile solvent system containing 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid. Pooled fractions of the pure peptides were lyophilized and analyzed by electrospray mass spectrometry to verify identity and homogeneity.
   </p>
   <title>
    Spin Labeling
   </title>
   <p>
    For producing the two peptides Pept-22-N and Pept-22-C, the genes encoding these peptides were chemically synthesized and inserted into pGBTNH vectors by using the BamHI/XhoI cloning sites (
    <a>
     Bao et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). Then, the cysteine-containing peptides were obtained according to the method for production of the WW1 and WW2 domains described above. To label the peptides with MTSSL ((1-oxyl-2,2,5,5-tetramethyl pyrroline-3-methyl)methanethiosulfonate, Toronto Research Chemicals, Canada), a 10-fold molar excess of MTSSL was added to each peptide in a 20 mM sodium phosphate buffer containing 50 mM NaCl (pH 8.0). The mixture was incubated for longer than 12 hr at 4°C, and the free compound was removed by size-exclusion chromatography. The resulting peptides were verified by mass spectrometry.
   </p>
   <title>
    GST Pull-Down Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    The generation of GST fusion proteins containing short peptides corresponding to the N-terminal, central, and C-terminal portions of Htt PRR was carried out as described previously (
    <a>
     Modregger et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). For pull-down assay, the GST fusion proteins were added to the glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (Amersham Biosciences) in a PBS buffer (10 mM sodium phosphate, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM dithiothreitol), and the suspension was agitated at 4°C for 30 min. The GST fusion protein-bound beads were washed three times in the same buffer to remove any unbound protein. An equimolar amount of SH3 or WW1-2 was added, and the suspension was agitated at 4°C for an additional 30 min. The resin was recovered by centrifugation, and, after excessive washing, the sample was resuspended in the sample buffer and subjected to SDS-PAGE in a 15% gel, followed by Coomassie staining.
   </p>
   <title>
    NMR Spectroscopy
   </title>
   <p>
    To solve the solution structure of the SH3GL3-SH3 domain, a
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N/
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C-labled sample containing ∼1 mM protein in a phosphate buffer (10 mM sodium phosphate, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM dithiothreitol, and 0.05% w/v sodium azide [pH 6.0] in 92% H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O/8% D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O or 100% D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O) was used for NMR experiments. All NMR data acquisition was carried out at 27°C on a Varian INOVA 600 spectrometer equipped with three RF channels and a triple-resonance pulsed-field gradient probe. The backbone and side chain
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H,
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N, and
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C resonances were assigned based on the spectra of 3D HNCO, HNCACB, CBCA(CO)NH, H(CCO)NH, C(CO)NH and 3D
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N TOCSY-HSQC, HCCH-TOCSY. NOE distance restraints for structure calculations were obtained from 3D
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-edited NOESY and
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C-edited NOESY (aliphatic
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C regions). Intermolecular NOEs between SH3GL3-SH3 and Pept-1-2-3 were obtained from 2D-filtered/edited NOESY experiments as described (
    <a>
     Peterson et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    For HYPA-WW1-2,
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N- or
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N/
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C-labeled sample containing ∼1 mM protein in a phosphate buffer (10 mM sodium phosphate, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM dithiothreitol, and 0.05% w/v sodium azide [pH 6.0] in 92% H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O/8% D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O or 100% D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O) was used for NMR experiments. The backbone resonances were assigned based on the spectra of 3D HNCO, HN(CA)CO, HNCACB, CBCA(CO)NH and 3D
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N TOCSY-HSQC,
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-edited NOESY.
   </p>
   <title>
    Structure Calculation and Analysis
   </title>
   <p>
    The NMRPipe software suite (
    <a>
     Delaglio et al., 1995
    </a>
    ) was applied to process the NMR data, and NMRView (
    <a>
     Johnson and Blevins, 1994
    </a>
    ) software packages were used for resonance peak picking and data analysis. The CNS program (
    <a>
     Brunger et al., 1998
    </a>
    ) with the ARIA module (
    <a>
     Nilges et al., 1997
    </a>
    ) was adopted to assign NOE peaks and to calculate structures. The protein structures were assessed by using PROCHECK (
    <a>
     Laskowski et al., 1996
    </a>
    ) and were displayed by the MOLMOL program (
    <a>
     Koradi et al., 1996
    </a>
    ). Hydrogen bond restraints (two per hydrogen bond) were generated by a combination of H/D exchange data, medium-range NOEs, and chemical shift index. Backbone dihedral angle restraints (ϕ and φ) were derived from the TALOS program (
    <a>
     Cornilescu et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). For SH3GL3-SH3, the restraints used for structural calculation are summarized in
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    . The structural calculation in combination with iterative NOE peak assignments was performed for 9 cycles, and a total of 200 structures were finally obtained. Ten structures of the lowest energies, which exhibit no NOE violation &gt; 0.3 Å and no dihedral violation &gt; 5°, were selected.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Determination of Backbone Relaxation Parameters
   </title>
   <p>
    All
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N relaxation data for WW1-2 were acquired at 25°C by using 2D proton-detected heteronuclear NMR experiments implementing the standard pulse sequences (
    <a>
     Farrow et al., 1994
    </a>
    ). A recycle delay of 1.5 s was used for measuring R
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and R
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    relaxation rates. The spectra for measuring the {
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H}-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N heteronuclear NOEs were recorded with a 2 s relaxation delay, followed by a 3 s period of proton saturation. In the absence of proton saturation, the spectra were recorded by a relaxation delay of 5 s. The relaxation rates, R
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and R
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , were obtained by fitting the measured peak intensities to a two-parameter function by using a nonlinear least-square fitting algorithm (
    <a>
     Press et al., 1992
    </a>
    ) and were presented as a ratio of R
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    to R
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    . The steady-state {
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H}-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N NOE enhancements were calculated as the ratio of peak intensity in spectra recorded with or without proton saturation.
   </p>
   <title>
    NMR Titration
   </title>
   <p>
    NMR titrations for SH3GL3-SH3 were performed at 27°C, and those for HYPA-WW1-2 were performed at 25°C.
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-labeled SH3 or WW1-2 was dissolved to a concentration of 0.25 mM in the above-mentioned NMR buffer, and the proline-rich peptides were added stepwise to give the peptide:protein molar ratios ranging from 0:1 to 8:1; each step was monitored by 2D
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H-
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N HSQC spectrum. The combined average chemical shift changes were calculated as Δδ
    <sub>
     ave
    </sub>
    = ([0.17Δδ
    <sub>
     N
    </sub>
    ]
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    + [Δδ
    <sub>
     H
    </sub>
    ]
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    )
    <sup>
     1/2
    </sup>
    , where Δδ
    <sub>
     H
    </sub>
    and Δδ
    <sub>
     N
    </sub>
    are the chemical shift changes in the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H and
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N dimensions, respectively. The titration curves were fitted assuming a bimolecular binding event as described (
    <a>
     Liu et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). Dissociation constants (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    ) were obtained by analyzing the chemical shift changes of three typical residues for SH3GL3-SH3 or its Q17A mutant upon addition of each peptide.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Two Tables and One Figure.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (260 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The coordinates and structure factors for SH3GL3-SH3 are available in the Protein Data Bank under ID code
    <a>
     2EW3
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bao et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.J. Bao, Y.G. Gao, Y.G. Chang, T.Y. Zhang, X.J. Lin, X.Z. Yan, H.Y. Hu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Highly efficient expression and purification system of small-size protein domains in
         <em>
          Escherichia coli
         </em>
         for biochemical characterization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Expr. Purif., 47 (2006), pp. 599–606
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Barnett et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Barnett, G. Bottger, A.T. Klein, H.F. Tabak, B. Distel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The peroxisomal membrane protein Pex13p shows a novel mode of SH3 interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 19 (2000), pp. 6382–6391
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bates et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Bates, P. Harper, L. Jones
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntington's Disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK (2002)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bedford et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.T. Bedford, D.C. Chan, P. Leder
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FBP WW domains and the Abl SH3 domain bind to a specific class of proline-rich ligands
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 16 (1997), pp. 2376–2383
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bompard and Caron, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Bompard, E. Caron
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of WASP/WAVE proteins: making a long story short
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 166 (2004), pp. 957–962
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brunger et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.T. Brunger, P.D. Adams, G.M. Clore, W.L. DeLano, P. Gros, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve, J.S. Jiang, J. Kuszewski, M. Nilges, N.S. Pannu,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystallography &amp; NMR system: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 54 (1998), pp. 905–921
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bruschweiler, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Bruschweiler
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New approaches to the dynamic interpretation and prediction of NMR relaxation data from proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol., 13 (2003), pp. 175–183
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cornilescu et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Cornilescu, F. Delaglio, A. Bax
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein backbone angle restraints from searching a database for chemical shift and sequence homology
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 13 (1999), pp. 289–302
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Dalgarno et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.C. Dalgarno, M.C. Botfield, R.J. Rickles
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3 domains and drug design: ligands, structure, and biological function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biopolymers, 43 (1997), pp. 383–400
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Delaglio et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Delaglio, S. Grzesiek, G.W. Vuister, G. Zhu, J. Pfeifer, A. Bax
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NMRPipe: a multidimensional spectral processing system based on UNIX pipes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 6 (1995), pp. 277–293
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         DiFiglia et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. DiFiglia, E. Sapp, K. Chase, C. Schwarz, A. Meloni, C. Young, E. Martin, J.P. Vonsattel, R. Carraway, S.A. Reeves,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin is a cytoplasmic protein associated with vesicles in human and rat brain neurons
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 14 (1995), pp. 1075–1081
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         DiProspero et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.A. DiProspero, E.Y. Chen, V. Charles, M. Plomann, J.H. Kordower, D.A. Tagle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Early changes in Huntington's disease patient brains involve alterations in cytoskeletal and synaptic elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Neurocytol., 33 (2004), pp. 517–533
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Douangamath et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Douangamath, F.V. Filipp, A.T. Klein, P. Barnett, P. Zou, T. Voorn-Brouwer, M.C. Vega, O.M. Mayans, M. Sattler, B. Distel, M. Wilmanns
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Topography for independent binding of α-helical and PPII-helical ligands to a peroxisomal SH3 domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 10 (2002), pp. 1007–1017
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Faber et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.W. Faber, G.T. Barnes, J. Srinidhi, J. Chen, J.F. Gusella, M.E. MacDonald
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin interacts with a family of WW domain proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hum. Mol. Genet., 7 (1998), pp. 1463–1474
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Farrow et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.A. Farrow, R. Muhandiram, A.U. Singer, S.M. Pascal, C.M. Kay, G. Gish, S.E. Shoelson, T. Pawson, J.D. Forman-Kay, L.E. Kay
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Backbone dynamics of a free and phosphopeptide-complexed Src homology 2 domain studied by 15N NMR relaxation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 33 (1994), pp. 5984–6003
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feany and La Spada, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.B. Feany, A.R. La Spada
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Polyglutamines stop traffic: axonal transport as a common target in neurodegenerative diseases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 40 (2003), pp. 1–2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fedoroff et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        O.Y. Fedoroff, S.A. Townson, A.P. Golovanov, M. Baron, J.M. Avis
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The structure and dynamics of tandem WW domains in a negative regulator of notch signaling, Suppressor of deltex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 34991–35000
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fielding, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Fielding
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NMR methods for the determination of protein-ligand dissociation constants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Top. Med. Chem., 3 (2003), pp. 39–53
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goehler et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Goehler, M. Lalowski, U. Stelzl, S. Waelter, M. Stroedicke, U. Worm, A. Droege, K.S. Lindenberg, M. Knoblich, C. Haenig,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A protein interaction network links GIT1, an enhancer of huntingtin aggregation, to Huntington's disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 15 (2004), pp. 853–865
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Harjes and Wanker, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Harjes, E.E. Wanker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The hunt for huntingtin function: interaction partners tell many different stories
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biochem. Sci., 28 (2003), pp. 425–433
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Holbert et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Holbert, I. Denghien, T. Kiechle, A. Rosenblatt, C. Wellington, M.R. Hayden, R.L. Margolis, C.A. Ross, J. Dausset, R.J. Ferrante, C. Neri
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Gln-Ala repeat transcriptional activator CA150 interacts with huntingtin: neuropathologic and genetic evidence for a role in Huntington's disease pathogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 98 (2001), pp. 1811–1816
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ilsley et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.L. Ilsley, M. Sudol, S.J. Winder
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The WW domain: linking cell signalling to the membrane cytoskeleton
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell. Signal., 14 (2002), pp. 183–189
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Johnson and Blevins, 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.A. Johnson, R.A. Blevins
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NMRView: a computer program for the visualization and analysis of NMR data
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 4 (1994), pp. 603–614
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kami et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Kami, R. Takeya, H. Sumimoto, D. Kohda
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Diverse recognition of non-PxxP peptide ligands by the SH3 domains from p67(phox), Grb2 and Pex13p
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 21 (2002), pp. 4268–4276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kay et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.K. Kay, M.P. Williamson, M. Sudol
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The importance of being proline: the interaction of proline-rich motifs in signaling proteins with their cognate domains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FASEB J., 14 (2000), pp. 231–241
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Khoshnan et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Khoshnan, J. Ko, P.H. Patterson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Effects of intracellular expression of anti-huntingtin antibodies of various specificities on mutant huntingtin aggregation and toxicity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 99 (2002), pp. 1002–1007
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Koradi et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Koradi, M. Billeter, K. Wuthrich
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         MOLMOL: a program for display and analysis of macromolecular structures
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Graph., 14 (1996), pp. 51–55 29–32
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Landles and Bates, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Landles, G.P. Bates
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin and the molecular pathogenesis of Huntington's disease. Fourth in molecular medicine review series
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO Rep., 5 (2004), pp. 958–963
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Laskowski et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.A. Laskowski, J.A. Rullmannn, M.W. MacArthur, R. Kaptein, J.M. Thornton
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         AQUA and PROCHECK-NMR: programs for checking the quality of protein structures solved by NMR
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 8 (1996), pp. 477–486
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Li et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.Y. Li, M. Plomann, P. Brundin
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntington's disease: a synaptopathy?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Mol. Med., 9 (2003), pp. 414–420
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Li and Li, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.H. Li, X.J. Li
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin-protein interactions and the pathogenesis of Huntington's disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Genet., 20 (2004), pp. 146–154
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Li, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.S. Li
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Specificity and versatility of SH3 and other proline-recognition domains: structural basis and implications for cellular signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 390 (2005), pp. 641–653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lin et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.T. Lin, R.M. Lu, W.Y. Tarn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The WW domain-containing proteins interact with the early spliceosome and participate in pre-mRNA splicing in vivo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 24 (2004), pp. 9176–9185
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y.F. Liu, R.C. Deth, D. Devys
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3 domain-dependent association of huntingtin with epidermal growth factor receptor signaling complexes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 8121–8124
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Liu, M.J. Macias, M.J. Bottomley, G. Stier, J.P. Linge, M. Nilges, P. Bork, M. Sattler
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The three-dimensional structure of the HRDC domain and implications for the Werner and Bloom syndrome proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Struct. Fold. Des., 7 (1999), pp. 1557–1566
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         MacDonald et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.E. MacDonald, C.M. Ambrose, M.P. Duyao, R.H. Myers, C. Lin, L. Srinidhi, G. Barnes, S.A. Taylor, M. James, N. Groot,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel gene containing a trinucleotide repeat that is expanded and unstable on Huntington's disease chromosomes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 72 (1993), pp. 971–983
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mahoney et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.M. Mahoney, V.K. Rastogi, S.M. Cahill, M.E. Girvin, S.C. Almo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Binding orientation of proline-rich peptides in solution: polarity of the profilin-ligand interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Am. Chem. Soc., 122 (2000), pp. 7851–7852
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Martin and Gusella, 1986
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.B. Martin, J.F. Gusella
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntington's disease. Pathogenesis and management
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         N. Engl. J. Med., 315 (1986), pp. 1267–1276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mayer, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.J. Mayer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3 domains: complexity in moderation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Sci., 114 (2001), pp. 1253–1263
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mizutani et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Mizutani, S. Suetsugu, T. Takenawa
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FBP11 regulates nuclear localization of N-WASP and inhibits N-WASP-dependent microspike formation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 313 (2004), pp. 468–474
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Modregger et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Modregger, N.A. DiProspero, V. Charles, D.A. Tagle, M. Plomann
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PACSIN 1 interacts with huntingtin and is absent from synaptic varicosities in presymptomatic Huntington's disease brains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hum. Mol. Genet., 11 (2002), pp. 2547–2558
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Musacchio, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Musacchio
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         How SH3 domains recognize proline
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Adv. Protein Chem., 61 (2002), pp. 211–268
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nilges et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Nilges, M.J. Macias, S.I. O'Donoghue, H. Oschkinat
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Automated NOESY interpretation with ambiguous distance restraints: the refined NMR solution structure of the pleckstrin homology domain from β-spectrin
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 269 (1997), pp. 408–422
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Passani et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.A. Passani, M.T. Bedford, P.W. Faber, K.M. McGinnis, A.H. Sharp, J.F. Gusella, J.P. Vonsattel, M.E. MacDonald
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin's WW domain partners in Huntington's disease post-mortem brain fulfill genetic criteria for direct involvement in Huntington's disease pathogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hum. Mol. Genet., 9 (2000), pp. 2175–2182
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Peterson et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.D. Peterson, C.A. Theimer, H. Wu, J. Feigon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New applications of 2D filtered/edited NOESY for assignment and structure elucidation of RNA and RNA-protein complexes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 28 (2004), pp. 59–67
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pires et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.R. Pires, C. Parthier, R. Aido-Machado, U. Wiedemann, L. Otte, G. Bohm, R. Rudolph, H. Oschkinat
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural basis for APPTPPPLPP peptide recognition by the FBP11WW1 domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 348 (2005), pp. 399–408
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Press et al., 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.H. Press, S.A. Teukolsky, W.T. Vetterling
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Numerical Recipes in C
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         (Second Edition)Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK (1992)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Qin et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z.H. Qin, Y. Wang, E. Sapp, B. Cuiffo, E. Wanker, M.R. Hayden, K.B. Kegel, N. Aronin, M. DiFiglia
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Huntingtin bodies sequester vesicle-associated proteins by a polyproline-dependent interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Neurosci., 24 (2004), pp. 269–281
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Santamaria et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Santamaria, Z. Wu, C. Boulegue, G. Pal, W. Lu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reexamination of the recognition preference of the specificity pocket of the Abl SH3 domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Recognit., 16 (2003), pp. 131–138
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sittler et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Sittler, S. Walter, N. Wedemeyer, R. Hasenbank, E. Scherzinger, H. Eickhoff, G.P. Bates, H. Lehrach, E.E. Wanker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3GL3 associates with the Huntingtin exon 1 protein and promotes the formation of polygln-containing protein aggregates
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 2 (1998), pp. 427–436
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sudol, 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Sudol
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure and function of the WW domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol., 65 (1996), pp. 113–132
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sugars and Rubinsztein, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.L. Sugars, D.C. Rubinsztein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Transcriptional abnormalities in Huntington disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Genet., 19 (2003), pp. 233–238
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sun et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Sun, A. Savanenin, P.H. Reddy, Y.F. Liu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Polyglutamine-expanded huntingtin promotes sensitization of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors via post-synaptic density 95
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 24713–24718
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vonsattel et al., 1985
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.P. Vonsattel, R.H. Myers, T.J. Stevens, R.J. Ferrante, E.D. Bird, E.P. Richardson Jr.
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuropathological classification of Huntington's disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Neuropathol. Exp. Neurol., 44 (1985), pp. 559–577
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wiesner et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Wiesner, G. Stier, M. Sattler, M.J. Macias
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Solution structure and ligand recognition of the WW domain pair of the yeast splicing factor Prp40
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 324 (2002), pp. 807–822
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zarrinpar et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Zarrinpar, R.P. Bhattacharyya, W.A. Lim
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The structure and function of proline recognition domains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Sci. STKE, 2003 (2003), p. RE8
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2006 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
