<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC2993637
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Leu628 of the KIX Domain of CBP is a Key Residue for the Interaction with the MLL Transactivation Domain
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     Physical interaction between the transactivation domain (TAD) of the mixed-lineage leukemia protein (MLL) and the KIX domain of the CREB binding protein (CBP) is necessary for MLL-mediated transcriptional activation. We show by alanine-scanning mutagenesis that hydrophobic surface residues of KIX, especially L628, are energetically important for binding the MLL TAD. NMR studies of the KIX-L628A mutant suggest that L628 plays a crucial role in conformational transitions at the MLL binding site, necessary for high affinity interactions with MLL. Unexpectedly, MLL also binds to the c-Myb/pKID site of KIX, highlighting the complex nature of interactions involving intrinsically disordered transcriptional activators.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     protein-protein interaction, NMR chemical shift perturbation, mixed lineage leukemia, transcriptional coacvitator CBP, transactivation domain, isothermal titration calorimetry
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Gene activation in higher eukaryotes is accomplished through the concerted action of transcription factors and transcriptional coactivators [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     1
    </xref>
    ]. CBP/p300 are general transcriptional coactivators that recruit the basal transcription machinery and modify chromatin via their histone acetyltransferase activities [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     2
    </xref>
    ]. They contain modular protein binding domains, including the KIX domain, that physically interact with various transcription factors [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    ]. The KIX domain provides two distinct binding surfaces for interactions with transcription factors; the TADs of the phosphorylated kinase-inducible domain of CREB (pKID) and c-Myb bind to a hydrophobic groove formed by the first and third α-helices of KIX, while the TAD of MLL binds to an opposite surface of KIX from the c-Myb/pKID site (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1A
    </xref>
    ) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    –
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <fig id="F1" position="float">
    <label>
     Figure 1
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      (A) Representation of the KIX structure in the ternary KIX·MLL·c-Myb complex (PDB 2AGH [
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       6
      </xref>
      ]). The six mutation sites are mapped onto the surface of KIX, color coded to indicate the effect of Ala substitution on
      <em>
       K
      </em>
      <sub>
       d
      </sub>
      for MLL binding: yellow, 2-15× increase in
      <em>
       K
      </em>
      <sub>
       d
      </sub>
      ; orange, 25-40× increase; red, 100× increase. Backbones of the bound MLL (2842-2860 only) and c-Myb are shown in blue and green, respectively. The figure was prepared using MOLMOL [
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       19
      </xref>
      ]. (B) Far-UV CD spectra, (C) urea-induced equilibrium unfolding transition, and (D) MLL binding isotherms of the wild-type and mutant KIX. Color codes are shown in (D). In (C) and (D), continuous lines are the curves fitted to a two-state transition and a one-site binding model, respectively.
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
    MLL belongs to the evolutionarily conserved trxG family, which acts as a positive regulator of homeobox (Hox) gene expression to control segment specificity in early embryogenesis through an epigenetic mechanism [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. Physical interaction between the MLL TAD and KIX is necessary for MLL-mediated transcriptional activation [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ]. Indeed, chromosomal translocations involving MLL cause the loss of several MLL domains including the TAD, resulting in infant and treatment-related leukemias [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. The NMR structure of the ternary KIX·MLL·c-Myb complex revealed that the MLL TAD binds to a groove formed at the interface between the G
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    -helix and the second and third α-helices of KIX [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ]. However, it is not clear which residues of KIX are energetically important in MLL binding. Here, we show by alanine-scanning mutagenesis and NMR experiments that L628 of KIX is a key residue for the interaction with the MLL TAD.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and Methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2.1. Sample preparation
    </title>
    <p>
     Wild-type and mutant KIX domains (residues 586-672) of mouse CBP were constructed, expressed and purified as previously described [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      4
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ]. Both wild-type and L628A mutant KIX were prepared with [
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N]- and [
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N,
     <sup>
      13
     </sup>
     C]-labeling for NMR experiments. Human MLL (2842-2469) was produced and purified as described [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ]. An additional glycine residue was present at the N-terminus of MLL as a remnant following thrombin cleavage. The molecular weights of the proteins were confirmed by mass spectrometry. The MLL concentration was measured using the Pierce BCA protein assay kit. The KIX concentration was determined by absorbance at 280 nm.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2.2. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC)
    </title>
    <p>
     ITC experiments were performed at 30°C using a MicroCal Omega VP-ITC instrument (MicroCal, Amherst, MA) as previously described [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      5
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      10
     </xref>
     ]. Samples were prepared in 20 mM Tris/acetate (pH 7.0) and 50 mM NaCl. All experiments were performed in duplicate. See
     <a>
      Supplementary text
     </a>
     for details.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2.3. Circular dichroism (CD) spectra
    </title>
    <p>
     CD spectra were measured on an Aviv 62DS spectropolarimeter at 30°C. The urea-induced equilibrium unfolding transition of KIX was monitored at 222 nm by preparing separate samples at each urea concentration. The mean residue ellipticity (MRE) was calculated as described [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ]. The equilibrium unfolding transition curves were analyzed assuming a two-state transition [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2.4. NMR spectroscopy
    </title>
    <p>
     NMR spectra were recorded using Bruker 500, 600, and 800 MHz spectrometers in buffer containing 20 mM
     <em>
      d
     </em>
     <sub>
      11
     </sub>
     -Tris/
     <em>
      d
     </em>
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -acetate (pH 7.0), 50 mM NaCl, 0.2% (w/v) NaN
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     and 10%
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O at 30°C, and analyzed using NMRPipe [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      12
     </xref>
     ] and NMRView [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      13
     </xref>
     ]. Backbone resonances of the wild-type and the L628A mutant of KIX in the free and the MLL-bound forms were assigned by standard triple resonance experiments using HNCA [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ], HN(CO)CA [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ], HNCACB [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      16
     </xref>
     ], and CBCA(CO)NH [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ]. The typical protein concentration was 0.5 mM. In titration experiments, an aliquot of ~2 mM unlabeled MLL was added to the NMR tube containing
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled KIX at each titration step.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2.5. Dissociation constants from chemical shift titrations
    </title>
    <p>
     The dissociation constants and the binding sites for the primary and secondary MLL binding to KIX were estimated by a global fit of
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H and
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N chemical shift changes, assuming a two-site binding model [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      10
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ]. Singular value decomposition (SVD) was used to estimate the number of binding sites and to remove the contribution of noise to experimental data [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ] (MA, JC Ferreon, HJD, and PEW, manuscript in preparation). See
     <a>
      Supplementary text
     </a>
     for details.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    3. Results &amp; Discussion
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     3.1. Ala-scanning mutagenesis at the MLL binding site
    </title>
    <p>
     We introduced single-site Ala substitutions at F612, R624, L628, Y631, L664, and R668 of KIX, residues which have direct contacts with MLL in the ternary complex [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      6
     </xref>
     ]. The six mutants showed essentially the same far-UV CD spectra, indicating that overall secondary structure is unaffected by the mutations (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1B
     </xref>
     ). However, the Y631A mutant was destabilized to urea unfolding, while the L628A mutant was slightly stabilized (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1C
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Table S1
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     The equilibrium dissociation constant,
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     , for MLL binding measured by ITC was 2.1 μM for wild-type KIX, consistent with the
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     of 2.8 μM reported previously for a shorter MLL construct [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      5
     </xref>
     ] (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1D
     </xref>
     ,
     <a>
      Supplementary Table S1
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S1
     </a>
     ). However,
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     was greatly affected by the mutations, with a reduction of over an order of magnitude in affinity seen for Y631A, L664A and F612A, and was too large to be determined for L628A. Lesser reductions of affinity were seen for R624A and R668A, indicating that hydrophobic residues are energetically more important for the KIX·MLL interaction. Consistent with this conclusion, Y631, L664, F612 and L628 are in contact with hydrophobic residues I2849, F2852, V2853, and L2854 of MLL [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      8
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     3.2. The KIX-L628A mutant
    </title>
    <p>
     Strikingly, MLL binding by the KIX-L628A mutant was not observed by ITC. We therefore performed an HSQC titration in which unlabeled MLL was added stepwise into
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled KIX-L628A (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2A
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S2
     </a>
     ). Upon titration with MLL, the KIX-L628A cross-peaks showed fast-exchanging shifts with a curvature, indicating weak but detectable interactions at more than one site. This was confirmed by SVD analysis, which gives an estimate of the number of meaningful components necessary for explaining the observed data set [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ] (
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S3
     </a>
     ). The titration points were therefore globally fit using a two-site binding model (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2B
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S4
     </a>
     ), giving a dissociation constant for the primary binding,
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d1
     </sub>
     , of 220 (±10) μM. The primary MLL binding site of KIX-L628A was found to be very similar to that of the wild-type KIX (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2C
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S5
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       (A) Regions of the
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H-
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N HSQC spectrum of the KIX-L628A mutant showing chemical shift changes upon titration with MLL. The cross-peak color changes gradually from black (free) to magenta according to the concentration ratio as shown in the bar above the figure. (B)
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H and
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N chemical shift titration curves for a subset of KIX-L628A resonances (colored points corresponding to residues according to the legend) upon titration with increasing amounts of MLL. The lines represent a global fit to the titration data, using a two-site binding model with
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d1
       </sub>
       = 220 μM and
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d2
       </sub>
       = 1.63 mM. (C,D) MLL binding sites on KIX-L628A. The weighted average chemical shift differences [
       <span>
        <math>
         <mrow>
          <mi>
           Δ
          </mi>
          <mi>
           δ
          </mi>
          <msub>
           <mrow>
            <mrow>
             <mo>
              (
             </mo>
             <mtext>
              N
             </mtext>
             <mo>
              ,
             </mo>
             <mtext>
              H
             </mtext>
             <mo>
              )
             </mo>
            </mrow>
           </mrow>
           <mrow>
            <mtext>
             av
            </mtext>
           </mrow>
          </msub>
          <mo>
           =
          </mo>
          <msqrt>
           <mrow>
            <msup>
             <mrow>
              <mrow>
               <mo>
                (
               </mo>
               <mi>
                Δ
               </mi>
               <msub>
                <mrow>
                 <mi>
                  δ
                 </mi>
                </mrow>
                <mtext>
                 H
                </mtext>
               </msub>
               <mo>
                )
               </mo>
              </mrow>
             </mrow>
             <mn>
              2
             </mn>
            </msup>
            <mo>
             +
            </mo>
            <msup>
             <mrow>
              <mrow>
               <mo>
                (
               </mo>
               <mi>
                Δ
               </mi>
               <msub>
                <mrow>
                 <mi>
                  δ
                 </mi>
                </mrow>
                <mtext>
                 N
                </mtext>
               </msub>
               <mo>
                /
               </mo>
               <mn>
                5
               </mn>
               <mo>
                )
               </mo>
              </mrow>
             </mrow>
             <mn>
              2
             </mn>
            </msup>
           </mrow>
          </msqrt>
         </mrow>
        </math>
       </span>
       <span>
       </span>
       <script>
        <math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mi><mi>δ</mi><msub><mrow><mrow><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mtext>N</mtext><mo>,</mo><mtext>H</mtext><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow></mrow><mrow><mtext>av</mtext></mrow></msub><mo>=</mo><msqrt><mrow><msup><mrow><mrow><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mi><msub><mrow><mi>δ</mi></mrow><mtext>H</mtext></msub><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><msup><mrow><mrow><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mi><msub><mrow><mi>δ</mi></mrow><mtext>N</mtext></msub><mo>/</mo><mn>5</mn><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt></mrow></math>
       </script>
       ] for KIX-L628A amide resonances between the free form and the bound form, in which the primary (C) or secondary binding site (D) is occupied, are mapped onto the surface of KIX in the ternary complex, using colors to indicate changes in chemical shift greater than 2 × standard deviation (SD) from the mean (red and blue), between 1 and 2 × SD from the mean (orange and cyan), and between mean and 1 × SD from the mean (yellow and green).
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Average
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H and
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N chemical shift differences, Δδ(N,H)
     <sub>
      av
     </sub>
     , between the wild-type and the L628A mutant of KIX in the free form showed that F612 and V629, which both contact L628A, are greatly perturbed by the mutation (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     ). Interestingly, T614, which does not have direct contact with L628, shows a very large chemical shift perturbation, indicating that through F612, the L628A mutation perturbs the L
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     loop located between the α
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     and α
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     helices. However, secondary Cα shifts (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     , lower panel) indicate that the overall secondary structures are not perturbed by the mutation.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       (A, upper) Histogram showing Δδ(N,H)
       <sub>
        av
       </sub>
       between the wild-type and the L628A mutant of KIX in the free form. Color codes are the same as in
       <xref ref-type="fig">
        Fig. 2
       </xref>
       . (A, lower) Histogram showing the secondary
       <sup>
        13
       </sup>
       Cα chemical shifts calculated by subtraction of random coil values [
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        20
       </xref>
       ] from the experimental data for the wild-type KIX (open bars) and the L628A mutant (gray bars) in the free form. Regions showing positive secondary Cα chemical shifts indicate a helical conformation. Secondary structure elements in the ternary KIX·MLL·c-Myb complex [
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        6
       </xref>
       ] are depicted at the top. (B) The same as in (A), but in the presence of MLL (1:1 and 1:2 KIX:MLL ratios for the wild-type KIX and the L628A mutant, where 94% and 74% of KIX are in the MLL-bound form, respectively). (C,D) The KIX structures in the binary KIX·c-Myb complex (PDB 1SB0 [
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        21
       </xref>
       ]) and in the ternary KIX·MLL·c-Myb complex, respectively. Residues having large Δδ(N,H)
       <sub>
        av
       </sub>
       are shown by spheres of radius corresponding to the van der Waals radius of each atom. In (D), the G
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       helix is colored cyan.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Binding of MLL to wild-type KIX induces enhanced formation of the G
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     3
     <sub>
      10
     </sub>
     -helix and displacement of the L
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     loop, allowing the side-chain of F612 to make close hydrophobic contacts with MLL (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3B-D
     </xref>
     ) [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      5
     </xref>
     ]. However, such a helix enhancement was not observed in KIX-L628A (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3B
     </xref>
     ). These results suggest that in addition to hydrophobic contacts with MLL, L628 may play crucial roles in the L
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     loop displacement and the enhanced G
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     helix formation, which are necessary for high affinity binding with MLL.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     3.3. Secondary MLL binding to KIX
    </title>
    <p>
     Unexpectedly, HSQC titrations also showed the presence of secondary MLL binding to KIX-L628A, with a dissociation constant,
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d2
     </sub>
     , of 1.63 (±0.05) mM (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     ). Large chemical shift changes were observed in and around the c-Myb/pKID binding site upon secondary binding, indicating that the second MLL ligand binds very weakly to the c-Myb/pKID site (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2D
     </xref>
     ). Chemical shift perturbations due to binding in the secondary site were also observed at the primary MLL site (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2D
     </xref>
     ). This is probably due to conformational changes rather than direct binding, because it is unlikely that two MLL molecules can bind simultaneously in the same site on KIX. Alternatively, it might be possible that deconvolution of the chemical shift changes associated with primary and secondary binding events was not perfect, because both binding events are not clearly separated in the titration curves, compared, for example, with
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-TAZ2 titration with p53 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
    <p>
     The secondary MLL binding to the c-Myb/pKID site was confirmed by HSQC titration of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled wild-type KIX with MLL (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4A
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Figure S6
     </a>
     ). Whereas slow to intermediate exchange was observed below 1:1 KIX:MLL ratios due to primary binding, fast-exchanging shifts were observed at greater than 1:1 ratios, indicating the presence of secondary MLL binding, which was confirmed by SVD analysis (
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S7
     </a>
     ). The titration curves referenced to the data at a 1:1 KIX:MLL ratio were globally fit with a two-site binding model, assuming that
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d1
     </sub>
     = 2.1 μM and that the chemical shift changes in the primary binding site are zero (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4B
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S8
     </a>
     ). The analysis revealed large chemical shift perturbations in and around the c-Myb/pKID binding site with a
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d2
     </sub>
     of 920 (±20) μM (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4C,D
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      Supplementary Fig. S9
     </a>
     ), showing unequivocally that MLL binds KIX at two sites.
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       (A) Regions of the
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H-
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N HSQC spectrum of wild-type KIX showing chemical shift changes upon titration with MLL. b and f indicate the peaks for the bound and free forms, respectively. (B)
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H and
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N chemical shift titration curves for a subset of KIX resonances upon titration with increasing amounts of MLL. The lines represent a global fit to the titration data, using a two-site binding model with
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d1
       </sub>
       = 2.14 μM and
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d2
       </sub>
       = 920 μM. (C,D) MLL binding sites on the wild-type KIX, as shown in
       <xref ref-type="fig">
        Fig. 2C,D
       </xref>
       . Δδ(N,H)
       <sub>
        av
       </sub>
       for primary binding was obtained from the HSQC spectra at 1:0 and 1:1 KIX:MLL ratios. Δδ(N,H)
       <sub>
        av
       </sub>
       for secondary binding was obtained from a global fit of titration curves.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     MLL has an amphipathic φ-x-x-φ-φ motif (φ = bulky hydrophobic residue and x = any residue), which is conserved in many KIX binding proteins including c-Myb and pKID [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      10
     </xref>
     ]. The primary sequence similarity indicates that MLL has the potential to bind the c-Myb/pKID site through the amphipathic motif, supporting our present finding. Although the affinity of the secondary binding event is weak, it highlights the complex nature of interactions involving hub proteins such as transcriptional coactivators.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     01
    </title>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (5.7M, doc)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <sec>
    <dl>
     <dt>
      CD
     </dt>
     <dd>
      circular dichroism
     </dd>
     <dt>
      CBP
     </dt>
     <dd>
      CREB binding protein
     </dd>
     <dt>
      CREB
     </dt>
     <dd>
      cyclic-AMP response element binding protein
     </dd>
     <dt>
      HSQC
     </dt>
     <dd>
      heteronuclear single quantum correlation
     </dd>
     <dt>
      ITC
     </dt>
     <dd>
      isothermal titration calorimetry
     </dd>
     <dt>
      MLL
     </dt>
     <dd>
      mixed-lineage leukemia protein
     </dd>
     <dt>
      MRE
     </dt>
     <dd>
      mean residue ellipticity
     </dd>
     <dt>
      pKID
     </dt>
     <dd>
      phosphorylated kinase-inducible domain of CREB
     </dd>
     <dt>
      SD
     </dt>
     <dd>
      standard deviation
     </dd>
     <dt>
      SVD
     </dt>
     <dd>
      singular value decomposition
     </dd>
     <dt>
      TAD
     </dt>
     <dd>
      transactivation domain
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Appendix A.
    <a>
     Supplementary Data
    </a>
   </title>
   <p>
    <a>
     Supplementary data
    </a>
    associated with this article can be found in the online version.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>