<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC2527902
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Molecular basis of the interaction between the antiapoptotic Bcl-2 family proteins and the proapoptotic protein ASPP2
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     We have characterized the molecular basis of the interaction between ASPP2 and Bcl-2, which are key proteins in the apoptotic pathway. The C-terminal ankyrin repeats and SH3 domain of ASPP2 (ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     ) mediate its interactions with the antiapoptotic protein Bcl-2. We used biophysical and computational methods to identify the interaction sites of Bcl-2 and its homologues with ASPP2. Using peptide array screening, we found that ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     binds two homologous sites in all three Bcl proteins tested: (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) the conserved BH4 motif, and (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) a binding site for proapoptotic regulators. Quantitative binding studies revealed that binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the Bcl-2 family members is selective at two levels: (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) interaction with Bcl-2-derived peptides is the tightest compared to peptides from the other family members, and (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) within Bcl-2, binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the BH4 domain is tightest. Sequence alignment of the ASPP2-binding peptides combined with binding studies of mutated peptides revealed that two nonconserved positions where only Bcl-2 contains positively charged residues account for its tighter binding. The experimental binding results served as a basis for docking analysis, by which we modeled the complexes of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     with the full-length Bcl proteins. Using peptide arrays and quantitative binding studies, we found that Bcl-2 binds three loops in ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     with similar affinity, in agreement with our predicted model. Based on our results, we propose a mechanism in which ASPP2 induces apoptosis by inhibiting functional sites of the antiapoptotic Bcl-2 proteins.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     apoptosis, peptides, protein–protein interactions, peptide arrays, docking
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Identification of the ASPP2 Binding Sites in Bcl-2 Family Proteins by Using Peptide Array Screening.
    </title>
    <p>
     We designed an array comprising 59 overlapping peptides derived from the antiapoptotic proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     , and Bcl-W. Peptide length was between 10 and 30 residues (
     <a>
      Table S1
     </a>
     ). Peptides were designed based on the secondary and tertiary structures of the parent proteins. ASPP2 893-1128, consisting of the Ankyrin and SH3 domains (ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     ), was expressed, purified, and screened for binding the peptide array (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Peptides from Yes-associated protein 1, which are known to bind ASPP2 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ), served as positive control (data not shown). ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     -bound peptides were derived from two homologous sites at all three tested antiapoptotic Bcl-2 proteins (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B–D
     </em>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The first site (“BH4 site”) is the N-terminal α-helix, represented by peptides Bcl-W 8–26, Bcl-2 7–24, and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     6–26. This site corresponds to the BH4 domain, which is conserved among antiapoptotic Bcl-2 family members, and is essential for apoptosis inhibition (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      19
     </xref>
     ). The second ASPP2 binding site (“proapoptotic site”) consists of parts of helix 2 and helix 3, represented by the binding peptides Bcl-2 45–108, Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     104–123, and Bcl-W 41–67. The common motif for all of these peptides is the sequence R-aromatic-R-R-X-F. This site overlaps with a known binding site for proapoptotic members from Bcl-2 family such as Bak and Bad (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      2
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 1.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Analysis of the ASPP2 binding sites in the Bcl-2 family proteins. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) An array consisting of overlapping peptides derived from the Bcl-2 family proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-W, and Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       was screened for binding ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       . Each dark spot represents binding of ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       to a specific peptide (
       <a>
        <span>
         Table 1
        </span>
       </a>
       ). (
       <em>
        B–D
       </em>
       ) The ASPP2 binding sites, as discovered in the peptide array screening, are highlighted on the known 3D structures of the Bcl family proteins. The BH4 site is in magenta and the proapoptotic site is in green. See
       <a>
        <span>
         Table 1
        </span>
       </a>
       for peptides details. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Bcl-2 [PDB entry
       <span>
        1YSW
       </span>
       (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        23
       </xref>
       )]. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       [PDB entry
       <span>
        1G5J
       </span>
       (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        20
       </xref>
       )]. (
       <em>
        D
       </em>
       ) Bcl-W [PDB entry
       <span>
        1O0l
       </span>
       (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        31
       </xref>
       )]. Figures were generated by using PyMOL (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        32
       </xref>
       ). (
       <em>
        E–G
       </em>
       ) Quantitative analysis of the interaction between ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       and Bcl-2 BH4 peptide (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        7
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        None
       </xref>
       –
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        24
       </xref>
       ) using three independent methods. (
       <em>
        E
       </em>
       ) Fluorescence spectroscopy. [=Q13625 ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3 protein]
       </sub>
       was titrated into fluorescein-labeled [=P10415 Bcl-2 7–24 protein], and the binding curve was fit to 1:1 binding model.
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       was found to be [=8058930 4.7 ± 0.2 μM kd]. (
       <em>
        F
       </em>
       ) SPR. Biotinylated [=P10415 Bcl-2 7–24 protein] peptide was captured on a ProteOn NLC sensor chip, followed by the association of 150 μl of [=Q13625 ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3 protein]
       </sub>
       , simultaneously injected at concentrations of 40, 30, 15, 10, and 7.5 μM (from top to bottom).
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       was found to be [=8058270 1.6 μM kd]. (
       <em>
        G
       </em>
       ) ELISA. ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       was adsorbed on the ELISA plate, and binding of the peptide was studied as described in
       <em>
        Materials and Methods
       </em>
       . The apparent
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       is at the low micromolar range, in agreement with the two other methods.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Binding between ASPP2
        <sub>
         Ank-SH3
        </sub>
        and peptides from Bcl-2 family proteins: SPR studies
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Quantitative Analysis of the Interactions Between ASPP2 and the Bcl-2 Family Proteins: Selectivity Among Proteins and Among Binding Sites.
    </title>
    <p>
     The peptide array method is semiquantitative and served for initial screening of the binding sites. To gain quantitative information about the binding of the Bcl peptides to ASPP2, the binding peptides discovered in the array screening were synthesized and their binding to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     was studied by using three independent quantitative methods: surface plasmon resonance (SPR), fluorescence spectroscopy, and ELISA. The peptides from the proapoptotic site were overlapping but not completely homologous, so we also tested the exact homologous peptides Bcl-2 103–120 and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     89–111, as well as short peptides containing the conserved R-aromatic-R-R-X-F motif: Bcl-2 103–120, Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     103–111, and Bcl-W 54–67 (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     The binding of all of the peptides to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     was quantified by SPR experiments because for some peptides binding was too weak to quantify by using fluorescence spectroscopy, which required much higher protein concentrations. The SPR results verified that all of the peptides selected in the peptide array indeed bind ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     . Quantitative analysis of the SPR binding data (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     and
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      F
     </em>
     ) revealed that the binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the Bcl-2 family proteins is selective at two levels. (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) Selectivity between proteins: Binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to Bcl-2 peptides is the tightest, binding of Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     is an order of magnitude weaker, and binding of Bcl-W is very weak. Fluorescence and ELISA binding studies confirmed that the Bcl-2 BH4 peptide (Bcl-2 7–24) bound tightest to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     , with affinity at the low-micromolar range (4.7 ± 0.2 μM;
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      E–G
     </em>
     ). (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) Selectivity between the two binding sites within Bcl-2: Binding to the BH4 domain (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , magenta) is an order of magnitude tighter than binding to the proapoptotic site (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , green, and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     The Tighter Binding of Bcl2 to ASPP2 Is Due to Extra Positive Charge at the Conserved Binding Interfaces.
    </title>
    <p>
     To reveal the basis for the selectivity in ASPP2 binding to the Bcl proteins, we aligned their ASPP2 binding sequences. Most amino acids are conserved in all three Bcl proteins (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ). However, there are some nonconserved amino acids. Within the aligned sequences of the BH4 domain, two positively charged amino acids exist in Bcl-2 and are missing from its homologues: (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) Lys-15 is replaced by Asp in the Bcl-W and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     , and (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) His-18 is replaced by Gly in Bcl-W and by Ser in Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     . In the proapoptotic site, instead of Bcl-2 Arg-103, Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     has Leu and Bcl-W has Thr. In all cases the Bcl-2 sequence is more positively charged than the others, which may explain its tighter binding to the negatively charged ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     (pI = 4.72). To examine the contribution of the positively charged residues to the tighter binding of the Bcl-2-derived peptide, we synthesized a series of Bcl peptides modified at the positively charged residues and compared their binding affinities to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     using ELISA (
     <a>
      Table S2
     </a>
     ). We tested peptides where the positive charge from the Bcl-2 sequence was eliminated or replaced by the corresponding residue from Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     (Bcl-2 7–24 K15A, H18A, K15D, H18S) and peptides where positive charges were introduced into the relevant positions at the Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     homologous peptide (Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     6–26 D15K, S18H). Bcl-2 7–24 K15A and H18A showed significant reduction in binding affinity to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     compared to the WT peptide (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). Introduction of a negative charge in Bcl-2 7–24 K15D abolished the binding almost completely (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). The Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     -derived mutated peptides bearing the additional positively charged residues—e.g., Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     6–26 D15K—showed significant increase in the binding affinity, whereas Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     6–26 S18H did not (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). However, introducing both residues into the Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     peptide had a synergistic effect that raised the binding to the level of the WT Bcl-2 peptide (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     and
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). In the mutated peptides derived from the proapoptotic domain, the modification Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     L103R (the corresponding residue in Bcl-2) did not result in a significant change in the binding to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     (data not shown). The contribution of the Arg residues to the binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the proapoptotic site was tested using NMR. The TOCSY spectrum of Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     103–111 was compared to its spectrum when incubated with ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     under identical conditions. The differences between the bound and nonbound peptide were extremely pronounced (
     <a>
      Fig. S2
      <em>
       A
      </em>
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      Table S3
     </a>
     ) in both amide and Hα proton chemical shifts. Changes in the chemical shifts of Arg-106 and -107 and S110 upon binding indicate their involvement in the interaction with ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      Fig. S2
      <em>
       B
      </em>
     </a>
     ). The Arg-104 amide was unresolved in the free state, but the Hα proton did not show a significant deviation in the bound state.
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 2.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Positively charged residues in Bcl-2 account for its tighter binding To ASPP2. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Sequence alignment of ASPP2 binding peptides: The ASPP2 binding peptides derived from the three Bcl proteins are bold and colored by amino acid type. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       and
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) ELISA studies of ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       binding to Bcl-2 and Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       peptides modified at the nonconserved amino acid K15 and H18 of Bcl-2. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Peptides in which the positively charged residues from the Bcl-2 peptides were replaced by alanine or by the corresponding residues from Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       . (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Peptides in which positive charges were introduced into the relevant positions at the Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       peptide.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We used ELISA to compare the binding affinities of Bcl-2 7–24 to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     at different ionic strengths and found that the ionic strength had only a modest effect on binding (
     <a>
      Fig. S3
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Docking Studies Suggest a Model for ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     Binding with Full-Length Bcl-2 and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     .
    </title>
    <p>
     To move from the peptide to the protein level and suggest structural models for the complexes between the full-length Bcl proteins and ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     , we performed docking studies. We used the algorithms PatchDock (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ) and RosettaDock (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      22
     </xref>
     ) to dock the structure of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ) to structures of Bcl-2 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      23
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ) and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      10
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      25
     </xref>
     ). We defined a biologically valid docking model as one that its protein–protein interface (within 5 Å) contains at least four residues from each experimentally detected ASPP2 binding peptide from Bcl-2/Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The 5-Å and four-residue limits were set based on known PPI (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     ). From the top 200 models generated, 19–29 models were valid according to our binding peptides data. To further select fitting models, we examined the sequence alignment of the Bcl proteins (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ) in the binding peptides regions. We looked for models that involve contacts of specific amino acids that are surface-exposed and conserved, as well as those that contribute to the tighter binding affinity of Bcl-2 to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     (Bcl-2 numbering; PDB entry
     <span>
      1YSW
     </span>
     ). (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) From the BH4 site: Y19, K20, and R24 are conserved, and K15 and H18 are unique to Bcl-2. (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) From the proapoptotic site: R104, Y105, R106, and R107 are conserved, and R103 is unique to Bcl-2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ). Our docking results suggested models for the complexes of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     with both Bcl-2 and Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). The SH3 domain of ASPP2 interacts with the BH4 domain of Bcl, and the Ank domain of ASPP2 interacts with the proapoptotic site of Bcl. The conserved interactions in both models involve mainly D/E from ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     with conserved K/R of Bcl-2/Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     .
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 3.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Docking model for the interaction between the ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       and Bcl-2/Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       proteins. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Bcl-2 binding to ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       . Bcl-2 is colored gray, the BH4 site is in magenta, and the proapoptotic site is in green. ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       is colored orange. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Two aligned models of Bcl-2 and Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       complexes with ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       . Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       is colored cyan, and Bcl-2 is in gray. ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       is colored red and orange for its complex models with Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       and Bcl-2
       <sub>
        ,
       </sub>
       respectively. Representative binding residues from both partners are depicted in sticks and spheres. The conserved interactions between Bcl-2 (PDB entry
       <span>
        1YSW
       </span>
       ) and ASPP2 (PDB entry
       <span>
        1ycs
       </span>
       ) are as follows: K15–D468 and E470; H18–D468 and E481; Y19–W467; K20–D468 and E481; R24–D352; R103–D358 and D359; Y105–P356; and R106–D333, D358, and E359. The homologous amino acids in Bcl-X
       <sub>
        L
       </sub>
       show the same interactions with ASPP2. For consistency with the PDB file, numbering of the ASPP2 residues is according to the sequence of its truncated form 53BP2.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Identification of the Bcl-2 Binding Sites in ASPP2.
    </title>
    <p>
     To identify the Bcl-2 binding sites in ASPP2 and further validate our docking model, we designed an array comprising 41 overlapping peptides derived from the Ank-SH3 domains of ASPP2 sequence (
     <a>
      Table S4
     </a>
     ). Bcl-2 1–217 was expressed, purified, and screened for binding the peptide array (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Peptides from the Bak protein, which are known to bind Bcl-2 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      2
     </xref>
     ), served as positive control (not shown). Bcl-2 bound several peptides derived from the ASPP2 Ank-SH3 domains (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 2
      </span>
     </a>
     ), which were in agreement with our docking model. They are derived from three major binding sites that form a continuous binding interface (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ): (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) an unstructured loop at the beginning of the SH3 domain, represented by ASPP2 1065–1082; (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) a loop following the first ankyrin repeat, represented by ASPP2 945–961 and ASPP2 931–942; and (
     <em>
      iii
     </em>
     ) the loop following the second ankyrin repeat, represented by ASPP2 978–988, ASPP2 988-1002, and ASPP2 993-1004. The binding peptides discovered in the array screening were synthesized, and their bindings to Bcl-2 1–217 were quantitatively studied by using fluorescence spectroscopy. Five of six peptides derived from the ASPP2 binding interface, as was revealed by our docking model, bound Bcl-2 with nanomolar affinity (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      C–E
     </em>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). ASPP2 1039–1053, the only selected peptide derived from the other interface of the protein that is not involved in Bcl-2 binding according to our model, did not show any binding. We assume that the positive signal in the peptide array is an artifact in this case.
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 4.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Bcl-2 binding sites in ASPP2. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) An array consisting of overlapping peptides derived from ASPP2 was screened for binding Bcl-2. Each dark spot represents binding of Bcl-2 to a specific peptide (
       <a>
        <span>
         Table 2
        </span>
       </a>
       ). (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) The Bcl-2 binding sites, as discovered in the peptide array screening, are colored blue on the 3D structure of ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       (PDB entry
       <span>
        1YCS
       </span>
       ). (
       <em>
        C–E
       </em>
       ) Quantitative analysis. Shown are representative binding curves of the interaction between Bcl-2 and the peptides derived from ASPP2
       <sub>
        Ank-SH3
       </sub>
       as indicated. Binding was quantified by using fluorescence spectroscopy as described in
       <em>
        Materials and Methods
       </em>
       . For binding affinity, see
       <a>
        <span>
         Table 2
        </span>
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 2.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Binding of Bcl-2 protein to peptides from ASPP2
        <sub>
         Ank-SH3
        </sub>
        : Fluorescence spectroscopy studies
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Using a combination of peptide array screening, biophysical methods, and docking studies, we characterized the interaction between ASPP2 and the Bcl-2 family proteins. We present evidence for a direct interaction of ASPP2 with the Bcl-2 family proteins Bcl-X
    <sub>
     L
    </sub>
    and Bcl-W. We identified the binding sites in both ASPP2 and Bcl-2 family proteins, demonstrated that binding of ASPP2 to the Bcl-2 family proteins is selective with preference to the BH4 domain of Bcl-2, and proposed a model for the structure of the complex between the proteins. Our computational model was in excellent agreement with our experimental data from the peptide array screening and quantitative binding studies.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our results show that peptides are a reliable model for the ASPP2–Bcl interaction. (
    <em>
     i
    </em>
    ) For each Bcl protein tested, ASPP2 bound only some peptides but not all of them, and most of the binding peptides were overlapping, indicating specific binding of particular Bcl sequences. (
    <em>
     ii
    </em>
    ) Nearly all of the ASPP2 binding residues in Bcl-2 are surface-exposed in the full-length protein, further supporting their importance for the interaction with ASPP2. (
    <em>
     iii
    </em>
    ) The ASPP2 binding sites on all Bcl proteins tested were homologous and known to be involved in PPI.
   </p>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Molecular Basis of the ASPP2–Bcl Interactions.
    </title>
    <p>
     The SPR studies showed selectivity in the binding of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the Bcl-derived peptides. The peptide array screening results, although semiquantitative, are in good agreement with the SPR results (compare peak intensities in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ). The docking studies, sequence alignment, NMR studies, and binding studies of mutated peptides all suggest that the extra positive charge of the Bcl-derived peptides is the reason for the selectivity in binding. The moderate ionic strength dependence of the interaction and the specific residues found by NMR to mediate the binding of the Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     peptide suggest that the binding is mediated mainly by specific local interactions between amino acids in both interaction sites in the Bcl proteins. Most of these residues are positively charged, and they bind negative amino acids in ASPP2. Binding does not seem to be governed by a global electrostatic effect. The tight binding of ASPP2 to Bcl-2 peptides may suggest that Bcl-2 is the major target protein from this family for apoptosis stimulation by ASPP2. The two sites identified in our study are in close spatial proximity, and it is likely that ASPP2 binds both of them in a cooperative manner: binding to the high-affinity BH4 site is followed by binding to the low-affinity proapoptotic site. Thus, apoptosis may be regulated by the ASPP2-Bcl interaction simultaneously via both binding sites (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     ). The affinity of ASPP2 to the Bcl-2 BH4 peptide is at the low-micromolar range, while the affinity of Bcl-2 to the ASPP2-derived peptides is submicromolar. The order of magnitude difference is probably due to the use of peptides, which form only part of the binding site.
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Fig. 5.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Proposed mechanism for induction of apoptosis after binding of ASPP2 to Bcl-2 family proteins. ASPP2 binds the antiapoptotic Bcl-2 family members at two functional sites and mediates apoptosis by inducing the release of other proapoptotic proteins that also bind Bcl-2 at those sites, which may enable their apoptotic activity, as specified in the text.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     In our recent studies we discovered an intramolecular interaction between the Ank-SH3 domains and the proline-rich region in ASPP2 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ). The site in the Ank-SH3 domain that binds the proline-rich domain (residues 931–961) overlaps the binding site we found for Bcl-2. This supports our model that the intramolecular interaction in ASPP2 regulates the intermolecular interactions of the protein (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Implications for Apoptosis Regulation by ASPP2: A Proposed Mechanism.
    </title>
    <p>
     Binding between the proapoptotic ASPP2 and antiapoptotic Bcl-2 family members is likely to maintain the balance between the pro- and antiapoptotic activity of both proteins. Based on our
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
     results, we propose a mechanism by which ASPP2 regulates apoptosis by preventing the antiapoptotic function of Bcl-2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     ). It may do so by (
     <em>
      i
     </em>
     ) binding the BH4 domain, which is essential for inhibition of apoptosis, and blocking its activity; or (
     <em>
      ii
     </em>
     ) binding at the known binding site for proapoptotic proteins of the Bcl-2 family, inhibiting their binding to Bcl-2 and allowing their apoptotic activity. For example, the BH4 domains of Bcl-X
     <sub>
      L
     </sub>
     and Bcl-2 are known to bind and inhibit the proapoptotic mitochondrial protein VDAC (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ). Binding of ASPP2 to Bcl-2 via the same site may release VDAC and allow its activity of releasing cytochrome C and inducing apoptosis. ASPP2 may also activate apoptosis by binding the known binding site for proapoptotic regulators from the Bcl-2 family such as Bak/Bak (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      8
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ), inducing their release from the complex, resulting in proapoptotic protein homooligomerization, mitochondrial membrane permeabilization, and apoptosis.
    </p>
    <p>
     Our structural model for the ASPP2–Bcl-2 interaction shows that the interacting peptides from both proteins do not bind in cavities but rather bind extended protein–protein interaction interfaces. These interfaces should be the target for further development of inhibitory peptides and small molecules. ASPP2 controls cell fate and hence is an important potential target for the development of anticancer drugs that will stimulate apoptosis by interfering with its regulation. Understanding the ASPP2–Bcl-2 interaction at the molecular and cellular levels could serve as a basis for such novel anticancer drug leads.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Materials and Methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Expression and Purification of ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     .
    </title>
    <p>
     pRSET HLT ASPP2 893-1128 vector (kind gift from A. R. Fersht, University of Cambridge) was expressed, and the protein was purified as described in ref.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Expression and Purification of Bcl-2 1–217.
    </title>
    <p>
     pHISparallel BCl-2 1–217 vector (provided by V. Shoshan-Barmatz, Ben-Gurion University of the Negev) was transformed into
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     BL21 cells. Cultures were grown at 37°C in 2× YT medium to an optical density at 600 nm of ≈0.8 and induced with 1 mM isopropyl-1-thio-β-
     <span>
      d
     </span>
     -galactoside (IPTG). Cells were harvested after 16 h of incubation at 22°C. The protein was purified on a fast-flow, 7.8-ml Ni Sepharose HP (100 × 10 mm) column (Amersham Biosciences), using an FPLC system (ÁKTA Explorer; Amersham Biosciences). The sample was further purified by filtration on a Sephacryl S100 column (950 × 26 mm; Amersham Biosciences). Ten percent glycerol was used throughout the purification to reduce aggregation.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Peptide Array Screening.
    </title>
    <p>
     The Bcl peptide array was synthesized by JPT. The peptides were acetylated at their N terminus (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      3
     </xref>
     ). Binding of human ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     to the cellulose-bound peptides was screened according to the protocol by Rüdiger
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      5
     </xref>
     ) with slight modifications as described in ref.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     . The binding was detected by using rabbit anti-ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     antibody that was produced in house.
    </p>
    <p>
     A second peptide array, derived from the ASPP2 sequence, was synthesized by INTAVIS Bioanalytical Instruments (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     ). The peptide array was immersed for 4 h in blocking solution (BS) [50 mM Tris·HCl (pH 7.5), 0.15 M NaCl, 0.05% Tween 20, nonfat dry milk 3.5%] and prewashed three times in TBST. Bcl-2 in final concentration of 2 μM was diluted with BS and incubated with the array overnight at 4°C. Washing steps included two times for 5 min in BS and three times for 5 min TBST. The binding was detected with Bcl-2-specific polyclonal rabbit antiserum, using a chemiluminescence blotting substrate Super Signal reagent (Beit Haemek) according to the manufacturer's instructions.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Peptide Synthesis and Purification.
    </title>
    <p>
     Peptides were synthesized on Applied Biosystems 433A peptide synthesizer, using standard Fmoc chemistry as described in ref.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     . Peptides were biotin- or fluorescein-labeled at the N terminus as described in refs.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     and
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA).
    </title>
    <p>
     ELISA detecting of the binding between biotinylated peptides (derived from Bcl-2 proteins) to ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     adsorbed to MaxiSorp plates (Nunc) was performed as described in ref.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Fluorescence Spectroscopy.
    </title>
    <p>
     Measurements were performed as described in refs.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     and
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     . Briefly, the fluorescein-labeled peptide [0.1 μM in 20 mM Hepes buffer (pH 7.3), 42 mM NaCl, 5% glycerol, and 5 mM DTT] was placed in a cuvette, and the nonlabeled protein was added at 1-min intervals and stirred for 10 sec. Dissociation constants (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ) were calculated by fitting the fluorescence titration curves (corrected for dilution) to 1:1 binding model (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Kinetic Measurements.
    </title>
    <p>
     All experiments were performed by using a Bio-Rad ProteOn XPR36 array biosensor that provides high throughput and a parallel processing approach with an SPR-based detector. The system was equilibrated with PBS-T buffer [20 mM Na-phosphate, 5 mM DTT, 105 mM NaCl, 0.005% Tween 20 (pH 7.4)]. Each SPR experiment used multichannel detection. At each channel, a different biotinylated peptide was captured to a ProteOn NLC sensor chip at 25°C, using a flow rate of 30 μl/min. One clear channel served as reference. This resulted in peptides coupled at response levels of 100–500 RU. For binding measures, ASPP2
     <sub>
      Ank-SH3
     </sub>
     was injected simultaneously (a single injection) at six different concentrations at a flow rate of 50 μl/min. The data for each analyte concentration series collected over the same target density surface were fit to the Langmuir 1:1 interaction model by using the integrated ProteOn Manager software. The average standard deviation was approximately ±5%. The equilibrium dissociation constant (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ) was derived from the
     <em>
      k
     </em>
     <sub>
      diss
     </sub>
     /
     <em>
      k
     </em>
     <sub>
      ass
     </sub>
     ratio (kinetics). Data from the binding equilibria of the peptides were also used to calculate an affinity value independent of the binding kinetics (equilibrium).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Docking Analysis.
    </title>
    <p>
     For the docking studies, we used PatchDock (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ), which is based on shape complementarity of surface patches, and RosettaDock (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      22
     </xref>
     ), which is based on simultaneous optimization of side-chain conformation and rigid body position of the two docking partners.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Supporting Information:
    </strong>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Acknowledgments.
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     We thank Prof. Gideon Schreiber, Prof. Atan Gross, Prof. Varda Shoshan-Barmaz, Prof. Moshe Kotler, Dr. Ora Furman, and Prof. Abraham Loyter for their invaluable help. This study was supported by a career development award from the Human Frontier Science Program Organization (to A.F.) and by a grant from the Israeli Cancer Association (to A.F.). H.B. is supported by a postdoctoral fellowship from the Lady Davis Fellowship Trust. S. Rüdiger was supported by a Marie Curie Excellence Grant of the European Union, a VIDI grant of the Netherlands Science Organization, and a High Potential grant of Utrecht University.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
