<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2011.01.026
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Linker length dependent binding of a focal adhesion kinase derived peptide to the Src SH3–SH2 domains
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      NMR spectroscopy
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Calorimetry
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Signalling
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Biophysics
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The Src family kinases (SFKs) are prototypical modular signalling proteins. SFKs share a common domain structure with an N-terminal myristoylation site, followed by a region that is unique for each family member, a Src homology 3 (SH3) domain, a Src homology 2 (SH2) domain, a tyrosine kinase domain and a C-terminal region containing a self-inhibitory tyrosine residue
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . The SH3 and SH2 domains are protein-interaction domains found in a large number of signalling proteins
    <a>
     [2]
    </a>
    . SH3 domains, first discovered in 1988
    <a>
     [3]
    </a>
    , bind to proline-rich sequences that adopt a left-handed helical conformation
    <a>
     [4]
    </a>
    , whereas SH2 domains recognize phosphorylated tyrosine residues. The SH2 and SH3 domains play a role both in regulating kinase activity and in recognition of substrates
    <a>
     [5]
    </a>
    . Fragments encompassing the SH3–SH2 domains (SH3SH2) from several SFKs have been characterized biochemically, structurally and computationally
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [7]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [10]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [11]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [14]
    </a>
    , because of the importance of these domains for the functioning of SFKs. Another tyrosine kinase, focal adhesion kinase (FAK), activates the SFKs Src and Fyn via interactions with their SH2 and SH3 domains
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [15]
    </a>
    . The linker region between the FERM (4.1 protein, ezrin, radixin, moesin; residues 35–355 for human FAK) and catalytic domain (residues 420–680) of FAK contains a tyrosine residue, Y397, which becomes phosphorylated in connection with FAK activation
    <a>
     [16]
    </a>
    . N-Terminal to the tyrosine, the linker contains a proline-rich region of the sequence RALPSIPKL (residues 368–376). These residues contain the SH3 domain binding motif PxxP
    <a>
     [17]
    </a>
    , whereas the phosphotyrosine region with sequence pYAEI is close to the consensus sequence for SH2 domain binding
    <a>
     [18]
    </a>
    . Peptides derived from FAK spanning both the proline-rich and phosphotyrosine sites have been shown to bind to SH3SH2 fragments in a bidentate manner
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    . It has been demonstrated that the interaction between the FAK peptide and the Fyn SH3SH2 domains is restricted to the canonical SH3 and SH2 binding sites and that the interaction does not affect the dynamic independence of the two domains
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    . The SH3 and SH2 domain binding motifs in the FAK fragment are separated by 22 amino acids, approximately 10 residues more than required to span the distance between the peptide-binding faces on the SH3 and SH2 domains
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    . This allows for simultaneous association of the SH3 and SH2 domains with their respective binding sites in the peptide. The presence of an SH3 binding motif is, however, somewhat puzzling, because SH3 interactions are weak compared to those of the SH2 domain and thus contribute little to the binding affinity. Furthermore, the long spacer separating the binding motifs would be expected to abolish or at least reduce the potential for cooperative binding, as has been reported for Fyn
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    . Here, we report on NMR and ITC experiments on the interaction between the Src SH3–SH2 combined domains and peptides based on the FAK binding motifs, separated by increasingly shorter spacers. The full length spacer ensures that both motifs bind to the SH3 and SH2 domains of the same protein molecule. Reduction of spacer length does not lead to cooperative binding. With short spacers peptide-mediated SH3–SH2 dimerisation becomes prominent. Interestingly, even with a spacer of only three amino acids dimerisation is observed.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and methods
   </title>
   <title>
    2.1. Materials
   </title>
   <p>
    Protein production and peptide synthesis are described in the
    <a>
     Supplementary material
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.2. Nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy
   </title>
   <p>
    NMR samples contained the
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-labelled protein in 20 mM potassium phosphate pH 6.5, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT and 6% D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O. All NMR experiments were performed at 303 K on a Bruker DMX600 spectrometer equipped with a TCI-Z-GRAD cryoprobe (Bruker, Karlsruhe, Germany). The data were processed with Azara (
    <a>
     http://www.bio.cam.ac.uk/azara/
    </a>
    ) and analyzed using Ansig for Windows
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Assignments were based on published work and checked with 3D NOESY-HSQC and 3D TOCSY-HSQC spectra recorded on a
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N SH3SH2 sample. Peptide titrations were performed through the addition of microliter aliquots of peptide stock solution with a concentration ranging from 1 to 5 mM to an SH3SH2 sample of 200 μM. Two-dimensional [
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N,
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H]-HSQC spectra were recorded at every step of the titration. Chemical shift perturbation (CSP) analysis is described in the
    <a>
     Supplementary material
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.3. Isothermal titration calorimetry
   </title>
   <p>
    Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) experiments were performed at 303 K in solutions of 20 mM HEPES pH 6.8, 100 mM NaCl and 1 mM TCEP on a Microcal (Northampton, MA) VP-ITC microcalorimeter. Experimental details can be found in the
    <a>
     Supplementary material
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    3. Results and discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    NMR titrations and ITC experiments were performed to characterize the interactions between the Src SH3SH2 protein fragment and peptides derived from the SH3 and SH2 domain binding sites in FAK, with gradually shorter spacers between the binding sites (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). The control peptides p2 and p3 comprise the isolated SH2 and SH3 binding motifs of FAK, respectively. Peptide p2 binds to the SH3SH2 protein with an equilibrium dissociation constant (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    ) of 140 nM (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Fig. S1
    </a>
    ) and the interaction is in the slow exchange regime on the NMR time scale (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    ). In contrast, peptide p3 binds to the SH3 domain with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of 212 μM, three orders of magnitude higher. Association and dissociation are fast on the NMR time-scale.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Peptides derived from FAK (SH3 and SH2 binding motifs underlined) with the decreasing length of the spacer between the SH3 binding site (RALPSIP) and the SH2 binding site (pYAEI). The peptides containing only the SH3 or SH2 binding motif are also shown. pY denotes a phosphotyrosine residue. All peptides were acetylated and amidated on the N-, and C-termini, respectively.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Peptide
          </th>
          <th>
           Sequence
          </th>
          <th>
           Number of residues removed compared to FAK sequence
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p32
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANSEKQGMRTHAVSVSETDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           0
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-3
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANSEKQGMAVSVSETDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           3
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-7
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANSEKQSVSETDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           7
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-11
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANSESETDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           11
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-15
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANTDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-16
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLANDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           16
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-17
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KLADD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           17
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-19
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-19∗
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KDD
           <span>
            YAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p2
          </td>
          <td>
           ETDD
           <span>
            pYAEI
           </span>
           IDEED
          </td>
          <td>
           –
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p3
          </td>
          <td>
           <span>
            RALPSIP
           </span>
           KL
          </td>
          <td>
           –
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 2.
        </span>
        <p>
         Thermodynamic parameters for peptides binding to Src SH3SH2. Uncertainties in
         <em>
          K
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          ΔH
         </em>
         and
         <em>
          ΔG
         </em>
         are the standard deviations of three experiments, the uncertainty in
         <em>
          TΔS
         </em>
         was calculated using standard error propagation.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Peptide
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (M)
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            ΔH
           </em>
           (kcal mol
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            TΔS
           </em>
           (kcal mol
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            ΔG
           </em>
           (kcal mol
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p3
          </td>
          <td>
           2.1 ± 0.1 × 10
           <sup>
            −4
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           −15.5 ± 0.7
          </td>
          <td>
           −10.4 ± 0.7
          </td>
          <td>
           −5.1 ± 0.1
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p2
          </td>
          <td>
           1.4 ± 0.5 × 10
           <sup>
            −7
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           −9.4 ± 0.3
          </td>
          <td>
           0.1 ± 0.4
          </td>
          <td>
           −9.4 ± 0.1
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-7
          </td>
          <td>
           2.8 ± 0.3 × 10
           <sup>
            −8
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           −20.5 ± 0.3
          </td>
          <td>
           −10.1 ± 0.3
          </td>
          <td>
           −10.5 ± 0.1
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           p-19
          </td>
          <td>
           4.2 ± 0.2 × 10
           <sup>
            −7
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           −12.1 ± 0.1
          </td>
          <td>
           −3.2 ± 0.1
          </td>
          <td>
           −8.8 ± 0.1
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Detail from HSQC spectra of Src SH3SH2 in titrations with peptides (A) p3, (B) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Detail from HSQC spectra of Src SH3SH2 in titrations with peptides (A) p3, (B) p2 and (C) p32. Spectra from several titration points are shown overlaid, with starting points (free protein) in black and titration end points shown in purple. Residues T17 and G155 are in the SH3 and SH2 binding sites, respectively.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (119 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Titrations of SH3SH2 with peptide p32, which contains both the SH3 and SH2 binding motifs separated by the full-length sequence as found in FAK, leads to chemical shift perturbations (CSPs) in the SH3 and SH2 domains that are similar to those caused by peptides p3 and p2 (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    ), indicating that the p32–SH3SH2 interaction is confined to the SH3 and SH2 peptide binding sites on the protein. The chemical exchange behaviour for SH3 amides in the titration with p32 is slow, contrary to that observed in the titration with p3 (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    ), because exchange of p32 between protein molecules is limited by the slow release from the SH2 binding site.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Average CSP in Src SH3SH2 caused by peptide binding are colour-coded on the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         Average CSP in Src SH3SH2 caused by peptide binding are colour-coded on the protein surface (PDB entry 1FMK
         <a>
          [20]
         </a>
         ). (A) Peptide p3 at a peptide-to-protein molar ratio of 10:1; (B) peptide p2 at a ratio of 5:1; (C) peptide p32 at a ratio 1.5:1; (D) peptide p-19 at a ratio of 10:1. Red:
         <em>
          Δδ
         </em>
         <sub>
          avg
         </sub>
         ⩾ 0.3 ppm; orange: 0.3 &gt;
         <em>
          Δδ
         </em>
         <sub>
          avg
         </sub>
         ⩾ 0.1 ppm; yellow: 0.1 &gt;
         <em>
          Δδ
         </em>
         <sub>
          avg
         </sub>
         ⩾ 0.04 ppm; blue:
         <em>
          Δδ
         </em>
         <sub>
          avg
         </sub>
         &lt; 0.04 ppm. Non-assigned residues are shown in grey. The figure was generated using PyMol (DeLano Scientific, Palo Alto).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (450 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Due to solubility problems for the longest peptides p32 and p-3, no high-quality ITC data could be obtained for these peptides. For peptide p-7, which is still long enough to span the distance between the SH3 domain and SH2 domain peptide binding sites on the SH3SH2 protein, ITC data (
    <a>
     Fig. S1
    </a>
    ) were fitted to a one-site binding model, yielding a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of 28 nM (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). This value agrees well with those determined with surface plasmon resonance and ITC by Thomas et al.
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    and Arold et al.
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    , for the binding of the Src and Fyn SH3SH2 domains to a FAK peptide containing both the SH3 and SH2 binding sites. Comparison with the results for p3 or p2 binding to SH3SH2 shows that the free energy change upon binding the peptide containing both an SH3 and SH2 binding motif is less than the sum of the free energy changes upon binding p2 and p3 (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ), indicating that the binding is anti-cooperative. This result is in agreement with what has been shown for the SH3SH2 domains of Fyn. It was proposed that restriction of the conformational freedom of the FAK peptide, together with possible binding-induced partial structure in the peptide, causes a small entropic penalty
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    . In the absence of favourable contributions from additional contacts outside the SH3 and SH2 binding sites, this leads to anti-cooperative binding. However, in contrast to the Fyn-FAK data, our results indicate an enthalpic penalty. The entropy term for p-7 binding equals the sum of those for p2 and p3 binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    Examination of the exchange characteristics of SH2 and SH3 resonances in NMR titrations with gradually shorter peptides into an SH3SH2 sample shows that for all peptides containing the phosphotyrosine the SH2 domain resonances remain in slow exchange. The SH3 resonances show the features of increasing exchange rates with decreasing linker length (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Detail from HSQC spectra of Src SH3SH2 showing SH3 domain residue G35 in ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         Detail from HSQC spectra of Src SH3SH2 showing SH3 domain residue G35 in titrations with peptides with decreasing separation between the SH2 and SH3 binding motifs (A–H). A titration with peptide p3, containing only the SH3-binding site, is shown in I. Spectra from several titration points are shown overlaid, with starting points (free protein) in black and titration end points shown in purple.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (567 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    For the shorter peptides, such as p-17 and p-19, the distance between the two binding motifs is too small for the peptide to bind to both domains simultaneously, causing the domains to compete for peptide binding. Rearrangement of the SH3 and SH2 domains to allow for simultaneous binding would require substantial domain movements, which would be reflected in considerable chemical shift perturbations of the residues linking the domains. The chemical shift perturbations for most of these residues are small, however. Thus, it was expected that in a titration p-17 and p-19 would first fill the high affinity site on the SH2 domain and only bind to the SH3 domain when the peptide–protein ratio was larger than one.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    However, CSPs were observed for SH3 resonances already at low ratios (
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    , inset). Apparently, the SH3 domain is able to bind the short peptides, even when the latter are bound to the SH2 binding site. Intramolecular binding is not possible for these peptides, so we inferred that intermolecular binding, i.e., peptide mediated SH3SH2 dimerisation, must be occurring at low peptide-to-protein ratios. At ratios well above equimolar, the excess of peptide enables the formation of complexes of two peptide molecules to one protein molecule. Consequently, the binding behaviour is expected to be at least biphasic for the CSPs of SH3 domain residues. One
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    describes the binding of an SH3 domain to a peptide already bound via its phosphotyrosine to another protein molecule (
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si1.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    ) and another relates to SH3 domain binding to a free peptide (
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si2.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    ). The model is illustrated in
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    . The CSP shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    for peptide p-19 cannot be fitted with a standard 1:1 binding curve (dotted line). A global simulation on the basis of the model reproduces the data well, as shown for the three residues, yielding
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si3.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = 550 μM and
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si4.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = 190 μM. Interestingly, the maximum CSP for residues Thr33 and Gly35, both in the SH3 domain, are the same for both phases (
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="19" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="32" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si5.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    =
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="19" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="32" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si6.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Eq. (S2)
    </a>
    ). The mode of peptide binding on the SH3 domain is apparently the same in both types of complexes. For the
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N amide nucleus of linker residue Thr166, this is not the case, with
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="19" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="32" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si7.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = −1.2 and
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="19" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="32" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si8.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = −0.52 ppm. Similar results were found for peptide p-17, with
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si9.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = 410 μM and
    <a>
     <img/>
     <noscript>
      &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si10.gif"&gt;
     </noscript>
    </a>
    = 105 μM (
    <a>
     Fig. S2
    </a>
    ). The control peptide p-19∗, in which the tyrosine is not phosphorylated, showed only CSP on the SH3 domain, indicating that SH2 binding was abolished. It exhibited a standard 1:1 binding curve for SH3 domain binding, with
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    = 116 μM (
    <a>
     Fig. S3
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Chemical shift perturbations for several 15N amide nuclei in SH3SH2 upon ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         Chemical shift perturbations for several
         <sup>
          15
         </sup>
         N amide nuclei in SH3SH2 upon titration with peptide p-19. The solid line and circles represents the data simulated with the model discussed in the text, with
         <a>
          <img/>
          <noscript>
           &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si11.gif"&gt;
          </noscript>
         </a>
         = 550 μM and
         <a>
          <img/>
          <noscript>
           &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si12.gif"&gt;
          </noscript>
         </a>
         = 190 μM. The best global fit to a 1:1 binding model is shown as a dotted line. The inset shows the lower part of the graph plotted on a linear scale.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (167 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Model of two-phase peptide binding. SH3-mediated dimer formation occurs with ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         Model of two-phase peptide binding. SH3-mediated dimer formation occurs with
         <a>
          <img/>
          <noscript>
           &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si13.gif"&gt;
          </noscript>
         </a>
         and binding of an SH3 domain to a free peptide occurs with
         <a>
          <img/>
          <noscript>
           &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="35" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si14.gif"&gt;
          </noscript>
         </a>
         . The dissociation constant for peptide bound to the SH2 domain is
         <a>
          <img/>
          <noscript>
           &lt;img height="20" border="0" style="vertical-align:bottom" width="36" alt="View the MathML source" title="View the MathML source" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579311000561-si15.gif"&gt;
          </noscript>
         </a>
         .
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (108 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    ITC experiments for peptide p-19 interacting with SH3SH2 yielded a single binding site with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    value of 0.4 μM (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Fig. S1
    </a>
    ), close to the value for peptide p2. Apparently, the ITC experiment only detects the binding of the SH2 domain to the peptide and is insensitive for the additional weak SH3 domain binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    The results of this study demonstrate that a reduction of the linker length between the SH3 and SH2 binding motifs in FAK does not increase the affinity for the SH3 domain.
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    shows that the dissociation rate for the SH3 domain increases, even for the slight reductions in linker length. For the long peptides, binding simultaneously to the SH3 and SH2 domains of SH3SH2, association to the SH3 domain occurs in the slow exchange regime, whereas for the peptides that only bind the SH3 domain (p3, p-19∗) the fast exchange regime is observed. This finding indicates that SH3 binding in the long peptides is coupled to SH2 binding and thus must occur within the same SH3SH2 molecule. Upon tight binding to the SH2 domain, the ‘local concentration’ of the SH3 domain of the same SH3SH2 molecule is very high and outcompetes binding to the SH3 domain of a second SH3SH2 molecule. Reduction of the linker to a length that is insufficient for simultaneous intramolecular binding to both domains showed, however, that the SH3SH2 dimer formation readily occurs in that case, even with a linker that separates the SH3 and SH2 binding motifs by merely three residues (peptide p-19), as is illustrated by
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Fig. S2
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    These findings raise the question why the SH3 binding site is present in FAK. The affinity for the SH2 site is about three orders of magnitude greater, so the contribution to the free energy of binding of the SH3 interaction is negligible. In fact, the binding of both domains exhibits negative cooperativity, at least for the FAK peptide. The structural independence of the binding to the two Src domains, as evident from the binding maps (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    ) and dimerisation behaviour of the short peptides, lead us to speculate that the SH3 binding could be important in a situation in which Tyr397 is not (yet) phosphorylated or unavailable and thus the interaction with the SH2 is insignificant or does not occur. It is known that FAK activation occurs as a combination of autophosphorylation and interaction with Src. Perhaps colocalisation and the initial weak FAK–Src SH3 interaction form the first step in the FAK activation process. This hypothesis is currently under investigation.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Supplementary data 1.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       General procedure and supplementary figures.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with DOC files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (905 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [1]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.J. Boggon, M.J. Eck
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure and regulation of Src family kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 23 (2004), pp. 7918–7927
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [2]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I.D. Campbell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Modular proteins at the cell surface
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Soc. Trans., 31 (2003), pp. 1107–1114
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [3]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.J. Mayer, M. Hamaguchi, H. Hanafusa
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel viral oncogene with structural similarity to phospholipase-C
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 332 (1988), pp. 272–275
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [4]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.S.C. Li
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Specificity and versatility of SH3 and other proline-recognition domains: structural basis and implications for cellular signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 390 (2005), pp. 641–653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [5]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.J. Yeatman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A renaissance for SRC
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Cancer, 4 (2004), pp. 470–480
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [6]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Panchamoorthy, T. Fukazawa, L. Stolz, G. Payne, K. Reedquist, S. Shoelson, Z. Songyang, L. Cantley, C. Walsh, H. Band
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Physical and functional interactions between SH2 and SH3 domains of the Src family protein tyrosine kinase p59(Fyn)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 14 (1994), pp. 6372–6385
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [7]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Tessari, L.N. Gentile, S.J. Taylor, D.I. Shalloway, L.K. Nicholson, G.W. Vuister
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Heteronuclear NMR studies of the combined Src homology domains 2 and 3 of pp60 c-Src: effects of phosphopeptide binding
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 36 (1997), pp. 14561–14571
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [8]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.W. Thomas, B. Ellis, R.J. Boerner, W.B. Knight, G.C. White, M.D. Schaller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH2- and SH3-mediated interactions between focal adhesion kinase and Src
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 577–583
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [9]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.T. Arold, T.S. Ulmer, T.D. Mulhern, J.M. Werner, J.E. Ladbury, I.D. Campbell, M.E.M. Noble
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The role of the Src homology 3-Src homology 2 interface in the regulation of Src kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 17199–17205
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [10]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.A. Young, S. Gonfloni, G. Superti-Furga, B. Roux, J. Kuriyan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dynamic coupling between the SH2 and SH3 domains of c-Src and hck underlies their inactivation by C-terminal tyrosine phosphorylation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 105 (2001), pp. 115–126
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [11]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.S. Ulmer, J.M. Werner, I.D. Campbell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3-SH2 domain orientation in Src kinases: NMR studies of Fyn
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure, 10 (2002), pp. 901–911
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [12]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Hofmann, K. Schweimer, A. Kiessling, E. Hofinger, F. Bauer, S. Hoffmann, P. Rosch, I.D. Campbell, J.M. Werner, H. Sticht
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Binding, domain orientation, and dynamics of the lck SH3–SH2 domain pair and comparison with other Src-family kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 44 (2005), pp. 13043–13050
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [13]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.M. Hochrein, E.C. Lerner, A.P. Schiavone, T.E. Smithgall, J.R. Engen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         An examination of dynamics crosstalk between SH2 and SH3 domains by hydrogen/deuterium exchange and mass spectrometry
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Sci., 15 (2006), pp. 65–73
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [14]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.D. Faraldo-Gomez, B. Roux
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         On the importance of a funneled energy landscape for the assembly and regulation of multidomain Src tyrosine kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 104 (2007), pp. 13643–13648
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [15]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.S. Cobb, M.D. Schaller, T.H. Leu, J.T. Parsons
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Stable association of pp60(Src) and pp59(Fyn) with the focal adhesion associated protein tyrosine kinase, pp125(Fak)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 14 (1994), pp. 147–155
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [16]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.K. Mitra, D.A. Hanson, D.D. Schlaepfer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Focal adhesion kinase: in command and control of cell motility
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 6 (2005), pp. 56–68
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [17]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.B. Cohen, R.B. Ren, D. Baltimore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Modular binding domains in signal-transduction proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 80 (1995), pp. 237–248
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [18]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.Y. Zhou, S.E. Shoelson, M. Chaudhuri, G. Gish, T. Pawson, W.G. Haser, F. King, T. Roberts, S. Ratnofsky, R.J. Lechleider, B.G. Neel, R.B. Birge, J.E. Fajardo, M.M. Chou, H. Hanafusa, B. Schaffhausen, L.C. Cantley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH2 domains recognize specific phosphopeptide sequences
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 72 (1993), pp. 767–778
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [19]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Helgstrand, P. Kraulis, P. Allard, T. Hard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ansig for Windows: an interactive computer program for semiautomatic assignment of protein NMR spectra
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biomol. NMR, 18 (2000), pp. 329–336
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [20]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.Q. Xu, S.C. Harrison, M.J. Eck
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Three-dimensional structure of the tyrosine kinase c-Src
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 385 (1997), pp. 595–602
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2011 Federation of European Biochemical Societies. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>