<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2011.05.015
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    The INAD Scaffold Is a Dynamic, Redox-Regulated Modulator of Signaling in the Drosophila Eye
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Scaffold proteins serve as platforms in signaling pathways by nucleating multiple proteins into macromolecular complexes and targeting them to specific regions within cells, and are critical for both efficiency and specificity of signaling events (
    <a>
     Bhattacharyya et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pawson and Nash, 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhang and Wang, 2003
    </a>
    ). The
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    visual PDZ domain protein Inactivation, no after-potential D (INAD) is one of the best understood model systems for the roles of scaffolding in signal transduction (
    <a>
     Huber, 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Montell, 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Tsunoda and Zuker, 1999
    </a>
    ). Within the microvilli of fly photoreceptor cells, INAD organizes the core components of the phototransduction pathway into a supramolecular complex, involving the Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -permeable transient receptor potential (TRP) channel, phospholipase Cβ (PLCβ/NORPA), and eye-specific protein kinase C (ePKC) via distinct PDZ domains, thus efficiently linking the G protein-coupled receptor rhodopsin to the Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -mediated signaling cascades (
    <a>
     Adamski et al., 1998
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Chevesich et al., 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Huber et al., 1996a
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kimple et al., 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Montell, 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Peng et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Shieh and Zhu, 1996
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Tsunoda et al., 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     van Huizen et al., 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wang and Montell, 2007
    </a>
    ). In this cascade, light photoisomerises rhodopsin, which activates PLCβ via the heterotrimeric Gq protein. PLCβ hydrolyses phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ), releasing inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ) and 1,2-diacylglycerol (DAG) and a proton, which leads to opening of TRP channels, and depolarization of photoreceptor cells (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ; for reviews, see
    <a>
     Hardie and Raghu, 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wang and Montell, 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hardie and Postma, 2008
    </a>
    ). DAG is also a potent activator of eye-PKC which phosphorylates both TRP and INAD and plays a key role in the termination of the light response (
    <a>
     Popescu et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Smith et al., 1991
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hardie et al., 1993
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Gu et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Huber et al., 1996b
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Peng et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Via the INAD-mediated assembly of the signaling complex, fly photoreceptors can respond to light with extremely fast kinetics (for reviews, see
    <a>
     Tsunoda and Zuker, 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Huber, 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hardie and Raghu, 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wang and Montell, 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hardie and Postma, 2008
    </a>
    ) and adapt to a huge dynamic range of light intensities (
    <a>
     Juusola and Hardie, 2001
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    A recent study indicated that in addition to acting as a master scaffolding protein, INAD plays a critical dynamic role in regulating phototransduction on a millisecond timescale (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). Namely, a pair of Cys residues in INAD PDZ5 (Cys606 and Cys645) undergo reversible, disulfide-mediated oxidation in response to light. When flies are kept in the dark, the two Cys residues in PDZ5 are in the reduced form. Upon exposure to bright light, PDZ5 is converted to the oxidized state by formation of the intramolecular Cys606-Cys645 disulfide bond. Importantly, the authors demonstrated that this transient, light-dependent disulfide-mediated oxidation is required for efficient visual signal termination as well as visually mediated reflex behavior of flies (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    However, there are a number of major conceptual challenges regarding the mechanistic basis of the INAD-mediated dynamic signaling. Most critically, the redox potential surrounding the INAD-organized signaling complex microvilli is not expected to fluctuate with large amplitude on a millisecond timescale in response to light. This immediately begs the question: how is the light-dependent, transient disulfide bond formation/breaking of INAD PDZ5 achieved? Additionally, it was shown that the ePKC is required for the conformational switch of PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). However, PDZ5 does not contain any obvious PKC phosphorylation sites. Furthermore, it is not clear how INAD PDZ5 maintains the reduced state when flies are kept in dark as the PDZ5 disulfide is highly stable due to its extremely negative redox potential. Finally, although the structure of INAD PDZ5 in its oxidized form contains a somewhat deformed target-binding groove (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ), it has not been proven that the target binding of INAD PDZ5 is disulfide bond dependent.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Here, we demonstrate that the redox potential of INAD PDZ5 is allosterically regulated by the direct conformational coupling of the fourth and fifth PDZ domains. Formation of the PDZ45 supramodule locks PDZ5 in the reduced state. Acidification uncouples the PDZ45 tandem and thereby unlocks its reduced conformation followed by the dissociation of the TRP channel from PDZ5. The allosteric regulation of the redox potential fluctuation of the INAD PDZ5 disulfide bond at a range of ∼330 mV is unprecedented for cellular signaling proteins. This protein redox potential regulation mechanism may have general implications in other cell signaling processes that utilize disulfide bond containing intracellular proteins. Finally, regulation of protein conformational couplings by protons originating from PLC-mediated PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    hydrolysis may represent a new paradigm for cellular signal transduction in general.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Identification of Specific INAD PDZ5 Ligands
   </title>
   <p>
    The most plausible explanation for the INAD PDZ5 disulfide-mediated visual signal regulation is that the two PDZ5 conformers have distinct target-binding properties. Oxidation of PDZ5 may cause temporary dissociation of its target, and thereby terminate signaling. Although PDZ5 has been implied to interact with PLCβ (
    <a>
     Tsunoda et al., 1997
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     van Huizen et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), the direct interaction between PDZ5/PLCβ remains controversial (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Xu et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), partly due to a sequencing error of PLCβ (the penultimate residue should be a “Tyr” instead of a “Cys” as originally reported). Identification of a specific PDZ5 target would be highly valuable in evaluating the mechanistic basis of the redox-dependent target binding of the domain. Aided by structure-based prediction of potential PDZ5 binders, we screened a small PDZ-binding peptide library. Among twelve peptides tested, the carboxyl peptide of proteoglycan NG2 showed the highest binding affinity toward reduced PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). These data also demonstrated that a bulky aromatic residue at the −2 position is critical, and Trp at the −1 position is highly preferred for carboxyl peptides to bind to PDZ5. The
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    ortholog of NG2 is Kon-tiki/Perdido (Kon/Perd), which has the same C-terminal four amino acids as NG2 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). As expected, the Kon peptide binds to PDZ5 with the same affinity as the NG2 peptide (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). A search of the
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    genome for proteins containing the carboxyl tail peptide sequences of “YWΨ” (“Ψ” represents Val, Leu, and Ile) identified Kon/Perd as the only match. Although the physiological relevance, if any, of the INAD PDZ5/Kon interaction is unknown, identification of Kon as a high-affinity PDZ5 ligand provides a powerful tool for investigating the impact of the PDZ5 conformational switch on its target binding. We demonstrate that the reduced-to-oxidized conformational transition of PDZ5 induces a ∼20-fold decrease in its affinity for the Kon peptide (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B; see
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    A–S1C available online), supporting the structure-based prediction that oxidation of PDZ5 can weaken its target binding (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Discovery of Specific Binding Targets of INAD PDZ5(A) Summary of the screening ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (888 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Kon Peptide-Binding Properties of PDZ5 in Reduced and Oxidized Forms, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1004 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Solution Structure of the INAD PDZ5-Kon Tail Peptide Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    To elucidate the molecular mechanism governing their specific interaction, we solved the solution structure of the reduced PDZ5/Kon peptide complex (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C;
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    D and
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). INAD PDZ5 adopts a canonical PDZ fold similar to its ligand-free form (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C) (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). The Kon peptide binds to the αB/βB groove of INAD PDZ5 by pairing antiparallelly with βB. The side chain of Val(0) of the Kon peptide inserts into the hydrophobic pocket at the end of the αB/βB groove. The side chain of Trp(−1) makes extensive contacts with Ile612 from βC and Ser598 from βB of PDZ5. A hydrogen bond between the side-chain amide of Trp(−1) and the backbone carbonyl of Gln(−3) further stabilizes the bound peptide. The side chain of Tyr(−2) is sandwiched between the aromatic rings of Tyr646 and Phe642 from αB (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D). The complex structure explains the high selectivity of PDZ5 for the Trp(−1) and Tyr(−2) in the Kon peptide.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Isolated PDZ5 Cannot Spontaneously Cycle between the Reduced and Oxidized Conformers
   </title>
   <p>
    In view of fast timescale of the fly visual signaling, we asked whether INAD PDZ5 might be able to cycle rapidly between the reduced and oxidized conformations by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy. The NMR spectrum of PDZ5 purified with buffer containing 1 mM DTT showed two distinct sets of peaks, each corresponding to the reduced and oxidized states (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    A). The result indicates that 1 mM DTT cannot reduce PDZ5 and the coexisting reduced and oxidized conformers exchange at a slow NMR timescale. PDZ5 could be completely oxidized when the purified protein was passed through a preparative gel filtration column twice with the column buffer undegassed and free of reducing reagent (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A, top trace). Upon addition of 10 mM DTT, the oxidized PDZ underwent a time-dependent conversion to its reduced state (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    A and 2B). The measured rate constant (from oxidized to reduced state) is ∼0.3 M
    <sup>
     -1
    </sup>
    · min
    <sup>
     -1
    </sup>
    , which is very slow considering the fast fly visual signaling events. We further measured the standard redox potential of the Cys606-Cys645 disulfide bond by NMR spectroscopy using DTT as the redox potential buffer (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). The conversion reaction at each DTT concentration was considered to be in equilibrium if the peak intensities of two spectra acquired for the same mixture were the same after 5 hr. The measured standard redox potential for the Cys606-Cys645 disulfide formation is −0.37 V (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D), a value far below the standard redox potentials of the cytoplasmic milieu in most cells (−0.2∼−0.3 V) (
    <a>
     Keese et al., 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Ostergaard et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Schafer and Buettner, 2001
    </a>
    ). Thus, both kinetic and thermodynamic data indicate that INAD PDZ5 is highly stable in its oxidized form and cannot spontaneously cycle between the reduced and oxidized conformations at speeds compatible with visual signaling. This implies that other factors must interact directly or indirectly with PDZ5 to regulate its redox potential and redox-dependent conformational cycling.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Oxidation Profiles of PDZ5 and PDZ45, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;2 and Figure&amp;nbsp;4(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (564 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Oxidation Kinetics and the Redox Potential of the Isolated PDZ5 and the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr2.gif" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr2.gif" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr2.gif"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (374 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    PDZ4&amp;5 Interact with Each Other to Form a Supramodule
   </title>
   <p>
    Tandem PDZ repeats often display distinct structural and functional properties when compared with individual PDZ domains (
    <a>
     Feng et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Feng and Zhang, 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Long et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). Because the INAD PDZ4 and PDZ5 domains are connected by a short linker with only 5 residues, we hypothesized that the PDZ45 tandem of INAD may also form a supramodule. Extensive trials of the domain boundaries showed that inclusions of a 10 residue extension N-terminal to PDZ4 and the entire C-terminal tail outside PDZ5 (i.e., residues 473–674, referred to as PDZ45 hereafter for simplicity) is essential for obtaining stable PDZ45 tandem samples. Different from the isolated PDZ5, the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H,
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-HSQC NMR spectrum of PDZ45 purified with buffer containing 1 mM DTT showed only one set of well-dispersed peaks, corresponding to the fully reduced state (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A). Comparison of the HSQC spectra of PDZ45 and PDZ5, both in their reduced states, revealed significant chemical shift differences of PDZ5 between its isolated and its PDZ45 tandem forms (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A), indicating that PDZ4 and/or the extensions in the two termini interact with PDZ5. We mapped the chemical shift differences of PDZ5 between the two forms onto its structure (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B). Residues at the beginning of βA and end of βF of PDZ5 showed large chemical shift differences, and such shift changes are expected as these two regions are covalently connected to PDZ4 and the C-terminal extension, respectively, in PDZ45. Importantly, large chemical shift changes were observed for the residues in βB, βC (including Cys606 in the βC1 position), αB (including Cys645 in αB), as well as the rest of the target peptide-binding region of PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B), indicating that the interaction of PDZ4 has a long-range conformational impact on PDZ5. This finding immediately points to the possibility that the light-dependent formation of the disulfide bond in PDZ5 may be allosterically regulated by PDZ4 coupling.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="PDZ4 Physically Interacts with PDZ5 to Form PDZ45 Supramodule, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (916 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Crystal Structure of the PDZ45/NG2 Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    The excellent NMR spectrum of PDZ45 indicates that the protein adopts a monodispersed conformation favorable for crystallization. The structure of the PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex was solved using the single-wavelength anomalous dispersion method with Se-Met derivative and refined to 2.6 Å resolution (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Consistent with the NMR shift perturbation assay (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B), the two PDZ domains in PDZ45 physically interact with each other (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). The interface between the two PDZ domains involves βB′, βC′, αB′, the βB′/βC′ loop, and the αA′/βD′ loop from PDZ4; and βB, βC, βD, the βB/βC loop, and the αA/βD loop from PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    ). Importantly, the C-terminal extension of PDZ5 (residues 664–674) tucks into a groove at the rear (relative to the putative target-binding groove) of PDZ4, physically stapling the two PDZ domains together (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B), revealing that the C terminus is essential for the structural integrity of PDZ45. The N-terminal extension of PDZ4 interacts intimately with residues from βA′ and αA′, explaining why this extension is also necessary for obtaining the properly folded tandem.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Crystal Structure of the PDZ45/NG2 Peptide Complex(A) Ribbon diagram of the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (575 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Consistent with the Ellman assay result, PDZ5 in the PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex is in the reduced form (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). The potential target-binding pocket of PDZ4 is occluded by the αA/βD loop of PDZ5 with the side chain of Arg625 inserting into the αB′/βB′ groove of PDZ4 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). The NG2 peptide binds to PDZ5 in a β-hairpin conformation (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). The last 4 residues of the NG2 peptide bind to PDZ5 in the PDZ45 tandem in an identical manner to the Kon peptide binding to the isolated PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    C). The main difference between the conformations of the target peptides in the NMR-derived PDZ5/Kon peptide complex and the X-ray-derived PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex is the lack of the mini-β strand of the PDZ5-bound Kon peptide (corresponding to Leu
    <sub>
     -8
    </sub>
    -Leu
    <sub>
     -7
    </sub>
    -Arg
    <sub>
     -6
    </sub>
    of the Kon peptide,
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    ), and this difference is likely to be an artifact of crystal packing (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    C and S3D).
   </p>
   <title>
    Formation of the PDZ45 Supramodule Dramatically Raises the Redox Potential of PDZ5
   </title>
   <p>
    The direct interaction between PDZ4&amp;5, together with the PDZ4 coupling-induced long-range conformational impact on PDZ5 revealed by NMR, hints that formation of the PDZ45 supramodule may alter the redox potential of PDZ5. To evaluate this possibility, we compared air-mediated oxidation of PDZ5 in its isolated and in the PDZ45 tandem forms. Reduced PDZ45 could not be oxidized after two or three cycles of gel-filtration chromatography (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). Specifically, we can directly observe that the chemical shifts of Cys606 and Cys645 did not change at all from its reduced conformation during the entire process (highlighted in a green circle in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). In addition to Cys645 and Cys606 in PDZ5, the other three Cys residues in PDZ4 also remained in the reduced form (data not shown). We repeated the same experiment with reduced PDZ5, keeping the concentration of PDZ5 at about double of the PDZ45 to ensure that the total Cys concentrations in the two series of experiments were comparable. In sharp contrast to what was observed for PDZ45, the NMR spectrum of PDZ5 after passing one cycle of the gel filtration column showed that the protein is a mixture of reduced and oxidized forms with a roughly equal population (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B, middle panel). Another cycle of the column fully converted the protein into its oxidized form (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B, right panel). The results shown in
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B indicate that coupling of PDZ4 allosterically alters the local environment of the Cys606&amp;645 pair in PDZ5 and renders them more resistant to oxidation. As the overall conformation of the Cys606&amp;645-harboring αB/βB groove remains largely the same upon forming the PDZ45 supramodule (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    ), the decreased oxygen-mediated oxidation speed of PDZ5 in the PDZ45 tandem likely correlates with an increased redox potential of the Cys606&amp;645 pair in PDZ45.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Formation of the PDZ45 Tandem Prevents the Disulfide-Mediated Oxidation of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (947 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To test the above hypothesis, we measured the standard redox potential of the Cys606-Cys645 disulfide in PDZ45. Because the reduced PDZ45 is highly stable even in sample buffers lacking any reducing reagents such as DTT, we performed PDZ45 oxidation experiment by incubating the protein in 50 mM Tris pH 7.0 containing increasing concentrations of GSSG. The oxidation of PDZ45 was monitored both by the Ellman assay and by NMR spectroscopy. The Ellman assay showed that only ∼40% of total Cys residues (equivalent to two of five Cys) were oxidized when the oxidation reaction reached to an equilibrium state (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    B). To assign which Cys residues were oxidized, we performed a series of time-dependent oxidation reactions of
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N-labeled PDZ45 with increasing concentrations of GSSG. As shown in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C, GSSG-mediated oxidation of PDZ45 induced chemical shift changes to Cys645 (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C1) and Cys606 (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C2). Additionally, a number of other residues from PDZ5 (e.g., Gly596, Leu597, Phe649, Gly651, Ala652), which reside in close vicinity of the PDZ5 αB/βB groove and thus spatially close to Cys606&amp;645, also showed obvious oxidation-induced chemical shift changes. In contrast the three Cys residues in PDZ4 (e.g., Cys539 shown in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C3) did not show detectable chemical shift changes upon PDZ45 oxidation. Taken together, the Ellman assay and NMR studies indicated that incubation of PDZ45 in the GSSG-containing buffer led to specific oxidation of the Cys606&amp;645 pair in the PDZ45 tandem, and the remaining three Cys residues in PDZ4 were not oxidized.
   </p>
   <p>
    The oxidation of PDZ45 by GSSG reached a steady/equilibrium state at ∼7 hr after the initiation of the reaction (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    C). By plotting the fraction of oxidized Cys606-Cys645 in PDZ45 at each equilibrium state as the function of the GSSG concentrations, we were able to measure the redox potential of the Cys606&amp;645 pair in PDZ45, and the value is −0.038 V (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    F). A very similar value (∼−0.040 V) was obtained from the Ellman-based assays (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    B). Taken together, our data unequivocally demonstrate that the formation of the PDZ45 supramodule stabilizes the reduced conformation of PDZ5 by dramatically raising the redox potential of the Cys606&amp;645 pair. It is envisioned that the reduced Cys606 and Cys645 of PDZ45 is highly stable at the intracellular milieu with typical redox potentials of −0.2∼−0.3 V. This is in stark contrast to the isolated PDZ5, of which the oxidized state is highly stable at the same cellular redox potentials (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    ). The standard redox potentials of PDZ5 in its isolated and in the PDZ45 tandem forms suggest that PDZ5 cannot spontaneously cycle between reduced and oxidized forms at the cellular milieu. We also noted that the Cys residues in PDZ45 have a much slower oxidation reaction speed than those in PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    C and S2D). Therefore, it seems that additional factor(s) must function together with cellular oxidant(s) to oxidize the Cys606&amp;645 pair of PDZ5.
   </p>
   <title>
    Acidification Uncouples the PDZ45 Supramodule and Regulates the Conformational Cycling of PDZ5
   </title>
   <p>
    Although PDZ4 modulates the redox potential of PDZ5 allosterically, the formation of the PDZ45 supramodule per se does not affect the target-binding property of PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B;
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    A). We investigated the allosteric conformational coupling between PDZ4&amp;5 in response to the Kon peptide binding using NMR spectroscopy (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    B and S4C). In line with the crystal structure, the Kon peptide specifically binds to PDZ5 (e.g., the large shift changes of Gly596 from the “GLGF” loop of PDZ5), but not to PDZ4 (e.g., no shift change of Gly500 from the “GLGF” loop of PDZ4). Importantly, in addition to residues directly involved in the binding of the Kon peptide, amino acid residues in the interface of PDZ4&amp;5 also experienced substantial target peptide-induced chemical shift changes. This result, together with the data shown in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    , reveals that the redox potential and the target binding of PDZ5 can be allosterically modulated by amino acid residues outside the domain.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Allosteric Coupling of the Two PDZ Domains in the PDZ45 Tandem, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1056 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We then tried to identify a potential regulatory switch for the redox potential cycling of PDZ5. The most obvious candidate was ePKC, as it is required for the light-induced oxidation of PDZ5 (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ), and PKC has been shown to phosphorylate INAD (
    <a>
     Huber et al., 1996b
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Popescu et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). PDZ45 contains two consensus PKC phosphorylation sites: Thr553 in αB of PDZ4 and Thr666 in the C-terminal tail of the tandem (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). The two Thr residues play active roles in the packing of the C-terminal tail with PDZ4 and are therefore necessary for the formation of the PDZ45 supramodule (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    D). Structural analysis predicts that phosphorylation of Thr553 and/or Thr666 would destabilize the interdomain interaction between PDZ4 and PDZ5 and thereby weaken or eliminate the allosteric coupling of the two PDZ domains. If this prediction is correct, the conformational cycling of PDZ5 could be explained by PKC-mediated phosphorylation of PDZ45.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="pH-Regulated, Allosteric Regulation of the PDZ45 Redox Potential(A) The domain ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (533 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To test this hypothesis, we made single and double Thr553Glu, Thr666Glu mutations to mimic PKC-mediated phosphorylation of PDZ45. Indeed, the Thr553,666Glu double mutant of PDZ45 led to enhanced oxidation in the H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    -mediated oxidation assay (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    E). However, to our disappointment, no obvious phosphorylations on Thr553/Thr666 (or on any other Thr and Ser residues in PDZ45) by PKC could be observed under numerous conditions tested (see
    <a>
     Figures S5
    </a>
    A–S5C for details).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Acidification-Induced Uncoupling of PDZ45, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;5(A&amp;ndash;C) INAD PDZ45 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1337 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We were forced to widen our screening by testing other Ser and Thr residues, which may function as the regulatory switch for the PDZ5 conformational cycling. Among many residues tested, we observed with extreme interest that substitution of Thr669 with Ala, a mutation originally designed to mimic non-phosphorylated state of the residue, led to dramatically increased phosphorylation of PDZ45 by PKC (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). The level of PKC-mediated phosphorylation of T669A-PDZ45 is even higher than the phosphorylation of INAD PDZ2 that can be physically docked on to the kinase (the first lane,
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). Structural analysis of PDZ45 reveals that the side chain of Thr669 from the C-terminal tail forms a strong hydrogen bond with the imidazole ring of His547 in PDZ4 (the average bond length of ∼2.7 Å in the eight PDZ45 molecules in each asymmetric crystal unit;
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    D). Substitution of Thr669 with Ala would eliminate the Thr669-His547 H-bond and thereby lead to uncoupling of the PDZ45 supramodule. Indeed, the T669A mutation of PDZ45 can be rapidly oxidized by a low concentration of H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (88 μM) at pH 7.5 when compared with the WT PDZ45 (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). It was shown recently by one of us (R.C.H.) that fly microvilli undergo rapid, light-induced acidification due to protons released by PLCβ-mediated hydrolysis of PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). It was shown that light activation leads to 0.1–0.2 pH unit change to the entire cell body and this pH change originates from rhabdomere. Although direct measurements of the local pH change are not available, a simple calculation taking account of the space occupied by the INAD-organized signaling complex and the volume of the entire rhabdomere, suggests that light-induced release of protons in the immediate vicinity of the INAD-organized signaling complex could lead to a decrease of several pH units. Such a pH decrease is capable of breaking the Thr669/His547 H-bond due to the protonation of His547 imidazole ring. In other words, protons produced by the light-induced PLC activity may act as the regulatory switch for the conformational coupling of the PDZ45 supramodule.
   </p>
   <p>
    Several lines of experimental evidence support the pH-induced conformational cycling model of PDZ45. First, CD and NMR experiments showed that PDZ45 displays a pH-dependent conformational change with major spectral changes occurring at pH ∼6.0, a value matching pKa of a His side chain (
    <a>
     Figures S5
    </a>
    D–S5I). Second, one would predict that the redox potential of PDZ5 in the PDZ45 tandem would undergo a sudden drop upon protonation of His547. Indeed, GSSG-mediated oxidation of PDZ45 displayed a pH-dependent decrease when pH of the sample buffer was lowered from 7.8 to 6.3, which is due to increased protonation of Cys606 and Cys645 at more acidic conditions (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    E). The GSSG-mediated oxidation of Cys606 and Cys645 in PDZ45 showed a sudden surge when pH of the buffer was further lowered from 6.3 to 5.8 (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    E), presumably due to the His547 protonation-induced uncoupling of PDZ4&amp;5. In comparison, the GSSG-mediated oxidation of PDZ5 alone followed a predicted pH-dependent decrease upon lowering the buffer pH (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    E). Third, the oxidation speed (mediated by either GSSG or H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) of PDZ45 was dramatically enhanced when pH of the sample buffer dropped from neutral condition to pH 5.8 (
    <a>
     Figures S5
    </a>
    J and S5K). We noticed that that PDZ5 in the PDZ45 tandem is even more susceptible to oxidation than the isolated PDZ5 at acidic pH conditions, possibly due to a new mode of interaction between PDZ4 and PDZ5 at low pH conditions (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    E;
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    K). Importantly, the decrease of pH does not induce overall unfolding of PDZ5 in the PDZ45 tandem (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    D), and PDZ5 or PDZ45 in the reduced form binds to target peptides with comparable affinities at pH 7.5 or 5.8 (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    F and 5G).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    INAD Binds to Two Discrete Sites of the TRP Channel Using Its PDZ3 and PDZ45 Domains
   </title>
   <p>
    The identification of the Kon peptide as a specific binder of PDZ5 prompted us to search for other potential PDZ5 targets in the
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    proteome. Interestingly, one candidate identified was the TRP channel (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A). We tested the binding between the C-terminal “GWL” motif of the TRP channel with INAD using a synthetic peptide containing the last 9 residues of TRP (“TGRMISGWL”) and found that this TRP peptide binds to PDZ45 with a low affinity (Kd ∼140 μM,
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B). NMR-based assays revealed that the peptide binds to the same pocket as the Kon peptide does (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C), indicating that the weak interaction between the TRP tail and PDZ45 is specific. In vivo, TRP forms multimers (
    <a>
     Montell, 2003
    </a>
    ) and INAD also has a tendency to form oligomers (
    <a>
     Xu et al., 1998
    </a>
    ). The multimerizations of both TRP and INAD could increase the binding avidity of the two proteins.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Bidentate Interaction Mode between the TRP Channel and INAD(A) Amino acid ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (853 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    It has been shown that an internal sequence (the “
    <sup>
     1264
    </sup>
    STV
    <sup>
     1266
    </sup>
    ” motif,
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A) of TRP is also required for TRP to interact with INAD, most likely via binding to PDZ3 (
    <a>
     Li and Montell, 2000
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Peng et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). We confirmed this finding using a GST-fused TRP peptide contain both the “
    <sup>
     1264
    </sup>
    STV
    <sup>
     1266
    </sup>
    ” and the “GWL” motifs. The WT GST-fused TRP peptide robustly binds to the purified full-length INAD (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D). Substitution of Val1266 with Ala weakens its interaction with INAD, and the replacement of Trp1274 with Ala eliminated the binding (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D). In contrast, the GST-fused TRP peptides showed no detectable binding to PDZ45 due to very weak interaction between the “GWL” motif of TRP and PDZ5 of INAD (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    E).
   </p>
   <p>
    We were able to purify a highly stable PDZ345/TRP C-terminal tail complex by coexpressing INAD PDZ345 and GB1-tagged TRPCT containing the last 15 residues (GB1-TRPCT) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    F). The INAD/TRP complex has a Kd of ∼0.1 μM (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    A), further confirming the stable bidentate interaction between PDZ345 and the TRPCT. If PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    hydrolysis induced acidification indeed functions as a regulatory switch of the Cys606&amp;645 oxidation, one would predict that the PDZ345/TPRCT complex would be stable at neutral pH. Lowering pH of the PDZ345/TPRCT complex sample would promote dissociation of the complex under oxidation conditions due to the protonation of His547. Exactly as predicted, the PDZ345/TRPCT complex remains stable even when the sample was treated with H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    F). In contrast, at low pH, even without H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , partial GB1-TRPCT dissociation from PDZ345 could be detected. We suspect that this pH-induced, partial PDZ345/TRPCT dissociation may result from the uncoupling of PDZ3 from PDZ45. Treatment of the PDZ345/TRPCT complex at pH 5.8 with H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    further promoted the complex dissociation (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Interaction of INAD PDZ Domains with the Tail Peptides from TRP and Fly PLC&amp;#946;, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (441 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The data in
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    B–6F and the results from earlier studies (
    <a>
     Li and Montell, 2000
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Peng et al., 2008
    </a>
    ) together reveal that the TRP channel uses two discrete binding sites to bind to PDZ3 and PDZ5 of INAD. Such a bidentate interaction between TRP and INAD would afford tight TRP/INAD complex formation, even though each site alone has relatively weak affinity. The multimerization-induced avidity effect would further enhance the TRP/INAD complex formation. More importantly, the bidentate interaction between TRP and INAD has a regulatory advantage in controlling the assembly between TRP and INAD, as the complex can be efficiently dissociated by disrupting either one of the two binding sites (e.g., via PDZ5 oxidation,
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H). Reciprocally, the multimerization property of TRP channel would further promote the disassembling of the TRP/INAD complex, thus generating a sharp transition between the complexed and the uncomplexed states.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Whole-Cell Voltage Clamped Responses from inaDT669A Mutant Photoreceptors(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (643 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Interestingly, although isolated PDZ5 has no detectable binding to the C-terminal tail of PLCβ, the PDZ45 tandem binds to the PLCβ tail peptide with a Kd ∼30 μM (
    <a>
     Figures S6
    </a>
    B and S6C). This finding is consistent with an earlier report showing that a mutation in PDZ5 of INAD (
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
    </em>
    ) leads to dissociation of PLCβ from INAD (
    <a>
     Tsunoda et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). Importantly, GSSG-mediated oxidation of PDZ45 abolished the tandem's PLCβ tail peptide binding (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C), pointing to a possibility that oxidation of PDZ45 can also disrupt the INAD/PLCβ complex.
   </p>
   <title>
    In Vivo Analysis of
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    Mutant Flies
   </title>
   <p>
    To test the pH-dependent formation of the H-bond between T669 and H547 in vivo, we introduced the T669A mutation into full-length INAD cDNA and expressed the construct in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
    </em>
    null mutant flies (
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    ,
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    A). In wild-type photoreceptors macroscopic responses to brief flashes of light have a time-to-peak (t-pk) of ∼40–50 ms, before relaxing rapidly to baseline. Responses in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    had a similar peak amplitude but a significantly delayed t-pk (approximately 60 ms) and slightly slower decay time course (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    A and 7B). Analysis of elementary responses to single photons (quantum bumps) revealed that this was primarily a consequence of a significant increase in quantum bump latency
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    ). This would be consistent with the TRP channel and/or PLC being maintained in a low sensitivity state, resulting in delayed activation.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Single Photon Responses (Quantum Bumps) in inaDT669A Mutant Photoreceptors, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867411005411-figs7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (214 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Following each quantum bump, believed to be generated within a single microvillus, the affected microvillus becomes flooded with Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    and is briefly (∼100 ms) refractory to further stimulation (
    <a>
     Scott et al., 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Liu et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). With sufficiently bright steps of illumination, this results in responses consisting of an initial peak that rapidly declines to minimum (“notch”) as photons arrive in the same microvilli during the refractory period, before rebounding to a maintained plateau (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    C–7E).
    <em>
     inad
     <sup>
      C645S
     </sup>
    </em>
    mutants, in which PDZ45 should be locked in the reduced state, were previously reported to lack this “notch” suggesting that the redox switch played an important role in rendering the channels refractory during this transient period of high Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    influx (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). We predicted that the
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    mutation, which should lock PDZ45 in the uncoupled oxidized state, might have a converse effect. To test this we recorded responses to 1 s light steps of increasing intensity, accurately calibrated in each cell in terms of effectively absorbed photons. The intensity dependence of both peak and plateau responses in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    were indistinguishable from controls (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F). However, consistent with a reduced sensitivity of the INAD-channel complex, when the depth of the notch in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    was plotted against intensity (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    G), it developed at significantly (approximately 2- to 3-fold) lower intensities than in controls.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <title>
    Allosteric Regulation of INAD PDZ45 Conformational Dynamics
   </title>
   <p>
    Scaffold proteins are traditionally viewed as passive molecular adaptors that “glue” signaling proteins together. Emerging evidence indicates that, in addition to such a passive role, scaffold proteins can actively participate in dynamic regulation of signaling events (
    <a>
     Bhattacharyya et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Feng and Zhang, 2009
    </a>
    ). The cycling of INAD PDZ5 between the reduced and oxidized states is an elegant example of direct signaling regulation by a scaffold protein (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ), although the underlying molecular mechanism has been unclear. In this work, we discovered that the redox potential of the Cys606&amp;645 pair of INAD PDZ5 undergoes a massive, conformation-coupled shift. Formation of the PDZ45 supramodule elevates the redox potential of PDZ5 disulfide to ∼−40 mV, locking the domain in its reduced conformation capable of binding to its targets with high affinity. Conformational uncoupling between PDZ4&amp;5 via protonation of His547 lowers the redox potential of PDZ5 to ∼−370 mV, leading to the oxidation of the Cys606-Cys645 pair and consequent dissociation of PDZ5 target. Presumably, rapid dissipation of the proton gradient will restore the INAD-PDZ45 supramodule for another round of signaling event (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H).
   </p>
   <p>
    In line with our in vitro analysis,
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    mutant flies, in which PDZ5 is decoupled from PDZ4 and effectively locked in the oxidized low-affinity state, display electrophysiological defects (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    ). Although subtle, it is striking that the defects in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    were essentially the converse of those previously reported in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      C645S
     </sup>
    </em>
    mutants, where PDZ5 is locked in the reduced, high-affinity state (
    <a>
     Mishra et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). Namely, although responses to intense flashes in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      C645S
     </sup>
    </em>
    failed to develop the “notch” characteristic of wild-type responses, the notch in
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    was significantly more pronounced (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    ). This supports Mishra et al.'s (2007) proposal that the dynamic switch to the oxidized state is required to induce the refractory period (
    <a>
     Hardie and Raghu, 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pumir et al., 2008
    </a>
    ), whereby a second photon absorbed in the same microvillus within ∼100 ms fails to generate a response.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the present study, we found that the TRP C-terminal binds avidly to the reduced PDZ345, whereas the PLC C-terminal binds with reasonably high affinity to PDZ45. Furthermore, protonation, leading to decoupling and oxidation of PDZ5, promotes dissociation of both TRP and PLC. We hypothesize that high-affinity binding of TRP and/or PLC maximizes sensitivity of the channel to activation by PLC, and that dissociation following oxidation results in a low sensitivity state (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H). In
    <em>
     inad
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    , PDZ5 is locked in the low-affinity, low-sensitivity state, potentially accounting for both the prolonged latency and the more pronounced notch. Conversely, the notch is abolished in
    <em>
     inad
     <sup>
      C654S
     </sup>
    </em>
    mutants where PDZ45 is locked in the high-affinity, maximally sensitive state.
   </p>
   <p>
    How might the dynamic interaction of TRP (and/or PLC) with INAD influence channel activity? TRP channels are activated by products of PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    hydrolysis (putatively protons and PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    depletion) and are also subject to pronounced positive and negative feedback by Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    influx (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ; for review, see
    <a>
     Hardie and Postma, 2008
    </a>
    ). In principle, TRP's interaction with INAD could modulate the dependency of channel gating on any of these factors. It may also be relevant that PLC is dynamically regulated during phototransduction in a Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    - and PKC-dependent manner (
    <a>
     Gu et al., 2005
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    It is noted that the oxidation speed of the Cys606&amp;645 pair is too slow to match the extremely fast fly vision signaling kinetics. This implies that additional regulatory factor(s) must exist to regulate the fly visual signaling process. One such factor might be ePKC. It is possible that PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    hydrolysis-induced acidification (via PLCβ) and INAD phosphorylation (via ePKC) act synergistically to achieve a rapid oxidation of PDZ5 required for fly visual signaling. The redox state of INAD might also be modulated by oxidants acutely generated upon light activation of fly photoreceptors, although these have not been reported to date. Alternatively, a pair of Cys with a redox potential between those of the two INAD PDZ5 conformers may function as a “facilitator” to catalyze the PDZ5 conformational cycling.
   </p>
   <title>
    Proton as a General Second Messenger in PLC/PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    Signaling Processes
   </title>
   <p>
    It is seldom recognized that PLC-mediated hydrolysis of PIP
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    releases protons. Along with the recent finding that the light-sensitive channels in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    can be activated by a combination of protons and phosphoinositide depletion (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), our results suggest that localized proton release by PLC may play a general role in receptor-mediated signaling processes. Proton-regulated dynamic signaling complex organization by scaffold proteins beneath PLC-containing membranes is likely to have broad implications for future studies and may force re-evaluation of many well-documented signaling events in biology.
   </p>
   <title>
    Supramodular Nature of the INAD PDZ45 Tandem
   </title>
   <p>
    The capacity of dynamic cycling of PDZ5 between its two distinct conformational states is enabled by the formation of the PDZ45 supramodule. The INAD PDZ45 supramodule, together with a number of recent examples, demonstrates that two or more PDZ domains connected in tandem often display distinct target-binding properties from each isolated domain or the simple sum of the isolated PDZ domains due to direct interactions of PDZ domains in the tandem (
    <a>
     Feng et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Long et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Long et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Long et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). An additional advantage of arranging multiple protein modules into a higher order supramodule is to build regulatory mechanisms into scaffold proteins, thereby enabling them to actively control signaling events organized around them (
    <a>
     Feng and Zhang, 2009
    </a>
    ). INAD takes the supramodule feature to another level. Productive binding between TRP channel and INAD requires PDZ3 and PDZ45 to be covalently linked together forming a PDZ345 supramodule.
   </p>
   <title>
    Conformation-Coupled Modulation of Protein Disulfide Redox Potentials
   </title>
   <p>
    Cys oxidations are known to regulate very broad cellular activities. It is generally accepted that oxidations of Cys in proteins occur either via a limited degree of cellular redox potential changes or generations of reactive oxidants as a result of cellular metabolism/signaling (
    <a>
     Janssen-Heininger et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rhee, 2006
    </a>
    ). In this paradigm, Cys residues in proteins act as sensors by passively responding to cellular redox potential changes or generations of reactive oxygen species, as redox potentials of protein disulfides generally do not change. Formation of inter- or intramolecular disulfide bonds are increasingly recognized as important activity regulatory mechanisms for cellular proteins and enzymes (see
    <a>
     Ago et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Fox et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kemble and Sun, 2009
    </a>
    for examples). The disulfide-mediated oxidation of INAD PDZ45 characterized in this work represents an unprecedented protein oxidation mechanism. The redox potential of the disulfide bond in PDZ5 is allosterically regulated by the conformational coupling of PDZ4. Formation of the PDZ45 supramodule raise the standard redox potential of PDZ5 by as much as 330 mV, thereby converting the Cys606-Cys645 disulfide of PDZ5 from the highly stable oxidized state to the extremely stable reduced state at cellular redox potentials. In view of the widespread existence of Cys residues in cellular proteins and enzymes, it is possible that such conformation-dependent redox potential oscillations also exist in other proteins. Such regulated, large amplitude redox potential oscillations of proteins and enzymes may be a general paradigm for cellular signal transduction regulations. One may envision that a combined action of reactive oxygen species and redox potential oscillations can further sharpen redox signaling events spatiotemporally.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Protein Expression and Purification
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    PDZ5 and PDZ45 were expressed in and purified in bacteria (see
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details).
   </p>
   <title>
    Fluorescence Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Fluorescence assays were performed on a PerkinElmer LS-55 fluorimeter at 20°C. In the assay, FITC (Molecular Probes) labeled peptide samples (∼1 μM) were titrated with binding partners in buffer containing 50 mM Tris (with pH value and DTT concentration specifically indicated, 50 mM NaCl, and 1 mM EDTA), and the titration curves were fitted with the GraphPad Prism 5 software package.
   </p>
   <title>
    Redox Measurements of PDZ5 and PDZ45
   </title>
   <p>
    Redox kinetics and thermodynamics (i.e., the standard redox potentials) of PDZ5 and PDZ45 were measured by NMR spectroscopy and the Ellman chemistry. Detailed procedures can be found in
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    NMR Structure Determination
   </title>
   <p>
    All protein samples used for NMR titration experiments were concentrated to 0.2∼0.5 mM in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.0, with 1 mM EDTA and 50 mM NaCl, with DTT concentrations specified). NMR spectra were acquired at 30°C on Varian NMR spectrometers. The PDZ5/Kon peptide complex was determined using standard NMR methods (see
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details).
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystallography
   </title>
   <p>
    Crystals of the PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex and the Se-Met-labeled PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex were obtained by the hanging drop vapor diffusion method at 16°C. The PDZ45/NG2 peptide complex crystals grew in the crystallization buffer containing 2.4 M (NH
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , and 0.1 M Tris (pH 8.5). The native and Se-Met X-ray data sets were collected at the Cornell High-Energy Synchrotron Source beamline A1. The detailed X-ray crystallographic methods can be found in the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    GST Pull-Down Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    In vitro binding between TRP C-terminal tail and INAD was assayed using GSH-Sepharose beads-based pull-down assay. INAD proteins (140 μg for INAD FL and 50 μg for PDZ45 in each assay) were first cleared by preincubating with 30 μl of GSH-Sepharose beads in 1 ml assay buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl [pH 7.5] containing 1 M NaCl, 1 mM DTT). Precleared INAD proteins were then mixed with 30 μl of GSH-Sepharose beads charged with 20 μg GST-TRP-CT at 4°C for 30 min. The GSH-Sepharose beads were washed three times with the assay buffer, and the retained proteins were assayed by SDS-PAGE with Coomassie blue staining.
   </p>
   <title>
    Analytical Gel Filtration Chromatography
   </title>
   <p>
    Analytical gel filtration chromatography was carried out on an AKTA FPLC system (GE Healthcare). Proteins were loaded on to a Superose 12 10/300 GL column 20 (GE Healthcare) equilibrated with a buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5, with 100 mM NaCl, and 1 mM EDTA with or without 1 mM DTT).
   </p>
   <title>
    Flies
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     Drosophila melanogaster
    </em>
    were raised in the dark at 25°C. The wild-type strain was
    <em>
     w
     <sup>
      1118
     </sup>
    </em>
    . Transgenic lines expressing
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      T669A
     </sup>
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      WT
     </sup>
    </em>
    cDNA under the Rh1 promoter were generated by standard P-element transformation and recombined into a
    <em>
     inaD
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
    </em>
    null background (
    <a>
     Tsunoda et al., 1997
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Electrophysiology
   </title>
   <p>
    Dissociated ommatidia were prepared as previously described (e.g.,
    <a>
     Henderson et al., 2000
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hardie et al., 2002
    </a>
    ) from newly eclosed adult flies and transferred to a recording chamber on an inverted Nikon Diaphot microscope. Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were made at room temperature (20°C ± 1°C) at −70 mV using electrodes of resistance ∼10–15 MΩ using standard solutions (see
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for further details). Photoreceptors were stimulated via a green light-emitting diode; intensities were calibrated in every cell in terms of effectively absorbed photons by counting quantum bumps at low intensities.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The coordinates of the PDZ5/Kon and PDZ45/NG2 complexes have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank under the accession codes of 2LA8 and 3R0H, respectively.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Tables S1 and S2.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (82 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S2. Article Plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (3953 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Adamski et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F.M. Adamski, M.Y. Zhu, F. Bahiraei, B.H. Shieh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Interaction of eye protein kinase C and INAD in Drosophila. Localization of binding domains and electrophysiological characterization of a loss of association in transgenic flies
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 17713–17719
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ago et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Ago, T. Liu, P. Zhai, W. Chen, H. Li, J.D. Molkentin, S.F. Vatner, J. Sadoshima
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A redox-dependent pathway for regulating class II HDACs and cardiac hypertrophy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 133 (2008), pp. 978–993
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bhattacharyya et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.P. Bhattacharyya, A. Remenyi, B.J. Yeh, W.A. Lim
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Domains, motifs, and scaffolds: the role of modular interactions in the evolution and wiring of cell signaling circuits
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Biochem., 75 (2006), pp. 655–680
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chevesich et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Chevesich, A.J. Kreuz, C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Requirement for the PDZ domain protein, INAD, for localization of the TRP store-operated channel to a signaling complex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 18 (1997), pp. 95–105
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feng and Zhang, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Feng, M. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Organization and dynamics of PDZ-domain-related supramodules in the postsynaptic density
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Neurosci., 10 (2009), pp. 87–99
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feng et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Feng, Y. Shi, M. Li, M. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tandem PDZ repeats in glutamate receptor-interacting proteins have a novel mode of PDZ domain-mediated target binding
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Biol., 10 (2003), pp. 972–978
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fox et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.C. Fox, M. Shafiq, D.C. Briggs, P.P. Knowles, M. Collister, M.J. Didmon, V. Makrantoni, R.J. Dickinson, S. Hanrahan, N. Totty,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox-mediated substrate recognition by Sdp1 defines a new group of tyrosine phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 447 (2007), pp. 487–492
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gu et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Gu, J. Oberwinkler, M. Postma, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mechanisms of light adaptation in Drosophila photoreceptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 15 (2005), pp. 1228–1234
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardie and Raghu, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. Hardie, P. Raghu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Visual transduction in
         <em>
          Drosophila
         </em>
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 413 (2001), pp. 186–193
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardie and Postma, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. Hardie, M. Postma
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phototransduction in microvillar photoreceptors of Drosophila and other invertebrates
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         ,in: T.D. Albright, R. Masland (Eds.), The Senses-a comprehensive reference Vision, Volume 1, Academic Press, Oxford (2008), pp. 77–130
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardie et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. Hardie, A. Peretz, E. Suss-Toby, A. Rom-Glas, S.A. Bishop, Z. Selinger, B. Minke
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein kinase C is required for light adaptation in
         <em>
          Drosophila
         </em>
         photoreceptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 363 (1993), pp. 634–637
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardie et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. Hardie, F. Martin, G.W. Cochrane, M. Juusola, P. Georgiev, P. Raghu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Molecular basis of amplification in
         <em>
          Drosophila
         </em>
         phototransduction. Roles for G protein, phospholipase C, and diacylglycerol kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 36 (2002), pp. 689–701
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Henderson et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.R. Henderson, H. Reuss, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Single photon responses in Drosophila photoreceptors and their regulation by Ca2+
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Physiol., 524 (2000), pp. 179–194
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huang et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Huang, C.H. Liu, S.A. Hughes, M. Postma, C.J. Schwiening, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Activation of TRP channels by protons and phosphoinositide depletion in Drosophila photoreceptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 20 (2010), pp. 189–197
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huber, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Huber
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Scaffolding proteins organize multimolecular protein complexes for sensory signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Eur. J. Neurosci., 14 (2001), pp. 769–776
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huber et al., 1996a
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Huber, P. Sander, A. Gobert, M. Bahner, R. Hermann, R. Paulsen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The transient receptor potential protein (Trp), a putative store-operated Ca2+ channel essential for phosphoinositide-mediated photoreception, forms a signaling complex with NorpA, InaC and InaD
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 15 (1996), pp. 7036–7045
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huber et al., 1996b
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Huber, P. Sander, R. Paulsen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phosphorylation of the InaD gene product, a photoreceptor membrane protein required for recovery of visual excitation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 271 (1996), pp. 11710–11717
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Janssen-Heininger et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y.M.W. Janssen-Heininger, B.T. Mossman, N.H. Heintz, H.J. Forman, B. Kalyanaraman, T. Finkel, J.S. Stamler, S.G. Rhee, A. van der Vliet
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox-based regulation of signal transduction: Principles, pitfalls, and promises
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Free Radic. Biol. Med., 45 (2008), pp. 1–17
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Juusola and Hardie, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Juusola, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Light adaptation in Drosophila photoreceptors: I. Response dynamics and signaling efficiency at 25 degrees C
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Gen. Physiol., 117 (2001), pp. 3–25
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Keese et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.A. Keese, R. Saffrich, T. Dandekar, K. Becker, R.H. Schirmer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Microinjected glutathione reductase crystals as indicators of the redox status in living cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 447 (1999), pp. 135–138
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kemble and Sun, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.J. Kemble, G. Sun
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Direct and specific inactivation of protein tyrosine kinases in the Src and FGFR families by reversible cysteine oxidation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 106 (2009), pp. 5070–5075
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kimple et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.E. Kimple, D.P. Siderovski, J. Sondek
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional relevance of the disulfide-linked complex of the N-terminal PDZ domain of InaD with NorpA
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 20 (2001), pp. 4414–4422
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Li and Montell, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.S. Li, C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TRP and the PDZ protein, INAD, form the core complex required for retention of the signalplex in Drosophila photoreceptor cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 150 (2000), pp. 1411–1422
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.H. Liu, A.K. Satoh, M. Postma, J. Huang, D.F. Ready, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         -dependent metarhodopsin inactivation mediated by calmodulin and NINAC myosin III
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 59 (2008), pp. 778–789
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Long et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Long, Z. Wei, W. Feng, C. Yu, Y.X. Zhao, M. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Supramodular nature of GRIP1 revealed by the structure of its PDZ12 tandem in complex with the carboxyl tail of Fras1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 375 (2008), pp. 1457–1468
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Long et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.F. Long, H. Tochio, P. Wang, J.S. Fan, C. Sala, M. Niethammer, M. Sheng, M. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Supramodular structure and synergistic target binding of the N-terminal tandem PDZ domains of PSD-95
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 327 (2003), pp. 203–214
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Long et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.F. Long, W. Feng, R. Wang, L.N. Chan, F.C. Ip, J. Xia, N.Y. Ip, M. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Autoinhibition of X11/Mint scaffold proteins revealed by the closed conformation of the PDZ tandem
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 12 (2005), pp. 722–728
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mishra et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Mishra, M. Socolich, M.A. Wall, J. Graves, Z. Wang, R. Ranganathan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dynamic scaffolding in a G protein-coupled signaling system
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 131 (2007), pp. 80–92
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Montell, 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Visual transduction in Drosophila
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol., 15 (1999), pp. 231–268
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Montell, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The venerable inveterate invertebrate TRP channels
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Calcium, 33 (2003), pp. 409–417
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Montell, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TRP channels in Drosophila photoreceptor cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Physiol., 567 (2005), pp. 45–51
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ostergaard et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Ostergaard, C. Tachibana, J.R. Winther
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Monitoring disulfide bond formation in the eukaryotic cytosol
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 166 (2004), pp. 337–345
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pawson and Nash, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Pawson, P. Nash
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Assembly of cell regulatory systems through protein interaction domains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 300 (2003), pp. 445–452
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Peng et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Peng, D.C. Popescu, N. Wang, B.H. Shieh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anchoring TRP to the INAD macromolecular complex requires the last 14 residues in its carboxyl terminus
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Neurochem., 104 (2008), pp. 1526–1535
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Popescu et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.C. Popescu, A.J. Ham, B.H. Shieh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Scaffolding protein INAD regulates deactivation of vision by promoting phosphorylation of transient receptor potential by eye protein kinase C in Drosophila
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Neurosci., 26 (2006), pp. 8570–8577
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pumir et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Pumir, J. Graves, R. Ranganathan, B.I. Shraiman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Systems analysis of the single photon response in invertebrate photoreceptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 105 (2008), pp. 10354–10359
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rhee, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.G. Rhee
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell signaling. H2O2, a necessary evil for cell signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 312 (2006), pp. 1882–1883
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schafer and Buettner, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F.Q. Schafer, G.R. Buettner
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox environment of the cell as viewed through the redox state of the glutathione disulfide/glutathione couple
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Free Radic. Biol. Med., 30 (2001), pp. 1191–1212
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Scott et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Scott, Y. Sun, K. Beckingham, C.S. Zuker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Calmodulin regulation of Drosophila light-activated channels and receptor function mediates termination of the light response in vivo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 91 (1997), pp. 375–383
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shieh and Zhu, 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.H. Shieh, M.Y. Zhu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of the TRP Ca2+ channel by INAD in Drosophila photoreceptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neuron, 16 (1996), pp. 991–998
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Smith et al., 1991
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.P. Smith, R. Ranganathan, R.W. Hardy, J. Marx, T. Tsuchida, C.S. Zuker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Photoreceptor deactivation and retinal degeneration mediated by a photoreceptor-specific protein kinase C
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 254 (1991), pp. 1478–1484
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tsunoda and Zuker, 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Tsunoda, C.S. Zuker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The organization of INAD-signaling complexes by a multivalent PDZ domain protein in Drosophila photoreceptor cells ensures sensitivity and speed of signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Calcium, 26 (1999), pp. 165–171
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tsunoda et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Tsunoda, J. Sierralta, Y. Sun, R. Bodner, E. Suzuki, A. Becker, M. Socolich, C.S. Zuker
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A multivalent PDZ-domain protein assembles signalling complexes in a G-protein-coupled cascade
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 388 (1997), pp. 243–249
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         van Huizen et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. van Huizen, K. Miller, D.M. Chen, Y. Li, Z.C. Lai, R.W. Raab, W.S. Stark, R.D. Shortridge, M. Li
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Two distantly positioned PDZ domains mediate multivalent INAD-phospholipase C interactions essential for G protein-coupled signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 17 (1998), pp. 2285–2297
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang and Montell, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Wang, C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phototransduction and retinal degeneration in Drosophila
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Pflugers Arch., 454 (2007), pp. 821–847
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Xu et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        X.Z. Xu, A. Choudhury, X. Li, C. Montell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Coordination of an array of signaling proteins through homo- and heteromeric interactions between PDZ domains and target proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 142 (1998), pp. 545–555
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yau and Hardie, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.W. Yau, R.C. Hardie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phototransduction motifs and variations
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 139 (2009), pp. 246–264
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang and Wang, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Zhang, W. Wang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Organization of signaling complexes by PDZ-domain scaffold proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acc. Chem. Res., 36 (2003), pp. 530–538
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <title>
      Supplemental References
     </title>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bax and Grzesiek, 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Bax, A., and Grzesiek, S. (1993). Methodological advances in protein NMR. Acc. Chem. Res.
        <em>
         26
        </em>
        , 131–138.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brunger et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Brunger, A.T., Adams, P.D., Clore, G.M., DeLano, W.L., Gros, P., Grosse-Kunstleve, R.W., Jiang, J.S., Kuszewski, J., Nilges, M., Pannu, N.S., et al. (1998). Crystallography &amp; NMR system: A new software suite for macromolecular structure determination. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         54
        </em>
        , 905–921.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cornilescu et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Cornilescu, G., Delaglio, F., and Bax, A. (1999). Protein backbone angle restraints from searching a database for chemical shift and sequence homology. J. Biomol. NMR
        <em>
         13
        </em>
        , 289–302.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Emsley and Cowtan, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Emsley, P., and Cowtan, K. (2004). Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         60
        </em>
        , 2126–2132.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Guntert et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Guntert, P., Mumenthaler, C., and Wuthrich, K. (1997). Torsion angle dynamics for NMR structure calculation with the new program DYANA. J. Mol. Biol.
        <em>
         273
        </em>
        , 283–298.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kay and Gardner, 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Kay, L.E., and Gardner, K.H. (1997). Solution NMR spectroscopy beyond 25 kDa. Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.
        <em>
         7
        </em>
        , 722–731.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Laskowski et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Laskowski, R.A., Moss, D.S., and Thornton, J.M. (1993). Main-chain bond lengths and bond angles in protein structures. J. Mol. Biol.
        <em>
         231
        </em>
        , 1049–1067.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sajewski and Whitesides, 1980
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Sajewski, R.P., and Whitesides, G.M. (1980). Rate constants and equilibrium constants for thiol-disulfide interchange reactions involving oxidized glutathione. J. Am. Chem. Soc.
        <em>
         102
        </em>
        , 2011–2015.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schneider and Sheldrick, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Schneider, T.R., and Sheldrick, G.M. (2002). Substructure solution with SHELXD. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         58
        </em>
        , 1772–1779.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Szajewski and Whitesides, 1980
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Szajewski, R.P., and Whitesides, G.M. (1980). Rate constants and equilibrium constants for thiol-disulfide interchange reactions involving oxidized glutathione. J. Am. Chem. Soc.
        <em>
         102
        </em>
        , 2011–2015.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Terwilliger, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Terwilliger, T.C. (2000). Maximum-likelihood density modification. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         56
        </em>
        , 965–972.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vagin et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Vagin, A.A., Steiner, R.A., Lebedev, A.A., Potterton, L., McNicholas, S., Long, F., and Murshudov, G.N. (2004). REFMAC5 dictionary: organization of prior chemical knowledge and guidelines for its use. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         60
        </em>
        , 2184–2195.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vonrhein et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Vonrhein, C., Blanc, E., Roversi, P., and Bricogne, G. (2007). Automated structure solution with autoSHARP. Methods Mol. Biol.
        <em>
         364
        </em>
        , 215–230.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wen et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Wen, W., Liu, W., Yan, J., and Zhang, M. (2008). Structure basis and unconventional lipid membrane binding properties of the PH-C1 tandem of rho kinases. J. Biol. Chem.
        <em>
         283
        </em>
        , 26263–26273.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref62'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wüthrich, 1986
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Wüthrich, K. (1986). NMR of Proteins and Nucleic Acids (New York: John Wiley).
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref63'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2011 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>