<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ccr.2014.07.007
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structure of the BRAF-MEK Complex Reveals a Kinase Activity Independent Role for BRAF in MAPK Signaling
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Significance
   </title>
   <p>
    <strong>
     The MAPK pathway is frequently activated in human cancers. Here we define a regulatory mechanism for MAPK pathway activation that can be bypassed by oncogenic mutations in the BRAF kinase domain. Our studies demonstrate that BRAF forms a high affinity complex with MEK1 that is independent of BRAF dimerization but sensitive to MEK1 phosphorylation. BRAF-MEK1 complexes are enriched in the cytosol of
     <em>
      BRAF
     </em>
    </strong>
    <sup>
     <strong>
      <em>
       WT
      </em>
     </strong>
    </sup>
    <strong>
     and
     <em>
      KRAS
     </em>
    </strong>
    <sup>
     <strong>
      <em>
       MT
      </em>
     </strong>
    </sup>
    <strong>
     tumor cells and disassociate upon pathway activation through either EGF stimulation or oncogenic BRAF mutations. Importantly, our work illustrates that recognition of MEK1 by BRAF is not the rate-limiting step in pathway activation, but rather BRAF-CRAF dimerization is. This has profound implications for both our fundamental understanding of MAPK biology and therapeutic design.
    </strong>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The Ras-RAF-MEK-ERK signaling pathway (mitogen-activated protein kinase [MAPK] pathway) plays a major role in cellular growth, differentiation, survival, and senescence (
    <a>
     Wellbrock et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Not surprisingly, this pathway is frequently dysregulated in human cancers with many tumors harboring RAS or RAF mutations resulting in constitutive activation of the pathway (
    <a>
     Roberts and Der, 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Schubbert et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). The three RAF isoforms in humans, ARAF, BRAF, and CRAF, have distinct mechanisms of activation (
    <a>
     Baljuls et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Galabova-Kovacs et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hu et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wimmer and Baccarini, 2010
    </a>
    ), with BRAF being less regulated overall (
    <a>
     Chong et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). Despite these differences, spatial activation of RAF by RAS-guanosine triphosphate (GTP) remains a common regulatory step for normal MAPK pathway activation. The association of RAS-GTP with the Ras binding domain of RAF at the plasma membrane promotes homodimerization or heterodimerization of RAF protomers (
    <a>
     Goetz et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kolch, 2000
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weber et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). This association, in addition to CRAF phosphorylation, results in an activating conformational change in the RAF kinase domain leading to phosphorylation of MEK on S218 and S222 (
    <a>
     Rajakulendran et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rushworth et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). Activated MEK in turn phosphorylates the terminal kinase ERK.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Kinase suppressor of Ras (KSR) is a scaffolding protein that can enhance the duration and amplitude of MAPK signaling (
    <a>
     Kornfeld et al., 1995
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sundaram and Han, 1995
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Therrien et al., 1995
    </a>
    ) through assembly of activating complexes involving BRAF, MEK, and ERK (
    <a>
     Clapéron and Therrien, 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kolch, 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nguyen et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Roy et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). KSR is homologous to RAF kinases but lacks both an important catalytic lysine within the kinase domain and the ability to bind RAS directly. While the physiological relevance of KSR catalytic activity remains controversial (
    <a>
     Brennan et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Michaud et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), the ability of KSR to activate RAF through KSR-RAF dimers is well established (
    <a>
     McKay et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rajakulendran et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). Thus, KSR plays an operative role in RAF activation in addition to regulating spatial and temporal dynamics of MAPK signaling. KSR, like RAF, binds MEK (
    <a>
     Brennan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). The crystal structure of MEK1 bound to the kinase domain of KSR2 reveals that MEK1 residues S218 and S222 lie at the heterodimer interface and are masked by KSR2 such that they are inaccessible for phosphorylation by RAF (
    <a>
     Brennan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). Thus, whether KSR or RAF is directly bound to MEK in vivo impacts the mechanism of signal transduction.
   </p>
   <p>
    The precise mechanism of pathway activation in the context of cancer provides an additional layer of complexity and is dependent on the underlying genetic mutation. For example, the kinase activating BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    mutation, found in more than 60% of melanomas, promotes MAPK pathway signaling independent of RAS activation (
    <a>
     Davies et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). While spatial activation and dimerization of RAF kinases are central regulatory mechanisms in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    mutant (MT) contexts (
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rushworth et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weber et al., 2001
    </a>
    ),
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines are insensitive to these regulatory events (
    <a>
     Röring et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). In contrast, nonactivating oncogenic mutations in the BRAF kinase domain promote pathway signaling through CRAF activation (
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P-loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    mutations activate the pathway through enhanced dimerization with CRAF independent of RAS but requiring CRAF activation loop phosphorylation and interaction with 14-3-3 (
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). Interestingly, unlike the activating
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    mutation that is mutually exclusive with respect to
    <em>
     RAS
    </em>
    mutations, tumor cell lines harboring
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    mutations may also have activating
    <em>
     RAS
    </em>
    mutations (i.e., MDA-MB-231), suggesting that RAS may play a role in enhancing pathway activation in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    tumors. Similarly, in vivo studies with the kinase dead BRAF mutant BRAF
    <sup>
     D594V
    </sup>
    illustrate that active RAS is required for
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      D594V
     </em>
    </sup>
    induced melanoma in mice (
    <a>
     Heidorn et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Therefore, in the context of nonactivating BRAF mutations, additional mechanisms are required to drive dimerization with CRAF and pathway activation, including but not limited to interactions with RAS and 14-3-3.
   </p>
   <p>
    The effects of BRAF inhibitors are similarly complex. ATP competitive inhibitors of BRAF such as vemurafenib (PLX4032) have shown significant antitumor activity in the clinic for treatment of metastatic melanomas harboring the
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    mutation (
    <a>
     Pérez-Lorenzo and Zheng, 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ribas and Flaherty, 2011
    </a>
    ). However, in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cells, BRAF inhibitors paradoxically activate the MAPK pathway by inducing dimerization of BRAF with CRAF in a RAS-GTP-dependent manner. The proposed molecular mechanism of RAF activation appears to be due to inhibitor binding to one protomer of RAF (i.e., BRAF) and inducing dimerization with a second RAF protomer (i.e., CRAF), which results in activation of the pathway through increased CRAF kinase activity (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Heidorn et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Poulikakos et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). With high concentration of inhibitor, both BRAF and CRAF protomers are bound to the inhibitor and signaling is blocked. It has also been reported that certain BRAF inhibitors can induce KSR-RAF dimers (
    <a>
     Hu et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     McKay et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). In this context inhibitor bound BRAF competes with CRAF for binding to KSR, suggesting that BRAF inhibitors can elicit allosteric effects on both kinase signaling as well as scaffolding components in the MAPK pathway (
    <a>
     McKay et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). Further, while most type I BRAF inhibitors paradoxically prime the pathway in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cells, not all type I BRAF inhibitors induce BRAF-CRAF or RAF-KSR dimers as this effect is conformation specific, requiring the active, closed conformation of the BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lavoie et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     McKay et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). Hence, conformation-specific paradoxical RAF activation underscores the importance of understanding the noncatalytic functions of this family of kinases.
   </p>
   <p>
    Recently, specific classes of allosteric MEK inhibitors were reported to sequester a RAF-MEK protein complex, which resulted in greater efficacy in
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cancer models (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ishii et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). This class of MEK inhibitor prevents RAF from phosphorylating MEK at S218 and S222 and therefore not only blocks MEK kinase activity but also RAF-dependent phosphorylation of MEK. Interestingly, these inhibitors cannot sequester a BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    -MEK protein complex and are not as effective in a
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    background (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). This raises the question whether preformed RAF-MEK complexes exist prior to MAPK pathway activation and if the specific genetic context determines the types of signaling complexes present basally in cells.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Cytosolic BRAF-MEK1 Complexes Are Enriched in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    Cells
   </title>
   <p>
    We analyzed phosphorylation of MEK1 across a panel of
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    ,
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    , and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines. In agreement with previous reports, we observe that phospho-MEK (pMEK) levels are elevated in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines (BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    or BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    ) but are dampened in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    A available online). Coimmunoprecipitation (coIP) of MEK1 with BRAF and CRAF revealed that endogenous BRAF-MEK1 complexes are enriched in multiple
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    <em>
     /KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines where pMEK levels are low, but are significantly less abundant in the
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines, where pMEK levels are elevated (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    A). Given the high degree of sequence identity between BRAF and CRAF kinase domains (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    B), we also observed CRAF-MEK1 complexes in a small subset of cell lines (i.e., PATU, Colo678). In order to ascertain the relative stoichiometry of this complex, we conducted serial MEK1 coimmunodepeletion experiments in HCT116 and HEK293 cell lines where basal pMEK levels were low and BRAF-MEK1 complexes were present. As seen in
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    C, even when all MEK1 and MEK1-BRAF complexes are immunodepleted from cell lysates, free BRAF and CRAF remain in the flow through, suggesting that not all of BRAF is bound to MEK1 and that there is a dynamic equilibrium between BRAF-MEK1 and free BRAF and CRAF in cell lines where complexes are observed (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    C). This result also suggests that substrate recognition (i.e., recognition of MEK1 by RAF) is not a rate-limiting step in RAF-dependent MEK phosphorylation. Whereas catalytic activity of BRAF enhances pMEK levels in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    lines, increased formation of BRAF-CRAF heterodimers and CRAF activation drive pathway activity in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P-loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines, as indicated by coIP of CRAF with BRAF and CRAF phosphorylation at S338 (pS338) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B). As one of the hallmarks of RAF activation is RAS-GTP-dependent membrane localization, we assessed whether the BRAF-MEK1 complex observed basally in
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines resides in the cytosol or membrane fraction. Subcellular fractionation studies in cell lines harboring
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    (HCT116),
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    (A375), or
    <em>
     RAS/RAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    (HEK293T) reveal that BRAF-MEK1 complexes reside in the cytosol of HCT116 and HEK293T cell lines, supporting the model where BRAF and CRAF are primarily cytosolic until activated (
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Marais et al., 1997
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). Collectively, these data indicate that enrichment of cytosolic BRAF-MEK1 complexes in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cells is coincident with decreased pMEK levels, suggesting that this complex is quiescent and awaiting pathway activation. Pathway activation following epidermal growth factor (EGF) stimulation of HEK293
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cells results in disruption of the BRAF-MEK1 complex and enhanced levels of phosphorylated MEK1 and ERK1/2 followed by reemergence of the BRAF-MEK complex at the longer time points when pMEK levels return to their basal levels (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D). Hence, dissociation and formation of the BRAF-MEK1 complex correlates with pathway activation, suggesting that this complex is a regulatory component in MAPK signaling.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Oncogenic Mutations of BRAF Disrupt a Cytosolic BRAF-MEK1 Complex(A) Immunoblot ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (712 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In order to assess directly whether RAF dimerization is required for interaction with MEK1 or RAS-GTP, we conducted cotransfection experiments in HEK293 cells with mCherry-tagged WT BRAF or BRAF
    <sup>
     R509H
    </sup>
    and Flag-tagged WT BRAF with growth factor stimulation. As seen in
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    D, pathway stimulation with EGF at very early time points (5 min) promotes BRAF association with RAS in a BRAF-dimerization-dependent manner, illustrating that BRAF dimerization is required for interaction with RAS-GTP. Notably, overexpression studies do not capture the dynamic plasticity between BRAF and MEK1 in response to EGF as observed with endogenous proteins. Our cellular studies illustrate that BRAF and MEK form a quiescent, cytosolic complex that can be activated upon pathway stimulation through RAF dimerization.
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystal Structure of BRAF with MEK1 Reveals a Face-to-Face Kinase-Substrate Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    To elucidate the molecular basis of the BRAF-MEK1 interaction, we determined a 2.85 Å crystal structure of the complex of human BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    (residues 432–726) with its substrate
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1 (MEK1 with N-terminal deletion, residues 62–393), ATP mimetic AMPPCP (ACP), and G-573 (
    <a>
     Choo et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), an ATP-uncompetitive inhibitor of MEK1 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A;
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). This structure revealed that BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    and
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1 form a stable tetramer in which a central BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    dimer interacts with two molecules of
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1. BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    and MEK1 form a face-to-face heterodimer with juxtaposed ATP binding sites (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B). This face-to-face interaction is analogous to the complex formed between p38 and its substrate MAPK-activated protein kinase 2 (
    <a>
     White et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). The details of the BRAF-MEK1 and p38-MK2 interactions differ considerably, indicating that variation in kinase-kinase interactions is tolerated and may have been exploited by evolutionary forces to generate additional regulatory mechanisms. Although it has been demonstrated that BRAF dimerization is important for enzymatic activity, the BRAF-MEK1 interaction is independent of BRAF dimerization with monomeric BRAF (BRAF
    <sup>
     R509H
    </sup>
    ) still competent to bind MEK1 with similarly high affinity as the dimeric BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    A and S2B) with K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    values in the 40–60 nM range. This is consistent with our transient transfection experiments where both BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    and the monomeric BRAF
    <sup>
     R509H
    </sup>
    immunoprecipitate with MEK.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="BRAF and MEK1 Form a Stable Tetramer that Is Mediated through the BRAF Dimer ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1171 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 interface is formed by both the β-rich N lobes and the predominantly α-helical C lobes, yielding a high affinity interaction (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    ∼43 nM;
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    B) with critical contacts between the activation segments (AS) of the two proteins (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and 2C). The active conformation of the BRAF AS is stabilized by an intramolecular salt bridge between R575, the conserved “R” in the BRAF “HRD” motif, and E611 in BRAF (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). E611 acts as a phosphomimic to stabilize the active conformation of BRAF AS and aligns structurally with phosphorylated threonine residues in the active conformation of kinases such as T197 in PKCα (Protein Data Bank [PDB] code
    <a>
     1ATP
    </a>
    ). Thus, R575 is not expected to interact with a phosphorylated residue in the AS as is typical for the HRD motif, suggesting that BRAF can adopt an active conformation in a complex with MEK1 in the absence of phosphorylation of its activation segment. Residues analogous to R575 and E611 are conserved across the RAF family, indicating this is a shared feature of all RAF family members.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the complex described above, BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    adopts an active-like conformation of the αC helix and AS, whereas MEK1 is in an inactive conformation (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B;
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    C). ACP and Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    are found in the MEK1 active site, while G-573 is bound at the adjacent allosteric site between the N and C lobes (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and 2C;
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    D). While G-573 and ACP are not necessary for formation of a tetrameric or dimeric BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 complex in solution (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    A and S2E), inclusion of G-573 stabilizes the complex in a preactivation-like state through specific interactions with the MEK1 activation loop. G-573 forms numerous interactions with MEK1 including a hydrogen bond with the amide backbone of S212 in the AS such that MEK1 residues S218 and S222 are not accessible for phosphorylation by BRAF (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    D) (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). In the absence of this inhibitor, the MEK1 activation loop is likely sufficiently flexible to access the active site of BRAF without disruption of the rest of the interface. Phosphorylation at S218 and S222 following incubation of RAF and MEK1 with ATP may result in dissociation of RAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 complexes due to the steric and electrostatic effects of phosphorylation. Binding of a nucleotide analog alone (AMP-PCP) in the absence of a MEK inhibitor has no effect on complex formation (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    E). However, these data do not eliminate the possibility that MEK1 is released from BRAF and then phosphorylated. To confirm that BRAF phosphorylation does not significantly affect the interaction with MEK1, we conducted mass spectrometric experiments where BRAF alone or in a complex with MEK1 was incubated with or without ATP. As observed in
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    F–S2M, purified recombinant BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    is constitutively phosphorylated at S446 and no significant changes in BRAF phosphorylation are observed when in a complex with MEK in the absence or presence of ATP. These data indicate that the BRAF-MEK complex is sensitive to MEK phosphorylation at S218 and S222 but not to the BRAF phosphorylation state.
   </p>
   <p>
    A comparison of our BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 structure to the structure of MEK1 in a complex with the kinase-like domain of KSR2 (KSR2
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    ) (
    <a>
     Brennan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    N) reveals overall structural similarities. However, unlike the BRAF kinase domain, the AS and αC helix of KSR are in an inactive conformation in a complex with MEK (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    O). Further, the KSR
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    is rotated ∼25° relative to the BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    , resulting in fewer interactions with the N and C lobes of MEK (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    N). The BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1, KSR2-MEK1 (
    <a>
     Brennan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ), and MEK1-MEK1 (
    <a>
     Ohren et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) interactions all utilize a common conserved surface on the C lobe of MEK1 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D), indicating that MEK1 binding to BRAF, KSR, or another MEK1 molecule is mutually exclusive. Further, given the high affinity BRAF-MEK1 complex exists as a stable heterotetramer in solution while the MEK1-MEK1 complex exists in a monomer-dimer equilibrium (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    A), formation of the BRAF-MEK1 heterotetramer would be favored over the MEK1-MEK1 homodimer. Thus, which protein MEK1 is associated with will depend on the cellular context, including the relative concentrations and affinities of potential binding partners. As BRAF is found in excess of immunodepleted MEK1 (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    C), it is not surprising that MEK1 is largely bound to BRAF in cell lines with low levels of basal pMEK.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To confirm the physiological relevance of the BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 crystal structure, we generated mutations targeting the heterodimer interface (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). Immunoprecipitation of transiently transfected BRAF from BRAF null cells (HEC1A
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      −/−
     </em>
    </sup>
    ) demonstrates that interface mutations either in the N-terminal lobe (R462E) or in the C-terminal lobe (I617R) of BRAF weaken binding to MEK1 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). Furthermore, the R462E substitution in the P loop of BRAF enhances CRAF phosphorylation on S338 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B), a known indicator of CRAF activity (
    <a>
     Hu et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Mason et al., 1999
    </a>
    ) similar to assessments of nonactivating mutations in the BRAF P loop (
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). In contrast, the BRAF I617R mutation alone completely disrupts binding to MEK1 and does not enhance CRAF phosphorylation on S338. While the structural rationale for the defect in MEK1 binding is clear, the rationale for loss of CRAF transactivation is not apparent. Complementary interface mutations in MEK1 also weaken or abolish BRAF binding as revealed by BRAF-MEK1 protein-protein interaction assays (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). Further, MEK1 variants with interface mutations result in diminished ERK phosphorylation (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D), suggesting that association with BRAF is a prerequisite for MEK1 phosphorylation and subsequent ERK phosphorylation. In sum, these data establish that the BRAF-MEK1 interface observed in the crystal structure is functionally relevant.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Point Mutations at the BRAF-MEK1 Interface Disrupt Dimer Formation and Have ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (788 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Oncogenic P Loop Mutations in BRAF Weaken the BRAF-MEK1 Dimer and Enhance Pathway Activation
   </title>
   <p>
    Activating, partially activating, and inactivating oncogenic BRAF mutations occur in the vicinity of the BRAF-AS and the BRAF-BRAF or BRAF-MEK1 interfaces (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A). While it has been reported that the nonactivating BRAF P-loop mutations require dimerization with CRAF to drive CRAF activation (
    <a>
     Freeman et al., 2013
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), it is unclear how these mutations affect BRAF and CRAF dimerization as the P-loop is on the opposite face of BRAF from the dimerization interface. Although the BRAF P-loop is partially disordered and any interactions it might make with the MEK1 activation loop during phosphorylation may be affected by the presence of G-573 in our structure, it lies in close proximity to a BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 salt bridge at the dimer interface (BRAF R462 and MEK1 E138;
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). As described above, overexpression of BRAF
    <sup>
     R462E
    </sup>
    in the HEC1A
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      −/−
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell line resulted in increased CRAF-Ser338 phosphorylation (pCRAF-S338), enhanced pMEK levels, and reduced interaction with MEK1 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). Similarly, the oncogenic P loop BRAF variants G464V, G464E, or G466V exhibit reduced MEK1 binding and enhanced CRAF binding (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B). Overexpression of these mutants in the HEC1A
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      −/−
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell line enhances CRAF mediated MEK1 activation, as indicated by pMEK and pCRAF-S338 levels (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). To test whether BRAF
    <sup>
     P loop
    </sup>
    mutations directly exhibit weakened affinity for MEK1, we assessed binding of BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    and BRAF
    <sup>
     P loop
    </sup>
    mutant proteins to MEK1 in pull-down assays. As seen in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D, recombinant BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    mutants—including BRAF
    <sup>
     R462E
    </sup>
    , which forms a direct salt bridge to MEK-E138 in our structure—exhibit weakened binding to MEK1 compared to BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    . While G464V and G464E have reduced enzymatic activity but similar K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    (ATP) compared to BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    , BRAF G466V/E mutants are catalytically inactive (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    C). Therefore, oncogenic mutations within the P loop of BRAF function in a kinase-independent manner by detrimentally affecting MEK1 binding to BRAF and enhancing CRAF mediated signaling resulting in elevated pMEK levels in cells.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Oncogenic Mutations in BRAF P-Loop Have Decreased Affinity to MEK1(A) MEK1 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (584 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    The BRAF V600E-K507 Salt Bridge Renders BRAF Kinase Activity Dimer Independent
   </title>
   <p>
    BRAF activity is known to be dependent on dimerization and all structures of BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    known to date are dimeric (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    A). The commonly mutated residue V600 in the BRAF-AS lies in close proximity to K507 in the αC helix of BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) such that a V600E mutation could form favorable electrostatic interactions with K507. Structures of ATP bound or apo BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -V600E are unavailable; however, our BRAF-MEK1 structure reveals similar positioning for V600 in the absence of any bound inhibitor (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). Consistent with published reports, we find that BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    catalytic activity requires BRAF dimerization, while BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    catalytic activity remains insensitive to this regulatory process (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B) (
    <a>
     Holderfield et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Both the BRAF-MEK1 structure as well as the structure of BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    bound to the inhibitor GDC-0879 display an active conformation of the αC helix and AS (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). In the context of BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    mutation, this conformation likely persists even in the absence of dimerization due to formation of a salt bridge between the negatively charged side chain of E600 with K507 in the αC helix in the BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). Accordingly, the charge-reversal mutation of K507 to glutamate, expected to disrupt this salt bridge, renders BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E, K507E
    </sup>
    activity dependent on dimerization (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). The K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    for ATP of BRAF
    <sup>
     WT
    </sup>
    and the dimer defective BRAF
    <sup>
     R509H
    </sup>
    is similar (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    C), showing that BRAF dimerization is not required for ATP or MEK1 binding but is necessary for catalytic activity. Thus, the V600E mutation renders BRAF constitutively active by stabilizing active conformations of BRAF independent of RAS induced dimerization with CRAF or BRAF.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Activating Mutation V600E Renders BRAF Kinase Activity Independent of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (616 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    BRAF Inhibitors Can Enrich or Disrupt a BRAF-MEK1 Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    Since the BRAF-MEK1 complex is enriched in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell lines where paradoxical activation with BRAF inhibitors is observed, we investigated the pharmacological effects of BRAF inhibitors on complex formation. The subtle variations in the conformation of BRAF observed in cocrystal structures (
    <a>
     Tsai et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wan et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wenglowsky et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) indicate that BRAF is a dynamic protein that adopts different conformations depending on the nature of the bound inhibitor (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    A). Type I BRAF inhibitors that stabilize the αC helix in an “active-like” conformation can induce priming of the MAPK pathway in
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    tumor lines through enhanced BRAF-CRAF dimerization (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Comparing “active-like” (current work) and “inactive” BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    structures (
    <a>
     Bollag et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Tsai et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wenglowsky et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A), we predicted that BRAF inhibitors such as vemurafenib, PLX4720, or AR004549 that shift the BRAF αC helix toward an inactive conformation would weaken MEK1 binding, while BRAF inhibitors such as GDC-0879 that favor the active orientation of the αC helix as well as the extended conformation of the BRAF-AS (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A;
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    A) would stabilize the BRAF-MEK1 complex. Indeed, GDC-0879 promotes binding of BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    to MEK1 in the presence of ATP or ACP in our in vitro biochemical assays, whereas vemurafenib decreases it (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B;
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    B). In HCT116 (
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    ) cells, the RAF inhibitor GDC-0879 primes the pathway as observed with elevated pMEK levels at the lowest concentration tested but then enriches the BRAF-MEK1 complex while dampening pMEK levels at the higher concentrations (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C). In contrast, vemurafenib destabilizes the BRAF-MEK1 complex, resulting in enhanced pathway activation and elevated pMEK levels (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C). Although vemurafenib does not substantially induce BRAF-CRAF dimerization (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), the dissociation of MEK1 from BRAF likely contributes to the priming observed with inhibitors that stabilize inactive conformations of BRAF, similar to what we have observed with the BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    mutant proteins. As expected, pathway priming by vemurafenib is not seen in A375 cells (
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      V600E
     </em>
    </sup>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D) where BRAF-MEK1 complexes are absent and the constitutively active kinase is inhibited. Vemurafenib also has little effect on pMEK levels or enrichment of RAF-MEK1 complexes in the
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      P-loop
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell line MDA-MB-231 (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    C) as the pathway is already primed (BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    and CRAF are constitutively dimerized and CRAF is activated). In contrast, GDC-0879 effectively inhibits pMEK levels in a dose-dependent manner in A375 tumor lines (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D) and in tumor lines such as MDA-MB-231 and H1666 that harbor BRAF P-loop mutations with concomitant enrichment of RAF-MEK1 complexes (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    E). This effect is due to the ability of GDC-0879 to stabilize the active conformation of BRAF preferred for binding to MEK1. In the absence of a structure of a BRAF P-loop mutant protein, it is difficult to predict what specific conformation the protein adopts, but given the dynamic nature of the P loop in BRAF and other protein kinases (
    <a>
     Huse and Kuriyan, 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Patel and Doerksen, 2010
    </a>
    ), it is likely that mutations in the BRAF P-loop impact the conformational dynamics of the BRAF kinase domain, which would be expected to impact interaction with MEK1. Thus, the mechanism of action of GDC-0879 is 2-fold in that it not only inhibits BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    enzymatic activity but also sequesters a dormant RAF-MEK1 complex in cells through stabilization of the active BRAF conformation.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Different Classes of BRAF Inhibitors Have Distinct Effects on the BRAF-MEK1 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1320 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    BRAF and MEK1 form a high affinity complex that is sensitive to MEK1 phosphorylation and to the active conformation of the BRAF kinase domain but is independent of BRAF dimerization. Further, complexes of BRAF and MEK1 exist in the cytosol of
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    and
    <em>
     KRAS
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      MT
     </em>
    </sup>
    cells awaiting additional signaling cues for RAS-mediated RAF dimerization and MEK phosphorylation resulting in dissociation of the BRAF-MEK1 complex. As the N-terminal domain of the full-length RAF acts as an autoregulatory domain preventing RAF dimerization and membrane localization (
    <a>
     Chong and Guan, 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Cutler et al., 1998
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Terai and Matsuda, 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Tran et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weber et al., 2001
    </a>
    ) and since the full-length RAF resides as a monomer in the cytosol under resting conditions (
    <a>
     Nan et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), we propose that the cytosolic and quiescent BRAF-MEK1 complex observed in cells is likely a heterodimeric complex with the N-terminal domain of the full-length BRAF preventing RAF dimerization until the pathway is stimulated (see model in
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    ). Pathway activation would result in BRAF-CRAF dimerization and formation of a transient, signaling competent heterotetrameric RAF-MEK1 complex that can rapidly phosphorylate MEK1 in
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    . This heterotetrameric complex is captured in our BRAF-MEK1 crystal structure in the presence of the MEK inhibitor G-573. Once MEK1 is phosphorylated, the RAF-MEK1 heterotetrameric complex is destabilized and phosphorylated MEK1 is available to phosphorylate the terminal kinase ERK in the signaling pathway. Over time as pathway feedback is induced and pMEK levels decrease, the BRAF-MEK1 complex is reestablished.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Model Depicting MAPK Pathway Activation in Different Genetic ContextsIn the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610814002992-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (609 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Our structural studies have generated insights on the diverse mechanisms of activating and nonactivating BRAF mutations. The BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    mutation activates the pathway by favoring a constitutively active conformation independent of BRAF dimerization, whereas nonactivating BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    mutations weaken the BRAF-MEK1 interface and enhance BRAF-CRAF dimerization (see model in
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    ). Hence, the presence of a preformed BRAF-MEK1 complex in cells suggests that substrate recognition (i.e., RAF recognition of its substrate MEK1) is not a rate-limiting step in RAF-MEK pathway signaling, but rather BRAF and CRAF dimerization is. Indeed, oncogenic mutations in BRAF either bypass the requirement for dimerization completely (i.e., BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    ), constitutively dimerize with CRAF (i.e., BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    mutations), or form constitutive BRAF homodimers through deletion of the BRAF N-terminal negative regulatory domain (
    <a>
     Sievert et al., 2013
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    As RAF dimerization is a key step in pathway activation, it is not surprising that BRAF and CRAF heterodimerization and MEK1 activation is tightly regulated and dependent on multiple factors including RAF phosphorylation and interaction with 14-3-3 (
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Ritt et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rushworth et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). BRAF and CRAF have distinct functions with respect to MEK1 activation, leading to a recent model in which BRAF functions as the “activator” of the CRAF “receiver” kinase through a dimerization-dependent mechanism that drives CRAF autophosphorylation (
    <a>
     Hu et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). In this model, CRAF association with MEK occurs only after membrane localization and dimerization of BRAF and CRAF. This agrees well with our observations that cell lines with low basal pMEK levels are enriched with high BRAF-MEK1 complexes and less so with CRAF-MEK1. As the relative stoichiometry of BRAF and CRAF can affect MAPK signaling output and since the MEK interaction with CRAF drives CRAF activation (
    <a>
     Hu et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Leicht et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), our data suggest that the presence of a BRAF-MEK1 complex modulates flux through the MAPK pathway. Accordingly, mutations in the BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    , which exhibit weakened interaction with MEK1 and enhanced dimerization with CRAF, likely position BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    to function as an “activator” of CRAF through a dimerization-dependent manner.
   </p>
   <p>
    Regulation of BRAF-CRAF dimerization through interaction with 14-3-3 is yet another mechanism to control pathway signaling. Mutation of CRAF-S621 or BRAF-S729 (residues recognized by 14-3-3) to alanine modulates binding of CRAF to BRAF and diminishes CRAF kinase activity even in the context of oncogenic BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    mutants, suggesting that mutation of the BRAF
    <sup>
     P-loop
    </sup>
    alone is not sufficient to activate the pathway (
    <a>
     Garnett et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Ritt et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rushworth et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). Hence, BRAF P-loop mutations enhance B and CRAF heterodimers in a 14-3-3-dependent fashion, resulting in enhanced CRAF activation. Interestingly, we were able to isolate MEK1-BRAF-14-3-3 complexes, indicating that the BRAF-MEK1 complex is stable even in the presence of the 14-3-3 protein (data not shown). Further studies are needed to understand how scaffolding and chaperone proteins affect MAPK pathway flux in the context of regulating BRAF-MEK1 complex formation.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our data also shed light on existing models of KSR as a scaffolding protein in canonical MAPK signaling. As our studies show that the BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 is a high affinity complex, local concentration and cellular stoichiometry of KSR may be a key determinant for displacing BRAF from MEK1. Furthermore, KSR may be more competent as a RAF activating protein, where it can enhance MAPK signaling by forming a dimer with BRAF or CRAF (
    <a>
     McKay et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Michaud et al., 1997
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rajakulendran et al., 2009
    </a>
    ) rather than serving to recruit MEK to BRAF-CRAF complexes activated by RAS on the plasma membrane (
    <a>
     Morrison, 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Müller et al., 2001
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Understanding different molecular mechanisms governing BRAF-mediated pathway activation may aid in developing mutation-appropriate therapeutic strategies. Type I ATP competitive BRAF inhibitors that position BRAF in an active conformation and enrich RAF-MEK1 complexes can antagonize the MAPK pathway by inhibiting both kinase-dependent and kinase-independent functions of BRAF. Sequestering signaling incompetent RAF-MEK1 complexes in cells with BRAF inhibitors may have particular utility in settings where kinase inactivating BRAF mutations are the drivers of pathway activity. Importantly, we show that ATP-competitive BRAF inhibitors can affect both kinase activity and the propensity of BRAF to engage in protein-protein interactions. In particular, the BRAF activation segment, αC helix and the P-loop exhibit conformational variability in the presence of inhibitors, oncogenic mutations, or protein binding partners. This conformational plasticity of BRAF alters pathway signaling analogous to the signaling mechanisms associated with G protein coupled receptors, nuclear hormone receptors, and small GTPase signaling proteins (
    <a>
     Kobilka and Deupi, 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nagy and Schwabe, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Vetter and Wittinghofer, 2001
    </a>
    ). As with these proteins, targeting kinases with ATP-competitive inhibitors that stabilize active or inactive conformations of the enzyme can not only block kinase activity directly but also elicit additional effects on pathway signaling due to altered protein-protein interactions. In the case of MAPK signaling, the additional effects are counterintuitive as enzymatic inhibitors can induce pathway activation by favoring BRAF-CRAF heterodimers (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Heidorn et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Poulikakos et al., 2010
    </a>
    ) or can block the pathway through both inhibition of enzymatic activity and enrichment of a dormant kinase-substrate (RAF-MEK1) protein complex as we have reported for both BRAF and MEK inhibitors (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). For other kinases, the effects will depend on the specifics of the signaling pathways involved. Thus, the conformational dependence of regulatory functions of proteins is an important factor for consideration in the discovery and design of therapeutic inhibitors.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <p>
    Additional procedures are described in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Antibodies, Reagents, and Cell Lines
   </title>
   <p>
    Anti-BRAF and -RHO GDI were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. Anti-CRAF was purchased from BD Biosciences. Anti-pMEK1/2, -MEK1, -ERK1/2, -pERK1/2, -Ras, -Cadherin, and -pCRAFS338 were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology. Anti-FLAG antibody and EGF were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Mammalian
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    cDNA expression constructs used in this work were described previously (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
    </a>
    ) and generated with the QuickChange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Agilent Technologies) using
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      WT
     </em>
    </sup>
    as the template. G-573 and GDC-0879 were synthesized at Genentech as described previously (
    <a>
     Choo et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hansen et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Vemurafenib was synthesized as described in WO2007002325. PLX4720 was purchased from Active Biochem. Cells were obtained from the Genentech cell line repository and were cultured according to ATCC specifications. The HEC1A
    <em>
     BRAF
    </em>
    <sup>
     <em>
      −/−
     </em>
    </sup>
    cell line has been described previously (
    <a>
     Kim et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Biochemical Detection of RAF-MEK1 Protein Complexes
   </title>
   <p>
    Biochemical BRAF-MEK1 homogeneous time-resolved fluorescence (hTRF) based experiments and kinase assays were conducted as described previously (
    <a>
     Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Detection of RAF-MEK1 complexes from cells was performed by coimmunoprecipitation. Briefly, cells were lysed in assay buffer (10 mM Tris [pH 7.4], 50 mM NaCl, 0.5% [v/v] NP-40, 1 mM EDTA, 1× protease inhibitors, and 1× HALT phosphatase inhibitors). MEK1, BRAF, or CRAF were immunoprecipitated from 1 mg of precleared cell lysate with rabbit anti-MEK1 (Millipore No. 07-641), rabbit anti-BRAF (Sigma No. A001328), or rabbit anti-CRAF (Millipore No. 07-396) overnight at 4°C. Protein A agarose beads (Thermo Scientific No. 53139) were used to capture the protein-antibody complex, followed by washes and the addition of SDS sample buffer. Samples were boiled and analyzed by immunoblot.
   </p>
   <title>
    Subcellular Fractionation
   </title>
   <p>
    Cells were harvested in fractionation buffer (20 mM Tris [pH 7.4], 50 mM NaCl, 1× EDTA-free protease inhibitors, and 1× HALT phosphatase inhibitors). After incubation on ice for 20 min, cells were homogenized by shearing through a 27-gauge needle. The sample was centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for 10 min to sediment the nuclei. The supernatant was then spun at 14,000 rpm for 30 min at 4°C to separate the sedimented membrane fraction from the soluble cytosolic fraction. The membrane pellet was washed with 1 ml of fractionation buffer, centrifuged at 14,000 rpm for 20 min at 4°C, and resuspended in fractionation buffer containing 1% NP-40. Fractions were analyzed by immunoblot.
   </p>
   <title>
    Protein Production, Purification, and Crystallization of BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1 and BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
   </title>
   <p>
    His-tagged human recombinant BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    (insect cells) and.
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1 (
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    ) were purified by affinity, ion exchange and size exclusion chromatography. BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    and excess
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK were incubated at 4°C, and the complex purified by size exclusion chromatography. The tetramer-containing fractions were pooled and concentrated to 16 mg/ml in a “complex buffer” (see
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    ). The BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -
    <sup>
     Δ
    </sup>
    <sup>
     N
    </sup>
    MEK1 complex crystallized in 2 μl hanging drops composed of equal amounts of protein at 16 mg/mL and well solution of 12%–18% PEG 8000 and 0.1 M Tris (pH 8.5–8.8). Crystals appeared after 3 weeks and grew to 100–200 μm in size in 5 weeks. Data were collected at SSRL beamline 11-1. The structure was solved by molecular replacement using PDB codes
    <a>
     1UWH
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     2EQC
    </a>
    as search models, revealing two BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    -MEK1 tetramers in the crystallographic asymmetric unit. Cycles of building and refinement resulted in the final model. Structural figures were created with Pymol. Crystals of BRAF
    <sup>
     KD
    </sup>
    bound to GDC-0879 were grown and the structure solved as described in
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Author Contributions
   </title>
   <p>
    J.R.H. conducted the biochemistry and cell biology experiments. J.S. solved the crystal structure of BRAF-MEK1 and BRAF-V600E with GDC-0879. J.R.H., J.S., S.G.H., and S.M. wrote the manuscript.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The BRAF-MEK1 and BRAF
    <sup>
     V600E
    </sup>
    -GDC-0879 structures were deposited and assigned PDB codes
    <a>
     4MNE
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     4MNF
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Supplemental Experimental Procedures, Figures S1–S5, and Table S1.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (8115 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (11946 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Baljuls et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Baljuls, T. Mueller, H.C. Drexler, M. Hekman, U.R. Rapp
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Unique N-region determines low basal activity and limited inducibility of A-RAF kinase: the role of N-region in the evolutionary divergence of RAF kinase function in vertebrates
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 282 (2007), pp. 26575–26590
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bollag et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Bollag, P. Hirth, J. Tsai, J. Zhang, P.N. Ibrahim, H. Cho, W. Spevak, C. Zhang, Y. Zhang, G. Habets,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Clinical efficacy of a RAF inhibitor needs broad target blockade in BRAF-mutant melanoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 467 (2010), pp. 596–599
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brennan et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.F. Brennan, A.C. Dar, N.T. Hertz, W.C. Chao, A.L. Burlingame, K.M. Shokat, D. Barford
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A Raf-induced allosteric transition of KSR stimulates phosphorylation of MEK
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 472 (2011), pp. 366–369
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chong and Guan, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Chong, K.L. Guan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of Raf through phosphorylation and N terminus-C terminus interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 36269–36276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chong et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Chong, J. Lee, K.L. Guan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Positive and negative regulation of Raf kinase activity and function by phosphorylation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 20 (2001), pp. 3716–3727
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Choo et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.F. Choo, M. Belvin, J. Chan, K. Hoeflich, C. Orr, K. Robarge, X. Yang, M. Zak, J. Boggs
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Preclinical disposition and pharmacokinetics-pharmacodynamic modeling of biomarker response and tumour growth inhibition in xenograft mouse models of G-573, a MEK inhibitor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Xenobiotica, 40 (2010), pp. 751–762
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Clapéron and Therrien, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Clapéron, M. Therrien
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         KSR and CNK: two scaffolds regulating RAS-mediated RAF activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 26 (2007), pp. 3143–3158
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cutler et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.E. Cutler Jr., R.M. Stephens, M.R. Saracino, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Autoregulation of the Raf-1 serine/threonine kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 95 (1998), pp. 9214–9219
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Davies et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Davies, G.R. Bignell, C. Cox, P. Stephens, S. Edkins, S. Clegg, J. Teague, H. Woffendin, M.J. Garnett, W. Bottomley,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mutations of the BRAF gene in human cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 417 (2002), pp. 949–954
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Freeman et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.K. Freeman, D.A. Ritt, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Effects of Raf dimerization and its inhibition on normal and disease-associated Raf signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 49 (2013), pp. 751–758
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Galabova-Kovacs et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Galabova-Kovacs, A. Kolbus, D. Matzen, K. Meissl, D. Piazzolla, C. Rubiolo, K. Steinitz, M. Baccarini
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         ERK and beyond: insights from B-Raf and Raf-1 conditional knockouts
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Cycle, 5 (2006), pp. 1514–1518
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Garnett et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.J. Garnett, S. Rana, H. Paterson, D. Barford, R. Marais
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Wild-type and mutant B-RAF activate C-RAF through distinct mechanisms involving heterodimerization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 20 (2005), pp. 963–969
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goetz et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.A. Goetz, J.J. O’Neil, M.A. Farrar
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Membrane localization, oligomerization, and phosphorylation are required for optimal raf activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 51184–51189
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hansen et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.D. Hansen, J. Grina, B. Newhouse, M. Welch, G. Topalov, N. Littman, M. Callejo, S. Gloor, M. Martinson, E. Laird,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Potent and selective pyrazole-based inhibitors of B-Raf kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 18 (2008), pp. 4692–4695
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hatzivassiliou et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Hatzivassiliou, K. Song, I. Yen, B.J. Brandhuber, D.J. Anderson, R. Alvarado, M.J. Ludlam, D. Stokoe, S.L. Gloor, G. Vigers,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAF inhibitors prime wild-type RAF to activate the MAPK pathway and enhance growth
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 464 (2010), pp. 431–435
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hatzivassiliou et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Hatzivassiliou, J.R. Haling, H. Chen, K. Song, S. Price, R. Heald, J.F. Hewitt, M. Zak, A. Peck, C. Orr,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mechanism of MEK inhibition determines efficacy in mutant KRAS- versus BRAF-driven cancers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 501 (2013), pp. 232–236
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Heidorn et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.J. Heidorn, C. Milagre, S. Whittaker, A. Nourry, I. Niculescu-Duvas, N. Dhomen, J. Hussain, J.S. Reis-Filho, C.J. Springer, C. Pritchard, R. Marais
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Kinase-dead BRAF and oncogenic RAS cooperate to drive tumor progression through CRAF
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 140 (2010), pp. 209–221
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Holderfield et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Holderfield, H. Merritt, J. Chan, M. Wallroth, L. Tandeske, H. Zhai, J. Tellew, S. Hardy, M. Hekmat-Nejad, D.D. Stuart,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAF inhibitors activate the MAPK pathway by relieving inhibitory autophosphorylation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 23 (2013), pp. 594–602
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hu et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Hu, H. Yu, A.P. Kornev, J. Zhao, E.L. Filbert, S.S. Taylor, A.S. Shaw
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mutation that blocks ATP binding creates a pseudokinase stabilizing the scaffolding function of kinase suppressor of Ras, CRAF and BRAF
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 108 (2011), pp. 6067–6072
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hu et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Hu, E.C. Stites, H. Yu, E.A. Germino, H.S. Meharena, P.J. Stork, A.P. Kornev, S.S. Taylor, A.S. Shaw
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Allosteric activation of functionally asymmetric RAF kinase dimers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 154 (2013), pp. 1036–1046
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huse and Kuriyan, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Huse, J. Kuriyan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The conformational plasticity of protein kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 109 (2002), pp. 275–282
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ishii et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Ishii, N. Harada, E.W. Joseph, K. Ohara, T. Miura, H. Sakamoto, Y. Matsuda, Y. Tomii, Y. Tachibana-Kondo, H. Iikura,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Enhanced inhibition of ERK signaling by a novel allosteric MEK inhibitor, CH5126766, that suppresses feedback reactivation of RAF activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 73 (2013), pp. 4050–4060
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kim et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.S. Kim, C. Lee, A. Foxworth, T. Waldman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         B-Raf is dispensable for K-Ras-mediated oncogenesis in human cancer cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 64 (2004), pp. 1932–1937
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kobilka and Deupi, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.K. Kobilka, X. Deupi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Conformational complexity of G-protein-coupled receptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Pharmacol. Sci., 28 (2007), pp. 397–406
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kolch, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Kolch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Meaningful relationships: the regulation of the Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK pathway by protein interactions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 351 (2000), pp. 289–305
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kolch, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Kolch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Coordinating ERK/MAPK signalling through scaffolds and inhibitors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 6 (2005), pp. 827–837
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kornfeld et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Kornfeld, D.B. Hom, H.R. Horvitz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The ksr-1 gene encodes a novel protein kinase involved in Ras-mediated signaling in C. elegans
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 83 (1995), pp. 903–913
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lavoie et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Lavoie, N. Thevakumaran, G. Gavory, J.J. Li, A. Padeganeh, S. Guiral, J. Duchaine, D.Y. Mao, M. Bouvier, F. Sicheri, M. Therrien
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inhibitors that stabilize a closed RAF kinase domain conformation induce dimerization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Chem. Biol., 9 (2013), pp. 428–436
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Leicht et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.T. Leicht, V. Balan, J. Zhu, A. Kaplun, A. Bronisz, A. Rana, G. Tzivion
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         MEK-1 activates C-Raf through a Ras-independent mechanism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochim. Biophys. Acta, 1833 (2013), pp. 976–986
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Marais et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Marais, Y. Light, H.F. Paterson, C.S. Mason, C.J. Marshall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Differential regulation of Raf-1, A-Raf, and B-Raf by oncogenic ras and tyrosine kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 4378–4383
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mason et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.S. Mason, C.J. Springer, R.G. Cooper, G. Superti-Furga, C.J. Marshall, R. Marais
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Serine and tyrosine phosphorylations cooperate in Raf-1, but not B-Raf activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 18 (1999), pp. 2137–2148
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McKay et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.M. McKay, D.A. Ritt, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Signaling dynamics of the KSR1 scaffold complex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 106 (2009), pp. 11022–11027
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McKay et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.M. McKay, D.A. Ritt, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAF inhibitor-induced KSR1/B-RAF binding and its effects on ERK cascade signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 21 (2011), pp. 563–568
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Michaud et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.R. Michaud, M. Therrien, A. Cacace, L.C. Edsall, S. Spiegel, G.M. Rubin, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         KSR stimulates Raf-1 activity in a kinase-independent manner
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 94 (1997), pp. 12792–12796
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Morrison, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         KSR: a MAPK scaffold of the Ras pathway?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Sci., 114 (2001), pp. 1609–1612
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Müller et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Müller, S. Ory, T. Copeland, H. Piwnica-Worms, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         C-TAK1 regulates Ras signaling by phosphorylating the MAPK scaffold, KSR1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 8 (2001), pp. 983–993
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nagy and Schwabe, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Nagy, J.W. Schwabe
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mechanism of the nuclear receptor molecular switch
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biochem. Sci., 29 (2004), pp. 317–324
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nan et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        X. Nan, E.A. Collisson, S. Lewis, J. Huang, T.M. Tamgüney, J.T. Liphardt, F. McCormick, J.W. Gray, S. Chu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Single-molecule superresolution imaging allows quantitative analysis of RAF multimer formation and signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 110 (2013), pp. 18519–18524
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nguyen et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Nguyen, W.R. Burack, J.L. Stock, R. Kortum, O.V. Chaika, M. Afkarian, W.J. Muller, K.M. Murphy, D.K. Morrison, R.E. Lewis,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Kinase suppressor of Ras (KSR) is a scaffold which facilitates mitogen-activated protein kinase activation in vivo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 22 (2002), pp. 3035–3045
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ohren et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.F. Ohren, H. Chen, A. Pavlovsky, C. Whitehead, E. Zhang, P. Kuffa, C. Yan, P. McConnell, C. Spessard, C. Banotai,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structures of human MAP kinase kinase 1 (MEK1) and MEK2 describe novel noncompetitive kinase inhibition
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 11 (2004), pp. 1192–1197
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Patel and Doerksen, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.Y. Patel, R.J. Doerksen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein kinase-inhibitor database: structural variability of and inhibitor interactions with the protein kinase P-loop
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Proteome Res., 9 (2010), pp. 4433–4442
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pérez-Lorenzo and Zheng, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Pérez-Lorenzo, B. Zheng
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeted inhibition of BRAF kinase: opportunities and challenges for therapeutics in melanoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biosci. Rep., 32 (2012), pp. 25–33
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Poulikakos et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.I. Poulikakos, C. Zhang, G. Bollag, K.M. Shokat, N. Rosen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAF inhibitors transactivate RAF dimers and ERK signalling in cells with wild-type BRAF
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 464 (2010), pp. 427–430
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rajakulendran et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Rajakulendran, M. Sahmi, M. Lefrançois, F. Sicheri, M. Therrien
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A dimerization-dependent mechanism drives RAF catalytic activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 461 (2009), pp. 542–545
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ribas and Flaherty, 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Ribas, K.T. Flaherty
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         BRAF targeted therapy changes the treatment paradigm in melanoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Clin. Oncol., 8 (2011), pp. 426–433
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ritt et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.A. Ritt, D.M. Monson, S.I. Specht, D.K. Morrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Impact of feedback phosphorylation and Raf heterodimerization on normal and mutant B-Raf signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 30 (2010), pp. 806–819
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Roberts and Der, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.J. Roberts, C.J. Der
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeting the Raf-MEK-ERK mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade for the treatment of cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 26 (2007), pp. 3291–3310
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Röring et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Röring, R. Herr, G.J. Fiala, K. Heilmann, S. Braun, A.E. Eisenhardt, S. Halbach, D. Capper, A. von Deimling, W.W. Schamel,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distinct requirement for an intact dimer interface in wild-type, V600E and kinase-dead B-Raf signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 31 (2012), pp. 2629–2647
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Roy et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Roy, G. Laberge, M. Douziech, D. Ferland-McCollough, M. Therrien
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         KSR is a scaffold required for activation of the ERK/MAPK module
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 16 (2002), pp. 427–438
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rushworth et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.K. Rushworth, A.D. Hindley, E. O’Neill, W. Kolch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation and role of Raf-1/B-Raf heterodimerization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 26 (2006), pp. 2262–2272
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schubbert et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Schubbert, K. Shannon, G. Bollag
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hyperactive Ras in developmental disorders and cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Cancer, 7 (2007), pp. 295–308
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sievert et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Sievert, S.S. Lang, K.L. Boucher, P.J. Madsen, E. Slaunwhite, N. Choudhari, M. Kellet, P.B. Storm, A.C. Resnick
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Paradoxical activation and RAF inhibitor resistance of BRAF protein kinase fusions characterizing pediatric astrocytomas
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 110 (2013), pp. 5957–5962
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sundaram and Han, 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Sundaram, M. Han
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The C. elegans ksr-1 gene encodes a novel Raf-related kinase involved in Ras-mediated signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 83 (1995), pp. 889–901
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Terai and Matsuda, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Terai, M. Matsuda
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The amino-terminal B-Raf-specific region mediates calcium-dependent homo- and hetero-dimerization of Raf
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 25 (2006), pp. 3556–3564
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Therrien et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Therrien, H.C. Chang, N.M. Solomon, F.D. Karim, D.A. Wassarman, G.M. Rubin
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         KSR, a novel protein kinase required for RAS signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 83 (1995), pp. 879–888
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tran et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.H. Tran, X. Wu, J.A. Frost
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         B-Raf and Raf-1 are regulated by distinct autoregulatory mechanisms
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 280 (2005), pp. 16244–16253
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tsai et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Tsai, J.T. Lee, W. Wang, J. Zhang, H. Cho, S. Mamo, R. Bremer, S. Gillette, J. Kong, N.K. Haass,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Discovery of a selective inhibitor of oncogenic B-Raf kinase with potent antimelanoma activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 105 (2008), pp. 3041–3046
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vetter and Wittinghofer, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I.R. Vetter, A. Wittinghofer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The guanine nucleotide-binding switch in three dimensions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 294 (2001), pp. 1299–1304
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wan et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.T. Wan, M.J. Garnett, S.M. Roe, S. Lee, D. Niculescu-Duvaz, V.M. Good, C.M. Jones, C.J. Marshall, C.J. Springer, D. Barford, R. Marais, Cancer Genome Project
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mechanism of activation of the RAF-ERK signaling pathway by oncogenic mutations of B-RAF
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 116 (2004), pp. 855–867
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Weber et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.K. Weber, J.R. Slupsky, H.A. Kalmes, U.R. Rapp
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Active Ras induces heterodimerization of cRaf and BRaf
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 61 (2001), pp. 3595–3598
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wellbrock et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Wellbrock, M. Karasarides, R. Marais
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The RAF proteins take centre stage
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 5 (2004), pp. 875–885
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wenglowsky et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Wenglowsky, L. Ren, K.A. Ahrendt, E.R. Laird, I. Aliagas, B. Alicke, A.J. Buckmelter, E.F. Choo, V. Dinkel, B. Feng,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Pyrazolopyridine inhibitors of B-Raf(V600E). Part 1: the development of selective, orally bioavailable, and efficacious inhibitors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         ACS Med. Chem. Lett., 2 (2011), pp. 342–347
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref62'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         White et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. White, C.A. Pargellis, J.M. Studts, B.G. Werneburg, B.T. Farmer 2nd
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Molecular basis of MAPK-activated protein kinase 2:p38 assembly
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 104 (2007), pp. 6353–6358
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref63'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wimmer and Baccarini, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Wimmer, M. Baccarini
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Partner exchange: protein-protein interactions in the Raf pathway
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biochem. Sci., 35 (2010), pp. 660–668
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref64'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>