<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.12.027
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structural Basis for DNA Binding Specificity by the Auxin-Dependent ARF Transcription Factors
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The plant hormone auxin controls numerous growth and developmental processes and is a key determinant of plant architecture (
    <a>
     Vanneste and Friml, 2009
    </a>
    ). Physiological approaches in the early 20
    <sup>
     th
    </sup>
    century have led to the identification of indole-3-acetic acid as the main natural auxin (
    <a>
     Thimann and Koepfli, 1935
    </a>
    ). In the past decades, genetic studies have revealed mechanisms of hormone biosynthesis (
    <a>
     Ljung, 2013
    </a>
    ), transport (
    <a>
     Grunewald and Friml, 2010
    </a>
    ), and response (
    <a>
     Chapman and Estelle, 2009
    </a>
    ). The cellular response to auxin involves ubiquitin-proteasome-dependent degradation of Auxin/Indole Acetic Acid (Aux/IAA) proteins, transcriptional corepressors (
    <a>
     Szemenyei et al., 2008
    </a>
    ) that act by binding auxin response factors (ARFs) (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). The latter are DNA-binding transcription factors that control the expression of the large set of auxin-dependent genes that mediate hormone-dependent growth and development (
    <a>
     Guilfoyle and Hagen, 2007
    </a>
    ). A central, yet unanswered question in auxin biology is how the simple tryptophan-like indole-3-acetic acid can trigger a wide variety of cellular responses. As the last step in auxin signaling prior to gene regulation, the ARF transcription factors are likely components to confer specificity to auxin response through selection of target genes. Consistent with a role in response diversification, the ARF family consists of 23 members in
    <em>
     Arabidopsis thaliana
    </em>
    and contains &gt;10 members even in the moss
    <em>
     Physcomitrella patens
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Finet et al., 2013
    </a>
    ).
    <em>
     ARF
    </em>
    genes are expressed in dynamic and different patterns during development (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    ), and genetic studies have shown that individual ARFs control distinct developmental processes (
    <a>
     Guilfoyle and Hagen, 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). For example, ARF5 (also named MONOPTEROS [MP] but for consistency referred to as ARF5 here) is critically required for several developmental auxin responses, including embryonic root and flower formation (
    <a>
     Berleth and Jürgens, 1993
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Przemeck et al., 1996
    </a>
    ), whereas ARF1 and 2 control senescence and floral organ abscission (
    <a>
     Ellis et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). These differences between ARFs are at least in part due to differences in protein sequence, as misexpression and promoter-swap studies demonstrated that ARF proteins are not equal (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). Instead, double-mutant analysis suggested that ARF1 and ARF5 act antagonistically (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). ARFs are modular transcription factors, consisting of several domains that have remained conserved despite hundreds of millions of years of evolution (
    <a>
     Finet et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). At their N terminus, all ARFs have a DNA-binding domain (DBD), followed by a middle region (MR) that determines whether ARFs activate or repress target genes (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ) and a C-terminal interaction domain (domain III/IV). The latter has been shown to mediate interactions between ARFs and their Aux/IAA inhibitors, as well as between ARFs (e.g.,
    <a>
     Kim et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). Several lines of evidence suggest that ARF domains are functionally autonomous, i.e., they act in isolation. First, both the DBD and the C-terminal interaction domains are found in other protein families. The DBD harbors a B3 DNA binding motif that is also found in many other plant transcription factors (
    <a>
     Swaminathan et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Similarly, the C-terminal interaction domain III/IV is also found in the interacting Aux/IAA proteins (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kim et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). Second, transient expression assays and domain swaps have demonstrated that each of the three domains can act in isolation (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Here, we address the atomic basis for sequence-specific DNA binding by ARF transcription factors and explore mechanisms by which variation in the ARF DBD selects different target genes. Most ARFs tested have been shown to bind a generic auxin response element (AuxRE;
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1999
    </a>
    ) that was identified based on its occurrence in auxin-dependent promoters (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1995
    </a>
    ). However, because target sites have not been screened exhaustively, it is unknown whether different ARFs prefer distinct binding sites and, if so, what the molecular basis is for such differences. Here, we have determined high-resolution crystal structures of the DNA-binding domains of two divergent ARFs, as well as an ARF-DNA complex. Structure-function analysis and saturating binding site selection lead to a redefined ARF binding motif, as well as a DNA-binding mechanism in which dimerization of ARF DNA binding domains generates cooperative binding to adjacent sites where spacing determines ARF binding affinity. Our study provides an atomic-level explanation for DNA-binding specificity in the auxin pathway.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Crystal Structures of ARF DNA-Binding Domains
   </title>
   <p>
    All ARFs carry a conserved DBD at their N terminus (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). This domain is often followed by an MR that directs transcriptional changes and a C-terminal domain (III/IV) that mediates protein-protein interactions (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). It is well established that domain III/IV is essential for the heterotypic ARF-Aux/IAA interactions that render ARF activity auxin dependent (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A;
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). The same domain has been proposed to mediate ARF-ARF interactions (
    <a>
     Kim et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), but whether this is biologically meaningful has not been established. The ARF DBD is sufficient for binding auxin-responsive promoters (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Its B3 subdomain is found in other transcription factors (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A; (
    <a>
     Swaminathan et al., 2008
    </a>
    ) and was shown to bind DNA in RAV1 (
    <a>
     Yamasaki et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), which suggests domain modularity. Interestingly, phylogenetic trees based on sequence alignments of only the DBD strongly resemble those derived from entire ARF proteins (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    available online), raising the possibility that variations in this domain contribute to the distinct properties of ARFs.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Structure of the ARF DNA-Binding Domain(A) Modular domain organization of ARF, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (711 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Phylogenetic Relationship of Arabidopsis ARFs and Their DNA-Binding Domains, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (200 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To gain insight into the mechanism of DNA binding by ARFs, we expressed and purified the DBD of ARF1 and ARF5/ MP. These two ARFs are phylogenetically distant (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    ), and their divergence occurred early in land plant evolution hundreds of millions of years ago (
    <a>
     Finet et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Based on mutant phenotypes and misexpression analysis, ARF1 and ARF5 are functionally divergent (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Schlereth et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), although both proteins are able to bind the same generic core DNA motif (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). Both proteins were purified to homogeneity and crystallized. The structure of ARF1-DBD was solved using single-wavelength anomalous diffraction (SAD) on a seleno-methionine (SeMet) derivative, and the resulting model was used for molecular replacement on the other structures (
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). We obtained two distinct structures of ARF1-DBD (solved to 1.45 and 2.67 Å resolution) and one of ARF5-DBD (2.15 Å). All three models subtly differed in the topology of several loops but showed the same overall structure (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B–1D,
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    A, and S2B). The crystal structures reveal that the ARF DBDs are composed of three distinct structural domains. One is the B3 domain (residues 120–226 in ARF1-DBD and 154–260 in ARF5-DBD;
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    C), which folds in a seven-stranded open β barrel structure (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B and 1D), similar to the B3 domains of
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    RAV1 (
    <a>
     Yamasaki et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) and Atlg16640 (
    <a>
     Waltner et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). Remarkably, the B3 domain in ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD is embedded in a larger fold context. The regions N- and C-terminal to the B3 domain together form a single second domain (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    A–S2C) that is very similar between ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B and 1C) and constitutes a dimerization domain (DD, see below). Thus, the B3 domain appears to be an insertion in the DD. Structure similarity searches (DALI [(
    <a>
     Holm and Rosenström, 2010
    </a>
    )]; PDBeFold [
    <a>
     Krissinel and Henrick, 2004
    </a>
    ]) on the DD show that there are no homologs in the Protein Data Bank (PDB), hence it defines a hitherto unknown fold, characterized by an antiparallel five-stranded central β sheet that is highly curved (∼100°), resulting in a taco-like shape (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B–1D and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Structures of ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD and New &amp;ldquo;Taco&amp;rdquo; Fold, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;1(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (868 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Finally, the last 80 C-terminal residues form a third separate ancillary domain (AD) that tightly interacts with the DD. The AD folds in a small five-stranded β-barrel-like structure. Structural similarity searches identified the Tudor domain of the human PHD-finger protein 20 (PDB entry 3QII), but the hydrophobic cage that recognizes methylated lysine residues (
    <a>
     Adams-Cioaba et al., 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2006
    </a>
    ) is missing from the ARF-DBD-AD.
   </p>
   <title>
    ARF Dimerization through the DBD
   </title>
   <p>
    Strikingly, in all crystal structures, ARF-DBDs homodimerized through their DD (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    D and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    A–S3C). The dimer interface contacts include hydrophobic interactions (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F) between several highly conserved residues (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    D and S3E), which indicates that this is most probably a physiologically meaningful interaction. It is stabilized by a network of hydrogen bonds, some mediated by water molecules (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E). Interestingly, α helix 6 (α6) of both monomers is juxtaposed and centered at a conserved (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    D and S3E) glycine residue (G245 in ARF1-DBD and G279 in ARF5-DBD). Other residues of this helix (A248, T249, and A253; in ARF5: A282, A283, and A287) engage in hydrophobic interactions (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    E and 1F), whereas the P233–S238 loop (ARF5: P267–S272) fits into a groove of the opposite monomer and involves interactions between S235 (ARF5: S269) on one monomer and K265 and E85 (ARF5: N299 and D118) on the other (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    E,
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    D, and S3E).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Dimerization and Cooperative DNA Binding by ARF-DBDs, Related to Figures 1 and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S3.
        <p>
         Dimerization and Cooperative DNA Binding by ARF-DBDs, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 1
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          3
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         (A– C) Crystal structures of ARF1-DBD-P (A), ARF5-DBD (B) and ARF1-DBD-G245A mutant (C) dimers colored by secondary structure elements (helices: red; sheets: green).
        </p>
        <p>
         (D) Conservation of dimer contacts. Residues in the dimer interface are colored by homology in the
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         ARF family. Blue: conserved; Green: conservative; Yellow: similar; Red: non-conserved. (B) Alignment of
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         ARF sequences, with conservation of residues colored as in (D).
        </p>
        <p>
         (E–G) (E and F) Binding of ARF1-DBD (F) and ARF5-DBD (G) to ER7 oligonucleotide, as well as ER7 with 1 (ER7(m)) or 2 (ER7(2 m)) AuxRE sites mutated. In all cases, the same concentration of ARF1-DBD (100 nM) or ARF5-DBD (125 nM) protein was used, and all measurements were performed on the same SPR chip. RU: Response Units.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1615 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To address whether dimerization is induced by the crystallization conditions or whether this also occurs in solution, small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) was used for ARF1-DBD. Although neither monomer nor dimer models explained the scattering data, a monomer:dimer equilibrium improved the fit dramatically (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). Hence, homodimerization also occurs in solution, and given that both ARF1 and ARF5 dimerize, this is likely a general property of ARF-DBDs.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="DBD Dimerization Is Critical for In&amp;nbsp;Vivo ARF5 Function(A) Small-angle X-ray ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (661 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To next determine whether ARF-DBD homodimerization is required for biological function, we mutated several amino acids in the dimerization interface of ARF5/MP (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ) and tested the ability of mutant proteins to replace the wild-type protein in vivo. The
    <em>
     arf5/mp
    </em>
    mutant is unable to establish an embryonic root and, as a consequence, forms rootless seedlings (
    <a>
     Hardtke and Berleth, 1998
    </a>
    ). Adventitious roots can, however, be induced postembryonically, and mutant plants have distinctive growth defects, including aberrant flowers or even naked, pin-like inflorescences (
    <a>
     Przemeck et al., 1996
    </a>
    ). Importantly, although S269N, G279A and N299S mutations did not impair ARF5 activity during embryonic root formation (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ), G279E, G279I, A282N, and A287N mutations all compromised ARF5 function in vivo (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B). In some cases, these mutated ARF5/MP proteins even induced dominant-negative defects in wild-type plants (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). To ascertain that the failure of these mutant proteins to complement the
    <em>
     arf5/mp
    </em>
    mutant is due to alterations in dimerization properties, rather than abnormal folding behavior, secondary structures were determined using circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy. Consistent with the solubility of purified mutant proteins, none showed deviations in its CD spectrum (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    ), suggesting that all fold normally. Hence, this analysis shows that amino acids at the dimerization interface, in particular in the α-6 helix (G279, A282, and A287), are required for ARF5/MP function in vivo.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Complementation of
         <em>
          mp-B4149
         </em>
         Mutant Phenotypes with Wild-Type and Engineered Mutated ARF/MP Transgenes
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           ARF5 Mutation
          </th>
          <th>
           ARF1 Position
          </th>
          <th>
           Number of Lines
          </th>
          <th>
           Embryonic Rescue (%)
           <hr/>
          </th>
          <th>
           Adult Phenotype
          </th>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Full Rescue
          </th>
          <th>
           Partial Rescue
          </th>
          <th>
           No Rescue
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            DNA-Binding Domain
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Wild-type
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           5
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           normal
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           H170A
          </td>
          <td>
           H136
          </td>
          <td>
           8
          </td>
          <td>
           75
          </td>
          <td>
           25
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           small, bushy flower defects
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R215A
          </td>
          <td>
           R181
          </td>
          <td>
           3
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           sterile, small plants, small fruits
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           P218A
          </td>
          <td>
           P184
          </td>
          <td>
           6
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           normal
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R220A
          </td>
          <td>
           R186
          </td>
          <td>
           8
          </td>
          <td>
           12.5
          </td>
          <td>
           62.5
          </td>
          <td>
           25
          </td>
          <td>
           flower defects, sterile
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Dimerization Domain
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           S269N
          </td>
          <td>
           S235
          </td>
          <td>
           5
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           small, bushy
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           N299S
          </td>
          <td>
           K265
          </td>
          <td>
           3
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           mild flower defects
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           A287N
          </td>
          <td>
           A253
          </td>
          <td>
           4
          </td>
          <td>
           25
          </td>
          <td>
           75
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           curled leaves, flower defect
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           A282N
          </td>
          <td>
           A248
          </td>
          <td>
           5
          </td>
          <td>
           40
          </td>
          <td>
           60
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           flower defect, sterile
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           G279E
          </td>
          <td>
           G245
          </td>
          <td>
           4
          </td>
          <td>
           25
          </td>
          <td>
           75
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           pins/small plants
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           G279I
          </td>
          <td>
           G245
          </td>
          <td>
           2
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
           small plants, small fruits, sterile
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           G279A
          </td>
          <td>
           G245
          </td>
          <td>
           3
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           normal
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Corresponding positions in ARF1 are indicated. Rescue was tested in T1 and T2 generations by scoring for the absence of rootless, transgenic seedlings (resistant to PPT). In addition, vegetative and floral defects were observed.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Circular Dichroism Spectra of ARF DBD Proteins, Related to Figures 3, 4, and 5" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S4.
        <p>
         Circular Dichroism Spectra of ARF DBD Proteins, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 3
         </a>
         ,
         <a>
          4
         </a>
         , and
         <a>
          5
         </a>
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (149 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To address whether these mutations indeed interfere with homodimerization in the context of a full-length ARF protein that also carries the C-terminal interaction domain (III/IV), we employed a fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET)-based interaction assay. Here, interactions between CFP- and YFP-tagged ARF5 are quantified in mesophyll protoplasts (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D;
    <a>
     Russinova et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), and we have previously used this assay to demonstrate ARF-Aux/IAA interactions in vivo (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). In this assay, wild-type ARF5 showed clear homodimerization as measured by a decrease in the average lifetime of the ARF5-CFP donor (expressed as FRET efficiency;
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). As expected from the position of the glycine in the dimerization interface, G279A, G279I, and G279E mutations significantly decreased the FRET efficiency and hence impair dimerization (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). To determine the relative contribution of the DBD and domain III/IV in homodimerization, a truncated ARF5 protein was generated in which domain III/IV was deleted (
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Krogan et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). Homodimerization still occurred, albeit at lower efficiency (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Similarly, the ARF3 protein, which naturally lacks domain III/IV (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1999
    </a>
    ), was also able to homodimerize (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E; compare with ARF3-CFP/free YFP control). Hence, the DBD is sufficient for dimerization in vivo, but interactions through domain III/IV may help to stabilize dimers. Indeed, when the G279I mutation was introduced in the truncated ARF5 protein lacking domains III/IV, FRET efficiency dropped to background levels (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Collectively, these data show that ARF proteins form dimers through interactions between their DNA-binding domains and that this DBD dimerization is required for ARF function in vivo. Sequence alignments show that the amino acids at the dimerization surface are deeply conserved in the ARF family (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    D and S3E), suggesting that this capacity is both widespread and ancient. The interaction surface is composed of many intermolecular interactions (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    E and 1F), which suggests that the interaction may be robust. Indeed, several mutations in residues at the surface (S269N, G279A, and N299S) are tolerated in vivo (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). To test whether such mutations indeed affect the interaction surface, we purified and crystallized the ARF1-G245A mutant (analogous to ARF5-G279A) and solved its structure to 2.3 Å resolution (
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). This showed an overall dimeric structure similar to wild-type ARF1-DBD (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    C). As predicted, the structure showed a disturbed dimerization interface (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    F) in which the 2-fold symmetry is broken and the 233–238 loop of one monomer could not bind the opposing monomer. In summary, the ARF interaction is robust and adaptive, as it tolerates a mutation that significantly affects the interaction surface. Yet, as more drastic mutations (G279E and G279I) in the same residue that measurably interfere with dimerization (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E) impair biological function (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ), we conclude that DBD dimerization is essential for in vivo function of ARF5.
   </p>
   <title>
    Mechanism of DNA Binding by ARFs
   </title>
   <p>
    Based on promoter analysis of an auxin-responsive gene in soybean, a canonical auxin-response element has been defined as TGTCTC (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1995
    </a>
    ). ARF1 was first identified in a screen for factors binding this motif (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). An inverted repeat of the same element, spaced by seven nucleotides (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A; ER7), was shown to be efficiently bound by ARF1 (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). To determine the structural basis for DNA binding, we cocrystallized ARF1-DBD and a double-stranded ER7 oligonucleotide and solved its structure to 2.9 Å (
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). The DNA binding interface is located at the tips of the U-shaped dimer. The two B3 domains bind to the inverted AuxRE elements located at both extremes of the oligonucleotide, and the connecting DNA sequence bridges the gap between the B3 domains (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). The DNA adopts a B-DNA conformation and is bent by 40°.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Cooperative DNA Binding through ARF-DBD Dimerization(A) ER7 nucleotide sequence ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1237 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The structures of apo-ARF1-DBD (without DNA) and DNA-bound ARF1-DBD are very similar, except that the B3 domains are rotated relative to the DDs by 25° (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    C and 3D). As a similar conformational difference is seen between the different apo structures of ARF1 and ARF5 (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    D and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    A), it appears that the B3 domain displays an intrinsic flexibility with respect to the DD and that DNA binding locks the protein into a conformation. Comparing apo- and DNA-bound structures shows that the N-terminal α1 helix functions as a pivot point on which the B3 domain is balanced, and the loops that connect the B3 domain to the DD run down on both sides of the helix (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). Interestingly, these loops are mostly disordered in the structures, which indicates flexibility. Given the dimerization of the DBD and the binding of each TGTCTC element to one of the monomers, this structure now explains the efficient binding of ARF1 to an inverted repeat sequence, as well as the constraints of the spacing between repeats (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1997
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Binding of two AuxRE sites by an ARF dimer suggests that DNA binding may be cooperative. To test whether this is the case, we used surface plasmon resonance (SPR) with immobilized oligonucleotides. Both ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD showed binding to ER7 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    E and 3F and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Binding was sequence specific, as mutating both AuxRE sites completely abrogated binding (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    E and 3F and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Consistent with cooperative binding, mutating only one of the two AuxRE sites reduced the affinity more than 2-fold (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    E, 3F,
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    F, and S3G and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). This cooperative binding behavior of wild-type ARFs predicts that mutations that disturb dimerization should affect DNA binding affinity. We tested this prediction by performing SPR measurements using S269N, G279E, and A282N mutant proteins. Indeed, all three proteins showed a clear reduction in DNA binding affinity to the ER7 oligonucleotide (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). These findings show that dimerization of the ARF DBD generates cooperative DNA-binding behavior. As dimerization is important for in vivo function of ARF5, this suggests that cooperative DNA binding is essential for normal ARF function.
   </p>
   <title>
    Recognition and Specificity of DNA Binding
   </title>
   <p>
    We next addressed the structural basis for specific DNA binding. The B3 domain recognizes the DNA largely at the major groove of both TGTCTC elements (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A, 4B,
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    C, and S5D). The B3 β barrel is positioned laterally to the DNA with the axis of the barrel almost parallel to the axis of the DNA double helix. Two adjacent β strands (β5 and β8) run over the major groove, parallel to the two sugar-phosphate backbones. The loops connecting these strands (R181–R186 and H136–G137; ARF5: R215–R220 and H170–G171), located on either side of the barrel, further penetrate the major groove and make interactions that contribute to specific DNA base recognition (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). In addition to these base contacts, DNA binding involves interactions of the DNA backbone with residues S131, S140, T191, and S194 (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B; ARF5: S165, S174, T227, and S230). In summary, ARF1 binding to the canonical TGTCTC motif involves both base contacts and backbone interactions, and the specific contacts involve only the 5′ bases on one strand, which explains why this part of the motif is critical for ARF DNA binding (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1999
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Sequence-Specific DNA Binding by ARF-DBDs(A) Detail of DNA-protein interface of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1758 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Dimerization and DNA Binding by ARF1-DBD, Related to Figures 1 and 3(A and C) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-figs5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S5.
        <p>
         Dimerization and DNA Binding by ARF1-DBD, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 1
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          3
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         (A and C) Stereo view of the ARF1-DBD dimer interface and (A) and the ARF1-DBD-ER7 protein-DNA interface (C).
        </p>
        <p>
         (B and D) 2Fo-Fc electron density map (blue) of the dimer interface of the apo ARF1-DBD (B) and the protein-DNA interface in the ARF1-DBD-ER7 complex (
         <strong>
          D
         </strong>
         ), contoured at 1 s. The difference density maps Fo-Fc are also shown, contoured at −3.5 s (red) and 3.5 s (green).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1731 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To determine whether the residues that mediate DNA binding in the crystal structure are also required for DNA binding in solution and for ARF function in vivo, several residues were individually mutated to alanines. Even though CD analysis showed that these mutant proteins showed normal overall structure (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    ), SPR analysis of ARF5-H170A (ARF1: H136) and ARF5-R215A (ARF1:R181) proteins revealed that, in both cases, ER7 binding was significantly reduced (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ), which supports a role in DNA binding. Correspondingly, neither of the H170A and R220A (ARF1: R186) mutants could restore normal development to the
    <em>
     arf5/mp
    </em>
    mutant, whereas the P218A (ARF1: P184) mutant was still partially functional (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). These findings support the validity of the protein-DNA contacts observed in the complex structure and show the atomic basis for DNA recognition by ARF proteins.
   </p>
   <p>
    Intriguingly, when comparing the DNA-binding amino acids among and between ARF1 and ARF5, all appear to be almost completely conserved (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    D, 4E, and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    C). This finding raises the question whether ARF1 and ARF5 bind qualitatively different sequences. Even though a generic AuxRE has been defined, no systematic exploration of sequence space has been reported. To determine the spectrum of binding motifs of each protein, we carried out a protein-binding microarray (PBM;
    <a>
     Godoy et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) analysis with recombinant ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD. This analysis is saturating for 6-mers (
    <a>
     Godoy et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) and allows statistical and quantitative evaluation of intrinsic binding site preference for the ARF-DBDs. However, longer motifs such as inverted AuxRE repeats that would be expected for ARF dimers cannot be reliably identified. Strikingly, the preferred binding site of both ARF1 and ARF5 appears to be TGTCGG (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    F and 4G), rather than the “canonical” AuxRE TGTCTC (
    <a>
     Ulmasov et al., 1995
    </a>
    ). It should be noted, however, that the latter is found as an enriched motif, although the former is strongly preferred (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    G). We did not observe a significant difference in the motifs bound by ARF1-DBD or ARF5-DBD (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    G), which is consistent with the invariance of DNA-contacting residues (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    D and 4E).
   </p>
   <p>
    We therefore conclude that the B3 domains of ARF1 and ARF5 do not have qualitatively distinct DNA binding specificity but bind the same spectrum of motifs with quantitatively different efficiency.
   </p>
   <p>
    We next tested which residues in the ARF5 protein contribute to sequence-specific DNA binding by performing PBM analysis on mutant proteins. Sequence-specific binding was lost when either P218 or R215 residues were mutated (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    ), whereas H170A and G171A mutations did not affect binding specificity. This analysis thus helps identify residues within the B3 domain that confer binding specificity (R215 and P218) and distinguish these from residues that contribute to DNA affinity (H170;
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). We next analyzed DNA-binding specificity of proteins impaired in dimerization. Neither ARF5-S269N nor ARF5-G279E altered the PBM binding profile (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    ). This shows that dimerization contributes to DNA binding affinity, but not to the specificity of DNA motif recognition.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="DNA Binding Specificity through Local Protein-DNA InteractionPBM binding ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (511 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Motif Spacing Constrains Specific ARF Binding
   </title>
   <p>
    We found that ARF proteins are extremely conserved at both their dimerization interface and their DNA-contacting residues. As a consequence, both ARF1 and ARF5 dimerize and bind qualitatively similar sequences. A key unanswered question therefore remains how different genes can be selected by different ARFs. We noticed that the largest variation between ARF1 and ARF5 DBDs is in the loops that connect the B3 and DD domains (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A). Therefore, in addition to quantitative differences in binding of the two ARF DBDs to distinct sequence motifs, one could envisage differences in binding of ARF dimers to complex motifs with varying spacing between AuxRE sites. To test this hypothesis, we performed SPR experiments using ER7 oligonucleotides in which the spacing between the two inverted TGTCTC sites was changed to 5 (ER5), 6 (ER6), 8 (ER8), or 9 (ER9). Both ARF1-DBD and ARF5-DBD bound to ER8 with similar efficiency as ER7 binding (
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    B and 6C and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Affinity of ARF1-DBD to ER5, ER6, and ER9 was strongly reduced (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ) to a level comparable to that of ER7 with one TGTCTC site mutated (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    E and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ) or to that of a mutant impaired in dimerization (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). In contrast, ARF5-DBD retained significant binding to all ER versions, although binding efficiency to ER5, ER6, and ER9 was slightly reduced compared with ER7 and 8 (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Hence, in addition to quantitative differences at the level of binding sites, ARF1 and ARF5 markedly differ in their ability to bind complex motifs depending on the spacing of the two binding sites. Such complex sites, with appropriate spacing, are indeed found in the promoters of direct and physiologically relevant ARF5/MP target genes (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D;
    <a>
     Schlereth et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yamaguchi et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). In the case of
    <em>
     LEAFY
    </em>
    , mutating this site abrogated MP-dependent gene regulation (
    <a>
     Yamaguchi et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), which suggests that it represents a physiologically relevant binding site.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="A Spacing-Based Model for ARF DNA-Binding Specificity(A) Conservation of amino ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413015961-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (628 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Our work provides the molecular basis for sequence-specific DNA binding by the ARF transcription factors (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    E). Strikingly, homodimerization of the DNA-binding domain generates cooperative binding behavior. Mutations that affect this dimerization do not qualitatively affect DNA binding specificity but reduce affinity, and their inability to rescue the
    <em>
     arf5/mp
    </em>
    mutant demonstrates the biological relevance of cooperativity for ARF function. This behavior introduces a nonlinear element in auxin response, which may contribute to the switch-like mode suggested for auxin activity (
    <a>
     Lau et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) and could confer robustness against small fluctuations in auxin levels (
    <a>
     Masel and Siegal, 2009
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, the ability of monomers to bind DNA, albeit with much lower affinity, suggests that genomes may harbor distinct high-affinity and low-affinity ARF binding sites. As dimer-bound high-affinity sites are more constrained due to specific spacing requirements, our study predicts that low-affinity sites will outnumber high-affinity sites.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our results also show that domains III/IV are not likely to be important for ARF dimerization upon DNA binding. Previously, a systematic yeast two-hybrid-based interaction analysis among and between ARF and Aux/IAA protein families concluded that ARF homodimerization is limited (
    <a>
     Vernoux et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). However, this study used only the previously known C-terminal domain III/IV. Our finding that the DBD represents a critical ARF dimerization domain calls for re-evaluation of this and other studies. Given the high degree of conservation of residues at the ARF-ARF interaction interface (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    E), along with the notion that the phylogenetically diverse ARF1, ARF3, and ARF5 all homodimerize, it is likely that most, if not all, ARFs homodimerize through their DBD. Whether or not ARFs can also heterodimerize and whether this would be biologically meaningful is another interesting open question.
   </p>
   <p>
    The identification of the ARF DBD as a dimerization domain in addition to the previously known domain III/IV also has interesting implications for both DNA recognition and auxin regulation. First, given domain modularity, it is possible that DNA-bound ARF dimers interact through their domains III/IV with other ARF dimers to build higher-order complexes, analogous to what has been suggested for MADS-box transcription factors (
    <a>
     Smaczniak et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). A testable prediction from such interactions would be that ARF complexes can bind more distantly spaced sites and induce DNA looping. Second, the ability of domains III/IV to mediate both homotypic (Aux/IAA or ARF-ARF) and heterotypic (ARF-Aux/IAA) interactions suggested that Aux/IAAs may obstruct ARF dimerization (reviewed in
    <a>
     Lokerse and Weijers, 2009
    </a>
    ). The existence of an additional dimerization domain in the ARFs suggests a different mechanism of Aux/IAA function. Although Aux/IAAs could, in principle, modulate the stability of ARF-ARF dimers formed through their DBDs, an attractive alternative hypothesis is that they act as competitive inhibitors to prevent the formation of domain III/IV-mediated higher-order DNA-bound ARF complexes.
   </p>
   <p>
    ARFs can have overlapping (
    <a>
     Ellis et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nagpal et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Okushima et al., 2005
    </a>
    ), (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    ), different (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2005
    </a>
    ), or even opposing (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) functions, and an important question is how these different activities are encoded in their structures. Often, in the Homeodomain family (
    <a>
     Berger et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Noyes et al., 2008
    </a>
    ), for example, variation in sequence-specific DNA binding in transcription factor families is generated by substitutions in the DNA-contacting residues. In contrast, intrinsic DNA-binding specificity among ARF proteins is highly similar, even between the phylogenetically diverse family members ARF1 and ARF5, a finding that is consistent with the limited sequence divergence at the DNA-binding surface. One potential caveat is that, even though ARF domains can fold and act in isolation (this study and
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ), it is possible that other domains alter DNA binding specificity by intramolecular interactions with the DBD. Particularly the middle region is very divergent between ARFs and correlated with the ability of ARFs to either activate or repress transcription (
    <a>
     Tiwari et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Nonetheless, we find that dimerization allows for variation of ARF DNA recognition at the level of spacing between two adjacent inverted binding sites. This mechanism, in which ARFs act as “molecular calipers” to bind uniquely spaced motifs, can at least account for differences between ARF1 and ARF5 and is consistent with in vivo binding sites for ARF5 (
    <a>
     Schlereth et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yamaguchi et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). The divergence in the loops connecting the B3 and DD domains extends beyond ARF1 and ARF5, and it is therefore conceivable that other ARFs also have distinct interdomain flexibility that allows unique binding site spacing. It will be interesting to address what distance can be accommodated by ARF complexes and if two binding sites can be separated by larger DNA loops or nucleosomes. In this context, it is important to note that the distance of seven bases between AuxRE sites in the ER7 substrate requires little or no protein conformational change or torsion of the DNA (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). In contrast, increasing or decreasing this distance will also rotationally displace the two binding sites. Hence, the different potential in binding between ARF1 and ARF5 depending on site spacing may either be a consequence of different flexibility of the dimer or a difference in the capacity of the two proteins to induce DNA bending or torsion. Given the different biophysical properties of A:T and G:C pairs, sequence within the spacer may also contribute to binding affinity.
   </p>
   <p>
    Transcription factor dimerization is a common element in transcriptional control. Often, dimerization is required for binding a single site, such as is the case in basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) factors (e.g., MyoD;
    <a>
     Ma et al., 1994
    </a>
    ) or by bZip factors (e.g., AP-1/CREB;
    <a>
     Kim and Struhl, 1995
    </a>
    ). Unlike many other examples, however, ARF DNA binding can involve either one or two binding sites, where the latter case involves cooperativity. Conceptually, the mechanism underlying sequence-specific DNA binding in the ARF family is similar to that found in the animal nuclear receptor (NR) family. Members of this family of transcription factors, whose nuclear localization and activity is modulated by membrane-permeable hormones such as retinoic acid or estrogen (
    <a>
     Mangelsdorf et al., 1995
    </a>
    ), bind DNA either as monomers or dimers (
    <a>
     Khorasanizadeh and Rastinejad, 2001
    </a>
    ). When bound as dimers, the choice of the partners determines the optimal spacing (3, 4, or 5 bases) between two tandem binding sites, a phenomenon that led to the formulation of the 3,4,5 rule (
    <a>
     Umesono et al., 1991
    </a>
    ). The case with ARFs is distinct as symmetric homodimers bind an inverted repeat rather than a tandem repeat as bound by the NR dimers, and in addition, the space between two binding sites is large for ARFs. Nonetheless, both NR (
    <a>
     Zechel et al., 1994
    </a>
    ) and ARFs can bind DNA cooperatively and contribute to generating specific responses to hormonal signals in the animal and plant kingdom.
   </p>
   <p>
    A key question in auxin biology is how this structurally simple molecule can elicit such a wide range of growth and developmental responses. Our study suggests a model in which diversification of gene expression responses follows from the distinct properties of dimeric complexes formed by the DNA-binding ARF transcription factors. This model, as well as the ARF structures presented here, will now open new avenues to define the mechanistic basis for context-dependent gene regulation in the auxin pathway.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Protein Expression and Purification
   </title>
   <p>
    Regions corresponding to the DBD of
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    ARF1 (At1g59750; residues 1–354) and ARF5 (At1g19850; residues 1–390) were amplified from cDNA clones using primers as listed in
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    using Phusion Flash polymerase (Finnzymes) and cloned in an expression vector pTWIN1 (New England Biolabs) to generate fusions with chitin-binding domain (CBD) and Intein. ARF-DBD-CBD fusion proteins were expressed in
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    strain Rosetta DE3 (Novagen). Protein expression was induced by 0.3 mM IPTG for 20 hr at 20°C, and proteins were purified from cell-free extracts by affinity chromatography on a chitin column followed by size exclusion chromatography on a Superdex 200PG column, both using an Akta Explorer 100 (GE Healthcare). Full details on expression and purification are described in the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    X-Ray Crystallography
   </title>
   <p>
    All crystals were grown at 20°C using sitting drop vapor diffusion experiments. Initial screens were performed using 80–200 nl droplets on 96-well plates using a Cartesian robot. Additive screens on initial hits showed improved crystal size and longevity with GSH/GSSG. Additional trials using the reducing agents GSH and DTT confirmed the dependence of crystal growth and stability on the reduction potential of the environment. Oligonucleotides used for crystallization were obtained from Biomers (Ulm, Germany). Full details on crystallization conditions, data collection, processing, structure determination, and refinement are given in
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Small-Angle X-Ray Scattering Measurements
   </title>
   <p>
    SAXS data of ARF1-DBD (concentration 3.2 mg/ml) were collected at beamline BM29 (ESRF, Grenoble). BSA references were used for calculating the molecular mass of ARF1-DBD. Measurements were carried out at 293 K, within a momentum transfer range of 0.01 Å
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    &lt; s &lt; 0.45 Å
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    . Calculation of the theoretical scattering curves of monomeric and dimeric ARF1 against the scattering data was performed using CRYSOL (
    <a>
     Svergun et al., 1995
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Surface Plasmon Resonance and Circular Dichroism Spectroscopy
   </title>
   <p>
    SPR measurements were performed using eight 2-fold dilution steps (800 nM, 400 nM, 200 nM, 100 nM, 50 nM, 25 nM, 12.5 nM, and 6.25 nM) of purified ARF-DBD proteins on a Biacore 3000 platform using double-stranded biotin-labeled oligonucleotides (5′-biotin; Eurogentec;
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    ) immobilized on SA chips (GE Healthcare). Data were analyzed with Scrubber2-T200 (BioLogic Software Pty Ltd).
   </p>
   <p>
    Circular dichroism was performed on 0.1 mg/ml dilutions of purified ARF DBD proteins in 0.1 M sodium borate buffer (pH 7.4) using a 1 mm quartz cell in a J-715 CD spectropolarimeter (Jasco). Traces are averages of 20 spectra and smoothed over 3 nm windows.
   </p>
   <title>
    Site-Directed Mutagenesis and Cloning
   </title>
   <p>
    Mutations were introduced into cDNA fragments corresponding to the ARF DBDs through PCR using primers as listed in
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    , and fragments were cloned into pTWIN1. The wild-type and mutated cDNA of ARF5-DBD were amplified and used to replace the genomic DBD in an 8.5 kb
    <em>
     MP
    </em>
    genomic fragment (
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2006
    </a>
    ) using the unique restriction sites
    <em>
     Xho
    </em>
    I and BamHI. Wild-type and mutant versions of the full-length ARF5 cDNA or a fragment truncated after T794 (after
    <a>
     Krogan et al., 2012
    </a>
    ) were LIC cloned (
    <a>
     De Rybel et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) using primers as listed in
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    into the PMON999 (Monsanto) vector and fused to sCFP3A or sYFP2 and transiently expressed in
    <em>
     A. thaliana
    </em>
    Columbia ecotype mesophyll protoplasts under the 35S promoter for FRET-FLIM assays. The ARF3 plasmids were previously described (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Protein-Binding Microarrays
   </title>
   <p>
    PBM11 was performed on ARF1-DBD, ARF5-DBD, and their mutated versions H170A, G171A, R215A, P218A, S269N, and G279E according to
    <a>
     Godoy et al. (2011
    </a>
    ) with modifications detailed in the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Plant Growth and Rescue Experiments
   </title>
   <p>
    Heterozygous plants of the
    <em>
     mp
    </em>
    -
    <em>
     B4149
    </em>
    strong allele (
    <a>
     Weijers et al., 2005
    </a>
    ) were transformed with a pGREEN vector carrying the construct pMP::MP and its different mutated versions by floral dipping with
    <em>
     A. tumefaciens
    </em>
    . Seeds carrying the transgene were screened on MS media with 15 mg/ml phosphinotricin (PPT). Segregation of the
    <em>
     monopteros
    </em>
    phenotype in the T2 generation was checked to determine the genotype of the T1 plants. The percentage of rootless seedlings observed in the progeny of heterozygous T1 plants was used to determine whether the transgene could rescue the phenotype.
   </p>
   <title>
    FRET-FLIM
   </title>
   <p>
    Transfections were performed as described (
    <a>
     Russinova et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) using
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    (Columbia wild-type) mesophyll protoplasts. Fluorescence lifetime imaging (FLIM) images were acquired with a Leica TCS SP5 X system equipped with a 63× 1.20 NA water immersion objective lens. sCFP fluorophore was excited using a pulse diode laser (40 nm) at a frequency of 40 mHz. Donor fluorescence was recorded via an external fiber output connected to the Leica SP5 X scan head and coupled to a Hamamatsu HPM-100-40 Hybrid detector (Becker &amp; Hickl), which has a time resolution of 120 ps. Donor fluorescence emission was obtained using a 470–500 nm band pass filter. Images of 128 × 128 pixels were acquired with acquisition times of 120 s. FRET-FLIM analysis in
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    leaf mesophyll protoplasts was performed as described previously (
    <a>
     Rademacher et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The Protein Data Base (PDB) accession numbers for the structures reported in this paper are 4LDV, 4LDW, 4LDU, 4LDX, and 4LDY.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Tables S1–S3.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (159 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (6639 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Adams-Cioaba et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.A. Adams-Cioaba, Z. Li, W. Tempel, Y. Guo, C. Bian, Y. Li, R. Lam, J. Min
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structures of the Tudor domains of human PHF20 reveal novel structural variations on the Royal Family of proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 586 (2012), pp. 859–865
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Berger et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.F. Berger, G. Badis, A.R. Gehrke, S. Talukder, A.A. Philippakis, L. Peña-Castillo, T.M. Alleyne, S. Mnaimneh, O.B. Botvinnik, E.T. Chan,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Variation in homeodomain DNA binding revealed by high-resolution analysis of sequence preferences
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 133 (2008), pp. 1266–1276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Berleth and Jürgens, 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Berleth, G. Jürgens
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The role of the
         <em>
          MONOPTEROS
         </em>
         gene in organising the basal body region of the
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         embryo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 118 (1993), pp. 575–587
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chapman and Estelle, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.J. Chapman, M. Estelle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mechanism of auxin-regulated gene expression in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Genet., 43 (2009), pp. 265–285
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ellis et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.M. Ellis, P. Nagpal, J.C. Young, G. Hagen, T.J. Guilfoyle, J.W. Reed
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR1 and AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR2 regulate senescence and floral organ abscission in
         <em>
          Arabidopsis thaliana
         </em>
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 132 (2005), pp. 4563–4574
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Finet et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Finet, A. Berne-Dedieu, C.P. Scutt, F. Marlétaz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Evolution of the ARF gene family in land plants: old domains, new tricks
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Biol. Evol., 30 (2013), pp. 45–56
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Godoy et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Godoy, J.M. Franco-Zorrilla, J. Pérez-Pérez, J.C. Oliveros, O. Lorenzo, R. Solano
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Improved protein-binding microarrays for the identification of DNA-binding specificities of transcription factors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant J., 66 (2011), pp. 700–711
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Grunewald and Friml, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Grunewald, J. Friml
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The march of the PINs: developmental plasticity by dynamic polar targeting in plant cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 29 (2010), pp. 2700–2714
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Guilfoyle and Hagen, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.J. Guilfoyle, G. Hagen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin response factors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Plant Biol., 10 (2007), pp. 453–460
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardtke and Berleth, 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.S. Hardtke, T. Berleth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         gene
         <em>
          MONOPTEROS
         </em>
         encodes a transcription factor mediating embryo axis formation and vascular development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 17 (1998), pp. 1405–1411
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Holm and Rosenström, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Holm, P. Rosenström
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dali server: conservation mapping in 3D
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 38 (Web Server issue) (2010), pp. W545–W549
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huang et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Huang, J. Fang, M.T. Bedford, Y. Zhang, R.M. Xu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Recognition of histone H3 lysine-4 methylation by the double tudor domain of JMJD2A
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 312 (2006), pp. 748–751
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Khorasanizadeh and Rastinejad, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Khorasanizadeh, F. Rastinejad
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nuclear-receptor interactions on DNA-response elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biochem. Sci., 26 (2001), pp. 384–390
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kim and Struhl, 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Kim, K. Struhl
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Determinants of half-site spacing preferences that distinguish AP-1 and ATF/CREB bZIP domains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 23 (1995), pp. 2531–2537
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kim et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Kim, K. Harter, A. Theologis
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein-protein interactions among the Aux/IAA proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 94 (1997), pp. 11786–11791
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Krissinel and Henrick, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Krissinel, K. Henrick
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Secondary-structure matching (SSM), a new tool for fast protein structure alignment in three dimensions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 60 (2004), pp. 2256–2268
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Krogan et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.T. Krogan, W. Ckurshumova, D. Marcos, A.E. Caragea, T. Berleth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Deletion of
         <em>
          MP/ARF5
         </em>
         domains III and IV reveals a requirement for
         <em>
          Aux/IAA
         </em>
         regulation in
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         leaf vascular patterning
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New Phytol., 194 (2012), pp. 391–401
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lau et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Lau, I. De Smet, M. Kolb, H. Meinhardt, G. Jürgens
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin triggers a genetic switch
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 13 (2011), pp. 611–615
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ljung, 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Ljung
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin metabolism and homeostasis during plant development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 140 (2013), pp. 943–950
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lokerse and Weijers, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.S. Lokerse, D. Weijers
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin enters the matrix—assembly of response machineries for specific outputs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Plant Biol., 12 (2009), pp. 520–526
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ma et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.C. Ma, M.A. Rould, H. Weintraub, C.O. Pabo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structure of MyoD bHLH domain-DNA complex: perspectives on DNA recognition and implications for transcriptional activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 77 (1994), pp. 451–459
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mangelsdorf et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.J. Mangelsdorf, C. Thummel, M. Beato, P. Herrlich, G. Schütz, K. Umesono, B. Blumberg, P. Kastner, M. Mark, P. Chambon, R.M. Evans
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The nuclear receptor superfamily: the second decade
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 83 (1995), pp. 835–839
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Masel and Siegal, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Masel, M.L. Siegal
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Robustness: mechanisms and consequences
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Genet., 25 (2009), pp. 395–403
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nagpal et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Nagpal, C.M. Ellis, H. Weber, S.E. Ploense, L.S. Barkawi, T.J. Guilfoyle, G. Hagen, J.M. Alonso, J.D. Cohen, E.E. Farmer,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin response factors ARF6 and ARF8 promote jasmonic acid production and flower maturation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 132 (2005), pp. 4107–4118
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Noyes et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.B. Noyes, R.G. Christensen, A. Wakabayashi, G.D. Stormo, M.H. Brodsky, S.A. Wolfe
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Analysis of homeodomain specificities allows the family-wide prediction of preferred recognition sites
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 133 (2008), pp. 1277–1289
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Okushima et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Okushima, P.J. Overvoorde, K. Arima, J.M. Alonso, A. Chan, C. Chang, J.R. Ecker, B. Hughes, A. Lui, D. Nguyen,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional genomic analysis of the
         <em>
          AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR
         </em>
         gene family members in
         <em>
          Arabidopsis thaliana
         </em>
         : unique and overlapping functions of ARF7 and ARF19
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Cell, 17 (2005), pp. 444–463
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Przemeck et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.K. Przemeck, J. Mattsson, C.S. Hardtke, Z.R. Sung, T. Berleth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Studies on the role of the
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         gene
         <em>
          MONOPTEROS
         </em>
         in vascular development and plant cell axialization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Planta, 200 (1996), pp. 229–237
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rademacher et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.H. Rademacher, B. Möller, A.S. Lokerse, C.I. Llavata-Peris, W. van den Berg, D. Weijers
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A cellular expression map of the
         <em>
          Arabidopsis AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR
         </em>
         gene family
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant J., 68 (2011), pp. 597–606
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rademacher et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.H. Rademacher, A.S. Lokerse, A. Schlereth, C.I. Llavata-Peris, M. Bayer, M. Kientz, A. Freire Rios, J.W. Borst, W. Lukowitz, G. Jürgens, D. Weijers
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Different auxin response machineries control distinct cell fates in the early plant embryo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 22 (2012), pp. 211–222
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Russinova et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Russinova, J.W. Borst, M. Kwaaitaal, A. Caño-Delgado, Y. Yin, J. Chory, S.C. de Vries
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Heterodimerization and endocytosis of
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         brassinosteroid receptors BRI1 and AtSERK3 (BAK1)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Cell, 16 (2004), pp. 3216–3229
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schlereth et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Schlereth, B. Möller, W. Liu, M. Kientz, J. Flipse, E.H. Rademacher, M. Schmid, G. Jürgens, D. Weijers
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         MONOPTEROS controls embryonic root initiation by regulating a mobile transcription factor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 464 (2010), pp. 913–916
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Smaczniak et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Smaczniak, R.G. Immink, J.M. Muiño, R. Blanvillain, M. Busscher, J. Busscher-Lange, Q.D. Dinh, S. Liu, A.H. Westphal, S. Boeren,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Characterization of MADS-domain transcription factor complexes in Arabidopsis flower development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 109 (2012), pp. 1560–1565
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Svergun et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Svergun, C. Barberato, M.H.J. Koch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         CRYSOL - a program to evaluate X-ray solution scattering of biological macromolecules from atomic coordinates
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst., 28 (1995), pp. 768–773
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Swaminathan et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Swaminathan, K. Peterson, T. Jack
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The plant B3 superfamily
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Plant Sci., 13 (2008), pp. 647–655
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Szemenyei et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Szemenyei, M. Hannon, J.A. Long
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TOPLESS mediates auxin-dependent transcriptional repression during
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         embryogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 319 (2008), pp. 1384–1386
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Thimann and Koepfli, 1935
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.V. Thimann, J.B. Koepfli
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identity of the growth-promoting and root-inducing substances of plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 135 (1935), p. 101
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tiwari et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.B. Tiwari, G. Hagen, T. Guilfoyle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The roles of auxin response factor domains in auxin-responsive transcription
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Cell, 15 (2003), pp. 533–543
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ulmasov et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Ulmasov, Z.B. Liu, G. Hagen, T.J. Guilfoyle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Composite structure of auxin response elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Cell, 7 (1995), pp. 1611–1623
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ulmasov et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Ulmasov, G. Hagen, T.J. Guilfoyle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         ARF1, a transcription factor that binds to auxin response elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 276 (1997), pp. 1865–1868
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ulmasov et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Ulmasov, G. Hagen, T.J. Guilfoyle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dimerization and DNA binding of auxin response factors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant J., 19 (1999), pp. 309–319
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Umesono et al., 1991
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Umesono, K.K. Murakami, C.C. Thompson, R.M. Evans
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Direct repeats as selective response elements for the thyroid hormone, retinoic acid, and vitamin D3 receptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 65 (1991), pp. 1255–1266
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vanneste and Friml, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Vanneste, J. Friml
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin: a trigger for change in plant development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 136 (2009), pp. 1005–1016
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vernoux et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Vernoux, G. Brunoud, E. Farcot, V. Morin, H. Van den Daele, J. Legrand, M. Oliva, P. Das, A. Larrieu, D. Wells,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The auxin signalling network translates dynamic input into robust patterning at the shoot apex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Syst. Biol., 7 (2011), p. 508
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Waltner et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.K. Waltner, F.C. Peterson, B.L. Lytle, B.F. Volkman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure of the B3 domain from
         <em>
          Arabidopsis thaliana
         </em>
         protein At1g16640
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Sci., 14 (2005), pp. 2478–2483
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Weijers et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Weijers, E. Benkova, K.E. Jäger, A. Schlereth, T. Hamann, M. Kientz, J.C. Wilmoth, J.W. Reed, G. Jürgens
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Developmental specificity of auxin response by pairs of ARF and Aux/IAA transcriptional regulators
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 24 (2005), pp. 1874–1885
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Weijers et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Weijers, A. Schlereth, J.S. Ehrismann, G. Schwank, M. Kientz, G. Jürgens
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Auxin triggers transient local signaling for cell specification in
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         embryogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 10 (2006), pp. 265–270
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yamaguchi et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Yamaguchi, M.F. Wu, C.M. Winter, M.C. Berns, S. Nole-Wilson, A. Yamaguchi, G. Coupland, B.A. Krizek, D. Wagner
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A molecular framework for auxin-mediated initiation of flower primordia
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 24 (2013), pp. 271–282
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yamasaki et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Yamasaki, T. Kigawa, M. Inoue, M. Tateno, T. Yamasaki, T. Yabuki, M. Aoki, E. Seki, T. Matsuda, Y. Tomo,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Solution structure of the B3 DNA binding domain of the
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         cold-responsive transcription factor RAV1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Cell, 16 (2004), pp. 3448–3459
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zechel et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Zechel, X.Q. Shen, P. Chambon, H. Gronemeyer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dimerization interfaces formed between the DNA binding domains determine the cooperative binding of RXR/RAR and RXR/TR heterodimers to DR5 and DR4 elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 13 (1994), pp. 1414–1424
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <title>
      Supplemental References
     </title>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Battye et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.G. Battye, L. Kontogiannis, O. Johnson, H.R. Powell, A.G. Leslie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         iMOSFLM: a new graphical interface for diffraction-image processing with MOSFLM
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.,
         <em>
          67
         </em>
         (2011), pp. 271–281
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Berger and Bulyk, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.F. Berger, M.L. Bulyk
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Universal protein-binding microarrays for the comprehensive characterization of the DNA-binding specificities of transcription factors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Protoc.,
         <em>
          4
         </em>
         (2009), pp. 393–411
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         De Rybel et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. De Rybel, W. van den Berg, A. Lokerse, C.Y. Liao, H. van Mourik, B. Möller, C.L. Peris, D. Weijers
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A versatile set of ligation-independent cloning vectors for functional studies in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Physiol.,
         <em>
          156
         </em>
         (2011), pp. 1292–1299
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         DeLano, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        DeLano, W.L. (2002). The Pymol Molecular Graphics System.
        <a>
         http://www.pymol.org
        </a>
        .
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Emsley et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Emsley, B. Lohkamp, W.G. Scott, K. Cowtan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Features and development of Coot
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.,
         <em>
          66
         </em>
         (2010), pp. 486–501
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Evans, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Evans
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Scaling and assessment of data quality
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.,
         <em>
          62
         </em>
         (2006), pp. 72–82
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gouet et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Gouet, E. Courcelle, D.I. Stuart, F. Métoz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         ESPript: analysis of multiple sequence alignments in PostScript
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioinformatics,
         <em>
          15
         </em>
         (1999), pp. 305–308
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Konarev et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.V. Konarev, V.V. Volkov, A.V. Sokolova, M.H.J. Koch, D.I. Svergun
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PRIMUS: a Windows PC-based system for small-angle scattering data analysis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst.,
         <em>
          36
         </em>
         (2003), pp. 1277–1282
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Larkin et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.A. Larkin, G. Blackshields, N.P. Brown, R. Chenna, P.A. McGettigan, H. McWilliam, F. Valentin, I.M. Wallace, A. Wilm, R. Lopez,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioinformatics,
         <em>
          23
         </em>
         (2007), pp. 2947–2948
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Murshudov et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.N. Murshudov, A.A. Vagin, E.J. Dodson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Refinement of macromolecular structures by the maximum-likelihood method
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.,
         <em>
          53
         </em>
         (1997), pp. 240–255
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pape and Schneider, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Pape, T.R. Schneider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         HKL2MAP: a graphical user interface for macromolecular phasing with SHELX programs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst.,
         <em>
          37
         </em>
         (2004), pp. 843–844
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sheldrick, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Sheldrick
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Macromolecular phasing with SHELXE
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Z Krist,
         <em>
          217
         </em>
         (2002), pp. 644–650
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Winn et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.D. Winn, C.C. Ballard, K.D. Cowtan, E.J. Dodson, P. Emsley, P.R. Evans, R.M. Keegan, E.B. Krissinel, A.G. Leslie, A. McCoy,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Overview of the CCP4 suite and current developments
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.,
         <em>
          67
         </em>
         (2011), pp. 235–242
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref62'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>