<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1097-2765(00)00137-4
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Molecular Basis for the Dephosphorylation of the Activation Segment of the Insulin Receptor by Protein Tyrosine Phosphatase 1B
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Disruption of the normal signaling responses to insulin underlies the pathogenesis of insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes and obesity. This observation has focused attention on identifying the components of the signaling pathways initiated by insulin and to define the mechanisms of hormone-induced signal transduction. Insulin signaling pathways begin at the insulin receptor (IR), which comprises two extracellular α subunits and two transmembrane β subunits. Activation of the receptor results in the autophosphorylation of both β subunits on tyrosine residues. The major sites of autophosphorylation within the protein tyrosine kinase (PTK) domain of the β subunit are Tyr-1158, Tyr-1162, and Tyr-1163 (using the numbering of
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ebina et al. 1985
    </xref>
    ), which are contained within the PTK activation segment (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     White et al. 1988
    </xref>
    ). Autophosphorylation of all three sites is required for maximal activation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     White et al. 1988
    </xref>
    ). Following activation, additional autophosphorylation reactions occur in the juxtamembrane segment and the C-terminal tail of the β subunit. IRK-catalyzed phosphorylation of proteins, such as IRS-1 and IRS-2, creates high-affinity binding sites for proteins that contain Src homology 2 (SH2) domains, such as phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3-K), resulting in the assembly of the multiprotein signaling complexes that mediate the effects of insulin on cellular metabolism, growth, and glucose homeostasis (reviewed by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Patti and Kahn 1998
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In the context of insulin signaling, protein phosphorylation is a reversible process, regulated by the coordinated action of protein kinases and phosphatases. Therefore, dephosphorylation of the insulin receptor by protein tyrosine phosphatases (PTPs) is also a critical component of the control of insulin signaling. Numerous studies have demonstrated that in humans, and in animal models, insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes and obesity is accompanied by increases in PTP activity and increases in the level of expression of defined members of the PTP family. In skeletal muscle and adipose tissue from insulin-resistant obese and diabetic subjects, the increased PTP activity has been linked primarily to changes in the expression of the receptor-like PTP LAR (leukocyte common antigen related) and the cytoplasmic enzyme PTP1B (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ahmad et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). Studies in cell culture models have indicated a functional link between LAR and dephosphorylation of the insulin receptor (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ahmad and Goldstein 1995
    </xref>
    ). However, disruption of the
    <em>
     LAR
    </em>
    gene in mice yields a complex phenotype consistent with a postreceptor defect in insulin signaling but associated with impaired activation of downstream signals, such as PI 3-kinase (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ren et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ). Therefore, attention has focused on PTP1B as a major regulator of insulin signaling.
   </p>
   <p>
    A significant body of preliminary data has implicated PTP1B in the regulation of insulin receptor signaling (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Byon et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ). Microinjection of purified PTP1B into
    <em>
     Xenopus
    </em>
    oocytes inhibited insulin-induced activation of S6 kinase and transition through the G2/M phase checkpoint. When overexpressed in Rat1 fibroblasts expressing the insulin receptor, PTP1B inhibited hormone-induced phosphorylation of the insulin receptor and downstream substrates and the incorporation of glucose into glycogen (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Chen et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). Furthermore, osmotic loading of neutralizing antibodies to PTP1B into hepatoma cells enhanced insulin-induced receptor autophosphorylation and phosphorylation of IRS-1, suggesting a direct effect of the phosphatase on the insulin receptor. Such direct effects were also supported by the demonstration of association between inactive Cys→Ser mutant forms of PTP1B, which may serve as substrate traps, and the insulin receptor (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bandyopadhyay et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). Although these studies were provocative, it was not until PTP1B knockout mice were generated that a functional link between PTP1B and the insulin receptor was established unequivocally. Disruption of the
    <em>
     PTP1B
    </em>
    gene yielded healthy mice that displayed enhanced sensitivity to insulin (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Elchebly et al. 1999
    </xref>
    ). When fed a high-fat diet, the PTP1B knockout mice were resistant to becoming obese and remained insulin sensitive, in contrast with their normal littermates, which displayed a rapid weight gain and insulin resistance. These effects coincided with enhanced tyrosine phosphorylation of the insulin receptor in the
    <em>
     PTP1B
    </em>
    <sup>
     −/−
    </sup>
    animals. Together, these data illustrate that the insulin receptor is an important physiological substrate of PTP1B and identify this phosphatase as a novel therapeutic target for the treatment of diabetes and obesity.
   </p>
   <p>
    An understanding of how PTP1B recognizes the tyrosine phosphorylated insulin receptor at a molecular level will provide a framework for the rational development of specific inhibitors of this interaction. The definition of PTP specificity in vivo is a combination of selection of phosphoprotein substrates by the PTP catalytic domain and the subcellular localization of the PTP, mediated by regulatory domains, which restricts access to substrates in a cellular context. The critical role of the catalytic domain of PTPs in defining substrate specificity in vivo has been demonstrated in studies involving substrate-trapping mutants (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Garton et al. 1996
    </xref>
    ), as well as through the use of PTP chimeras (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     O'Reilly and Neel 1998
    </xref>
    ). PTP catalytic domains prefer phosphopeptide substrates relative to free phosphotyrosine, with K
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    /K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    for optimal phosphopeptides being 3–4 orders of magnitude higher than for phosphotyrosine alone (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zhang et al. 1993a
    </xref>
    ). This highlights the importance of interactions between residues flanking the pTyr residue and the phosphatase. PTP1B, for example, displays significant preference for peptides with acidic residues N-terminal to the substrate phosphotyrosine residue, although to date, little is known concerning preferences for residues on the C-terminal side (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The crystal structure of PTP1B alone and in a complex with a phosphopeptide, corresponding to an autophosphorylation site of the epidermal growth factor receptor (DADEpYL), revealed the basis for the selectivity of PTP1B for phosphotyrosine-containing peptides (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jia et al. 1995
    </xref>
    ). However, in contrast to the EGF receptor peptide, which contains a single tyrosine phosphorylation site, the activation segment of the insulin receptor is phosphorylated on three sites (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     White et al. 1988
    </xref>
    ). To investigate the molecular details of the recognition of the activation segment of the insulin receptor by PTP1B, we have determined the crystal structures of complexes between a substrate-trapping mutant form of PTP1B and a series of mono-, bis-, and trisphosphorylated peptides corresponding to the sequence of the activation segment of the insulin receptor. We have integrated the structural studies with a kinetic analysis of the dephosphorylation of these peptides by wild-type PTP1B and an analysis of the interaction between the peptides and substrate-trapping mutant forms of the phosphatase. In addition, we have tested the effects of mutations in PTP1B, rationalized from the crystal structures, on its interaction with these peptides. These data reveal that PTP1B specifically recognizes a single pTyr residue, pTyr-1162, in the activation segment. Specificity results from defined interactions between the enzyme and its substrate. Sequence comparisons with other PTPs suggest that the features of PTP1B that confer this specificity will be unique to this phosphatase and its close relative, TCPTP.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Recognition of Phosphopeptides Modeled on the Activation Segment of the Insulin Receptor as Substrates of PTP1B
   </title>
   <p>
    The activation segment within the PTK domain of the insulin receptor contains three sites of autophosphorylation, pTyr-1158, pTyr-1162, and pTyr-1163. Synthetic peptides modeled on the activation segment sequence RDIYETDYYRKGGKGLL were generated in mono-, bis-, or trisphosphorylated forms and tested as substrates for PTP1B in assays in vitro. The catalytic domain of human PTP1B (residues 1–321) was used in all crystallographic and kinetic studies described here. Dephosphorylation was followed in a continuous fluorimetric assay that measures the changes in fluorescence of the peptide substrates accompanying conversion of phosphotyrosine to tyrosine (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zhang et al. 1993b
    </xref>
    ). Dephosphorylation of the activation segment–derived peptides displayed classic Michaelis-Menten kinetics (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1A
    </xref>
    ). Interestingly, PTP1B exhibited a striking preference for the bis- and trisphosphorylated peptides, with K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    s of 14 and 8 μM, respectively, compared to the peptides in which phosphotyrosine was incorporated into each site individually. All of the monophosphorylated forms of the peptide are poor substrates for PTP1B with K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    s of &gt;100 μM.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Dephosphorylation of the IR Trisphosphopeptide and PTP1B Peptide Binding ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (240 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Since K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    is influenced both by the rate of formation and breakdown of the enzyme–substrate complex, we sought to focus on enzyme–substrate complex formation through the use of a substrate-trapping mutant form of PTP1B. Previously, we had shown that mutation to alanine of the invariant aspartic acid residue, Asp-181, which functions as a general acid in catalyzing protonation of the tyrosyl leaving group of the substrate, impaired catalysis but did not alter the affinity of PTP1B for its substrate (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Flint et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). The K
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    of the PTP1B-D181A mutant is reduced by a factor of 10
    <sup>
     5
    </sup>
    compared to the wild-type enzyme, with the result that catalysis is slowed to such an extent that complexes of PTP1B and its substrates can be isolated (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Flint et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). The peptide DADEpYL, modeled on a site of autophosphorylation of the EGF receptor, has been used extensively in the enzymatic characterization of PTP1B, with reported K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    s ranging from 5 μM to 23 μM (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    ). When we mixed
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P-labeled DADEpYL peptide with a GST-tagged, PTP1B-D181A fusion protein, we observed formation of a stable, radioactively labeled complex in which binding of the phosphopeptide to the mutant PTP1B was saturable (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    , inset). Using subsaturating quantities of labeled DADEpYL peptide, we examined the ability of the various phosphorylated forms of the insulin receptor activation segment peptide to inhibit formation of the radioactively labeled PTP1B-D181A/DADEpYL peptide complex. We found that, consistent with the kinetic analysis, the bis- and trisphosphorylated forms of the insulin receptor peptide were more effective competitors than the monophosphorylated peptides for the PTP1B trapping mutant (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    ). However, under these conditions, in which we focussed on enzyme–substrate complex formation, the presence of phosphate on both of the adjacent tyrosine residues (pTyr-1162 and pTyr-1163) resulted in an ∼70-fold increased potency compared to the monophosphorylated peptides. In addition, the substrate-trapping mutant form of PTP1B did not distinguish between the different monophosphorylated peptides. The importance of the presence of adjacent pTyr residues in a substrate was further reinforced by the observation that the bis- and trisphosphorylated insulin receptor peptides were ∼7 fold more potent than the DADEpYL peptide in inhibiting complex formation with radioactively-labeled DADEpYL.
   </p>
   <title>
    Overall Structure of the PTP1B Insulin Receptor–Derived Phosphopeptide Complexes
   </title>
   <p>
    In order to understand the recognition of the activation segment of the insulin receptor as a substrate of PTP1B at the molecular level, we determined the structure of complexes between the PTP1B-C215A mutant and mono-(pTyr-1163), bis-(pTyr-1162, -1163), and trisphosphopeptides derived from the activation segment of the IR.
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    lists the peptides cocrystallized with PTP1B. All structures were determined by means of molecular replacement and refined to resolutions of between 2.4 and 2.0 Å. The general features of all IRK phosphopeptides bound to PTP1B are similar to that of the previously determined EGFR peptide–PTP1B complex (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jia et al. 1995
    </xref>
    ). The catalytic site of PTP1B is formed from a cleft on the protein molecular surface. The base of the cleft comprises residues of the conserved PTP loop with the phosphate group of the substrate coordinated by main chain amide groups and the side chain of the Arg-221 residue in this motif. Within the PTP loop, the invariant cysteine residue (Cys-215) is positioned for nucleophilic attack on the phosphate moiety of the substrate. The depth of the cleft is determined by an invariant tyrosine, Tyr-46 from the pTyr loop, which is a major determinant of specificity for phosphotyrosine. Binding of substrate induces a conformational change in the protein in which the WPD loop (residues 179–187), which contains the invariant Asp residue (Asp-181), closes around the substrate to create the phosphotyrosine recognition pocket and generate the catalytically competent form of the enzyme. The IRK peptides bind to PTP1B with the same orientation, perpendicular to the parallel region of the central β sheet, with residues of the peptide flanking the substrate pTyr residue adopting an extended β strand conformation (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Structure of the PTP1B Bisphosphorylated IR Peptide Complex(A) Overview. The PTP ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (307 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Crystallographic Data and Refinement Statistics
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           IRK C215A PTP-1B Peptide Complex
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Parameters
          </td>
          <td>
           RDIpYETDpYpYRK
          </td>
          <td>
           ETDpYpYRKGGKGLL
          </td>
          <td>
           ETDYpYRKGGKGLL
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Crystal Parameters
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Space Group
          </td>
          <td>
           P2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
          </td>
          <td>
           P2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
          </td>
          <td>
           P2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           a (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           42.55
          </td>
          <td>
           44.83
          </td>
          <td>
           44.13
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           b (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           89.12
          </td>
          <td>
           90.11
          </td>
          <td>
           89.03
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           c (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           50.13
          </td>
          <td>
           53.59
          </td>
          <td>
           52.76
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           α (°)
          </td>
          <td>
           90.0
          </td>
          <td>
           90.00
          </td>
          <td>
           90.00
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           β (°)
          </td>
          <td>
           111.19
          </td>
          <td>
           99.21
          </td>
          <td>
           99.98
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           γ (°)
          </td>
          <td>
           90.0
          </td>
          <td>
           90.00
          </td>
          <td>
           90.00
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Z
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Data Collection and Processing Statistics
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Resolution (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           2.0
          </td>
          <td>
           2.4
          </td>
          <td>
           2.2
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Measurements (n)
          </td>
          <td>
           160,237
          </td>
          <td>
           105,145
          </td>
          <td>
           163,090
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Unique reflections (n)
          </td>
          <td>
           24,096
          </td>
          <td>
           16,411
          </td>
          <td>
           20,806
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Complete (%)
          </td>
          <td>
           94.5 (75.9)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           99.4 (96.0)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           99.4 (98.4)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R
           <sub>
            sym
           </sub>
           <a>
            <sup>
             b
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           5.8 (20.2)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           5.8 (13.2)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           5.8 (22.1)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Mean I/σI
          </td>
          <td>
           14.3
          </td>
          <td>
           20.3
          </td>
          <td>
           11.7
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           X ray source
          </td>
          <td>
           SRS PX9.6
          </td>
          <td>
           SRS PX7.2
          </td>
          <td>
           SRS PX9.6
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           λ (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           0.87
          </td>
          <td>
           1.488
          </td>
          <td>
           0.87
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Refinement Statistics
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Resolution (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           2.0
          </td>
          <td>
           2.4
          </td>
          <td>
           2.2
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Reflections (% complete)
          </td>
          <td>
           94.9%
          </td>
          <td>
           99.3%
          </td>
          <td>
           99.3%
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Protein and ligand atoms
          </td>
          <td>
           2486
          </td>
          <td>
           2501
          </td>
          <td>
           2482
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Water molecules (n)
          </td>
          <td>
           254
          </td>
          <td>
           121
          </td>
          <td>
           84
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R
           <sub>
            free
           </sub>
          </td>
          <td>
           22.72
          </td>
          <td>
           24.6
          </td>
          <td>
           22.85
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R factor
           <a>
            <sup>
             c
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           20.82
          </td>
          <td>
           20.7
          </td>
          <td>
           21.22
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rmsd main chain bond lengths (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           .0143
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0101
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0139
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rmsd side chain bond lengths (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           .0239
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0167
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0212
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rmsd main chain bond angles (°)
          </td>
          <td>
           2.42
          </td>
          <td>
           1.89
          </td>
          <td>
           2.3
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rmsd side chain bond angles (°)
          </td>
          <td>
           3.58
          </td>
          <td>
           2.57
          </td>
          <td>
           3.3
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        λ, wavelength; rmsd, root mean square deviation; Z, number of molecules in the asymmetric unit.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         a
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          Numbers in parentheses refer to the values in the highest resolution shell.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         b
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          R
          <sub>
           sym
          </sub>
          = ∑
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          ∑
          <sub>
           i
          </sub>
          | I(h) − I
          <sub>
           i
          </sub>
          (h) | / ∑
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          ∑
          <sub>
           i
          </sub>
          I
          <sub>
           i
          </sub>
          (h), where I
          <sub>
           i
          </sub>
          (h) and I (h) are the i
          <sup>
           th
          </sup>
          and mean measurements of the intensity of reflection h.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         c
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          R factor = ∑
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          | F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          − F
          <sub>
           c
          </sub>
          | / ∑
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          , where F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          and F
          <sub>
           c
          </sub>
          are the observed and calculated structure factor amplitudes of reflection h.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Structure of PTP1B Bisphosphorylated IR Peptide (ETDpY
    <sup>
     1162
    </sup>
    pY
    <sup>
     1163
    </sup>
    RKGGKGLL) Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    In total, seven residues (1160–1166) of the bisphosphopeptide are visible in the electron density map (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    ). The bisphosphopeptide, which is phosphorylated on tyrosines corresponding to 1162 and 1163 in the IR activation loop sequence (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ), interacts with PTP1B in a defined manner such that pTyr-1162 is located at the catalytic site, indicating a substrate selectivity for pTyr-1162 relative to pTyr-1163 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2A
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2B
    </xref>
    ). This mode of peptide recognition results from the extensive and specific PTP1B–peptide interactions involving residues both N- and C-terminal to the substrate pTyr residue, in particular Asp-1161, pTyr-1163, and Arg-1164. The pTyr residue at the catalytic site (pTyr-1162) interacts with PTP1B in an identical manner to that observed for the pTyr residue in the EGFR peptide–PTP1B complex (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3D
    </xref>
    ) (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jia et al. 1995
    </xref>
    ). The phenyl ring of pTyr-1162 is sandwiched between the aromatic side chains of Tyr-46 and Phe-182 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2B
    </xref>
    ). Bidentate hydrogen bonds between the carboxylate side chain of Asp-48 and the peptide amide NH groups of pTyr-1162 and pTyr-1163 (P+1) are important in orientating the peptide.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Surface Representation of PTP1B in Complex with pTyr-Containing Peptides(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (368 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The second phosphotyrosine residue of the peptide, pTyr-1163 (P+1), is located within a shallow groove on the protein surface connected via a channel to the catalytic pTyr-binding cleft (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4
    </xref>
    ). The phosphate group of the pTyr residue is located in a similar position to that previously observed by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Puius et al. 1997
    </xref>
    for high concentrations of aryl-phosphates bound to PTP1B. Interactions between pTyr-1163 and the protein are dominated by the salt bridges between its phosphate group and the side chains of Arg-24 and Arg-254 of PTP1B, the latter residue being invariant within the PTP family. In addition to direct phosphate interactions, Arg-24 and Arg-254 interact indirectly with the phosphate group via two ordered water molecules, one of which also accepts a hydrogen bond from the main chain amide of Gly-259 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4
    </xref>
    ). The phenyl ring of pTyr-1163 participates in long contacts with the amide side chain of Gln-262 and the side chain of Met-258. Due to the absence of a defined pocket in which to situate the phenyl ring of pTyr-1163, it is poorly ordered and may adopt numerous conformations when bound at the P+1 site. The electron density corresponding to the phosphate group of pTyr-1163 is well defined in unbiased 2F
    <sub>
     o
    </sub>
    -F
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    and F
    <sub>
     o
    </sub>
    -F
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    simulated annealing OMIT maps (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    ), whereas that for the phenyl ring is weak and fragmented within both maps. In addition, a comparison of the conformations of pTyr-1163 in the bis- and trisphosphopeptide PTP1B complexes and with the structure by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Puius et al. 1997
    </xref>
    of PTP1B in 53 mM pTyr reveals differences in the conformation of the phenyl ring but shows that the binding pocket for the phosphate group is maintained in an identical position (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4
    </xref>
    ). The specificity of this site for a pTyr residue C-terminal to the substrate pTyr, rather than the shorter pSer and pThr residues, is primarily due to the length of pTyr, which is the correct size to allow its phosphate group to reach Arg-24 and Arg-254. The presence of a Gly residue at position 259 is a critical structural feature of this site in PTP1B that allows an interaction with a bulky phosphotyrosine residue. PTPs with amino acids having more bulky side chains at this position, which interestingly includes all receptor-like PTPs, would sterically hinder these interactions.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Binding Pocket for pTyr-1163The bisphosphorylated peptide (green), ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (137 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In addition to interactions involving the tandem phosphotyrosine residues, the bisphosphorylated peptide also makes several other interactions with PTP1B. Firstly, N-terminal to the substrate pTyr residue, the carboxylate group of Asp-1161 (P-1) of the IR peptide accepts a hydrogen bond from the guanidinium group of Arg-47 of PTP1B. This interaction is responsible for the preference of PTP1B toward peptides with acidic residues N-terminal to the substrate pTyr residue. Similar interactions were observed between the Glu (P-1) and Asp (P-2) residues of the EGFR peptide in complex with PTP1B (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jia et al. 1995
    </xref>
    ), although the conformation of the Arg-47 side chain differs between the two complexes (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3D
    </xref>
    ). Conformational flexibility of the Arg-47 side chain allows it to interact with a variety of acidic amino acids N-terminal to the pTyr site. This is consistent with kinetic data showing that peptides with acidic amino acids within five residues of the pTyr site are the preferred substrates of PTP1B (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zhang et al. 1993a
    </xref>
    ) and the important role that Arg-47 plays in this interaction (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Sarmiento et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ). A second N-terminal interaction is a long hydrogen bond that is formed between the carbonyl oxygen atom of Thr-1160 and the main chain amide NH group of Arg-47.
   </p>
   <p>
    A feature of the bisphosphopeptide–PTP1B complex is the presence of peptide–protein interactions involving residues C-terminal to the substrate pTyr. In addition to pTyr-1163 (P+1), residues at P+2 and P+4 also interact with the protein. The P+2 residue is Arg-1164, and its guanidinium side chain forms a classic π-cation interaction with the phenyl ring of Phe-182 of the WPD loop (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2B
    </xref>
    ). The guanidinium group of Arg-1164 is positioned parallel to the phenyl ring of Phe-182, a geometry that is preferred in protein structures (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Gallivan and Dougherty 1999
    </xref>
    ). The Arg–Phe interaction illustrates the concerted character of the peptide–protein interactions, since it requires the WPD loop to adopt the closed conformation that is induced by the interaction of the substrate pTyr residue at the catalytic site. Arg-1164 also forms a main chain interaction through its NH group with the carbonyl oxygen atom of the Gln-262 amide side chain, although this interaction would not provide specificity, as Gln-262 is invariant throughout the PTP family. The initial 2F
    <sub>
     o
    </sub>
    -F
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    unbiased maps with only the pTyr-1162 and N-terminal residues 1160 and 1161 used in phasing revealed strong and defined electron density for Arg-1164 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    ). The C terminus of the peptide is further anchored via a hydrogen bond between the carbonyl oxygen atom of Gly-1166 and the guanidinium group of Arg-24. Details of the PTP1B–peptide interactions are illustrated in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Schematic Representation of the PTP1B Bisphosphorylated IR Peptide Interactions" src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (277 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Structure of PTPIB Trisphosphorylated IR Peptide Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    To determine whether pTyr-1158 plays a role in mediating interactions between the activation segment of the IR and PTP1B, we cocrystallized PTP1B with a trisphosphorylated peptide corresponding to residues 1155–1165 of the IR (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). In general, the trisphosphorylated and bisphosphorylated IR peptide–PTP1B complexes are essentially similar. The trisphosphopeptide–PTP1B interactions are dominated by the residues Asp-1161–Arg-1164. The most significant observation from this structure is that residues N-terminal to Glu-1159, including pTyr-1158, were disordered, indicating that there is no defined binding pocket for pTyr-1158 on the enzyme and that pTyr-1158 is not a specificity determinant for PTP1B–IR interactions. This crystallographic observation is consistent with the results of our enzymatic and binding assays (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    ), which illustrate that PTP1B recognizes the bis- and trisphosphopeptides with similar affinity, implying that pTyr-1158 does not confer additional binding affinity upon the PTP1B–peptide complex. One difference between the two phosphopeptide–PTP1B complexes is that the two residues C-terminal to pTyr-1163 of the trisphosphorylated peptide are poorly ordered. It is likely that this results from the absence of Gly-1166 in the trisphosphopeptide, which in the bisphosphopeptide interacts with Arg-24 of PTP1B.
   </p>
   <title>
    Mutational Analysis of the pTyr-1163 Binding Site
   </title>
   <p>
    To test the importance of defined residues in the binding site for pTyr-1163, we prepared a series of point mutations and assessed their effect on catalytic function. Specifically, we used
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    -NPP, a low Mr phosphate ester, which as a substrate would be expected to interact only at the catalytic site, and the trisphosphorylated IR peptide as substrates in these assays. Consistent with its role in forming a salt bridge with the phosphate group of pTyr-1163, we found that mutation of Arg-24 in PTP1B decreased affinity for the trisphosphorylated IR peptide but did not alter the K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    for
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). Similar results were observed in the binding assay using PTP1B-D181A substrate-trapping mutant (data not shown). However, attempts to examine the importance of Arg-254 and Gly-259 were unsuccessful because these residues appear to play a role at the catalytic site that is independent of a function at the second pTyr-1163 binding site. We found that replacement of Gly-259 with the bulkier hydrophobic residue Val, with the aim of restricting access to the pTyr-1163 binding pocket, resulted in similar 10-fold decreases in both affinity and K
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    for
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP and the trisphosphopeptide (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). It has been reported that such mutations may effect the position of Gln-262, resulting in partial occlusion of the catalytic site (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Peters et al. 2000
    </xref>
    ). Similarly, mutation of Arg-254 to either Lys or Gln was inhibitory for dephosphorylation of
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP, exerting effects on both K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    and K
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). Arg-254 may also function at the catalytic site by increasing its positive electrostatic potential to enhance phosphate interactions and/or to stabilize the thiolate form of the nucleophilic cysteine residue. Although mutation of Arg-24 does impair recognition of the trisphosphorylated IR peptide, the magnitude of the effect is not sufficient to account for the increased affinity displayed by PTP1B for IR peptides with the adjacent pTyr residues (pTyr-1162–pTyr-1163) compared to the singly phosphorylated peptides. Clearly, other interactions contribute to this enhanced affinity, for example the Arg-254–phosphate interactions, mediated by Gly-259. However, because of the nature of their pleiotropic roles, it is not possible to probe the function of these two residues by site-directed mutagenesis.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 2.
        </span>
        <p>
         Kinetic Constants for Dephosphorylation of the Trisphosphorylated IR Peptide (pTyr-1158, 1162, 1163) by PTP1B: Effect of Mutations in the Second Phosphate Binding Pocket
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
           RDIpY
           <sup>
            1158
           </sup>
           ETDpY
           <sup>
            1162
           </sup>
           pY
           <sup>
            1163
           </sup>
           RKGGKGLL
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            P
           </em>
           NPP
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           PTP1B
          </td>
          <td>
           K
           <sub>
            M
           </sub>
           [μM]
          </td>
          <td>
           K
           <sub>
            cat
           </sub>
           [s
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           ]
          </td>
          <td>
           K
           <sub>
            cat
           </sub>
           /K
           <sub>
            M
           </sub>
           × 10
           <sup>
            −3
           </sup>
           [M
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           s
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           ]
          </td>
          <td>
           K
           <sub>
            M
           </sub>
           [μM]
          </td>
          <td>
           K
           <sub>
            cat
           </sub>
           [s
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           ]
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Wild type
          </td>
          <td>
           7.5 ± 1.9
          </td>
          <td>
           11.3 ± 0.82
          </td>
          <td>
           1514
          </td>
          <td>
           0.53
          </td>
          <td>
           8.3
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R24E
          </td>
          <td>
           15.9 ± 3.9
          </td>
          <td>
           12.2 ± 1.0
          </td>
          <td>
           765
          </td>
          <td>
           0.60
          </td>
          <td>
           7.3
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           M258A
          </td>
          <td>
           7.4 ± 1.8
          </td>
          <td>
           15.0 ± 1.0
          </td>
          <td>
           1998
          </td>
          <td>
           0.7
          </td>
          <td>
           8.0
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R24E and M258A
          </td>
          <td>
           13.9 ± 2.8
          </td>
          <td>
           14.5 ± 0.99
          </td>
          <td>
           1042
          </td>
          <td>
           0.56
          </td>
          <td>
           7.9
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           G259V
          </td>
          <td>
           61.7 ± 16.4
          </td>
          <td>
           1.24 ± 0.18
          </td>
          <td>
           20
          </td>
          <td>
           5.0
          </td>
          <td>
           0.93
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R254K
          </td>
          <td>
           (&gt;100)
          </td>
          <td>
           —
          </td>
          <td>
           —
          </td>
          <td>
           3.3
          </td>
          <td>
           3.1
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R254Q
          </td>
          <td>
           (&gt;100)
          </td>
          <td>
           —
          </td>
          <td>
           —
          </td>
          <td>
           12.2
          </td>
          <td>
           0.49
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Structure of the PTP1B pTyr-1163 Monophosphorylated IR Peptide Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    Relative to the IRK bis- and trisphosphopeptides, the monophosphopeptides are poor substrates of PTP1B, displaying K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    values &gt;10-fold higher than for the multiple phosphorylated peptides. Furthermore, in the binding assays using the substrate-trapping mutant of PTP1B, the EC
    <sub>
     50
    </sub>
    values are ∼70-fold higher for the monophosphopeptides than the bis- and trisphosphorylated forms (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    ). A comparison of the structure of PTP1B in complex with a peptide monophosphorylated on the residue corresponding to Tyr-1163 in the insulin receptor activation segment with the PTP1B bis- and trisphosphopeptide complexes provides a structural explanation for these findings. Only five residues (1160–1164) of the monophosphopeptide are clearly visible in the electron density map of the structure of the complex. Peptide–protein interactions are formed only by the catalytic site pTyr side chain and nonspecific peptide–enzyme main chain interactions; all other peptide side chains are poorly ordered and do not interact with PTP1B (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3C
    </xref>
    ). Similarly to other PTP1B–peptide interactions, the carboxylate side chain of Asp-48 accepts hydrogen bonds from the main chain amide groups of pTyr-1163 and Arg-1164 (P+1), hence defining the peptide orientation. The N terminus of the peptide is anchored to PTP1B via a conserved hydrogen bond between the carbonyl oxygen of Asp-1161 (P-2) and the main chain amide of Arg-47. This orientation of the peptide places the phenyl ring of the peptide Tyr-1162 residue in close proximity to the side chain of Arg-47. However, there is no visible density for the guanidinium group of Arg-47, and a potential π-cation interaction between Tyr-1162 and Arg-47 is not observed.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Although several members of the PTP family have been implicated in the dephosphorylation and inactivation of the IR, recent evidence from studies of gene disruption in mice has focused attention on PTP1B as a major regulator of insulin-induced signaling, acting at the level of the IR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     11
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    ). In this study, we have analyzed how PTP1B recognizes mono-, bis- and trisphosphorylated forms of a peptide derived from the sequence of the IR activation segment. Our studies provide a molecular explanation for the dephosphorylation process, revealing the importance of residues both N- and C-terminal to the substrate pTyr residue in defining both PTP1B peptide affinity and selectivity. The presence of tandem pTyr residues, pTyr-1162 and pTyr-1163, dramatically enhances the affinity of the substrate for PTP1B, indicating that a pTyr residue adjacent to the substrate phosphorylation site plays a critical role in specificity. Extensive and specific interactions were observed between PTP1B and the tandem phosphotyrosine motif with pTyr-1162 at the catalytic site and pTyr-1163 at the P+1 recognition site. Residues Asp-1161 and Arg-1164, which flank the tandem pTyr motif, also form numerous contacts with PTP1B. A number of findings indicate that the recognition of a pTyr residue at the P+1 site is determined by its phosphate group and that selectivity for a pTyr residue at this site occurs only in the context of a tandem pTyr-peptide motif. First, our binding studies demonstrated that the phosphate group on pTyr-1163 of the bis-(pTyr-1162, -1163) phosphopeptide increases the peptide affinity for PTP1B by 70-fold relative to the same peptide with a tyrosine residue at 1163 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    ). Second, the crystal structures show that whereas the phosphate group of the pTyr residue forms numerous contacts with the protein, the phenyl ring is less well ordered, adopts multiple conformations, and forms no defined interactions with the protein (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4
    </xref>
    ). The observation that peptides with tandem pTyr residues bind with high affinity to PTP1B is in agreement with a recent study by Ramachandran and colleagues who observed that peptides containing two adjacent nonhydrolyzable analogs of pTyr (difluorophosphonomethyl-Phe) were potent inhibitors of PTP1B (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Desmarais et al. 1999
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Our data suggest that PTP1B preferentially dephosphorylates pTyr-1162 within a trisphosphorylated IR activation segment. This observation explains experiments that showed that dephosphorylation of the trisphosphorylated IR activation segment catalyzed by PTPs present in liver extracts correlates with loss of activity of the IR with over 80% of the initial dephosphorylation occurring at either pTyr-1162 or pTyr-1163 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     King et al. 1991
    </xref>
    ). Also, preferential dephosphorylation by PTP1B of the tandem pTyr motif within a multiply phosphorylated IR peptide has been observed previously (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ramachandran et al. 1992
    </xref>
    ). Autophosphorylation of the IRK occurs in an ordered process, with pTyr-1163 being the last of three residues to be phosphorylated (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Dickens and Tavare 1992
    </xref>
    ). An ordered dephosphorylation process, which occurs in a different sequence from that of autophosphorylation, could have important implications for IRK regulation. For example, a β subunit dephosphorylated on pTyr-1162 and containing pTyr-1158 and pTyr-1163 may be a poor substrate for the second β subunit of the IRK receptor; therefore, following dephosphorylation of pTyr-1162 by PTP1B, the inactive subunit will not be readily rephosphorylated by the neighboring, potentially active β subunit. The structure of a complex between PTP1B and the IR PTK domain would reveal whether enzyme–substrate interactions occur beyond the immediate vicinity of the IR activation segment. However, it is likely that the dominant PTP1B–IRK interactions are mediated by the activation segment of the IR and catalytic domain of PTP1B. Autophosphorylation of the IR activation segment is necessary and sufficient to mediate PTP1B–IR interactions in vivo (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bandyopadhyay et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ), and this interaction is disrupted by phosphopeptides modeled on the IRK activation segment (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Seely et al. 1996
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The PTP1B–substrate interactions combine not only to provide the affinity for recognition of the IR by PTP1B, but also to enable the phosphatase to replace, and thereby disrupt, the intramolecular associations that are formed within the activation segment of the IR following autophosphorylation. The structure of the autophosphorylated activation segment of the IR shows that adjacent phosphotyrosines are stabilized by intramolecular salt bridges between the phosphates of pTyr-1162 and pTyr-1163 and the side chains of Arg-1164 and Arg-1155, respectively (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Hubbard 1997
    </xref>
    ). Disruption of these salt bridges is necessary for recognition of the IR activation segment as a substrate of PTP1B. The role of Tyr-1162 in inhibiting the substrate binding site that is seen in the structure of the inactive IRK (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Hubbard et al. 1994
    </xref>
    ) suggests that the phosphorylation state of this residue will be crucial to kinase activity by both destabilizing the activated state of the IR and by promoting Tyr-1162 inhibition of the IR catalytic site. In the crystal structure of the complex between PTP1B and the trisphospho-IR activation segment, we noted a lack of interactions between pTyr-1158 and the phosphatase. This observation is consistent with the results of our enzymatic and binding assays, which illustrate that PTP1B recognizes the bis- and trisphosphopeptides as substrate with similar affinity. It is possible that other PTPs may dephosphorylate the IR activation segment, particularly pTyr-1158, and LAR has been implicated as one such enzyme. In an analysis of the regioselectivity of dephosphorylation of the trisphosphopeptide corresponding to the IR activation segment, Walsh and colleagues demonstrated that LAR sequentially dephosphorylates pTyr-1158 followed by either pTyr-1162 or pTyr-1163 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Lee et al. 1992
    </xref>
    ). In contrast to PTP1B, the K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    for the dephosphorylation of the bisphosphopeptide containing pTyr-1162 and pTyr-1163 by LAR is the same as that for a pTyr-1162-containing monophosphopeptide at 302 μM and 280 μM, respectively. LAR dephosphorylates peptides containing pTyr-1158 with K
    <sub>
     M
    </sub>
    values of ∼30 μM, suggesting that it recognizes this site preferentially (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Lee et al. 1992
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Our structural data highlight the importance of an Asp/Glu-pTyr-pTyr-Arg/Lys motif for optimal substrate recognition by PTP1B. Therefore, we searched the sequence databases for matches with this motif with the aim of identifying novel potential substrates of PTP1B. Several candidates were noted, including the RPTKs Trk, FGF, and NGF receptors and Axl. Of particular interest is the observation that the JAK family of PTKs contains this sequence, for example, Glu-Tyr-Tyr-Arg in Tyk2 and Glu-Tyr-Tyr-Lys in Jak2. When one considers that the satiety hormone leptin recognizes a classic cytokine receptor that is coupled to Jak family PTKs for signaling (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Touw et al. 2000
    </xref>
    ), it will be very interesting to ascertain whether the effects of PTP1B on diet-induced obesity (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Elchebly et al. 1999
    </xref>
    ) may be exerted through dephosphorylation of Jaks. Furthermore, the Jak PTKs have also been implicated in signaling responses to insulin and growth factors, raising the possibility that they may also be targets for PTP1B in these signal transduction pathways.
   </p>
   <p>
    Comparison of PTP1B with other PTP structures and sequences suggests that the recognition of the Asp-pTyr-pTyr-Arg motif by PTP1B will be unique to this phosphatase and its close relative TCPTP. Of the residues of PTP1B that interact with the side chains of residues flanking the catalytic site pTyr residue, four are unique to PTP1B in comparison to other phosphatases that have been implicated in insulin signaling. Plotting the degree of sequence conservation between PTP1B, LAR, PTPα, and SHP2 onto the surface of the PTP1B–IR peptide complex reveals how the specificity of the IR peptide–PTP1B interactions is generated (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 6
    </xref>
    ). Specifically, Arg-47, which forms a salt bridge with Asp-1161 (P-1), and Phe-182, which interacts with Arg-1164 (P+2), are poorly conserved residues. Of particular importance is the mode of recognition of pTyr-1163 (P+1). Our phylogenetic analysis indicates that the binding site for this residue will be unique to PTP1B and TCPTP. Arg-24, which functions to stabilize the interactions with the pTyr phosphate residue, is poorly conserved within the PTP family, being located in the α1′ helix that is N-terminal to the conserved PTP catalytic domain. The presence of glycine at position 259 is also critical for the recognition of pTyr-1163. Non-glycine residues at this position would sterically hinder the interactions of a pTyr residue with the phosphatase by blocking access to the pTyr binding pocket. The presence of non-Gly residues at residue 259 and the absence of Arg-24 in other putative IR PTPs, such as LAR and PTPα, suggest that these enzymes are unlikely to recognize a tandem bis-pTyr-containing peptide in the same manner as PTP1B, a notion consistent with the kinetic data of Walsh and colleagues (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Lee et al. 1992
    </xref>
    ). Interestingly, one of the pTyr-1163 contact residues, Arg-254, is invariant in all PTP sequences, and therefore the presence of bulky residues at residue 259 may be important in preventing other PTPs from recognizing peptides containing a pTyr residue C-terminal to the substrate-pTyr residue, thereby generating specificity in vivo.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Molecular Surface of PTP1BThe bisphosphorylated IR peptide is bound, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276500001374-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (136 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Although many structural features within the catalytic site, as well as the underlying mechanism of catalysis, are conserved between members of the PTP family, this study reveals that elements of the PTP1B–IR peptide interaction will be unique to this PTP. Therefore, our data suggest the possibility that it may be feasible to generate specific, small molecule inhibitors of the interaction between PTP1B and the activation segment of the IR, offering novel therapeutic strategies for the treatment of diabetes and obesity.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Cloning, Expression, and Purification of Recombinant Proteins
   </title>
   <p>
    The catalytic domain of the catalytic site C215A mutant of human PTP1B (residues 1–321) was purified as described previously (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Barford et al. 1994
    </xref>
    ). The following point mutations were made in PTP1B: (i) R24E, (ii) R254K and R254Q, (iii) M258A, and (iii) G259V. In addition, the following mutations were made in combination: (i) R24E/M258A, (ii) R24E/G259V, and (iii) R24E/M258A/G259V. In addition, for the peptide binding studies, the above PTP1B mutants were expressed as GST fusion proteins in the context of the D181A substrate-trapping mutation.
   </p>
   <title>
    Phosphopeptides
   </title>
   <p>
    The peptides used in the structural study were synthesized by Princeton Pharmaceuticals and MWG Biotech. For the enzyme kinetic studies, as well as for the peptide competition assays, mono-, bis-, and trisphosphopeptides modeled on the IR activation loop sequence RDIYETDYYRKGGKGLL were synthesized by Synpep Ltd (Dublin, CA). Radiolabeled EGFR-peptide (DADEYL) was phosphorylated with the β subunit of the insulin receptor kinase as described previously (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Myers et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Enzyme Assays Using Low–Molecular Weight Substrates
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     Para
    </em>
    -nitrophenyl phosphate (
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP, Sigma) was used in enzymatic reactions to determine whether mutations in PTP1B affect overall catalytic efficiency. All enzyme reactions using
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP substrates were carried out in buffer A (100 mM NaAc [pH 5.5], 50 mM NaCl, 0.1% [w/v] BSA, and 3 mM DTT). Assays were initiated by addition of enzyme to the reaction mixtures containing different concentrations of the substrate (
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP usual range 0.16–10 mM). Reactions were carried out in microtitre plates at 25°C for 15 or 30 min. The dephosphorylation of
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NPP was terminated by the addition of 100 μl of 0.5 M NaOH, and the enzyme activity was determined by measuring the absorbance at 405 nm. A standard curve of
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    -nitrophenol (
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    NP), for calculating the release of inorganic phosphate, was determined in parallel with the samples. Kinetic parameters were determined using nonlinear regression hyperbolic fit to classical Michaelis-Menten kinetic models.
   </p>
   <title>
    Enzyme Assays Using Phosphopeptide Substrates
   </title>
   <p>
    The PTP1B-catalyzed dephosphorylation of phosphotyrosine-containing peptides was followed with a continuous fluorimetric assay described by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zhang et al. 1993b
    </xref>
    using a PC1 fluorometer (ISS instruments; Champaign, IL). IR peptides were diluted in buffer B (50 mM 3,3-dimethylglutarate, 100 mM NaCl, and 3 mM DTT [pH 6.5]), equilibrated to room temperature in a 200 μl microcuvette and the background fluorescence recorded for 3 min. The reaction was initiated by the addition of enzyme (10 μl of 4.7 nM PTP1B). The kinetic parameters for dephosphorylation of the phosphopeptides by PTP1B were determined from measurements of the initial reaction rates at various peptide substrate concentrations (range 1–100 μM), ensuring less than 5% product formation. Initial reaction rates were determined in quadruplicate using the appropriate corrections for background fluorescence (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Peptide Substrate Competition Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    The interaction between IR peptides and the substrate-trapping mutant form of PTP1B was quantitated in a peptide competition assay, using 900 pmol of glutathione S-transferase (GST)-PTP1B fusion protein and
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P-labeled EGFR peptide (DADEpYL, 3 μM final concentration). A peptide mixture (200 μl) containing
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P-labeled EGFR peptide and different concentrations of unlabeled IR peptide (range 0.01–200 μM) in buffer C (50 mM HEPES, 100 mM NaCl, 3 mM DTT [pH 7.0]) were transferred to a centrifugal filter device (Millipore, Ultrafree-MC filter unit) and incubated with GST-PTP1B fusion protein (also in buffer C) in a final volume of 400 μl. After incubation for 10 min at 4°C, the complexes of GST-PTP1B and bound peptide substrate were separated from free peptide by centrifugation. The filter unit containing the GST-bound complexes was washed in ice cold buffer C and centrifuged at 14,000 × g for 1 min. The filter unit was counted after addition of 2 ml of liquid scintillant (EcoLume). The EC
    <sub>
     50
    </sub>
    values were calculated from at least two independent experiments, using a nonlinear curve fit to the classical one site binding equation of a ligand to its receptor (Prism version 3, GraphPad software).
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystallization of C215A PTP1B Catalytic Domain with the IRK Peptides
   </title>
   <p>
    C215A PTP1B was dialyzed into 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 25 mM NaCl, 0.2 mM EDTA, and 3 mM DTT. The solution was concentrated, and IRK peptide was added so the final mixture would contain 10 mg/ml (0.3 mM) C215A PTP1B and a 3-fold molar excess (0.9 mM) IRK peptide. For crystallization, 4 μl of this solution was mixed with an equal volume of the crystallization buffer (14%–18% PEG, 0.2 M MgCl
    <sub>
     2,
    </sub>
    or 0.2 M MgOAc, 5 mM DTT, 0.1 M HEPES [pH 7.0]). Crystals were grown using the hanging drop vapor diffusion method at 4°C and grew as needles with a maximum thickness of ∼50 μm after 2 weeks.
   </p>
   <title>
    Data Collection and Processing
   </title>
   <p>
    Crystals were flash frozen in cryoprotectant buffer (14%-18% PEG, 0.2 M MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    or 0.2 M MgOAc, 5 mM DTT, 0.1 M HEPES [pH 7.0]). Data were collected as indicated in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    . All crystallographic data were processed using the HKL package (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Otwinowski and Minor 1997
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Structure Determination of the PTP1B IRK Peptide Complex Crystals
   </title>
   <p>
    The structure of PTP1B in complex with the bisphosphorylated IRK peptide was solved using the AMORE molecular replacement program (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Navaza 1994
    </xref>
    ) with D181A PTP1B as a search model (N. Repas and D. B., unpublished data). The monophosphorylated pTyr-1162 and trisphosphorylated IRK peptide structures were also solved using AMORE, but the starting models were the PTP1B coordinates from the PTP1B bisphosphoryated IRK structure. (The peptide coordinates were removed.)
   </p>
   <p>
    The crystal structures were refined using the CNS software package (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Brünger et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ). Refinement was alternated with rounds of model building in O (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jones et al. 1991
    </xref>
    ). Water molecules were also built using the automated water-building program in CNS. The final R values and the resolution limits for these structures are listed in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         1
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        F Ahmad, B.J Goldstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional association between the insulin receptor and the transmembrane PTP LAR in intact cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1995), pp. 448–453
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         2
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        F Ahmad, J.L Azevedo, R Cortright, G.L Dohm, B.J Goldstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Alterations in skeletal muscle protein-tyrosine phosphatase activity and expression in insulin-resistant human obesity and diabetes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Clin. Invest., 100 (1997), pp. 449–458
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         3
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        D Bandyopadhyay, A Kusari, K.A Kenner, F Liu, J Chernoff, T.A Gustafson, J Kusari
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B complexes with the insulin receptor in vivo and is tyrosine-phosphorylated in the presence of insulin
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 1639–1645
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         4
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        D Barford, J.C Keller, A.J Flint, N.K Tonks
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Purification and crystallization of the catalytic domain of human protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B expressed in
         <em>
          Escherichia coli
         </em>
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 239 (1994), pp. 726–730
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         5
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.T Brünger, P.D Adams, G.M Clore, W.L DeLano, P Gros, R.W Grosse-Kunstleve, J.S Jiang, J Kuszewski, M Nilges, N.S Pannu,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystallography ans NMR system: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 54 (1998), pp. 905–921
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         6
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.C Byon, A.B Kussari, J Kusari
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PTP1B acts as a negative regulator of insulin signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell Biochem., 182 (1998), pp. 101–108
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         7
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        H Chen, S.J Wertheimer, C.H Lin, S.L Katz, K.E Amrein, P Burn, M.J Quon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein-tyrosine phosphatases PTP1B and syp are modulators of insulin-stimulated translocation of GLUT4 in transfected rat adipose cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 8026–8031
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         8
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S Desmarais, R.W Friesen, R Zamboni, C Ramachandran
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         phenylalanine-containing peptide inhibitors of protein tyrosine phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem J., 337 (1999), pp. 219–223 [Difluro(phosphono)methyl]
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         9
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M Dickens, J.M Tavare
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Analysis of the order of autophosphorylation of human insulin receptor tyrosines 1158, 1162 and 1163
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 186 (1992), pp. 244–250
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         10
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y Ebina, L Ellis, K Jarnagin, M Edery, L Graf, E Clauser, J.H Ou, F Masiarz, Y.W Kan, I.D Goldfine,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The human insulin receptor cDNA: the structural basis for hormone-activated transmembrane signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 40 (1985), pp. 747–758
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         11
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M Elchebly, P Payette, E Michaliszyn, W Cromlish, S Collins, A.L Loy, D Normandin, A Cheng, J Himms Hagen, C.C Chan,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Increased insulin sensitivity and obesity resistance in mice lacking the protein tyrosine phosphatase-1B gene
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 283 (1999), pp. 1544–1548
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         12
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J Flint, T Tiganis, D Barford, N.K Tonks
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development of “substrate-trapping” mutants to identify physiological substrates of protein tyrosine phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 94 (1997), pp. 1680–1685
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         13
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.P Gallivan, D.A Dougherty
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cation-pi interactions in structural biology
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 96 (1999), pp. 9459–9464
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         14
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J Garton, A.J Flint, N.K Tonks
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of p130(cas) as a substrate for the cytosolic protein tyrosine phosphatase PTP-PEST
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 16 (1996), pp. 6408–6418
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         15
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.R Hubbard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structure of the activated insulin receptor tyrosine kinase in complex with peptide substrate and ATP analog
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 16 (1997), pp. 5572–5581
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         16
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.R Hubbard, L Wei, L Ellis, W.A Hendrickson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structure of the tyrosine kinase domain of the human insulin receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 372 (1994), pp. 746–753
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         17
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z Jia, D Barford, A.J Flint, N.K Tonks
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural basis for phosphotyrosine peptide recognition by protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 268 (1995), pp. 1754–1758
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         18
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.A Jones, J.Y Zou, S.W Cowan, M Kjeldgaard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. A, 50 (1991), pp. 157–160
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         19
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.J King, R.P Sharma, G.J Sale
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Site-specific dephosphorylation and deactivation of the human insulin receptor tyrosine kinase by particulate and soluble phosphotyrosyl protein phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J, 275 (1991), pp. 413–418
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         20
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.D Klaman, O Boss, O.D Peroni, J.K Kim, J.L Martino, J.M Zabolotny, N Moghal, M Lubkin, Y.B Kim, A.H Sharpe,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Increased energy expenditure, decreased adiposity and tissue-specific insulin sensitivity in PTP1B-deficient mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 20 (2000), pp. 5479–5489
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         21
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.P Lee, H Cho, W Bannwarth, E.A Kitas, C.T Walsh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NMR analysis of regioselectivity in dephosphorylation of a triphosphotyrosyl dodecapeptide autophosphorylation site of the insulin receptor by a catalytic fragment of LAR phosphotyrosine phosphatase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Sci., 1 (1992), pp. 1353–1362
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         22
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.P Myers, J.P Stolarov, C Eng, J Li, S.I Wang, M.H Wigler, R Parsons, N.K Tonks
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         P-TEN, the tumor suppressor from human chromosome 10q23, is a dual-specificity phosphatase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 94 (1997), pp. 9052–9057
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         23
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J Navaza
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         AMoRe: an automated package for molecular replacement
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. A, 50 (1994), pp. 157–163
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         24
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A Nicholls, R Bharadwaj, B Honig
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         GRASP: graphical representation and analysis of surface properties
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biophys. J., 64 (1993), p. A166
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         25
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.M O'Reilly, B.G Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural determinants of SHP-2 function and specificity in Xenopus mesoderm induction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 18 (1998), pp. 161–177
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         26
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z Otwinowski, W Minor
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Methods Enzymol, 276 (1997), pp. 307–326
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         27
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.E Patti, C.R Kahn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The insulin receptor: a critical link in glucose homeostasis and insulin action
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Basic Clin. Physiol. Pharmacol., 9 (1998), pp. 89–109
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         28
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        G Peters, L Iverson, S Branner, H Anderson, S Mortensen, O Olsen, K Moller, N Moller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Residue 259 is a key determinant of substrate specificity of protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B and alpha
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem, 275 (2000), pp. 18201–18209
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         29
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y.A Puius, Y Zhao, M Sullivan, D.S Lawrence, S.C Almo, Z.Y Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of a second aryl phosphate-binding site in protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B: a paradigm for inhibitor design
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 94 (1997), pp. 13420–13425
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         30
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        C Ramachandran, R Aebersold, N.K Tonks, D.A Pot
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Sequential dephosphorylation of a multiply phosphorylated insulin receptor peptide by protein tyrosine phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 31 (1992), pp. 4232–4238
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         31
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.M Ren, P.M Li, W.R Zhang, L.J Sweet, G Cline, G.I Shulman, J.N Livingston, B.J Goldstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Transgenic mice deficient in the LAR protein-tyrosine phosphatase exhibit profound defects in glucose homeostasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Diabetes, 47 (1998), pp. 493–497
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         32
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M Sarmiento, Y Zhao, S.J Gordon, Z.Y Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Molecular basis for substrate specificity of protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol.Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 26368–26374
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         33
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.L Seely, P.A Staubs, D.R Reichart, P Berhanu, K.L Milarski, A.R Salteil, J Kusari, J.M Olefsky
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PTP1B interacts with the activated insulin receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Diabetes, 45 (1996), pp. 1379–1385
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         34
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.D Thompson, D.G Higgins, T.J Gibson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 22 (1994), pp. 4673–4680
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         35
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        I.P Touw, J.P De Koning, A.C Ward, M.H Hermans
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Signaling mechanisms of cytokine receptors and their perturbances in disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell Endocrinol., 160 (2000), pp. 1–9
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         36
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.F White, S.E Shoelson, H Keutmann, C.R Kahn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A cascade of tyrosine autophosphorylation in the beta-subunit activates the phosphotransferase of the insulin receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 263 (1988), pp. 2969–2980
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         37
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z.Y Zhang, A.M Thieme Sefler, D Maclean, D.J McNamara, E.M Dobrusin, T.K Sawyer, J.E Dixon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Substrate specificity of the protein tyrosine phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 90 (1993), pp. 4446–4450 a
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         38
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z.Y Zhang, D Maclean, A.M Thieme Sefler, R.W Roeske, J.E Dixon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A continuous spectrophotometric and fluorimetric assay for protein tyrosine phosphatase using phosphotyrosine-containing peptides
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anal. Biochem., 211 (1993), pp. 7–15 b
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2000 Cell Press.  All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>