<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(00)00096-9
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Accessory Protein Facilitated CFTR-CFTR Interaction, a Molecular Mechanism to Potentiate the Chloride Channel Activity
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The
    <em>
     A
    </em>
    TP
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    inding
    <em>
     c
    </em>
    assette (ABC) superfamily proteins are important functional transporters in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes, playing the primary roles in mediating the entry and exit of a variety of molecules. They form the largest group of paralogous proteins both in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    with 80 members and in
    <em>
     Bacillus subtilis
    </em>
    with 78 members, implicating their critical roles in cellular physiology. Although the precise number is currently unknown, existing information also suggests that this family of proteins is highly represented in the human genome. Furthermore, abnormal function of ABC transporters has been directly linked to the causes of several human diseases.
   </p>
   <p>
    Cystic fibrosis (CF) is an autosomal recessive disorder caused by mutations in the
    <em>
     CFTR
    </em>
    gene, which encodes a chloride-conducting channel (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    ). The CFTR protein is a paradigmatic member of ABC transporters. Like other ABC transporters, CFTR comprises two hydrophobic core regions, where each contains six putative membrane-spanning segments and two nucleotide binding domains (NBDs). Unique to CFTR is an additional large cytoplasmic domain (R domain) connecting the first and second halves of the CFTR molecule (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Riordan et al. 1989
    </xref>
    ). The cloned
    <em>
     CFTR
    </em>
    gene encodes a chloride channel that is activated by phosphorylation of the R domain by cAMP-activated kinases (PKA), and agonistic ATP binding to and hydrolysis by the NBD domain(s) (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     10
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The genetic cause of human cystic fibrosis by
    <em>
     CFTR
    </em>
    mutations has been well established (see review by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zielenski and Tsui 1995
    </xref>
    ). Physiological experiments have suggested that the native CFTR channel is a macromolecular complex that can be regulated by various accessory-interacting proteins (see reviews by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     al-Awqati, 1995
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Wine 1995
    </xref>
    ). Like many other members of the ABC transporter superfamily, the precise stoichiometry of the CFTR channel is not known.
   </p>
   <p>
    Using a combination of biochemical and molecular techniques, we have identified a multivalent CFTR binding protein, CAP70, which is capable of facilitating intermolecular CFTR interaction. By directly testing its effects on the CFTR channel activity, we found that dimeric binding to the C terminus of CFTR by the recombinant CAP70 protein or a monoclonal antibody is sufficient to potentiate the chloride current. Our results suggest that the CFTR channel is a dynamic macromolecular complex. The modulation of intermolecular contacts by a cytoplasmic accessory protein provides a molecular basis for their functional plasticity.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Identification of CAP70
   </title>
   <p>
    The C-terminal amino acid sequences of CFTR predicted from the cloned genes are highly conserved among many species (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1A
    </xref>
    ). To test the hypothesis that the C-terminal region may be involved in the interaction with accessory proteins, an affinity column using glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion was constructed which contained the 15 C-terminal residues of the human CFTR protein (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1A
    </xref>
    ). The binding proteins specific for the CFTR affinity column were purified from mouse kidney extracts. When separated on SDS-PAGE, at least four polypeptides specific for the GST-CFTR column were identified. These
    <em>
     C
    </em>
    FTR-
    <em>
     A
    </em>
    ssociated
    <em>
     P
    </em>
    roteins (CAPs) had molecular masses of 40, 55, 70, and 85 kDa (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1B
    </xref>
    ). The binding specificity to the CFTR C terminus was demonstrated by the restricted association with GST-CFTR beads, but not GST alone beads. The individual CAPs could interact either directly with the CFTR C terminus or indirectly through association with another CAP.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Identification of CAP70(a) Amino acid sequence alignment of the C termini of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (343 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    On the basis of the intensity of the Coomassie stain, CAP70 was the most abundant polypeptide retained by the affinity column and it thus served as a good candidate for direct interaction with the CFTR C terminus. To determine the amino acid sequence, a large-scale purification was carried out. The resultant purified proteins were fractionated on SDS-PAGE, and transferred and immobilized onto a polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane. To avoid potential N-terminal protection, the CAP70 polypeptide on the membrane was digested in situ and the released tryptic peptides were purified by HPLC. Microsequencing of internal tryptic peptides from the purified CAP70 revealed two sequences of 26 residues and 19 residues, respectively (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1C
    </xref>
    ). Although the tryptic peptides did not identify any known genes in the database, comparison of the peptide sequences with those in NCBI databases revealed several expression sequence tag (EST) clones. The sequence analyses of the full-length cDNA revealed that
    <em>
     CAP70
    </em>
    was a mouse homolog of
    <em>
     PDZK1
    </em>
    .
    <em>
     PDZK1
    </em>
    is a human gene identified in a yeast two-hybrid screen using MAP17 as bait. MAP17 was initially identified by using the differential display technique that was selected for genes upregulated in renal cell carcinoma compared with normal renal parenchyma. The function of MAP17 is currently unknown (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Kocher et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     CAP70
    </em>
    contained an open reading frame of 519 amino acids with a predicted molecular mass of 56 kDa. The deduced mouse CAP70 (mCAP70) amino acid sequence contained the two tryptic peptides, which confirmed that the two peptides were indeed derived from one protein (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1C
    </xref>
    ). CAP70 protein comprises four PDZ domains, which are also known as GLGF repeats, or disks-large homology repeats (DHRs) (see reviews by
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Kennedy 1995
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Sheng 1996
    </xref>
    ). PDZ domains belong to a family of protein binding modules that have been shown to interact with target proteins through binding either to the C termini (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Kim et al. 1995
    </xref>
    ) or less commonly to internal regions (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     29
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     12
    </xref>
    ). Recent reports have shown that PDZ domains have diverse peptide binding specificity (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ). The tandem arrangement of four PDZ domains suggests that CAP70 is likely to function by binding to multiple proteins to organize a macromolecular complex.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Tissue distribution of the human CAP70 messenger RNA was examined using Northern blot analysis. The 2.7 kb CAP70 transcript was found mainly in kidney, liver, and small intestine (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2A
    </xref>
    ). To further investigate the expression pattern, an antibody against mCAP70 was developed and affinity purified. This antibody specifically recognized a 70 kDa polypeptide, and strong immunoblot signals were consistently found in kidney, liver, and small intestine. A significant amount of CAP70 protein could be detected in brain, lung, and testis (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2B
    </xref>
    ). In addition, a relatively low level of 70 kDa polypeptide could also be detected from pancreas, stomach, and colon after longer exposure (data not shown). The expression pattern of
    <em>
     CAP70
    </em>
    partially overlapped with the tissue distribution of CFTR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Tissue Distribution and Subcellular Localization of CAP70(a) Tissue distribution ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (289 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The subcellular localization of CAP70 was mainly restricted to apical domains of epithelial cells as demonstrated by immunofluorescence staining (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    ). In kidney and small intestine, a dense staining of CAP70 was colocalized along the brush border (apical membrane domains) as revealed by the rhodamine-conjugated phloidin staining (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    , panels A–F). In kidney, the distribution of CAP70 was restricted mainly to the proximal tubules. The surrounding glomerulus and other tubular structures did not contain a significant level of CAP70 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    , panels A–C). In both tissue samples, the staining could be abolished by antigen, i.e., the purified CAP70 (data not shown). The tissue and subcellular distribution of CAP70 was consistent with the CFTR localization (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    ), thus in agreement with the potential association of CAP70 with CFTR in vivo.
   </p>
   <title>
    Interaction between CAP70 and CFTR
   </title>
   <p>
    To determine whether and which region of CAP70 is responsible for direct interaction with the C terminus of CFTR, individual PDZ domains were expressed as hemagglutinin (HA) and green fluorescent protein (GFP)-fusions in human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293 cells (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3B
    </xref>
    ). The protein lysates of transfected HEK293 cells were tested for association with the CFTR C terminus by an affinity “pull-down” assay.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3B
    </xref>
    shows that PDZ1, PDZ3, and PDZ4 could be precipitated by glutathione agarose beads with bound GST fusion of the CFTR C terminus (lanes 3), but not by GST beads alone (lanes 2). The binding affinity (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    ) was measured by surface plasmon resonance (SPR) method using a synthetic peptide (EEVQDTRL, C-peptide-TRL) corresponding to the last eight amino acids of CFTR and the purified GST fusion proteins of the individual PDZ domains (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    ). The binding affinity varied from 8 nM of PDZ3 to 220 nM of PDZ1. Mutation of C-peptide-TRL to TRA abolished the interaction (data not shown). Thus, the CFTR-CAP70 interaction could be mediated through independent binding of the PDZ1, PDZ3, and PDZ4 domains of CAP70 to the C terminus of CFTR.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Interaction between CAP70 and CFTR(a) Schematic diagrams of the constructs for ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (271 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The multivalent binding capability may provide a mechanism for CAP70 to assemble multiple CFTR molecules. To test this hypothesis, we coexpressed CAP70 in HEK293 cells with the CFTR C-terminal domains that were differentially tagged with either HA epitope (HA-CFTR-Ct) or green fluorescent protein (GFP-CFTR-Ct) (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3C
    </xref>
    ). Multimerization of the CFTR C-terminal domain by CAP70 was assessed based on whether HA-CFTR-Ct can be coimmunoprecipitated with GFP-CFTR-Ct in the presence of CAP70.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3D
    </xref>
    shows that HA-CFTR-Ct was precipitated by an anti-GFP antibody only upon the coexpression of CAP70 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3D
    </xref>
    , upper panel). Substitution of the terminal TRL with TRA (HA-CFTR-Ct*), which eliminated the CAP70-CFTR interaction (data not shown), abolished the coprecipitation under the same conditions (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3D
    </xref>
    , lower panel). The data show that CAP70 is capable of nucleating a protein complex that contains more than one CFTR C-terminal domain. The recruitment of CFTR into the complex requires its ability to bind to CAP70. We also attempted the above experiment using differentially tagged full-length CFTR constructs. A combination of nonspecific CFTR aggregation and differential expression level of CAP70 and full-length CFTR fusions in transiently transfected cells rendered the experiment unsuccessful (data not shown).
   </p>
   <p>
    To further investigate the interaction of CAP70 with CFTR in a cellular environment, HEK293 cells were transfected with functional GFP-CFTR in the presence or absence of CAP70. The transfected cells were lysed and immunoprecipitated with an affinity-purified anti-CAP70 antibody. The immunoprecipitates were then labeled with PKA in the presence of [
    <sup>
     33
    </sup>
    P]-γ−ATP and resolved by SDS-PAGE. The GFP-CFTR fusion could be immunoprecipitated with the anti-CAP70 antibody only in cells that were cotransfected with CFTR and CAP70 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3E
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To investigate the potential native association of CAP70 and CFTR, coimmunoprecipitation experiments were performed using human airway epithelial cell line Calu-3, where functional expression of native CFTR was detected (e.g.,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Shen et al. 1994
    </xref>
    ) and CAP70 protein was also found (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3F
    </xref>
    ). The CFTR protein was detected in the protein complex precipitated by anti-CAP70 antibody (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3G
    </xref>
    ). In contrast, the CFTR protein was not detectable using the preimmune serum. Furthermore, the signal of CFTR coimmunoprecipitated by anti-CAP70 antibody could be competed by the purified recombinant CAP70. The efficiency of the antigenic CAP70 competition was further enhanced when the CFTR binding sites in CAP70 were preblocked with excess amounts of the C-peptide-TRL.
   </p>
   <p>
    The localization of native CAP70 and CFTR was examined using confocal microscopy of immunofluorescence stained primary culture derived from human bronchial epithelial cells. CAP70 is a protein that is more abundant than CFTR. Consistent with this notion, the result revealed that CAP70 partially colocalized with CFTR in discrete small clusters in the peripheral region of the cell (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3H
    </xref>
    ). The weaker staining signal of CFTR presumably resulted from the anti-R domain antibody because anti-C terminus antibody, which recognizes the same epitope as CAP70, is not useful for this study. Interestingly, CAP70-specific staining was also found in the perinuclear region. In contrast, the CAP70 protein in native tissue was restricted to apical region (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2C
    </xref>
    ). These results suggest that the localization of CAP70 and possibly the association of CFTR with CAP70 are regulated in vivo.
   </p>
   <title>
    Potentiation of CFTR Channel Activity by CAP70
   </title>
   <p>
    The functional effect of the CAP70 binding was examined by patch-clamp recording of the CFTR chloride channel activity using transiently transfected HEK293 cells. The CFTR current is PKA- and ATP-dependent and present only in transfected cells. The authenticity of the CFTR currents was further confirmed by the pharmacological behavior. The currents were insensitive to 4,4′-diisothiocyanostilbene-2,2′-disulfonic acid (DIDS) but could be inhibited by glybenclamide. The CAP70 used in this study was expressed in
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    as a GST fusion and was purified to homogeneity after removing the GST portion by thrombin cleavage (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4A
    </xref>
    ). To test whether the recombinant CAP70 has any effect on the CFTR-mediated ion conducting activity, we studied the channel behavior using both single channel recording and macropatch recording techniques.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4B
    </xref>
    shows a trace with typical CFTR characteristics, including linear current voltage relation, a 9.3 ± 0.1 pS (n = 19) conductance and the PKA- and ATP-dependent channel opening. In the absence of PKA and ATP, CAP70 alone was not sufficient to activate the channel and had no effect on membrane conductance (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4B
    </xref>
    ). Under the inside-out macropatch configuration, application of CAP70 (40 nM) potentiated the CFTR chloride channel activity by nearly 60% (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4C
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4D
    </xref>
    ). The maximal potentiation was usually achieved in less than 5 min (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4C
    </xref>
    ). The potentiation was reversed within 2–3 min when the patched membrane was perfused with the competitive CFTR C-peptide.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Effect of CAP70 on the Wild-Type CFTR Channel(a) Expression and purification of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (210 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To further characterize CAP70-mediated modulation, we studied the CAP70's effects using single channel recording techniques. The open probability (
    <em>
     P
     <sub>
      o
     </sub>
    </em>
    ) of CFTR channel was typically 0.23 ± 0.02 (n = 19) in the presence of 0.5 mM ATP. Upon application of the recombinant CAP70, the CFTR channel was switched to a more active state, where both open probability (
    <em>
     P
     <sub>
      o
     </sub>
    </em>
    ) and mean open time (MOT) increased in a dose-dependent manner (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4F
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4G
    </xref>
    , closed squares). The potentiation reached a maximum at 40 nM of CAP70. A higher concentration of CAP70 induced a decline from the maximal potentiation, suggesting that the stoichiometry of the CAP70-CFTR complex plays a role in the optimal potentiation (see
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 7
    </xref>
    and Discussion). The CAP70-mediated potentiation was dependent on PKA and ATP. In the presence of 200 nM of peptide, only C-peptide-TRL (EEVQDTRL), and not mutated C-peptide-TRA (EEVQDTRA), was able to abolish the CAP70-mediated potentiation, consistent with the results of the binding experiments (data not shown). In addition, amino acid substitution of the last residue leucine with alanine (L1480A) in CFTR, which abolishes the binding to CAP70, completely eliminated the CAP70-mediated potentiation (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4F
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4G
    </xref>
    , closed circles), suggesting that the potentiation requires a direct interaction between CAP70 and the CFTR C terminus.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="A Proposed Model of CAP70-Mediated Potentiation on the CFTR ChannelCFTR monomers ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (102 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Purified CAP70 even at 250 nM behaved as a monomer as tested by gel filtration chromatography (data not shown). Results from the binding studies (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3
    </xref>
    ) showed that there were three CFTR interacting PDZ domains present in CAP70. To test for which one and how many interacting PDZ domains are necessary for the potentiation, the truncated CAP70 proteins corresponding to PDZ1–2, PDZ2–3, PDZ3–4, and PDZ3 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5A
    </xref>
    ) were expressed and purified to apparent homogeneity (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5B
    </xref>
    ). These truncated proteins all displayed the ability to bind the C terminus of CFTR (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3B
    </xref>
    ). PDZ3, PDZ1–2, and PDZ2–3 each contain one CFTR binding site. When tested by excised inside-out patch recording, these truncated proteins were unable to induce any potentiation effect on the CFTR channel (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5c-5f
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5i
    </xref>
    ). In contrast, PDZ3–4, which contains two binding sites, displayed potentiation activity similar to that induced by the full-length CAP70 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5g-5i
    </xref>
    ). These data showed that PDZ3–4 was sufficient to exert the potentiation activity.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Mapping the Minimal Region of CAP70 Essential for Potentiation of CFTR(a) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (243 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The potentiation activity of the PDZ3–4 fusion could result from either bivalent binding of PDZ3–4 to two CFTR molecules, possible potentiation sequence motifs within the PDZ4 domain, or a combination of binding and potentiation sequence motifs. To distinguish between these possibilities, we tested the effect of a tandem PDZ3 domain protein (PDZ3–3) on CFTR channel activity.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4F
    </xref>
    shows this tandem chimeric PDZ protein indeed exhibited the potentiation activity, which is consistent with the notion that bivalent binding is responsible for the potentiation.
   </p>
   <p>
    To directly test whether the bivalent binding is sufficient for the potentiation, we used a monoclonal antibody that recognized the last four residues (DTRL-COOH) of CFTR. The bivalent binding by the antibody would bring two CFTR molecules in proximity, reminiscent of the bivalent binding ability of PDZ3–4 or PDZ3–3.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 6A
    </xref>
    shows that this antibody, a completely unrelated protein to CAP70, could also potentiate the channel activity (the lower trace). The antibody effects were abolished by competition of 100 nM of the C-peptide-TRL (data not shown). A control monoclonal antibody (anti-HA tag) at the same concentration did not show any such effect (the upper trace). This result demonstrated that the bivalent binding activity is sufficient for the potentiation, suggesting that CAP70 functions by modulating intermolecular CFTR-CFTR interaction. Such a configuration of dimeric CFTR gives rise to more active channels when activated by PKA and ATP.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Effect of the Monoclonal Antibody on the CFTR Channel Activity(a) The continuous ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867400000969-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (429 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Structural studies of several prokaryotic ABC-like transporters have provided important biochemical insights into the function of this large family of proteins and their potential relevance to mutations in ABC transporters that cause a variety of diseases (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     2
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     13
    </xref>
    ). Because these structures are either partial or from nonparadigmatic transporters, the quaternary structure of mammalian ABC transporters remains largely unknown. Recent progress in low resolution structural studies has revealed images of purified multidrug resistant P-glycoprotein, suggesting that the monomeric form is sufficient for substrate binding and ATP hydrolysis (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Rosenberg et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The CFTR protein regulates and is regulated by a variety of transporting processes. It has been speculated that the CFTR quaternary structure may also undergo dynamic changes. Thus, it is essential to determine the existence and organization of potential heteromeric and homomeric CFTR interactions with other functionally coupled proteins. Results consistent with possible homomeric CFTR-CFTR interaction include the finding that a tandem fusion of two CFTR coding sequences resulted in a functional channel which exhibited one single unitary conductance identical to that of CFTR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Zerhusen et al. 1999
    </xref>
    ). In addition, electron microscopy studies revealed that the CFTR channel on the cell surface has a size that is considerably larger than that of a monomer (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Eskandari et al. 1998
    </xref>
    ). The result has also led to the suggestion that imaged particles are CFTR dimers. In contrast, biochemical studies on purified or coimmunoprecipitated protein showed that the purified recombinant CFTR protein is consistent with the monomeric channel or an unstable oligomer that could not survive the experimental procedures (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Marshall et al. 1994
    </xref>
    ). Furthermore, the purified P-glycoprotein was also seen as a monomer (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Rosenberg et al. 1997
    </xref>
    ). A possible explanation for the existing data is that the CFTR channel may interact to form a transitional dimer. Such a dimeric form is unstable, distinct from a typical multimeric channel complex such as a voltage-gated potassium channel, where the purified recombinant protein complex is stable and remains in a stoichiometry identical to its native form (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Li et al. 1994
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The potentiation by recombinant CAP70 was dependent on the bivalent binding ability and not on a specific potentiation region of CAP70. Thus, modulation of the intermolecular CFTR interaction is an attractive mechanism for the potentiation activity.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 7
    </xref>
    shows a proposed model for the CAP70-mediated potentiation. This model predicts that CFTR, in the absence of CAP70, exists either as a monomer or as a transient dimer when activated by PKA and ATP. In the presence of CAP70, the formation of CAP70-(CFTR)
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    allows for a more effective association with an additional CFTR molecule because the bound CAP70 provides at least two possible beneficial effects: (1) added affinity via either a PDZ1 or a PDZ4 association with another CFTR molecule, and (2) improved contact geometry between the two interacting CFTR molecules. The CAP70-configured (CFTR)
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    complex, when activated by PKA phosphorylation and agonistic ATP, induces a more active CFTR channel. Thus, the model also predicts that with an increasing CAP70 concentration, the highest affinity PDZ3 domain begins to dominate the binding. Under such conditions, although CAP70 remains in complex with CFTR, the bivalent CAP70-(CFTR)
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    configuration is less favorable. As a result, the potentiation by CAP70 will become less pronounced. Consistent with this model, a high concentration of CAP70 showed significantly reduced potentiation (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4f–4i
    </xref>
    ). The third prediction from this model is that a bivalent binding of two PDZ domains with equally high affinity would stabilize the CFTR-CFTR interaction. Therefore, we should not observe the aforementioned decline. Instead, the potentiation would reach a plateau phase with a less pronounced decline phase even at higher concentrations. Consistent with this prediction, the effect of the tandem PDZ protein of PDZ3-PDZ3 induced potentiation followed by a plateau phase at higher concentrations (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4F
    </xref>
    , open circles). The binding affinity of PDZ3 is significantly higher than that of PDZ1 or PDZ4 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    ). However, the concentration of PDZ3-PDZ3 required for the maximal potentiation was not significantly lower than that of CAP70 despite the expected higher affinity (avidity) to CFTR. This inconsistency may be due to potential unfavorable constraints as a result of the chimeric construction. While the mechanistic details by which CAP70 potentiates the CFTR channel require further investigation, it would be particularly interesting to test the potential role of the parallel contact geometry of two NBD2 domains as a result of CAP70 binding.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>