<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC196235
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Molecular basis for the discrimination of repressive methyl-lysine marks
 in histone H3 by Polycomb and HP1 chromodomains
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     On the histone H3 tail, Lys 9 and Lys 27 are both methylation sites
 associated with epigenetic repression, and reside within a highly related
 sequence motif ARKS. Here we show that the chromodomain proteins Polycomb (Pc)
 and HP1 (
     <span>
      h
     </span>
     eterochromatin
     <span>
      p
     </span>
     rotein
     <span>
      1
     </span>
     ) are
 highly discriminatory for binding to these sites in vivo and in vitro. In
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     S2 cells, and on polytene chromosomes, methyl-Lys 27 and
 Pc are both excluded from areas that are enriched in methyl-Lys 9 and HP1.
 Swapping of the chromodomain regions of Pc and HP1 is sufficient for switching
 the nuclear localization patterns of these factors, indicating a role for
 their chromodomains in both target site binding and discrimination. To better
 understand the molecular basis for the selection of methyl-lysine binding
 sites, we solved the 1.8 Å structure of the Pc chromodomain in complex
 with a H3 peptide bearing trimethyl-Lys 27, and compared it with our
 previously determined structure of the HP1 chromodomain in complex with a H3
 peptide bearing trimethyl-Lys 9. The Pc chromodomain distinguishes its
 methylation target on the H3 tail via an extended recognition groove that
 binds five additional residues preceding the ARKS motif.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     Polycomb, HP1, heterochromatin, histone H3, lysine methylation, epigenetic
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Specific binding of Pc to methyl-Lys 27
    </title>
    <p>
     The chromodomains of Pc and HP1 are highly conserved (54% identity in
 protein sequence; see
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1A
     </xref>
     ).
 Moreover, the Pc chromodomain contains three “caging” aromatic
 residues that were shown in HP1 to be necessary for methyl-Lys 9 binding
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and Khorasanizadeh
 2002
     </xref>
     ). The amino acid sequences immediately surrounding Lys 9 and
 Lys 27 in the H3 tail are very similar as shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1B
     </xref>
     and, in particular,
 share a consensus sequence ARKS. However, the residues flanking this consensus
 motif are unrelated. To determine the extent by which Pc and HP1 are able to
 discriminate between the Lys 9 and Lys 27 methylation sites, we used a set of
 synthetic methylated H3 peptides to measure the relative binding affinities of
 their chromodomains to these histone H3 tail segments. Fluorescence
 polarization measurements indicated a clear preference of the chromodomain of
 <span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983904" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="P26017" type="participant">Pc</span> for the trimethylated Lys 27 site. Specifically, the dissociation constant
 for the <span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983904" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="P02299" type="participant">trimethyl-Lys 27 peptide</span> was <span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983904" annotator="elias" type="value">5</span><span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983904" annotator="elias" type="unit">μM</span>, and that
 for the <span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983851" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="P02299" type="participant">trimethyl-Lys 9 peptide</span> 
 was <span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983851" annotator="elias" type="value">125</span><span id="12897054" source="intactdb" intactdbid="6983851" annotator="elias" type="unit">μM</span> (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig.
 1C
     </xref>
     ). In contrast, the HP1 chromodomain bound to the trimethyl-Lys
 9 peptide with an affinity of 4 μM and to the trimethyl-Lys 27 peptide with
 an affinity of 64 μM (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig.
 1C
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and Khorasanizadeh
 2002
     </xref>
     ). These data indicate that both protein modules discriminate
 methyl marks effectively, with Pc showing a 25-fold selectivity and HP1
 showing a 16-fold selectivity for the cognate versus noncognate target
 sequences.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Preferential binding of Pc and HP1 chromodomains to different
 methyl-lysines on the histone H3 tail. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Sequence alignment of the
 chromodomains of HP1 and Pc. Three conserved aromatic residues forming an
 aromatic cage for methyl-lysine recognition in HP1 are highlighted. Secondary
 structure elements of the HP1 chromodomain fold are illustrated on
       <em>
        top
       </em>
       . (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Sequence of the N terminus (residues 1-36) of
 histone H3. The “neighborhoods” of the Lys 9 and Lys 27
 methylation sites are very similar; identical sequence stretches surrounding
 both sites are boxed. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Binding of the chromodomains of Pc
 (residues 1-98) and HP1 (residues 17-76) to different methylated and
 unmodified H3 peptides in fluorescence polarization assays. K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       (μM) values are listed in the
       <em>
        bottom.
       </em>
       Note that neither
 chromodomain interacts with the unmodified H3 tail.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We also investigated to what extent the degree of methylation affected
 target selection. Binding of Pc to a peptide with mono- or dimethylated Lys 27
 peptides was about five times weaker than binding to the trimethylated Lys 27
 peptide, but still much stronger than binding to the trimethylated Lys 9
 peptide (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1C
     </xref>
     ). Furthermore,
 no significant interactions between the Pc chromodomain and mono- or
 dimethylated Lys 9 peptides were observed. HP1 binding to dimethyl- and
 monomethyl-Lys 9 was weakened 2-fold and 15-fold, respectively. These results
 indicate that the degree of methylation does affect the binding of both
 chromodomains to their target sites and that the trimethyl-lysine is the
 preferred level of modification for both proteins in vitro. In the context of
 trimethyl-lysine, each protein shows clear discrimination for its cognate
 site, likely because of differences in sequence context of the trimethyl-Lys
 in H3 as well as the binding groove of the chromodomain (see below).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Colocalization of Pc and H3 Lys 27 methylation on polytene
 chromosomes
    </title>
    <p>
     Using immunofluorescence staining, we have previously shown that the HP1
 protein is localized almost exclusively to the chromocentric heterochromatin
 of
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     salivary gland polytene chromosomes, a chromosomal
 domain highly enriched in H3 Lys 9 methylation
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ). To
 investigate the specific localization pattern of the Pc protein and to
 correlate its distribution with chromosomal regions of H3 Lys 9 and H3 Lys 27
 methylation, we performed similar immunostaining experiments using newly
 developed anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27-specific antibodies in combination with
 antibodies specific for Pc. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2A
     </xref>
     , the
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27-specific antibodies recognized many bands on the
 arms of polytene chromosomes. A weaker immunofluorescence signal for this
 modification was detected around the chromocentric regions. Whether the lower
 staining in this area represents a low level of H3 Lys 27 trimethylation at
 the chromocenter or might be caused by slight cross-reactivity of the
 antibodies with the H3 Lys 9 methyl mark is unknown (data not shown; see
 Materials and Methods). Importantly, the bands labeled by the
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27-specific antibodies were highly correlated with
 bands detected by anti-Pc-specific antibodies. Indeed, &gt;90% of bands
 labeled by these antibodies showed a clear overlap
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2A
     </xref>
     , merged image). In
 contrast, antibodies specific for H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K9 only labeled the
 chromocenter, but did not stain regions overlapping with the anti-Pc-specific
 antibodies (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2B
     </xref>
     ). Similar
 results were obtained using anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9-specific antibodies (data
 not shown). The colocalization of H3 Lys 27 trimethylation with Pc complex
 proteins was independently verified by double labeling experiments using an
 anti-Psc (
     <span>
      p
     </span>
     osterior
     <span>
      s
     </span>
     ex
     <span>
      c
     </span>
     omb)-specific
 monoclonal antibody in combination with the anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27-specific
 polyclonal antibodies (data not shown). The immunostaining experiments are
 consistent with recruitment of Pc to regions of H3 Lys 27 trimethylation but
 not to regions of H3 Lys 9 trimethylation. This interpretation is in excellent
 agreement with the observed binding preferences of the chromodomains of HP1
 and Pc for methylated H3 tails in vitro.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Colocalization of Pc with H3 Lys 27 trimethylation, but not H3 Lys 9
 trimethylation on polytene chromosomes. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Immunostaining of
 salivary gland polytene chromosomes with anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K27-specific
 antibodies and anti-Pc antibodies. Many bands on the arms of the polytene
 chromosomes are labeled by both antibodies (as shown by yellow bands in the
 merged image), indicating colocalization of the Pc protein with sites of H3
 Lys 27 trimethylation. It is not clear whether the weaker signal of H3 Lys 27
 trimethylation occasionally observed around the chromocentric regions
 represents a true accumulation of this modification or might be caused by
 slight cross-reactivity of the antibodies with the H3 Lys 9 methyl mark. DNA
 was stained with DAPI, and the arrow points to the chromocenter. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       )
 Double labeling with anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K9-specific antibodies and
 anti-Pc-specific antibodies. The anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K9-specific antibodies
 stain mainly the chromocenter (denoted by an arrow in the DAPI staining), but
 not the many bands where the Pc protein is localized.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Different subnuclear localizations of Pc and HP1 in S2 cells are
 correlated with different histone H3 methyl marks
    </title>
    <p>
     To further analyze and compare the localization of histone H3 methylation
 on Lys 9 and Lys 27 with that of the HP1 and Pc proteins in vivo, we performed
 indirect immunofluorescence studies on
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Schneider S2 cells.
 In these diploid male cells, antibodies specific for H3 dimethylated or
 trimethylated on Lys 9 accumulated in defined, often more internal, subnuclear
 regions (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     ). In contrast,
 immunostaining with antibodies specific for H3 trimethylated on Lys 27 showed
 a more diffuse, external nuclear staining pattern, which almost decorated the
 whole cell nucleus (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3B
     </xref>
     ).
 Costaining with antibodies specific for HP1 showed a complete overlap with the
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9 signal as indicated by the yellow spots in the merged
 image (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     ). These findings
 are in good agreement with previously published observations on other cellular
 systems and reinforce the idea that HP1 is recruited to sites of Lys 9
 methylation in vivo (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Moazed
 2001
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheutin et al.
 2003
     </xref>
     ). However, little, if any, significant overlap was detected
 between the anti-HP1 and anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27 immunostainings. HP1 is
 rather excluded from regions enriched in Lys 27 methylation in this cell line
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3B
     </xref>
     ). Furthermore, Pc
 showed a subnuclear distribution very similar to the anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27
 signal. Again, almost no overlap in staining with HP1 was detected
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3C
     </xref>
     ). Thus, Pc-mediated
 gene silencing and H3-Lys 27 methylation appear to be similarly distributed in
 diploid S2 cells. Both are mainly localized to areas distinct from the
 heterochromatic regions marked by enrichment in HP1 and H3-Lys 9
 methylation.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Localization of HP1, Pc, and repressive H3 methyl-lysine marks to distinct
 regions of the nucleus in S2 cells. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Immunostaining of S2 cells
 with anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       K9-specific (red) and anti-HP1-specific (green)
 antibodies shows colocalization to putatively heterochromatic regions inside
 the cell nucleus. Coimmunostaining of anti-HP1-specific antibodies with
 anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K27-specific (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) or anti-Pc-specific
 (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) antibodies, in contrast, shows strict exclusion from nuclear
 regions enriched in HP1. DNA inside the cell nucleus was stained with
 DAPI.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Importance of the different chromodomains of Pc and HP1 for distinct
 subnuclear targeting
    </title>
    <p>
     Based on the different binding preferences of the chromodomains of Pc and
 HP1 for selective methyl marks on H3 tail peptides in vitro, and the distinct
 cellular localization patterns of Pc and HP1, we next wanted to test if the
 chromodomains of Pc and HP1 are sufficient for subnuclear targeting in vivo.
 Therefore, we generated chimeric fusion protein constructs, replacing the
 chromodomain of Pc with that of HP1 (Pc
     <sup>
      HP1-CD
     </sup>
     -V5) and the
 chromodomain of HP1 with that of Pc (HP1
     <sup>
      Pc-CD
     </sup>
     -V5). These chimeric
 fusion protein constructs and their wild-type counterparts were transiently
 transfected into S2 cells. The cellular distribution of the fusion proteins
 was then analyzed by immunofluorescence using antibodies directed against the
 common V5 tag. Equal expression levels of the fusion proteins were confirmed
 by Western blotting (data not shown). As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     , the transiently
 expressed HP1-V5 fusion protein showed a subnuclear staining pattern very
 similar to that observed for the endogenous HP1 protein (see
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3A
     </xref>
     ). In addition, good
 overlap with heterochromatic regions stained by the
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9-specific antibodies was detected. In contrast, the
 HP1
     <sup>
      Pc-CD
     </sup>
     -V5 chimeric fusion protein did not show a focal
 localization, but was rather dispersed throughout almost the whole cell
 nucleus in many cells inspected. Very little colocalization with H3
 dimethylated on Lys 9 was detected (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig.
 4B
     </xref>
     ). Conversely, the Pc-V5 fusion protein localized to regions
 outside of the heterochromatic domains stained by the
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9-specific antibodies, similar to the endogenous Pc
 protein (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4C
     </xref>
     ). Swapping the
 chromodomain of Pc with that of HP1 resulted in a focal subnuclear
 distribution reminiscent of that of HP1 (Pc
     <sup>
      HP1-CD
     </sup>
     -V5;
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4D
     </xref>
     ). Furthermore, this
 chimeric fusion protein was often closely associated with the heterochromatic
 regions stained by the anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9-specific antibodies
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4D
     </xref>
     ). The importance of
 the chromodomain for Pc localization was further emphasized by the loss of
 specific subnuclear targeting of an Ile 69-Asp 70 deletion mutant, which had
 previously been identified in an unbiased genetic screen
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Messmer et al. 1992
     </xref>
     ; data not
 shown). In our in vitro binding assays, this mutant Pc chromodomain was not
 able to interact with the trimethyl-Lys 27 H3 peptide presumably because of
 loss of necessary structure for peptide binding (see below). Our chromodomain
 swapping experiments implicate an important role for the different
 chromodomains of Pc and HP1 in both target site binding and discrimination.
 They further emphasize the critical targeting role of the chromodomains for
 the biological function of these factors.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Importance of the different chromodomains of Pc and HP1 for distinct
 subnuclear targeting in vivo. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Full-length HP1 fused to a V5-tag
 was transiently expressed in S2 cells. Immunostaining with antibodies specific
 for the V5-tag (green) shows colocalization with H3 dimethylated on Lys 9
 (red). (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) The chromodomain of HP1 was replaced by the chromodomain
 of Pc (HP1
       <sup>
        Pc-CD
       </sup>
       -V5). Coimmunostaining with anti-V5- and
 anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       K9-specific antibodies shows exclusion of this chimeric
 fusion protein from the heterochromatic regions enriched in H3 Lys 9
 dimethylation. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) A transiently expressed Pc-V5 fusion protein
 localizes to regions that are low in anti-H3-Me
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       K9 staining.
 (
       <em>
        D
       </em>
       ) Replacement of the Pc chromodomain with that of HP1
 (Pc
       <sup>
        HP1-CD
       </sup>
       -V5) results in recruitment of this fusion protein to
 regions enriched in H3 Lys 9 dimethylation. Exemplary cells of a broader
 spectrum of phenotypes are shown.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Overall structure of the Pc chromodomain-methyl-Lys 27 H3 peptide
 complex
    </title>
    <p>
     To visualize how the Pc protein binds the methyl-Lys 27-containing histone
 H3 tail, we crystallized its chromodomain in complex with a synthetic peptide
 corresponding to residues 15-32 of histone H3 with a trimethyl-lysine at
 residue 27. The crystals diffracted to 1.8 Å resolution, and the
 structure was solved using molecular replacement.
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     summarizes the quality
 of the X-ray diffraction data and the structure refinement parameters. The
 electron density map was interpretable throughout the entire chromodomain
 region (residues 23-73). Analysis of the |2Fo - Fc| and |Fo - Fc| difference
 maps clearly indicated electron density for the bound position of the H3
 peptide in the complex as shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
 5A
     </xref>
     . The bound H3 peptide density observed corresponds to residues
 20-28, including clear density for trimethyl-Lys 27.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig5" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 5.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Structure of the Pc chromodomain (residues 15-77) in complex with the
 trimethylated-Lys 27 H3 tail (residues 15-32) at 1.8 Å resolution.
 (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Stereo diagram of an |Fo - Fc| simulated annealing omit map
 contoured at 2.5σ in which the H3 tail peptide was omitted for map
 calculation. Side chains that make critical contacts are depicted; the
 chromodomain backbone is in brown, and the electron density of the H3 peptide
 is in magenta. Residues 15-19 and 29-32 of the peptide appear to be
 unstructured, suggesting that only Leu 20-Ser 28 of the histone H3 tail
 participate in binding to the chromodomain. Broken lines indicate
 intermolecular hydrogen bonds. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) The chromodomains of both Pc
 (blue) and HP1 (green) contain three aromatic residues that form
 superimposable cages around the methyl-ammonium groups of Lys 27 (red) and Lys
 9 (yellow), respectively. The van der Waals radii of the Pc aromatic rings and
 the methyl-Lys 27 methyl-ammonium atoms are shown. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Superposition
 of the backbone structures of the Pc (brown) and HP1 (blue) chromodomains
 bound to Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K27 and Me
       <sub>
        3
       </sub>
       K9 H3 tail peptides,
 respectively.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Crystallographic data and refinement information
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
    <p>
     The histone peptide forms a β-strand structure that lies between two
 β-strands from one face of the chromodomain, completing a three-stranded
 sheet and the overall β-sandwich architecture of the protein. We
 previously observed this binding mode in the structure of the HP1 chromodomain
 in complex with H3-peptide-bearing trimethyl-Lys 9. The methyl-Lys 27
 interacts with the Pc protein via a cation-π interaction reminiscent of the
 mode seen in the HP1 chromodomain interaction with methyl-Lys 9
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and Khorasanizadeh
 2002
     </xref>
     ). The aromatic cages of the two complexes superimpose with an
 RMSD of 0.7 Å, supporting our previous prediction that aromatic cages in
 diverse chromodomains act as a recognition substructure for methyl-lysines in
 target sequences (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and
 Khorasanizadeh 2002
     </xref>
     ). Within the aromatic cage, one of the
 residues of the Pc chromodomain, Trp 50, is different from its counterpart in
 HP1, Tyr 48 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5B
     </xref>
     ). Mutation
 of Trp 50 to Tyr does not change the affinity of Pc for its target peptide
 significantly (K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     = 7 μM for the binding of the W50Y variant to
 trimethyl-Lys 27 H3 peptide). Other architectural features of the HP1 and Pc
 chromodomains are highly related. Comparison of the HP1 and Pc complex
 structures reveals that the chromodomains and H3 tail peptides superimpose
 with an RMSD of 0.74 Å and 1.0 Å over all of their overlapping
 C
     <sub>
      α
     </sub>
     atoms, respectively
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5C
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Molecular basis for discrimination of methyl-Lys 9 and methyl-Lys 27
 by Pc and HP1
    </title>
    <p>
     Despite the fact that the chromodomains of HP1 and Pc are similarly
 structured, their peptide-binding grooves show distinct features
 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 6A
     </xref>
     ). The most striking
 difference is the extent of peptide-protein interactions in these two
 complexes. A total of six residues of the H3 tail were observed and ordered in
 the HP1 complex (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and Khorasanizadeh
 2002
     </xref>
     ). These correspond to the sequence stretch Gln 5 to Ser 10.
 In the structure of Pc complex with trimethyl-Lys 27 H3, a total of nine
 residues corresponding to the sequence stretch Leu 20 to Ser 28 are observed.
 As a result of a more extended peptide-binding groove in the Pc protein, its
 interactions with the Lys 27 site bury 1482 Å
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     , whereas the
 interaction of HP1 with the Lys 9 site buries 1063 Å
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     . The
 remaining peptide residues in each case were present in the crystals as
 confirmed by mass spectrometry, but are unobserved because of disorder,
 presumably caused by their lack of binding interaction with the chromodomain
 surface.
    </p>
    <fig id="fig6" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 6.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Structural basis for the recognition of methyl-Lys 27 by the Pc
 chromodomain. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Surface depictions of the Pc and HP1 chromodomain
 H3 tail-binding interfaces. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Closeup view of the surface of the Pc
 chromodomain (
       <em>
        left
       </em>
       ) that interacts with residues 20-24 of the H3
 tail, and the surface of the HP1 chromodomain (
       <em>
        right
       </em>
       ) that interacts
 with residues 5-7 of the H3 tail.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     The two complexes show differences in the recognition of the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4
 position (Gln 5 vs. Lys 23), where
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     corresponds to the methyl-lysine
 (see
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1B
     </xref>
     for the H3
 sequence). This appears to have important consequences for the Pc peptide
 interactions. Within the peptide, Lys 23 donates a hydrogen bond to the
 backbone carbonyl of Ala 21, thus stabilizing the extended conformation bound
 in the Pc groove (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 6B
     </xref>
     ). Gln
 5 does not form a similar stabilizing interaction when bound to the HP1
 chromodomain. Another important difference is the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 5 position of
 the peptides (Thr 22 vs. Lys 4). In the Pc complex, Thr 22 of the peptide is
 appropriately positioned to donate a hydrogen bond to the side chain of a
 conserved chromodomain residue, Lys 48. A lysine in this position of the
 peptide would not be able to make this interaction, and in fact would cause
 charge repulsion with the lysine of the chromodomain. In addition, Thr 22
 together with Leu 20 of the peptide form backbone hydrogen bonds with the Arg
 67 side chain of the Pc protein. This interaction would not be possible with
 the HP1 protein, as Arg 67 is not conserved and is instead substituted by Asp
 62 in HP1. These observations indicate that the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4 through
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 7 positions interact with the Pc protein through several backbone
 contacts. As such, these do not provide specific recognition per se, but
 stabilize the overall strand conformation of the H3 tail. As an important
 consequence, the side chain of
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 5 is oriented to hydrogen-bond
 with the Pc protein, and the side chains of
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4 and
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 6
 are allowed to form complementary van der Waals contacts on the Pc surface.
 Together these interactions provide the necessary specificity for
 discrimination of residues
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4 through
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 7 by the Pc
 protein.
    </p>
    <p>
     Whereas the Pc chromodomain recognizes an extended surface encompassing
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4 through
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 7 residues, HP1 appears to be more
 discriminating for residues in the immediate vicinity of the methyl-Lys
 corresponding to the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 1 through
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 3 residues
 (TARK
     <sup>
      9
     </sup>
     vs. AARK
     <sup>
      27
     </sup>
     ). This is shown through mutagenesis
 studies in which the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 3 residue alone is changed from one target
 site to the other. Mutation of Thr 5 to Ala (corresponding to residue 24)
 reduced the peptide-binding affinity of HP1 by sixfold (K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     = 27
 ± 4 μM for the binding of HP1 to the T5A variant of a trimethyl-Lys
 9 H3 peptide). Conversely, when Ala 24 is changed to Thr, the peptide-binding
 affinity of Pc did not change significantly (K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     = 8 ± 1
 μM for the binding of Pc to the A24T variant of a trimethyl-Lys 27 H3
 peptide). Together, these results indicate that the HP1 protein is much more
 discriminating than Pc for the residue in the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 3 position.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Understanding the biological role of posttranslational histone
 modifications requires understanding the mechanisms by which these marks are
 selectively recognized by conserved protein modules. The following conclusions
 can be drawn from the work presented here: Two very similar chromodomains of
 Pc and HP1 interact differently with two very similar methyl-lysine marks in
 the histone H3 tail, methyl-Lys 9 and methyl-Lys 27. The inverse preference of
 target binding observed in vitro is reflected in nonoverlapping localization
 and recruitment of these factors to differentially modified regions of
 chromatin in vivo. Our newly solved structure of the Pc chromodomain in
 complex with a target H3-peptide-bearing methyl-Lys 27 confirms our previous
 finding that clustering of three chromodomain aromatic residues forms an
 aromatic cage for methyl-lysine binding. Furthermore, comparison of the
 structures of Pc and HP1 complexes shows how their chromodomains have evolved
 to discriminate related but distinct regions of the histone H3 tail.
   </p>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Structural aspects of chromodomain methyl-lysine binding
    </title>
    <p>
     In both the HP1 and Pc complexes, histone tail interactions are stabilized
 by the formation of hydrogen bonds and a complementary surface, whereas the
 recognition of the methyl-lysine mark is mediated by an aromatic cage
 consisting of three residues. An intriguing feature of our structural analyses
 of the HP1 and Pc methyl-lysine H3 tail complexes is that the recognition of
 specific target sites is highly restricted to the N-terminal
 “faces” of the Lys 9- and Lys 27-binding sites. No residues
 C-terminal to
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     + 1 (Ser 10 or Ser 28) are seen in the
 three-dimensional structures. Therefore, the specificity of interaction has to
 be derived from hydrophobic and van der Waals interactions between the
 chromodomain and residues not only N-terminal to the methyl-lysine mark but
 also N-terminal to the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 2 residue because both Lys 9 and Lys 27
 are embedded into the same sequence motif ARKS. Whereas the Pc chromodomain
 forms an extended groove that discriminates its target via the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 4
 to
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 7 residues of the H3 tail, the HP1 chromodomain does not form
 stable interactions with the corresponding residues in its target, but is more
 discriminating for the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 3 position. This interpretation of the
 complex structures is consistent with our mutagenesis analysis of the H3 tail
 motif surrounding the Lys 9 and Lys 27 methyl marks, where mutation of the
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     - 3 position had a significant effect on the binding of HP1 to its
 cognate target, but did not impair Pc affinity for methyl-Lys 27. Therefore,
 we conclude that more than a single key residue is important for target
 selection by the chromodomains of HP1 and Pc. This asymmetric and selective
 binding to a cognate mark and its surrounding residues is reminiscent of SH2
 domains and other cellular signaling docking modules
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Pawson et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ). Future
 structural studies of other chromodomains that recognize a methyl-lysine in
 distantly related sequence context should provide additional insights about
 the target selectivity. For example, Lys 4 in histone H3 can also be
 methylated, and the sequence context of this methyl mark is very different
 from Lys 9 and Lys 27 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig.
 1B
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Interestingly, the interacting peptide regions of the H3 tail that are in
 contact with the chromodomains in both, the Pc and HP1 complexes, contain
 additional residues known to be posttranslationally modified. These include
 phospho marks on Ser 10 and Ser 28 and an acetyl mark on Lys 23. At present it
 is not clear to what extent combinations of these marks with the methyl-lysine
 marks of Lys 9 and Lys 27 exist. However, additional modifications could
 influence the binding affinity and selectivity of chromodomain modules to
 methyl-lysine marks additively, synergistically, or antagonistically.
 Therefore, the analysis of such effects will be important for future
 biochemical and structural analyses and should help to delineate the
 regulation of modules binding to histone marks
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Strahl and Allis 2000
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jenuwein and Allis 2001
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Polycomb, HP1, and targeting of chromatin modifiers
    </title>
    <p>
     Our studies show a clear preference of the Pc chromodomain for the H3 Lys
 27 methyl mark. How does this activity of Pc contribute to PcG function? In
 the case of the formation of heterochromatin and the initially genetically
 defined pathway of suppression of variegation, it has been suggested that
 methylation of H3 on Lys 9 by Suv3-9 generates a docking site for the HP1
 (also known as Suv2-5) chromodomain. Further recruitment of Suv3-9 by the
 chromo shadow domain of HP1 has been postulated to lead to a perpetuation and
 spreading of a heterochromatic domain until blocked by yet unknown mechanisms
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Bannister et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Dillon and Festenstein 2002
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Grewal and Elgin 2002
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Snowden et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ).
 Similarly, Esc-E(z)-dependent methylation of Lys 27 (and possibly Lys 9) and
 consecutive recruitment of Pc and Pc-containing complexes might contribute to
 the stability of the PcG complex, particularly in the early stages of assembly
 at a PRE by permitting complex formation to spread to neighboring sequences
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Poux et al.
 2001a
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      b
     </xref>
     ). This
 interpretation of the specific binding of Pc to methyl-Lys 27 is in agreement
 with studies demonstrating loss of chromosome binding for several components
 of PRC1 upon inactivation of E(z)
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Rastelli et al. 1993
     </xref>
     ) and is
 consistent with several other in vivo results that imply synergy between these
 complexes (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Simon and Tamkun
 2002
     </xref>
     ). However, it is unclear at present if dynamic perpetuated
 spreading of a Lys 27 mark indeed exists and is dependent on Pc recruitment
 and Esc-E(z) enzymatic activity. Other possible functions for the binding of
 Pc to the Lys 27 methyl mark include a more static maintenance effect that
 could contribute to epigenetic memory. In this model, the recruitment of
 Esc-E(z) would be independent of and precede any involvement of Pc binding.
 Alternatively, although complex recruitment could be constitutive, the
 decision to repress or not could depend on an epigenetic switch mediated by
 Lys 27 methylation and its interaction with local Pc/PRC1
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Breiling et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Czermin et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     However, alternative routes and mechanisms of Pc and PcG recruitment to
 local sites of chromatin besides recognition of Lys 27 methylation might also
 exist. For example, studies involving the localization of a chimeric HP1
 protein containing the chromodomain of Pc on polytene chromosomes implied
 critical interactions of the Pc chromodomain with other PcG components that
 are recruited to PcG sites (Platero et al.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      1995
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      1996
     </xref>
     ). Therefore, the
 particular localization patterns observed for the wild-type and chimeric
 proteins in our swapping experiments might be the result of additive effects,
 including other targeting mechanisms besides methyl-lysine binding.
 Nevertheless, it is intriguing to note that the subnuclear localization
 patterns for wild-type and chimeric Pc and HP1 proteins are coincident with
 the localization of specifically recognized methyl-lysine marks on the histone
 H3 tail. It is unclear to what extent additional regions of the proteins
 C-terminal to the chromodomains could contribute to subnuclear localization
 and function. For example, different studies have implicated the C-terminal
 chromo shadow domain and hinge regions of HP1 in addition to the chromodomain
 in the specific subnuclear targeting of this factor
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Smothers and Henikoff 2001
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Muchardt et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheutin et al. 2003
     </xref>
     ). However,
 a C-terminal truncation of Pc did not affect its specific chromosomal
 localization (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Messmer et al.
 1992
     </xref>
     ). Additional studies will have to address the exact
 contribution of the chromodomains and their recognition and binding of
 particular methyl-lysine marks to the specific functions of the Pc and HP1
 proteins.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Materials and methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Antibodies
    </title>
    <p>
     Polyclonal antibodies against H3-K9 (Me)
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     and H3-K9
 (Me)
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     were from Upstate Biotech, Inc.; the monoclonal antibody
 against HP1 was obtained from the Hybridoma Bank at the University of Iowa.
 Antibodies against H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Silva et al. 2003
     </xref>
     ), Pc
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Messmer et al. 1992
     </xref>
     ), and Psc
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Martin and Adler 1993
     </xref>
     ) were
 kind gifts from Thomas Jenuwein (Research Institute of Molecular Pathology,
 The Vienna Biocenter, Vienna, Austria), Renato Paro (ZMBH, University of
 Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany), and Paul Adler (Biology Department and
 Cancer Center, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA), respectively. The
 monoclonal anti-V5 antibody was purchased from Invitrogen.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Peptide preparation
    </title>
    <p>
     Synthetic peptides of the H3 tail were prepared at the Core Facility of
 Baylor College of Medicine. Peptides corresponding to the Lys 9 and Lys 27
 regions include residues 1-15 and 15-32, respectively (see
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1A
     </xref>
     ). Unmodified as well as
 modified lysines (mono-, di-, and trimethylation) were incorporated at the Lys
 9 and Lys 27 positions. A nonnative Tyr residue at the C terminus of each
 peptide was used for concentration determination by UV absorption
 measurements. Peptides were labeled with fluorescein as previously described
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Molecular biology
    </title>
    <p>
     For binding studies, the chromodomain of Pc (residues 1-90) was amplified
 by PCR and cloned into the
     <em>
      Bam
     </em>
     HI/
     <em>
      Nde
     </em>
     I sites of the pET16b
 vector (Novagen). For crystallization, Pc residues 15-77 were fused to a
 His
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     -tag by PCR and cloned into the
     <em>
      Bam
     </em>
     HI/
     <em>
      Nde
     </em>
     I
 sites of the pET11a vector. The construct for the expression of the
 chromodomain of HP1 (residues 17-76) has been described previously
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs and Khorasanizadeh
 2002
     </xref>
     ). Full-length
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     HP1 (residues 1-206) and Pc
 (1-390) were PCR-amplified and cloned into the
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI/
     <em>
      Xho
     </em>
     I
 sites of the pMT/V5-His A vector (Invitrogen). The chromodomain of HP1
 (residues 23-77) and Pc (residues 21-74) were swapped using staggered PCR by
 incorporation of overlapping oligonucleotides. Chimeric cDNAs were then cloned
 into the pMT/V5-His A vector. Site-directed mutagenesis was performed
 according to the QuikChange protocol (Stratagene).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Binding assays
    </title>
    <p>
     Fusion proteins with N-terminal His-tag were expressed in
     <em>
      Escherichia
 coli
     </em>
     strain BL21 (DE3) (Novagen) and purified by Ni
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     -affinity
 chromatography (QIAGEN). Protein concentrations were determined by absorbance
 spectroscopy using predicted extinction coefficients (for Pc chromodomain,
 ε
     <sub>
      280
     </sub>
     = 22,190 M
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     cm
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     ; for HP1
 chromodomain, ε
     <sub>
      280
     </sub>
     = 17,780 M
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     cm
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     ).
 Peptide concentrations were determined using absorbance spectroscopy
 (extinction coefficient for tyrosine, ε
     <sub>
      280
     </sub>
     = 1280
 M
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     cm
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     ; extinction coefficient for fluorescinated
 peptides, ε
     <sub>
      492
     </sub>
     = 68,000 M
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     cm
     <sup>
      -1
     </sup>
     ).
 Fluorescence polarization binding assays were performed under conditions of 20
 mM imidazole (pH 7.0), 25 mM NaCl, and in the presence of 100 nM
 fluorescein-labeled peptide following a previously described protocol
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jacobs et al. 2001
     </xref>
     ). Data
 were obtained using a Teacan Polarion 96-well plate reader by setting it on
 automatic gain and 100 flashes. Sample plates were kept on ice until
 fluorescence reading at room temperature.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     S2 cell transfection and immunofluorescence
    </title>
    <p>
     S2 cells were grown at room temperature in Schneider's
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FBS. Cells were transfected using
 the calcium phosphate method as instructed by the manufacturer (Invitrogen).
 Expression of fusion proteins was induced by adding 250 μM CuSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     for 12 h. For immunofluorescence staining, ∼5 × 10
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
     cells
 were spun onto glass coverslips in 6-well tissue culture dishes (2000 rpm, 4
 min). Cells were fixed in solution I (1× PBS, 3.7% formaldehyde, 1%
 Triton X-100, 2% NP-40) for 10 min, washed in 1× PBST (PBS with 1%
 Triton X-100) three times for 10 min. Slides were blocked for 1 h and
 incubated with the indicated primary antibodies overnight in a humidified
 atmosphere. Dilutions for primary antibodies were anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     K9
 (1:500), anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27 (1:500, preabsorbed with
 H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K9 peptide at 5 μg/mL), anti-HP1 (1:500), anti-Pc (1:400),
 anti-Psc (1:100), and anti-V5 (1:500). Slides were washed in 1× PBST
 three times for 10 min and incubated with the appropriate secondary antibodies
 for 2 h in a humidified atmosphere. After washing in 1× PBST, DNA was
 stained with DAPI (1 μg/mL) for 10 sec. Pictures were taken on a Zeiss
 Axiopod II equipped with a 60× lens. Cells with intermediate levels of
 fusion protein expression were selected.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Polytene chromosome immunofluorescence
    </title>
    <p>
     Staining of polytene chromosomes was performed essentially as previously
 described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jin et al. 2000
     </xref>
     ).
 In brief, salivary glands from third instar larvae were dissected in 1×
 PBS, fixed in solution I for 60 sec, followed by incubation in solution II
 (50% glacial acetic acid, 3.7% formaldehyde in H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O) for 2 min.
 Slides were transferred to solution III (50% acetic acid, 16.7% lactic acid in
 H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O) for 2 min. The fixed salivary glands were squashed, frozen in
 liquid N
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , dehydrated in 95% ethanol, and washed two times in
 1× PBST, 30 min each. Immunostaining was essentially performed as
 described for S2 cells. For sequential double labeling using two polyclonal
 antibodies from rabbits, the first primary antibodies (anti-Pc, 1:400) were
 incubated with the polytene tissue at room temperature for 2 h. After washing
 (1× PBST, three times for 10 min), FITC-conjugated goat anti-rabbit
 secondary antibodies (1:200, F
     <sub>
      ab
     </sub>
     fragment) were applied at room
 temperature for 1 h. After washing (1× PBST, three times for 10 min),
 slides were blocked with the corresponding unlabeled goat anti-rabbit
 antibodies (F
     <sub>
      ab
     </sub>
     fragment at 70 μg/mL, at room temperature for 2
 h). After washing, the second primary antibodies (either
 anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K9 or anti-H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27) were applied (at room
 temperature for 2 h), followed by incubation with Cy3-conjugated goat
 anti-rabbit secondary antibodies.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Crystallization, data collection, and refinement
    </title>
    <p>
     Purified Pc chromodomain (residues 15-77) was dialyzed into 20 mM Tris-HCl
 (pH 8.0), 50 mM NaCl, and concentrated to 5 mg/mL before addition of
 H3-Me
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     K27 peptide to reach a final protein-to-peptide molar ratio
 of 1:5. Single crystals in space group
 I2
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     2
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     2
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     (
     <em>
      a
     </em>
     = 32.12,
     <em>
      b
     </em>
     =
 75.81,
     <em>
      c
     </em>
     = 80.46) were grown by the hanging drop vapor diffusion
 method at 10°C or 4°C by mixing 1.5 μL of the protein-peptide
 solution with 1.5 μL of a reservoir solution containing 0.1 M Tris-HCl (pH
 8.5), 0.2 M Li
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     SO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , and 30% polyethylene glycol 4000.
 Crystals were cryoprotected in the same solution supplemented with 25%
 ethylene glycol and flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen for data collection at the
 Advanced Photon Source Beamline SBC 19-ID. Data were processed and scaled with
 HKL2000 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Otwinowski and Minor
 1997
     </xref>
     ). Phases were solved by molecular replacement with MOLREP
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Vagin and Teplyakov 1997
     </xref>
     )
 using the HP1 chromodomain crystal structure (PDB code 1KNA) as the model.
 MOLREP produced a clear solution with a correlation coefficient of 0.31 and
 R
     <sub>
      crystal
     </sub>
     of 0.52. Rigid-body refinement of this solution using
 REFMAC5 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Murshudov et al.
 1997
     </xref>
     ) reduced the R
     <sub>
      factor
     </sub>
     to 0.42 and R
     <sub>
      free
     </sub>
     to 0.46. This model was then submitted to ARP/wARP
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Perrakis et al. 1999
     </xref>
     ) to be
 used only as a source of phases for automatic main-chain tracing and
 side-chain docking as well as refinement. ARP/wARP successfully traced
 residues 25-73 of the Pc chromodomain and 21-28 of the H3 tail, reducing the
 R
     <sub>
      crystal
     </sub>
     and R
     <sub>
      free
     </sub>
     to 0.27 and 0.36, respectively.
 Residues 23 and 24 of Pc and 20 of H3 were manually built as there was clear
 density present in a simulated annealing composite omit map calculated using
 CNS (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Brunger et al. 1998
     </xref>
     ).
 Subsequent rounds of manual rebuilding and refinement using O
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jones and Kjeldgaard 1994
     </xref>
     )
 and CNS and addition of water molecules led to the converged
 R
     <sub>
      crystal
     </sub>
     and R
     <sub>
      free
     </sub>
     values reported in
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Coordinates
    </title>
    <p>
     Atomic coordinates and structure factors have been deposited in the Protein
 Data Bank (accession code 1PDQ).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Notes
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     <strong>
      Corresponding authors.
     </strong>
    </p>
    <p>
     Article and publication are at
 http://www.genesdev.org/cgi/doi/10.1101/gad.1110503.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
