<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1097-2765(03)00112-6
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structural Basis for Bile Acid Binding and Activation of the Nuclear Receptor FXR
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Bile acids are the endogenous ligands for FXR, the nuclear receptor that transcriptionally regulates their production, movement, and absorption
    <a>
     Chawla et al. 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Goodwin and Kliewer 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lu et al. 2001
    </a>
    . As the end products of hepatic cholesterol catabolism, bile acid production is intimately linked to cholesterol homeostasis. In humans, inherited genetic defects associated with the impairment of bile acid homeostasis lead to severe cholestatic disease and vitamin absorption deficiency
    <a>
     Achord 1990
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hofmann 1999a
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hofmann 1999b
    </a>
    . Due to its role in the regulation of cholesterol and bile acid levels, FXR is a potential drug target for treatment of hyperlipidemia and cholestatic disease. To understand the mechanism of bile acid binding and activation in FXR, we solved two crystal structures of its ligand binding domain (LBD) in the presence of a GRIP-1 coactivator peptide. One structure contains the high-affinity bile acid 6α-ethyl-chenodeoxycholic acid (6ECDCA) solved at 2.5 Å resolution, and the second structure contains 3-deoxyCDCA, solved at 2.9 Å resolution
    <a>
     (Table 1)
    </a>
    . Together, these structures show how the physiological activities of bile acids are dictated by the chemical composition of their unique steroid skeleton.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Crystallographic Data and Refinement Statistics
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
           6-ethyl-CDCA
          </th>
          <th>
           3-deoxy-CDCA
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Space group
          </td>
          <td>
           P2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
           2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
           2
          </td>
          <td>
           P2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
           2
           <sub>
            1
           </sub>
           2
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Resolution (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           24.3–2.50 (2.59–2.50)
          </td>
          <td>
           15.0–2.90 (3.0–2.9)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Unit cell dimension (a, b, c) (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           99.829 107.452 69.280
          </td>
          <td>
           99.535 107.129 69.206
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Unique reflections
          </td>
          <td>
           24427
          </td>
          <td>
           12668
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Completeness (%)
          </td>
          <td>
           92.8 (77.2)
          </td>
          <td>
           98.9 (99.6)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Average redundancy
          </td>
          <td>
           4.0 (3.4)
          </td>
          <td>
           4.7 (4.8)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R
           <sub>
            sym
           </sub>
           (%)
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.4 (28.2)
          </td>
          <td>
           7.1 (45.8)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R
           <sub>
            working
           </sub>
           <a>
            <sup>
             b
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           25.1
          </td>
          <td>
           25.4
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           R
           <sub>
            free
           </sub>
           <a>
            <sup>
             c
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           28.1
          </td>
          <td>
           29.0
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rms deviation bonds (Å)
          </td>
          <td>
           0.010
          </td>
          <td>
           0.011
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rms deviation angles (deg)
          </td>
          <td>
           1.6
          </td>
          <td>
           1.9
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rms dihedral angles (deg)
          </td>
          <td>
           19.5
          </td>
          <td>
           22.3
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rms improper angles (deg)
          </td>
          <td>
           0.93
          </td>
          <td>
           1.10
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Values in parentheses are for the highest resolution shells.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         a
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          R
          <sub>
           sym
          </sub>
          = Σ|I
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          − &lt;I
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          &gt;|/ΣI
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          , where &lt;I
          <sub>
           h
          </sub>
          &gt; is the average intensity over symmetry equivalent reflections.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         b
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          R
          <sub>
           working
          </sub>
          = Σ||F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          | − |F
          <sub>
           c
          </sub>
          ||/Σ|F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          |, where F
          <sub>
           o
          </sub>
          and F
          <sub>
           c
          </sub>
          are the observed and calculated structure-factor amplitudes.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         c
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          R
          <sub>
           free
          </sub>
          was calculated using 5% of data excluded from refinement.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results and Discussion
   </title>
   <title>
    Overall Architecture of FXR
   </title>
   <p>
    The FXR protein was expressed from
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    with a N-terminal polyhistidine tag and purified as described in the Experimental Procedures. Crystals of FXR bound to 6ECDCA or 3-deoxyCDCA were obtained under the same conditions. These crystals exhibited identical crystallographic parameters and showed the same molecular arrangements of FXR
    <a>
     (Table 1)
    </a>
    . The asymmetric units contain two representations of the FXR, herein referred to as the
    <em>
     a
    </em>
    and the
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    complexes, which differed in the number of coactivator peptides bound to FXR (one peptide in the
    <em>
     a
    </em>
    complex, two peptides in the
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    complex).
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    show the overall disposition of the LBD, the ligand and coactivator peptides from the 6ECDCA crystal. The electron density maps clearly show that the A ring of the bile acid faces the C-terminal helix 12, the activation function 2 (AF2) of the receptor
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    . This orientation was unanticipated, as progesterone, estrogen, testosterone, and glucocorticoids are all oriented in the opposite direction with their D rings facing helix 12 of their respective receptors
    <a>
     Bledsoe et al. 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Brzozowski et al. 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sack et al. 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Shiau et al. 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Williams and Sigler 1998
    </a>
    . Bile acid binding directly places helix 12 against helices 3, 4, and 10
    <a>
     (Figure 1)
    </a>
    . This receptor conformation represents the “activated” state, whereby helix 12 stabilizes the binding of coactivator peptide
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Overall Views of FXR and Its Ligand Interactions(A) Perpendicular views of the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (750 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Activation Mechanism of FXR(A) 6ECDCA and 3-deoxyCDCA interactions with the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (387 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Interaction of FXR with Coactivator(A) Comparison of the a and b complexes ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (527 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Bile Acid Binding and Discrimination
   </title>
   <p>
    Bile acids are water-soluble amphipathic steroids that play important roles in cholesterol disposal and intestinal lipid absorption through micelle formation. The physiochemical properties of the bile acid skeleton are essential in this regard, displaying a convex hydrophobic face and a concave hydrophilic face. The steroid nucleus in bile acids is not flat, due to a hydrogen atom at C5 oriented in the β configuration
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    . This substituent causes the A/B ring juncture to be
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    , forcing ring A to lie outside of the plane of the BCD ring system. As a result, the separation between the 3α-OH and the C-24 carboxylate of CDCA (14 Å) is substantially shorter than the contour length of the molecule (21 Å), giving bile acids a rounded profile that allows a close fit with respect to the pocket in FXR
    <a>
     (Figures 1B and 1C)
    </a>
    .
    <a>
     Figures 1B and 1C
    </a>
    show how the shape of the FXR ligand binding pocket complements the nonplanar bile acid skeleton.
   </p>
   <p>
    The FXR ligand binding pocket also utilizes the amphipathic properties of the bile acids to provide additional molecular recognition beyond their unique shape. Bile acids contain distinct α and β faces. The β face is composed of a continuous hydrocarbon surface punctuated with the angular methyl groups at C18 and C19
    <a>
     (Figure 1C)
    </a>
    . The primary and secondary bile acids contain a common β face, and a distinct α face on which hydroxyls are displayed in the 3α, 7α, and 12α positions. The relative affinities of chenodeoxycholic acid (CDCA), deoxycholic acid (DCA), cholic acid (CA), and lithocholic acid (LCA) for FXR
    <a>
     Makishima et al. 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Parks et al. 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wang et al. 1999
    </a>
    are dictated by their specific pattern of axial hydroxyl groups at the 7 and 12 positions. The side chain oxygen of Tyr366 hydrogen bonds with the axial 7α-OH on ring B, and the lack of this hydroxyl in LCA lowers its affinity. Moreover, as the pocket does not provide any polar side chains to accommodate the 12α-OH group on ring C, the binding of CA and DCA would be energetically costly in comparison to CDCA. The FXR structure also reveals pockets that are not entirely filled by substituents found on naturally occurring bile acids
    <a>
     (Figure 1B and 1C)
    </a>
    . The semisynthetic bile acid 6ECDCA
    <a>
     (Pellicciari et al., 2002)
    </a>
    places the 6α-ethyl group into one such hydrophobic cavity that exists between the side chains of Ile359, Phe363, and Tyr 366, accounting for its higher affinity.
   </p>
   <p>
    The current structures also provide an explanation for how conjugated bile acids bind and activate FXR. Mammalian and nonmammalian bile acids are often amidated with glycine or taurine at the C24 carboxylate, and these conjugations are known to only modestly affect the binding affinity and activation efficacy
    <a>
     Makishima et al. 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Parks et al. 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wang et al. 1999
    </a>
    . The structure shows that the carboxylate oxygens of CDCA hydrogen bond with the guanidino group of Arg328 side chain located at the entry point of the pocket. The proximity of the carboxylate on the ligand to the solvent suggests that conjugated amino acids would be positioned completely out of the pocket and solvent exposed, thus not impacting receptor activation. Since amidation still preserves a carbonyl oxygen for hydrogen bonding with Arg328, the bile acid binding affinity would also remain largely unchanged.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    As a sensor of physiological levels of enterohepatic bile acids, FXR binds to its cognate ligands with ∼1000-fold weaker affinity than other steroid receptors bind to their cognate hormones, yet FXR shows remarkable specificity for bile acids
    <a>
     Makishima et al. 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Parks et al. 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wang et al. 1999
    </a>
    .
    <a>
     Figures 1B and 1C
    </a>
    show that the steroid skeleton and the ligand pocket lack a sufficient number of hydrogen bond donors and acceptors to fully account for bile acid discrimination from other steroid hormones. Instead, the FXR ligand binding pocket has evolved to recognize bile acids both using their unique nonplanar shapes and amphipathic physiochemical properties.
   </p>
   <p>
    The physical-shape discrimination mechanism employed by FXR for ligand binding precludes essentially all other steroids and cholesterol metabolites from acting on this receptor. Estrogens have an aromatic ring A and thus no possibility of
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    -
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    isomerism at carbon-5. Progesterone, aldosterone, glucocorticoids, and testosterone contain a 4-ene structure in ring A, and cholesterol contains a 5-ene in ring B, and therefore all lack the necessary 5β hydrogen required to juncture A/B rings into
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    . In addition to their differing shapes, none of these other molecules share the amphipathic and detergent-like properties uniquely associated with the α and β faces of bile acids that are both critical to their biological function and make their binding to FXR possible.
   </p>
   <title>
    π-Cation Receptor Activation Trigger
   </title>
   <p>
    All naturally occurring bile acids contain a
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    -oriented A/B ring juncture and a 3α-hydroxyl group in their A ring. The FXR structure shows the A ring and the 3-hydroxy group oriented toward helix 12 where they interact with the His444 on helix 10/11 and Trp466, the only residue from helix 12 in close proximity to the ligand
    <a>
     (Figure 2A)
    </a>
    . These two residues function as the receptor's activation trigger through formation of a desolvated π-cation interaction directly contacted and stabilized by the bile acid
    <a>
     (Figure 2A)
    </a>
    . The bile acid A ring also contacts Tyr358, which further restricts the position of His444. The π-cation interaction between the indole ring of a Trp (π electron system) and the Nε (cation) on a perpendicularly oriented His side chain has been described in other biological systems but never observed as a molecular switch for receptor activation
    <a>
     (Ma and Dougherty, 1997)
    </a>
    . We infer that in the absence of ligand, the same His-Trp interaction cannot be stabilized due to insufficient physical constraints on these residues. The loss of their interaction would remove the necessary support for helix 12 in its active position.
   </p>
   <p>
    The 3α hydroxyl on ring A is the most polar functionality on the steroid nucleus due to its equatorial position with respect to the hydrocarbon ring system
    <a>
     (Figure 1C)
    </a>
    . To gauge the relative contributions to receptor activation from the 3-OH group versus the ring A surface, we studied 3-deoxyCDCA in biochemical assays and by X-ray crystallography. We found that the 3-deoxyCDCA is able to recruit the region-3 LXXLL motif of GRIP-1 with an EC
    <sub>
     50
    </sub>
    of 3 μM, in comparison to CDCA which shows an EC
    <sub>
     50
    </sub>
    of 16 μM (see
    <a>
     Figure 2B
    </a>
    ). The small increase in potency is likely due to the decreased hydrophilicity of 3-deoxyCDCA, which aids desolvation of the ligand. These results suggested that the 3-hydroxyl alone is not responsible for activation of the receptor. To directly visualize how the 3-deoxy bile acid activates FXR, we solved the crystal structure of its complex and examined the ligand with respect to the activation trigger
    <a>
     (Figure 2A)
    </a>
    . We found that ring A of the 3-deoxyCDCA still contacts and orients His444 and Trp466, allowing the same π-cation interaction as in the 6ECDCA complex. A hydrogen bond to the side chain nitrogen on His444, no longer available from the 3-OH of ring A, is instead donated by the side chain OH group of Tyr358. Overall, the structure shows helix 12 in the identical activated conformation seen in the 6ECDCA structure and still supporting the association of coactivator peptide. Therefore, a correctly positioned ring A is the dominant factor mediating the agonist function of bile acids.
   </p>
   <p>
    A sequence alignment shows that the amino acids responsible for the binding of the sex steroids, glucocorticoids, and mineralocorticoids are more closely conserved between their receptors than with FXR
    <a>
     (Figure 4)
    </a>
    . Nevertheless, all of these receptors form their ligand binding pockets largely via determinants located on helices 3, 5, 7, 10/11, and 12. Importantly, every residue responsible for the binding of rat FXR to bile acids is identical in the human FXR protein
    <a>
     (Figure 4)
    </a>
    . However, mouse FXRβ, which is a pseudogene in humans, contains several differences at these residue positions but also appears to use lanosterol as its endogenous ligand
    <a>
     (Otte et al., 2003)
    </a>
    . As the π-cation activation trigger had not been previously seen in other steroid receptors, we compared sequences in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    to look for the conservation of this pair of His and Trp residues. Besides the FXR proteins, LXRα and LXRβ receptors are the only other receptors with identically positioned His and Trp residues
    <a>
     (Figure 4)
    </a>
    . As LXRα and LXRβ bind to oxysterols and regulate genes that are also related to cholesterol and bile acid homeostasis
    <a>
     Lu et al. 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Peet et al. 1998
    </a>
    , these receptors may be activated via a similar π-cation molecular switch.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Sequences Used for Ligand Binding by the Steroid ReceptorsYellow shading shows ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1097276503001126-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1519 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Coactivator Interactions
   </title>
   <p>
    The GRIP-1 coactivator contains three separate nuclear receptor interaction domains (NIDs), each consisting of a LXXLL motif
    <a>
     Darimont et al. 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Xu et al. 1999
    </a>
    . Synthetic peptides corresponding to NID-1, NID-2, and NID-3 regions bind to bile acid-activated FXR weakly, with NID-1 binding with K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    &gt; 500 μM, NID-2 binding with K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    of ∼160 μM, and NID-3 binding with K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    of ∼330 μM
    <a>
     (Figure 3B)
    </a>
    . The coactivator peptide in the structures is NID-3, with the sequence KENAL
    <strong>
     L
    </strong>
    RY
    <strong>
     LL
    </strong>
    DKD. Both
    <em>
     a
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    complexes show a peptide binding in the primary activator groove as described for other receptors
    <a>
     (Figure 3A)
    </a>
    <a>
     Bledsoe et al. 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Brzozowski et al. 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Darimont et al. 1998
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Gampe et al. 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nolte et al. 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Shiau et al. 1998
    </a>
    . However, the
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    complexes of both the 6ECDCA and 3-deoxyCDCA structures show a second copy of NID-3 bound adjacent to the primary coactivator peptide
    <a>
     (Figure 3A)
    </a>
    . This arrangement allows the two antiparallel NIDs to form cross interactions via their hydrophobic side chains in a manner that requires the agonist conformation of helix 12. The inability of the second peptide to occupy its site in complex
    <em>
     a
    </em>
    appears to be caused by the lack of the necessary access arising from a crystal packing effect involving a symmetry related subunit.
    <a>
     Figure 3B
    </a>
    shows the electron density maps for both peptides in complex
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    , and
    <a>
     Figure 3C
    </a>
    shows a schematic drawing of these peptide-peptide and peptide-FXR contacts.
   </p>
   <p>
    Within the NID-3 LXXLL motif, Arg3 and Tyr4 (occupying the XX positions) are not conserved among the coactivator NIDs and are solvent exposed in the complexes described here
    <a>
     (Figure 3A)
    </a>
    . By contrast, Leu2 and Leu6, which are highly conserved in coactivator NIDS, are responsible for forming the peptides' contacts to FXR
    <a>
     (Figure 3C)
    </a>
    . Leu5 forms the peptide-peptide interactions with Leu1 in the
    <em>
     b
    </em>
    complexes
    <a>
     (Figures 3A and 3C)
    </a>
    . Through the two sets of Leu5/Leu1 interactions, the binding of one peptide enhances the binding of the second peptide by providing a more favorable interaction site. These peptide-peptide interactions would suggest that two NIDs contained within the same polypeptide should bind to FXR with significantly higher affinity, due to the constraints on their physical freedom.
   </p>
   <p>
    <a>
     Figure 3B
    </a>
    shows that an extended GRIP-1 region (NID [1-3]) that contains more than one NID motif does in fact bind to the FXR more with 100 times greater strength (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    0.8 μM) than any of its isolated NID elements. This higher affinity is consistent with two NIDs in the same coactivator binding cooperatively to a single FXR-LBD subunit. However, another interpretation could be that the larger coactivator fragment is providing the energy for the dimerization of two FXR subunits. The crystal structure of PPARγ in combination with an extended coactivator fragment
    <a>
     (Nolte et al.,1998)
    </a>
    shows the coactivator forming a bridge across the dimer interface of two LBDs. Therefore, we tested for the subunit dimerization of FXR-LBDs in the absence and presence of the NID (1-3) fragment
    <a>
     (Figure 3E)
    </a>
    . Using gel filtration chromatography, we find that the FXR-LBD is monomeric in solution and that the addition of GRIP-1 NID (1-3) results in a complex consistent in size with a single subunit of FXR-LBD bound to a single NID (1-3) polypeptide. These results, together with the binding data in
    <a>
     Figure 3D
    </a>
    and the direct crystallographic observations shown in
    <a>
     Figures 3A and 3B
    </a>
    , are all consistent with a p160 coactivator forming its high-affinity interactions with an FXR-LBD by providing two LXXLL surfaces for the interaction.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Summary and Conclusions
   </title>
   <p>
    The current structural study demonstrates a series of unanticipated findings associated with bile acid binding and activation of FXR. The bile acids are discerned from other steroids by their unusual physical shape and amphipathic properties. Bile acids occupy their pocket with their steroid nucleus positioned in the reverse orientation of all other steroids. This arrangement allows the distinctive
    <em>
     cis
    </em>
    -oriented ring A to impart the activated state to FXR by directly contacting a π-cation molecular switch deep in the pocket. The 3-OH group, which is conserved in all common bile acids, is not necessary for FXR activation. FXR is able to interact with a LXXLL motif that occupies the primary coactivator site, as well as a second motif that requires the agonist conformation of the receptor and further enhances the binding affinity of coactivator. Importantly, none of these features of FXR could have been predicted from structural studies thus far reported for other nuclear receptors.
   </p>
   <p>
    Therapeutic bile acid supplementation has been a mainstay of Eastern medicine for centuries
    <a>
     (Achord, 1990)
    </a>
    . More recently the bile acid UDCA has been used to treat cholestasis by displacement of more toxic bile acids from the enterohepatic pool
    <a>
     (Hofmann, 1999b)
    </a>
    . However, UDCA is FXR silent and as such does not block de novo bile acid synthesis and has limited clinical efficacy. With the availability of these FXR structures, the potential exists to design new therapeutic bile acids with a modified balance of physiochemical and biological properties for treatment of cholestasis. In addition, the insights onto the molecular details of receptor activation should guide the development of nonsteroidal FXR modulators to impact hepatic cholesterol homeostasis, dietary cholesterol absorption, and serum triglycerides levels.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Crystallization and Structure Determination
   </title>
   <p>
    The ligand binding domain of rat FXR was subcloned into Nde1-BamH1 sites of pET16b vector (Novagen) and expressed with an N-terminal his-tag in BL21-DE3
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    . The cells were grown overnight in the presence of 0.5 mM IPTG. These cells were pelleted and frozen for long-term storage. For protein purification, the cells were thawed and sonicated in lysis buffer (400 mM NaCl, 10 mM imidazole, 10% glycerol, 20 mM Tris [pH 8.0]). The protein was purified using conventional Ni-NTA chromatography followed by loading on a 100 cm Superdex G200 column (Pharmacia). Ligand was added, and the protein concentration brought to 4–5 mg/ml by ultrafiltration followed by the addition of coactivator peptide. Crystals were grown in hanging drops by using polyethylene glycol as the precipitant, together with ethylene glycol (for cryoprotection) and 0.1M PIPES (pH 6.4). Crystals were flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, and the diffraction data were collected at beamline APS BM-19 in Argonne National Laboratory. Diffraction data were scaled and reduced with HKL2000
    <a>
     (Otwinowski and Minor, 1997)
    </a>
    . The structure of the 6ECDCA complex was solved using the molecular replacement with MOLREP
    <a>
     (Vagin and Teplyakov, 1997)
    </a>
    . The search model consisted of the RAR LBD (PDB 1lbd) that was altered to remove most of the unconserved loops. The 3-deoxyCDCA structure was subsequently solved with molecular replacement using the refined 6ECDCA coordinates for the search model. Difference (Fo-Fc) maps calculated using phases derived from the 6ECDCA structure, but structure factors from the 3deoxyCDCA data clearly showed strong negative peaks corresponding to the 3-OH and 6-ethyl positions of the 3-deoxyCDCA, consistent with the differences in these ligands. Both structures were refined with multiple rounds of refinement with CNS
    <a>
     (Brunger et al., 1998)
    </a>
    followed by manual rebuilding.
   </p>
   <title>
    Coactivator Binding Assays
   </title>
   <p>
    The binding of coactivator peptides to FXR was measured using a fluorescence anisotropy-based assay with a Beacon 2000 (PanVera) system. Synthetic peptides were made at the University of Virginia Biomolecular Research Facility, corresponding to sequences shown in the
    <a>
     Figure 3B
    </a>
    legend. These peptides, as well as
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    -expressed GRIP-1 NID (1-3) protein (sequence 563–767 of GRIP-1/SCR-2), were N-terminal fluorescein-labeled using previously described methods
    <a>
     (Jacobs et al., 2001)
    </a>
    . To measure the K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    values for FXR-coactivator binding, the fluorescence anisotropy values of the peptides (50 nM concentrations) were measured in the presence of 2.5 mM bile acid concentrations and increasing FXR protein concentration. To determine EC
    <sub>
     50
    </sub>
    values, the fluorescence anisotropy values of peptide (50 nM) were measured in the presence of FXR (0.1 mM) and increasing ligand concentrations. Data were fitted using the equation A = [A
    <sub>
     f
    </sub>
    − (A
    <sub>
     b
    </sub>
    − A
    <sub>
     f
    </sub>
    )][protein]/(K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    + [protein]), where A
    <sub>
     f
    </sub>
    and A
    <sub>
     b
    </sub>
    are the anisotropy values of the free and bound peptides, respectively.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The Protein Data Bank code for the structure reported in this paper is 1OSV.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Achord 1990
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.L. Achord
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Is oriental folk use of bear bile vindicated (yet)?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gastroenterology, 98 (1990), pp. 1090–1091
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bledsoe et al. 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.K. Bledsoe, V.G. Montana, T.B. Stanley, C.J. Delves, C.J. Apolito, D.D. McKee, T.G. Consler, D.J. Parks, E.L. Stewart, T.M. Willson,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structure of the glucocorticoid receptor ligand binding domain reveals a novel mode of receptor dimerization and coactivator recognition
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 110 (2002), pp. 93–105
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brunger et al. 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.T. Brunger, P.D. Adams, G.M. Clore, W.L. DeLano, P. Gros, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve, J.S. Jiang, J. Kuszewski, M. Nilges, N.S. Pannu,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystallography &amp; NMR system: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 54 (1998), pp. 905–921
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brzozowski et al. 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.M. Brzozowski, A.C. Pike, Z. Dauter, R.E. Hubbard, T. Bonn, O. Engstrom, L. Ohman, G.L. Greene, J.A. Gustafsson, M. Carlquist
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Molecular basis of agonism and antagonism in the oestrogen receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 389 (1997), pp. 753–758
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chawla et al. 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Chawla, J.J. Repa, R.M. Evans, D.J. Mangelsdorf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nuclear receptors and lipid physiology: opening the X-files
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 294 (2001), pp. 1866–1870
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Darimont et al. 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.D. Darimont, R.L. Wagner, J.W. Apriletti, M.R. Stallcup, P.J. Kushner, J.D. Baxter, R.J. Fletterick, K.R. Yamamoto
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure and specificity of nuclear receptor-coactivator interactions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 12 (1998), pp. 3343–3356
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gampe et al. 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.T. Gampe Jr., V.G. Montana, M.H. Lambert, A.B. Miller, R.K. Bledsoe, M.V. Milburn, S.A. Kliewer, T.M. Willson, H.E. Xu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Asymmetry in the PPARγ/RXRα crystal structure reveals the molecular basis of heterodimerization among nuclear receptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 5 (2000), pp. 545–555
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goodwin and Kliewer 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Goodwin, S.A. Kliewer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nuclear receptors. I. Nuclear receptors and bile acid homeostasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Am. J. Physiol. Gastrointest. Liver Physiol, 282 (2002), pp. G926–G931
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hofmann 1999a
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.F. Hofmann
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bile acids: the good, the bad, and the ugly
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         News Physiol. Sci., 14 (1999), pp. 24–29 a
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hofmann 1999b
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.F. Hofmann
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The continuing importance of bile acids in liver and intestinal disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Arch. Intern. Med., 159 (1999), pp. 2647–2658 b
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Jacobs et al. 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.A. Jacobs, S.D. Taverna, Y. Zhang, S.D. Briggs, J. Li, J.C. Eissenberg, C.D. Allis, S. Khorasanizadeh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Specificity of the HP1 chromo domain for the methylated N-terminus of histone H3
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 20 (2001), pp. 5232–5241
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lu et al. 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.T. Lu, J.J. Repa, D.J. Mangelsdorf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Orphan nuclear receptors as eLiXiRs and FiXeRs of sterol metabolism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 37735–37738
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ma and Dougherty 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.C. Ma, D.A. Dougherty
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The cation-π interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Chem. Rev., 97 (1997), pp. 1303–1324
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Makishima et al. 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Makishima, A.Y. Okamoto, J.J. Repa, H. Tu, R.M. Learned, A. Luk, M.V. Hull, K.D. Lustig, D.J. Mangelsdorf, B. Shan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of a nuclear receptor for bile acids
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 284 (1999), pp. 1362–1365
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nolte et al. 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.T. Nolte, G.B. Wisely, S. Westin, J.E. Cobb, M.H. Lambert, R. Kurokawa, M.G. Rosenfeld, T.M. Wilson, C.K. Glass, M.V. Milburn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ligand binding and co-activator assembly of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 395 (1998), pp. 137–143
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Otte et al. 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Otte, H. Kranz, I. Kober, P. Thompson, M. Hoefer, B. Haubold, B. Remmel, H. Voss, C. Kaiser, M. Albers,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of farnesoid x receptor beta as a novel mammalian nuclear receptor sensing lanosterol
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 23 (2003), pp. 864–872
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Otwinowski and Minor 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Otwinowski, W. Minor
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Methods Enzymol., 276 (1997), pp. 307–326
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Parks et al. 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.J. Parks, S.G. Blanchard, R.K. Bledsoe, G. Chandra, T.G. Consler, S.A. Kliewer, J.B. Stimmel, T.M. Willson, A.M. Zavacki, D.D. Moore, J.M. Lehmann
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bile acids: natural ligands for an orphan nuclear receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 284 (1999), pp. 1365–1368
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Peet et al. 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.J. Peet, B.A. Janowski, D.J. Mangelsdorf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The LXRs: a new class of oxysterol receptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev., 8 (1998), pp. 571–575
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pellicciari et al. 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Pellicciari, S. Fiorucci, E. Camaioni, C. Clerici, G. Costantino, P.R. Maloney, A. Morelli, D.J. Parks, T.M. Willson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         6alpha-ethyl-chenodeoxycholic acid (6-ECDCA), a potent and selective FXR agonist endowed with anticholestatic activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Med. Chem., 45 (2002), pp. 3569–3572
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rochel et al. 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Rochel, J.M. Wurtz, A. Mitschler, B. Klaholz, D. Moras
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The crystal structure of the nuclear receptor for vitamin D bound to its natural ligand
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 5 (2000), pp. 173–179
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sack et al. 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.S. Sack, K.F. Kish, C. Wang, R.M. Attar, S.E. Kiefer, Y. An, G.Y. Wu, J.E. Scheffler, M.E. Salvati, S.R. Krystek Jr.,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystallographic structures of the ligand-binding domains of the androgen receptor and its T877A mutant complexed with the natural agonist dihydrotestosterone
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 98 (2001), pp. 4904–4909
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shiau et al. 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.K. Shiau, D. Barstad, P.M. Loria, L. Cheng, P.J. Kushner, D.A. Agard, G.L. Greene
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The structural basis of estrogen receptor/coactivator recognition and the antagonism of this interaction by tamoxifen
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 95 (1998), pp. 927–937
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vagin and Teplyakov 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Vagin, A. Teplyakov
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Molrep: an automated program for molecular replacement
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Crystallogr., 30 (1997), pp. 1022–1025
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang et al. 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Wang, J. Chen, K. Hollister, L.C. Sowers, B.M. Forman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Endogenous bile acids are ligands for the nuclear receptor FXR/BAR
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 3 (1999), pp. 543–553
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Williams and Sigler 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.P. Williams, P.B. Sigler
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Atomic structure of progesterone complexed with its receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 393 (1998), pp. 392–396
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Xu et al. 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Xu, C.K. Glass, M.G. Rosenfeld
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Coactivator and corepressor complexes in nuclear receptor function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev., 9 (1999), pp. 140–147
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2003 Cell Press.  All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>