<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.04.033
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Inhibition of Basal FGF Receptor Signaling by Dimeric Grb2
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Members of the fibroblast growth factor receptor (FGFR) family of receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) are key regulators of many cellular processes, including proliferation, cell-cycle control, migration, and differentiation (
    <a>
     Turner and Grose, 2010
    </a>
    ). Aberrances in enzymatic activity of these receptors causes a variety of human cancers and developmental defects (
    <a>
     Robertson et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pollock et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Beenken and Mohammadi, 2009
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wesche et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). FGFRs are composed of an extracellular region that consists of two or three immunoglobulin (Ig)-like domains, a transmembrane region, and an intracellular region that includes a tyrosine kinase domain and flanking regulatory polypeptide sequences. FGFR signaling is initiated by the binding of extracellular growth factors that are conjugated to cell surface heparin sulfate proteoglycans (HSPGs). On engaging the growth factor, the receptor dimerizes, resulting in upregulation of intrinsic kinase activity and subsequent autophosphorylation of specific tyrosine residues in the C termini. This provides sites for recruitment of proteins and activation of downstream signaling pathways such as the mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase pathway. The relationship between phosphorylation and signal transduction is not, however, quite that simple. Phosphorylation of FGFR2 prior to extracellular stimulation in numerous cell lines, even under conditions of serum starvation, has been widely observed (
    <a>
     Mansukhani et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Takeda et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kunii et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Bryant et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ahmed et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Importantly this “background” level of phosphorylation experienced by the receptor is insufficient to activate a downstream response until growth factor stimulation occurs. Therefore, rather than being in a nonphosphorylated “ground state,” the receptor is, in effect, being held in a nonsignaling, phosphorylated state primed for upregulation and full activity. To ensure that this primed state is incapable of effecting aberrant signals, a strict negative control mechanism is required to prohibit full activation until FGFR2 is exposed to growth factor.
   </p>
   <p>
    Numerous alternative gene splicing events dictate structural variants and, hence, function of FGFR2. Splicing of sequences encoding the C terminus provides a major group of FGFR2 isoforms. Variants that result in deletions of the C-terminal sequence show enhanced transforming activity (
    <a>
     Cha et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). These variants are expressed in increased amounts in gastric cancer cell lines (
    <a>
     Itoh et al., 1994
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ishii et al., 1995
    </a>
    ) and in a majority of human breast carcinoma cells (
    <a>
     Cha et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). Recently, point mutations in the C-terminal region of FGFR2 have also been linked with melanoma (
    <a>
     Gartside et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). This suggests an important role for the C terminus of FGFR2 in control of receptor activity.
   </p>
   <p>
    It was recently reported that the C-SH3 domain of growth factor receptor-bound protein 2 (Grb2) binds to a proline-rich sequence at the very C terminus of FGFR2 prior to growth factor stimulation. Deletion of the last 10 residues of the receptor abrogated Grb2 binding and concomitantly downregulated the phosphorylation of FGFR2 in the basal state (
    <a>
     Ahmed et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, basal phosphorylation is also compromised in cells expressing the oncogenic S252W mutation in FGFR2, which is unable to bind Grb2. Therefore, Grb2 is strongly implicated in controlling FGFR2 kinase activity prior to growth factor stimulation.
   </p>
   <p>
    Grb2 is ubiquitously expressed and plays a role in several signaling pathways from RTKs. As an adaptor protein, it is generally thought to play a passive role in signal transduction, possessing no enzymatic activity of its own. It largely consists of an SH2 domain sequentially sandwiched between N- and C-terminal SH3 domains. The SH2 domain binds phosphorylated tyrosine residues on RTKs and their auxiliary docking proteins, whereas the SH3 domains recognize proline-rich sites on numerous proteins, including the guanine nucleotide exchange factor son-of-sevenless (Sos) upstream of the MAPK pathway (
    <a>
     Li et al., 1993
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rozakis-Adcock et al., 1993
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Here we describe a mechanism whereby Grb2 exerts control of FGFR2 kinase activity prior to growth factor binding. Dimeric Grb2 recruits two receptor molecules and promotes phosphorylation of FGFR2 in the absence of extracellular stimulus. Binding of Grb2 to the C terminus of FGFR2 regulates the activation of a downstream signaling response. We demonstrate that Grb2 is a novel target for FGFR2 and show that, on stimulation by FGF, the kinase activity of the receptor is upregulated, promoting the phosphorylation of Grb2 and its concomitant release from the receptor. This leaves FGFR2 free to effect downstream signaling.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>