<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.057
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Interaction of Circadian Clock Proteins CRY1 and PER2 Is Modulated by Zinc Binding and Disulfide Bond Formation
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    In mammals, many physiological, metabolic, and behavioral processes are regulated in a daytime-dependent manner. Circadian (∼24 hr) rhythms are generated by endogenous circadian clocks, which are operated by interconnected transcriptional and translational feedback loops (
    <a>
     Young and Kay, 2001
    </a>
    ). Additionally, the cellular redox state plays an essential role in circadian clock regulation and links the clock to the cell's metabolic state (
    <a>
     Eckel-Mahan and Sassone-Corsi, 2009
    </a>
    ). In anucleate human red blood cells, several circadian oxidation rhythms have been described, including cysteine oxidation cycles in the H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    scavenging peroxiredoxins, the daily rhythmic transition between dimeric (mostly oxidized) and tetrameric (mostly reduced) hemoglobin, and daily nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH)/nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) oscillations (
    <a>
     O’Neill and Reddy, 2011
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, circadian cycles of peroxiredoxin oxidation occur in all kingdoms of life and are interconnected with the circadian gene-regulatory transcriptional feedback loops in DNA-containing cells (
    <a>
     Edgar et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     O’Neill and Reddy, 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     O’Neill et al., 2011
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In the canonical gene-regulatory feedback loop of the mammalian circadian clock, the basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH)-PAS (PER-ARNT-SIM) transcription factors BMAL1 and CLOCK activate the transcription of three period (
    <em>
     Per1
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     2
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     3
    </em>
    ) and two cryptochrome (
    <em>
     Cry1
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     2
    </em>
    ) clock genes. CRY proteins repress the transcriptional activity of the CLOCK/BMAL1 complex toward the
    <em>
     Cry
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     Per
    </em>
    genes (
    <a>
     Griffin et al., 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kume et al., 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     van der Horst et al., 1999
    </a>
    ), as well as a large number of clock-controlled genes regulating circadian physiology (
    <a>
     Koike et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). Additionally, CRYs are involved in the regulation of glucose homeostasis, insulin secretion, and tissue-specific insulin sensitivity (
    <a>
     Barclay et al., 2013
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lamia et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The CRY repressor activity is determined by posttranslational modifications, as well as the daily rhythmic synthesis, nuclear translocation, and degradation of CRYs, which are controlled by interactions with PER1/2 (
    <a>
     Yagita et al., 2002
    </a>
    ) and with the E3 ligase components FBXL3 (
    <a>
     Gatfield and Schibler, 2007
    </a>
    ) and FBXL21 (
    <a>
     Hirano et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yoo et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). The CRY tails and the most C-terminal helix (α22) of the cryptochrome photolyase homology region (PHR) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A) are involved in transcriptional repression of CLOCK/BMAL1 (
    <a>
     Chaves et al., 2006
    </a>
    ) and BMAL1 binding (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). The PHR interacts with C-terminal regions of PER1 and PER2 (
    <a>
     Eide et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Miyazaki et al., 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Ozber et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Tomita et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yagita et al., 2002
    </a>
    ), with FBXL3 (
    <a>
     Lamia et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), FBXL21 (
    <a>
     Hirano et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yoo et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) and with the PAS domains of CLOCK (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Domain Architecture and Crystal Structure of mCRY1/mPER2 Heterodimer(A) Domain ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1048 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Phosphorylation of Ser71 by AMP kinase (AMPK) in response to the cell’s metabolic state reduces CRY1 stability by enhancing FBXL3 binding and weakening PER2 binding (
    <a>
     Lamia et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, PER2 is reported to compete for CRY1 binding to the CLOCK/BMAL1-E-box complex (
    <a>
     Ye et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). These data suggest that PER2 might have overlapping CRY1-binding sites with FBXL3 and CLOCK/BMAL1, which play a role in the regulation of CRY1 stability and transcriptional repression activity. Indeed, our mouse CRY1 (mCRY1) crystal structure revealed partly overlapping mCRY1 regions that are involved in mPER2 and FBXL3 interactions, as well as transcriptional repression activities of mCRY1 (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Consistent with our structure-based mutational analyses (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), the mCRY2/FBXL3/SKP1 complex structure (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) showed that FBXL3 interacts with the flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD)-binding pocket, the C-terminal helix α22, and the C-terminal lid of the mCRY-PHR. Moreover, competition with mPER2 or FAD disrupts a preformed mCRY2/FBXL3 complex (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), and a period-lengthening small-molecule compound that competes with FAD binding stabilizes mCRY1 by inhibiting ubiquitination (
    <a>
     Hirota et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Here, we have determined the crystal structure of the complex between the mCRY1-PHR and a C-terminal mPER2 fragment in order to (1) provide further insights into how alternative binding of mPER2, FBXL3, mCLOCK/BMAL1, or FAD regulates mCRY1 stability and transcriptional repression activity and (2) to advance the development of CRY-stabilizing compounds that affect clock or clock-controlled metabolic functions. mPER2 winds around mCRY1, covering extensive surface areas that significantly overlap with the binding sites of FBXL3 and mCLOCK/BMAL1. Interestingly, our complex structure revealed a jointly coordinated zinc ion that critically stabilizes full-length mCRY1-mPER2 interactions in mammalian cells. Our mutational analyses suggest that (1) formation of the Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bond, which we observed in the apo-mCRY1 structure (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), weakens mCRY1-mPER2 interactions, and (2) zinc facilitates formation of the reduced state of mCRY1 and stabilizes the mCRY1/mPER2 complex. The regulation of mCRY1-mPER2 interactions by zinc binding and CRY disulfide bond formation/reduction may provide a molecular link between the circadian clock and the cell’s metabolic/oxidative state.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Crystal Structure of the Mouse CRYPTOCHROME1-PERIOD2 Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    Using limited proteolysis, we identified a stable mCRY1/mPER2 core complex comprising the mCRY1-PHR (residues 1 to 496) and mPER2 residues 1132 to 1252 (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    , and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    available online). We have determined its 2.45 Å crystal structure using molecular replacement with apo-mCRY1 (PDB ID 4K0R [
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ]) as search model in combination with experimental selenium single-wavelength anomalous dispersion (Se-SAD) phasing (
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="mCRY1/mPER2 Interactions and Sequence Alignments of mPER2, Related to Figures 1, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S1.
        <p>
         mCRY1/mPER2 Interactions and Sequence Alignments of mPER2, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 1
         </a>
         ,
         <a>
          2
         </a>
         ,
         <a>
          5
         </a>
         , and
         <a>
          7
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         (A) Schematic representation of mCRY1/mPER2 interface contacts.
         <em>
          C-terminal helix (α22) interface
         </em>
         : Central Interactions of Arg483, Lys485, Gln486, Gln490 (mCRY1 α22) and Asp321 (mCRY1 sulfur loop) are described in the main text. Asp321 also makes hydrophilic interactions to Arg1158 of mPER2. Additional hydrophobic interactions are established between Tyr488 (mCRY1 α22) and mPER2 residues Trp1195, Pro1202, Ile1205 and between Leu479 (α22) and mPER2 residues Leu1160, Val1163 and Leu1164. Pro319 (mCRY1 sulfur loop) packs into a hydrophobic pocket, which is lined by Ile487 (mCRY1 α22) as well as Lys1170, Leu1171 and Leu1174 of mPER2 α3.
         <em>
          Zinc interface
         </em>
         : Interactions are described in the main text.
         <em>
          mPER2(α4)-cap interface
         </em>
         : Phe405 of the mCRY1 C-terminal lid is embedded in a hydrophobic pocket composed of Pro1179, Phe1181, Leu1189, Trp1195 of mPER2 and Leu148, Val316, Phe409, Tyr488 and Leu491 of mCRY1. Additionally, His1193
         <sub>
          mPER2
         </sub>
         hydrogen bonds to the backbone of Phe405 and Gln407. Leu148 (mCRY1 α5-α6 connector loop) makes hydrophobic interactions with Leu1189 and Phe1181 of mPER2. The side chain of Thr149 forms a direct hydrogen bond to Glu1188 and a water mediated hydrogen bond to Glu1191 of mPER2 α4. The backbones of Thr149 and Leu148 hydrogen bond to the Glu1188 side chain.
         <em>
          mPER2(α1-2)-mCRY1(α12) interface
         </em>
         : The backbones of Tyr466 to Met470 in the loop preceding mCRY1 α22 as well as Lys329 and Asn323 (mCRY1 α12) are critical for positioning of mPER2 α2. Lys329 forms direct or water mediated hydrogen bonds to backbone oxygens of Ile1149 to Tyr1153 (mPER2 α2), while Asn323 forms a hydrogen bond to the Tyr1153 side chain. Ala328 is positioned opposite Thr1145 and Ala1143 in the loop connecting mPER2 helices α1 and α2. Trp1139 (mPER2 α1) hydrogen bonds to Glu383 (mCRY1 α15) and inserts into a hydrophobic cave, which is lined by Leu327, Ala328, Ala331 (α12) and Lys379, Val380 (α15) of mCRY1.
        </p>
        <p>
         (B) Secondary structure assignment of mouse PER2 (mPER2) and alignment of its orthologs from
         <em>
          Homo sapiens
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          gallus gallus
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          Xenopus laevis
         </em>
         and
         <em>
          danio rerio
         </em>
         . Conserved residues are colored in dark yellow. Blue dots indicate mCRY1 interacting residues. Zinc coordinating residues are highlighted with brown boxes. Residues that were mutated for further analysis of the mCRY1/mPER2 interaction are labeled with black letters (Asp1167, Phe1181, His1193, Cys1210, Cys1213).
        </p>
        <p>
         (C) Alignment of mPER2 and its homologs mPER1 and mPER3. The zinc coordinating residues Cys1210 and Cys1213 are conserved in mPER1 and mPER3. The alignments in
         <a>
          Figures S1
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          S2
         </a>
         were generated in ClustalOmega (
         <a>
          Goujon et al., 2010
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          Sievers et al., 2011
         </a>
         ) and modified in Jalview (
         <a>
          Waterhouse et al., 2009
         </a>
         ).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1350 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Sequence Alignment and Structural Elements of mCRY1, Related to Figures 1, 2, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S2.
        <p>
         Sequence Alignment and Structural Elements of mCRY1, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 1
         </a>
         ,
         <a>
          2
         </a>
         , and
         <a>
          7
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         Secondary structure assignment of mouse CRY1 (mCRY1) and alignment of its homolog mouse CRY2 (mCRY2) and its orthologs from
         <em>
          Homo sapiens
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          gallus gallus
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          Xenopus laevis
         </em>
         and
         <em>
          danio rerio
         </em>
         . Conserved residues are colored in dark cyan. Green dots indicate mPER2 interacting residues. Zinc coordinating residues are highlighted with brown boxes. Residues that were mutated for further analysis of the mCRY1/mPER2 interaction are labeled with black letters (Thr149, Pro319, Ala328, Lys329, Cys363, Cys412, Cys414, His473, Lys485, Gln486).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1978 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In our mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure, mCRY1 adopts the typical cryptochrome/photolyase fold (
    <a>
     Müller and Carell, 2009
    </a>
    ) with an N-terminal α/β domain, a C-terminal α-helical domain, and a connecting linker region (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    ). Superposition of apo-mCRY1 and mCRY1/mPER2 reveals several differences between the two mCRY1 structures, especially in the C-terminal lid, which significantly alters its conformation (see below), the antenna recognition loop, the phosphate-binding loop, the linker region, and the C-terminal helix α22 (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    A–S3D). The other characteristic loops of the 6-4-photolyase/animal cryptochrome family, i.e., the protrusion loop, the α5-α6 loop, and the electron-rich sulfur loop (
    <a>
     Hitomi et al., 2009
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    ) do not change significantly upon mPER2 binding.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Comparison of mPER2-Bound mCRY1 Structure with apo-CRY1, mCRY2, and dCRY, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S3.
        <p>
         Comparison of mPER2-Bound mCRY1 Structure with apo-CRY1, mCRY2, and dCRY, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 2
         </a>
         ,
         <a>
          3
         </a>
         , and
         <a>
          4
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         (A) Ribbon presentation of superposed apo-mCRY1-PHR (gray) and mCRY1-PHR (cyan) from the mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure (rmsd = 0.886 Å for 457 CRY Cα positions). The antenna recognition loop (residues 39-46) as well as residues 167-177 in the linker region are unordered in the apo-mCRY1 structure, but well defined in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex. The C-terminal lid (Cys402 to Pro415) alters its conformation and the phosphate binding loop is less defined in the mPER2-complex structure. No significant changes are observed in the protrusion loop, the α5-α6 connector loop and the electron-rich sulfur loop.
        </p>
        <p>
         (B) Superposition of the antenna recognition loop in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex (cyan/yellow) with (left) apo-mCRY1 (gray; pdb 4K0R [
         <a>
          Czarna et al., 2013
         </a>
         ]) and dCRY (magenta; pdb 4JZY [
         <a>
          Czarna et al., 2013
         </a>
         ]; rmsd = 1.427 Å for 439 CRY Cα positions) and with (right) apo-mCRY2 (green, pdb 4I6E [
         <a>
          Xing et al., 2013
         </a>
         ]). The ordered antenna recognition loop of the mCRY1/mPER2 complex reaches into the antenna chromophore binding pocket (cbp), but in a different position than the dCRY antenna recognition loop. mPER2 strands β0 and β1 are located nearby and may therefore influence the conformation of the antenna loop. Potentially, the coordination of a chloride ion (Cl
         <sup>
          −
         </sup>
         ) by Ser102, which is located in the vicinity of the antenna chromophore binding pocket and which is a predicted phosphorylation site of mCRY1 (
         <a>
          Lamia et al., 2009
         </a>
         ), affects the antenna recognition loop conformation in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex. Furthermore, a PEG molecule from the crystallization solution is located in the vicinity of the cbp (not shown). In apo-mCRY2 and FBXL3-bound mCRY2 (only apo-mCRY2 is superimposed for clarity) the antenna recognition loop forms a surface exposed α-helix that superimposes with β0 and β1 of mPER2 in our mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure (right).
        </p>
        <p>
         (C) Superposition of the C-terminal helix α22 of apo-mCRY1 (gray) and the mCRY1/mPER2 complex (cyan/yellow). Helix α22 could be built to completeness in the complex structure. Arg483 forms a salt bridge to Asp321 in the sulfur loop, in the mPER2 complex additionally to Asp1167 (mPER2 helix α3). Pro319 (sulfur loop) also interacts with mPER2 α3.
        </p>
        <p>
         (D) mCRY1-mPER2 (cyan/yellow) interface at the C-terminal lid with apo-mCRY1 (gray) superimposed. In the complex, Phe405 points away from the mCRY1-PHR body and embeds into a huge hydrophobic pocket composed of Pro1179, Phe1181, Leu1189, Trp1195 of mPER2 and Leu148, Val316, Phe409, Tyr488 and Leu491 of mCRY1 (Leu491 and Tyr488 are not shown for clarity.) In the apo-mCRY1 structure, Phe406 to Phe410 are built as alanine due their unordered side chains. In the complex, Gln407 and Gln408 are well defined and reorient to allow for backbone hydrogen bonding of His1193
         <sub>
          mPER2
         </sub>
         . Phe410 embeds into a hydrophobic pocket composed of His359, Trp399, Leu400 and Try413 and forms a backbone hydrogen bond with the Arg367 side chain. His411 moves away from the mCRY1 body and forms a hydrogen bond with the backbone of Ala1204
         <sub>
          mPER2
         </sub>
         .
        </p>
        <p>
         (E) Superposition of apo-mCRY1-PHR (gray) and apo-mCRY2-PHR (green, pdb 4I6E [
         <a>
          Xing et al., 2013
         </a>
         ]) (rmsd = 1.031 Å for 445 CRY Cα positions). In contrast to the apo-mCRY1 structure, the disulfide bridge between Cys381 and Cys430 (corresponding to Cys363 and Cys412 of mCRY1) is broken in the apo-mCRY2 structure.
        </p>
        <p>
         (F) Superposition of apo-mCRY1-PHR (gray) and mCRY2/FBXL3 (pdb 4I6J [
         <a>
          Xing et al., 2013
         </a>
         ]; mCRY2 in green, FBXL3 LRR in light pink) (rmsd = 1.434 Å for 459 CRY Cα positions). In the mCRY2/FBXL3 structure, Cys430 is in disulfide bridge distance to Cys340 of FBXL3 LRR.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1537 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    mPER2 winds around the α-helical domain of mCRY1 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B). The crystallized mPER2 fragment comprises five α helices (α1–α5, Ile1138–Thr1198) and a short N-terminal antiparallel β sheet formed by residues 1132–1136 (β1) and part of the cloning overhang of mPER2 (β0). Residues Gly1199 to Glu1214 following helix α5 adopt a well-ordered loop structure. The most C-terminal residues 1215–1252 of the crystallized mPER2[1132–1252] fragment are not seen in the electron density due to conformational disorder (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    B, and S1C). Our CD spectra of the mCRY1[1–496]/mPER2[1132–1252] complex support the high helical content of mCRY1-bound mPER2 in solution. CD spectra of apo-mPER2[1132–1252], however, suggest that unbound mPER2 is significantly less structured (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). We therefore propose that mCRY1 binding induces α-helical folding of the C-terminal mPER2 fragment.
   </p>
   <title>
    The mCRY1/mPER2 Complex Is Stabilized by Four Interfaces and a Zinc Ion
   </title>
   <p>
    Several elements of the mCRY1-PHR are involved in mPER2 binding: the C-terminal helix α22 and its preceding connector loop, the C-terminal lid, the sulfur loop, the loop connecting helices α5 and α6, helix α12, and helix α15. Overall, the mCRY1/mPER2 complex buries a 3221 Å
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    solvent-accessible surface area.
   </p>
   <p>
    Helix α22 constitutes a central component of the mCRY1-mPER2 interface. It is embedded between mPER2 helix α3 and the loop region C-terminal to mPER2 α5 (“C-terminal helix interface”;
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A). Notably, Arg483 and Lys485 (mCRY1 α22) are involved in mPER2 binding and transcriptional repression in mammalian cells (
    <a>
     Ozber et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), as well as in interactions with purified C-terminal mBMAL1 fragments (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). In apo- and mPER2-bound mCRY1, Arg483 forms an intramolecular salt bridge with Asp321 (sulfur loop), which likely contributes to positioning of α22 (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    C). In the mCRY1/mPER2 complex, Arg483 forms an additional salt bridge to Asp1167 (mPER2 α3) (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    A, right, and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    C). Furthermore, Gln486 and Gln490 (α22) hydrogen bond to Gln1168
    <sub>
     mPER2
    </sub>
    , and Gln486 also hydrogen bonds to the backbone of Leu1164
    <sub>
     mPER2
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A, left). The sulfur loop further stabilizes the position of mPER2 α3, mostly via hydrophobic interactions of Pro319
    <sub>
     mCRY1
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    A, right, and
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A). On the other side of mCRY1 α22, Lys485 forms a hydrophilic side-chain interaction with Asp1206 and a backbone hydrogen bond with Val1207 in the C-terminal mPER2 loop region (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A, left).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Close-Up View of mCRY1-mPER2 InterfacesCrucial interface residues are shown as ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (953 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Notably, Cys1210 and Cys1213 in the C-terminal mPER2 loop region and mCRY1 residues Cys414 (lid) and His473 (α22) tetrahedrally coordinate a zinc ion (“zinc interface”;
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B,
    <a>
     2
    </a>
    B,
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A, and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    ). An anomalous difference map calculated for positioning of the selenomethionines of mPER2 gave first evidence for the zinc ion in the crystal (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    A and S4B). An X-ray fluorescence scan confirmed its presence (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    C). Atomic absorption spectroscopy confirmed the presence of zinc in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in solution, but not in the single proteins due to their incomplete zinc-binding sites (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="mCRY1/mPER2 Heterodimer Binds Zinc in the Crystal and in Solution, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S4.
        <p>
         mCRY1/mPER2 Heterodimer Binds Zinc in the Crystal and in Solution, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 2
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          6
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         (A) mCRY1/mPER2 complex (cyan/yellow) with selenium anomalous difference map. (Seleno)methionine residues of mPER2 (blue) are shown as atomic sticks. The selenium anomalous difference map (red, 4 σ level) was calculated at 2.8 Å resolution using anomalous differences of the peak wavelength (λ
         <sub>
          peak
         </sub>
         = 0.9763 Å). The N-terminal methionine as well as a methionine in the cloning overhang of mPER2 are disordered. An unexpected additional peak gave first evidence for the presence of a zinc ion (Zn, brown, see arrow) at the interface of CRY and PER.
        </p>
        <p>
         (B) Close-up view of the zinc interface: The Fo-Fc omit map (2.8 σ level, green) was calculated omitting the side chains of Cys414 and His473 (mCRY1) and Cys1210 and Cys1213 (mPER2) as well as the tetrahedrally coordinated zinc ion. The 2.8 Å selenium anomalous difference map (λ
         <sub>
          peak
         </sub>
         ) showed density for Zn (4 σ level, red).
        </p>
        <p>
         (C) Identification of zinc in the mCRY1/mPER2 crystal by X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy. Zinc is unambiguously identified by its Kα emission line at 8,630 eV.
        </p>
        <p>
         (D) Presence of zinc in mPER2, mCRY1 and the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in solution. 1) Control, buffer (25 mM HEPES pH 7.0, 100 mM NaCl, 2 mM DTT), 2) mPER2[1119-1252] individually purified from
         <em>
          E. coli
         </em>
         , 3) mCRY[1-496] individually purified from insect cells, 4) mCRY1[1-496]/mPER2[1132-1252] complex, copurified from mixed lysates. Buffer and proteins were subjected to inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry (ICP-OES) analysis. The signal intensities at the zinc-specific wavelength of 213.857 nm are shown. Only copurified mCRY1[1-496]/mPER2[1132-1252] complex binds zinc (strong signal), while single mCRY1 and mPER2 proteins are zinc-free in solution (weak signal).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (691 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Another heterodimer interface is formed between mCRY1 α12 and mPER2 helices α1 and α2 (referred to as “mPER2(α1-2)-mCRY1(α12) interface”;
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A). mPER2 α1 additionally contacts mCRY1 α15, whereas mPER2 α2 also interfaces with Tyr466 to Met470 in the loop preceding mCRY1 α22. Trp1139 (mPER2 α1) contacts mCRY1 α12 and α15. Lys329 (mCRY1 α12) hydrogen bonds to backbone oxygens of Ile1149 to Tyr1153 (mPER2 α2) and Asn323 to the Tyr1153 side chain. The loop connecting mPER2 α1 and α2 winds tightly around Ala328 of mCRY1 α12.
   </p>
   <p>
    mPER2 α4, which is part of a 20 amino acid stretch (1179 to 1198) reported to be essential for mCRY1 binding in cell-based assays (
    <a>
     Tomita et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), packs against the C-terminal lid (including Phe405) and the α5–α6 connector loop (including Leu148 and Thr149) of mCRY1 (“mPER2(α4)-cap interface”;
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    D and
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A). Leu148 makes hydrophobic interactions with Leu1189 and Phe1181 of mPER2, whereas Thr149 hydrogen bonds to Glu1188 and (water mediated) to Glu1191 of mPER2 α4.
   </p>
   <title>
    The mCRY C-Terminal Lid Adopts Variable Conformations and Is Involved in Disulfide Bond Formation and Zinc Coordination
   </title>
   <p>
    The major difference between the apo-mCRY1 and mCRY1 complex structure manifests in the conformation of the C-terminal lid. Although the side chains of residues Phe406 to Phe410 are disordered in the apo structure, the loop is well defined and adopts a deviating orientation in the complex structure (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). This is likely due to its packing against α4, α5, and the C-terminal loop of mPER2 (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B,
    <a>
     2
    </a>
    D,
    <a>
     3
    </a>
    B, and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    D). The apo-mCRY1 structure contains a disulfide bridge between Cys363 and Cys412, which has the potential to be a redox-dependent link to the FAD-binding pocket (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Located in the immediate vicinity of the zinc interface, this disulfide bridge is broken in the complex structure (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     3
    </a>
    ). Thereby, we hypothesize that the C-terminal lid gains a higher flexibility for interaction with mPER2.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="C-Terminal Lid and FAD-Binding Pocket of the mCRY1/mPER2 Complex(A&amp;ndash;C) The ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (811 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In apo-mCRY1, Phe405 is embedded in a hydrophobic pocket of the mCRY1-PHR. In the mCRY1/mPER2 complex, however, Phe406 occupies the hydrophobic pocket of apo-Phe405, whereas Phe405 projects to the surface (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A) and embeds into a huge hydrophobic pocket lined by PER and CRY residues (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    D,
    <a>
     S1
    </a>
    A, and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    D). The mPER2-bound lid conformation is additionally stabilized by backbone hydrogen bonding of Phe405 and Gln407 with His1193
    <sub>
     mPER2
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D) and by Phe410, which inserts into a hydrophobic pocket, including His359 and Trp399 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <p>
    In apo- and FBXL3-bound mCRY2 (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), the lid adopts yet another position than in apo- and mPER2-bound mCRY1. Phe424 and Phe423 of mCRY2/FBXL3 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C) and apo-mCRY2 (data not shown) position just as the corresponding Phe406 and Phe405 in apo-mCRY1. Phe428
    <sub>
     mCRY2
    </sub>
    (corresponding to Phe410
    <sub>
     mCRY1
    </sub>
    ) is not embedded in the mCRY-PHR but is turned away from the mCRY2 core and mediates interactions with FBXL3. Interestingly, in both the apo-mCRY2- and the mCRY2/FBXL3 complex structure, there is no disulfide bridge between Cys381 and Cys430 (corresponding to Cys363 and Cys412 in mCRY1) (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    C,
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    E, and S3F). Instead, Cys430 forms an intermolecular disulfide bridge with Cys340 of FBXL3 in the mCRY2/FBXL3 complex structure (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <title>
    The FAD-Binding Pocket of mCRY1
   </title>
   <p>
    The mCRY2/FBXL3/SKP1 complex structure (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) revealed that the C-terminal tail of FBXL3 occupies the FAD-binding pocket of mCRY2. In our mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure, however, the FAD-binding pocket is accessible, unoccupied, and in a very similar conformation as in apo-mCRY1 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B) and apo-mCRY2. Notably, the side chains of Gln289, Trp292, and His355 adopt an introversive position, which would interfere with FAD binding. mPER2 binding does not affect the conformation of His355 and Gln289, but reorientation of Trp292 is required to allow for the positioning of Gln407 in the mPER2-bound lid conformation. We therefore suggest that, although mPER2 binding to mCRY1 may somewhat negatively affect FAD binding by enforcing an unfavorable side-chain orientation of Trp292, it neither requires nor fully excludes the presence of FAD.
   </p>
   <title>
    Structural Basis for Mutually Exclusive Binding of mPER2 and FBXL3 to mCRY
   </title>
   <p>
    Our mCRY1/mPER2 crystal structure explains why mPER2-bound mCRY2 is completely devoid of FBXL3 in HEK293 cells and a purified C-terminal mPER2 fragment displaces mCRY2 from FBXL3 (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    ). Whereas mPER2 α3 blocks binding of the leucine-rich repeat (LRR) N domain of FBXL3 to helix α22 and the sulfur loop of mCRY (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B, left), the C-terminal mPER2 loop region, including the zinc interface, interferes with binding of the LRR C domain of FBXL3 to mCRY α22 and the lid (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B, right). Moreover, mPER2 α4 and α5 completely overlap with the conserved mCRY2 C-terminal extension sequence (CCS), implying that the CCS adopts a deviating orientation in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B, right).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="mPER2 and FBXL3 LRR Are Mutually Exclusive in Binding to mCRY1/2(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (642 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The high sequence identity (86%) and conservation of mCRY binding residues between FBXL3 and FBXL21 (
    <a>
     Hirano et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yoo et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) suggest that these two counteracting E3-ligase subunits bind to the same mCRY surface regions, and therefore, simultaneous binding of FBXL21 and mPER2 is unlikely, too.
   </p>
   <title>
    Analyses of mCRY1-mPER2 Interactions In Vitro
   </title>
   <p>
    To validate our mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure in solution and to assess the relative contributions of the different interfaces in vitro, we have generated mPER2[1119–1252] fragments with point mutations in the mCRY1/mPER2 interfaces. Effects of these mutations on the mCRY1-mPER2 interaction were analyzed in pull-down assays using total lysates and in native gels using purified proteins (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    A, 5C, and 5D). The single H1193E mutation in the mPER2(α4)-cap interface, which aims to electrostatically interfere with binding to the mCRY1 C-terminal lid (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D), showed wild-type (WT)-like behavior in both assays. However, in combination with the D1167R mutation in the C-terminal helix interface (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A, right), the H1193E mutation further weakens mCRY1 binding. Binding of mCRY1 was even more severely impaired through the additional F1181R mutation, which also targets the interaction with the mCRY1 C-terminal lid (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). These results suggest that both interfaces (C-terminal helix interface and mPER2(α4)-cap interface) are of similar importance for complex formation in vitro. In addition, our native gel analyses imply that the mCRY1 tail is not required for mCRY1/mPER2 complex formation, as comparable results were gained with the mCRY1-PHR and full-length mCRY1 (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    C and 5D).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Biochemical Analysis of mCRY1/mPER2 Interfaces(A) Ni2+ pull-down from total cell ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (511 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Mutation of the zinc-coordinating residues Cys1210 and Cys1213 to alanine surprisingly did not compromise complex formation in vitro, neither in the total lysate (natural presence of zinc) nor in the purified system (supplied with zinc acetate) (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    A, 5C, and 5D). Furthermore, no difference in complex formation was observed for WT proteins whether zinc was added to the buffer or not (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    C and 5D), implying that the zinc-binding interface is of minor importance for complex formation in vitro. Affinity measurements (isothermal titration calorimetry, ITC) further support this result because a K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    in the lower nanomolar range was observed for the mCRY1-mPER2 interaction even in the absence of zinc ions (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). However, zinc binding clearly stabilizes the purified mCRY1/mPER2 complex as demonstrated by the higher melting temperature of the WT complex compared to the zinc-free mCRY1/mPER2(C1210A/C1213A) mutant complex in our thermofluor experiments (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A). Furthermore, ITC experiments revealed that the WT mCRY1/mPER2 complex binds zinc ions with a nanomolar affinity (K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of ∼8 nM) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="High-Affinity Zinc Binding Stabilizes the mCRY1-mPER2 Complex(A) Melting ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (184 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    mCRY1-mPER2 Heterodimer Interfaces Are Present in a Cellular Context
   </title>
   <p>
    To validate our mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure in a cellular environment and in the context of full-length mCRY1 and mPER2 proteins, we have tested mCRY1 interface mutants for their effect on the stability of the mCRY1/mPER2 complex using a luciferase complementation assay (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    A). Full-length mCRY1 and mPER2 (WT or mutants) were expressed as fusion proteins with C- and N-terminal firefly luciferase fragments in HEK293 cells (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). mPER2-mCRY1 interactions lead to a functional luciferase whose activity was measured in cell lysates.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="mCRY1/mPER2 Complex Formation Is Regulated by Four Interfaces, a Zinc Ion, and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (394 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The mCRY1 T149E mutation was designed to sterically and electrostatically weaken interactions with mPER2 α4 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). Consistent with our structure and the reported importance of mPER2 helices α4 and α5 for mCRY-mPER interactions (
    <a>
     Tomita et al., 2010
    </a>
    ), the T149E mutation drastically reduced mPER2 binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    Disruption of the interaction of mCRY1 α22 with mPER2 α3 (Q486R) and with the loop connecting mPER2 α5 with the zinc-binding motif (K485D) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A, K485D/Q486R double mutant) drastically reduced mPER2 binding to below 10%. This confirms the existence and importance of the combined C-terminal helix interface in a cellular environment. The P319R mutation in the mCRY1 sulfur loop should also weaken the interaction with mPER2 α3 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). Whereas the P319R mutation moderately reduced binding in our luciferase complementation assay (this study), the K485D single mutation reduced binding to ∼20% (
    <a>
     Czarna et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). This finding suggests that mCRY1 binding to the mPER2 loop region (targeted by K485D) is more important than the interaction with the long mPER2 helix α3 (targeted by Q486R and P319R) in vivo.
   </p>
   <p>
    A double mutation in the mPER2(α1–2)-mCRY1(α12) interface (A328R/K329D) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C) reduces mPER2 interactions by about one half. We conclude that mPER2 helices α1 and α2 contribute to mCRY1 binding also in a cellular environment but are not as important for complex stability as for example helix α4.
   </p>
   <title>
    Zinc Binding and Adjacent Disulfide Bond Formation Are Interdependent in a Cellular Context and In Vitro
   </title>
   <p>
    To define potential roles of the zinc ion and the CRY1 Cys363-Cys412 disulfide bridge in a cellular environment, we have mutated the zinc-coordinating residues of mCRY1 (Cys414 and His473) and mPER2 (Cys1210 and Cys1213), as well as Cys363 and Cys412 to alanine. The mutants were tested for their effect on the stability of the mCRY1/mPER2 complex using a luciferase complementation assay in HEK293 cells (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Zinc-Dependent mCRY1-mPER2 Interaction in Living Cells, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;7(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (249 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The mCRY1 single mutations C414A and H473A significantly reduced mPER2 binding, with the C414A single mutation being more effective. Furthermore, very weak interactions were observed between the mPER2(C1210A/C1213A) double-mutant protein and wild-type or C414A mutant mCRY1, indicating that zinc coordination is of vital importance for the formation of a stable complex between full-length mCRY1 and mPER2 in vivo.
   </p>
   <p>
    C412A and C363A single mutations, which prevent formation of the Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bridge, slightly enhanced mPER2 binding in some of our luciferase complementation assays yet behaved wild-type like in other experiments. We propose that disruption of this disulfide bridge enhances mPER2 binding by facilitating the observed conformational changes of the mCRY1 lid (discussed above). The mild and somewhat fluctuating impact of the C412A and C363A single mutations on mPER2 binding probably depends on the redox status and hence the extent of Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bridge formation in the HEK293 cells.
   </p>
   <p>
    To test whether mCRY1 exists in an oxidized form also in living cells, we analyzed mCRY1 disulfide bridge formation in HEK293 cells by N-Ethylmaleimide (NEM) and Maleimide-PEG (MP) modification (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    B). Indeed, we found increased molecular weight forms of mCRY1 (CRY1-MP) only in lysates that were dithiothreitol (DTT) treated before MP modification, but not when lysates were either left untreated or when potential disulfide bridges were stabilized with H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    . This indicates that full-length mCRY1 also occurs in oxidized forms within cells.
   </p>
   <p>
    Quite surprisingly, the mCRY1 C414A/C412A and the C414A/C363A double mutations only weakened mPER2 binding to ∼50% in our luciferase complementation assay (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A). Furthermore, mCRY1 single- (C412A) or double (C412A/C414A)-mutant proteins showed ∼50% binding activity toward mPER2 proteins containing the C1210A/C1213A double mutation. Hence, the C412A and C363A mutations partially rescue the severe weakening of the mCRY1-mPER2 interaction by the mCRY1 (C414A) and mPER2 (C1210A/C1213A) mutations, suggesting that reduction of the Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bridge and the resulting increased flexibility of the mCRY1 C-terminal lid decrease the severity of disruption of the zinc-binding site.
   </p>
   <p>
    To further elucidate whether the mCRY1 Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bridge forms in dependence of zinc in the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in vitro, we kept purified zinc-containing and zinc-free mCRY1/mPER2 complexes under reducing or nonreducing conditions and monitored the mCRY1 oxidation status by mass spectrometry (MS) (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    ). The presence of zinc in the complexes was analyzed in parallel by atomic absorption spectroscopy (ICP-OES) (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    ). Under nonreducing conditions, only a moderate amount of the putatively oxidized mCRY1 species (with the total mass reduced by ∼2 Da as expected for the oxidation of a disulfide bridge) is observed in the zinc-bound WT mCRY1/mPER2 complex (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    A, middle). However, in the zinc-free mCRY1/mPER2(C1210A/C1213A) mutant complex (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    B), as well as when the zinc ion is removed from the WT complex through EDTA (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    A, right), mCRY1 appears almost completely oxidized. To test whether the mCRY1 oxidation status is affected by disulfide bond formation between Cys412 and Cys363, we mutated Cys412 to alanine. Indeed, the C412A mutation substantially reduced mCRY1 oxidation in the zinc-free mCRY1(C412A)/mPER2(C1210A/C1213A) mutant complex (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C), indicating that Cys412 oxidation accounts for a significant fraction of the MS peak CRY
    <sub>
     p1
    </sub>
    assigned to oxidized mCRY1 protein. However, we also found a moderate amount of putatively oxidized mCRY1 after aeration in the C412A mutant, suggesting additional disulfide bond formation (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C). Notably, the behavior of the purified zinc-free mCRY1(C412A)/mPER2(C1210A/C1213A) complex mirrors that of the WT mCRY1/mPER2 complex in our MS experiments (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    D). This observation is consistent with the partial rescue of zinc-binding deficiency by the C412A and C363A mutations observed in our luciferase complementation experiment (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Liquid Chromatography Electrospray-Ionization Mass Spectrometry Analysis of WT ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1002 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Zinc Content of the mCRY1/mPER2 Complex in Solution, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;6(1) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867414005352-figs7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (489 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In conclusion, our mutational analyses confirm the presence of all heterodimer interfaces revealed by our mCRY1/mPER2 crystal structure and indicate an interdependent role of the coordinated zinc ion and of the mCRY1 Cys412-Cys363 disulfide bridge, among others, in the positive (zinc) and negative (disulfide bridge) regulation of the mCRY1-mPER2 interaction in vivo.
   </p>
   <title>
    Zinc Ions Bind to the mCRY1/mPER2 Complex in a Cellular Context and Enhance the mCRY1-mPER2 Interaction in Living Cells
   </title>
   <p>
    To test whether zinc can bind to the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in a cellular environment, we transiently transfected HEK293 cells with full-length mPER2 or full-length mCRY1 either as WT versions or with mutations in the three zinc-coordinating cysteines (mCRY1: C414A; mPER2: C1210A and C1213A) and the disulfide bridge forming Cys412 of mCRY1. To ensure that sufficiently stable mCRY1/mPER2 complexes are formed even without zinc coordination, we used the mCRY1 (C412A and C414A) double mutant, which enhanced mCRY1-mPER2 interaction compared to the C414A single mutation in our luciferase complementation assays (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A). Immunoprecipitated mPER2 was incubated with mCRY1-containing cell lysate in the presence of the radioactive zinc isotope
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    . A 7-fold increase in
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    radioactivity was detected when mPER2- and mCRY1-containing cell lysates were used. Mutations in the zinc coordination site led to a substantial and significant reduction of zinc binding (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    C). In addition, immunoprecipitated mPER2 incubated with a control lysate did essentially not incorporate
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    B). Together, these results indicate that zinc can bind to the full-length mCRY1/mPER2 complex in a cellular context, and this binding depends on critical zinc-coordinating cysteine residues in both proteins. The residual radioactivity observed for the mutant proteins could be due to
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    binding to large endogenous mCRY1/mPER2 complexes recruited via mPER PAS domain homodimer interactions (
    <a>
     Kucera et al., 2012
    </a>
    ), as well as unspecific zinc binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    To investigate whether zinc ions also contribute to the stabilization of the mCRY1-mPER2 interaction in living cells, we created two reporter U2-OS cell lines that stably express mPER2 and mCRY1 split luciferase fusion proteins either as WT proteins or with mutations in the zinc-coordinating residues Cys414 (mCRY1), Cys1210, and Cys1213 (mPER2), as well as the disulfide bridge forming Cys412 of mCRY1 (mut: C412A/C414A/C1210A/C1213A). Treatment with zinc (but not iron) ions dose-dependently enhances the bioluminescence in cells expressing WT mPER2 and mCRY1, but not or to a much lesser extent in cells expressing mutant mCRY1 and mPER2 proteins, indicating that zinc coordination indeed contributes to mCRY1-mPER2 interaction strength, and this effect depends on the integrity of the zinc-coordinating residues (
    <a>
     Figures 7
    </a>
    D and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Our crystal structure of the mCRY1/mPER2 heterodimer shows an intimate and high-affinity clock protein complex with a zinc interface that critically stabilizes the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in mammalian cells. Our cell-based and in vitro (LC-ESI-MS/ICP-OES) studies suggest that the coordinated zinc ion structurally facilitates the reduction of a nearby located disulfide bridge of mCRY1 (probably between Cys412 and Cys363, among others), which likely enhances the flexibility of the mCRY1 C-terminal lid and thereby mPER2 binding. This functionally important interplay between an intermolecular composite 3Cys/1His zinc-binding site in a heterodimer interface and one or more intramolecular disulfide bonds formed by nearby located cysteine residues has not been observed in other zinc-binding proteins (e.g.,
    <a>
     Maret, 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Auld, 2001
    </a>
    ). Notably, the redox-regulated chaperone Hsp33 and anti-σ factor RsrA use intramolecular cysteine-containing zinc centers as redox sensors (
    <a>
     Ilbert et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). In both proteins, oxidative or disulfide stress leads to oxidation and, hence, disulfide bond formation of their zinc-coordinating cysteines, as well as zinc release, which induce conformational changes leading to their functional activation. On the other hand, betaine-homocysteine methyltransferase is reversibly inactivated through oxidation of its zinc-coordinating cysteines and zinc release (
    <a>
     Evans et al., 2002
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Our LC-ESI-MS/ICP-OES experiments show that the mCRY1/mPER2 complex does not release its zinc ion under nonreducing conditions (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    , number 2). Instead, the experiments suggest that zinc release supports mCRY1 oxidation (
    <a>
     Figures S6
    </a>
    A, top right, and
    <a>
     S6
    </a>
    B) and that this oxidation also involves Cys412 (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C). Using the same basic elements (i.e., a zinc ion and a nearby located highly reactive cysteine) but in a different structural arrangement, mode of action, and interplay, the CRY1/PER2 complex therefore may act as a sensor of the rhythmically changing redox state of the cell, which was proposed to be involved in driving circadian rhythms (
    <a>
     Edgar et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     O’Neill and Reddy, 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     O’Neill et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wang et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In general, there are various intracellular zinc pools described such as zinc in vesicles, zinc tightly bound to macromolecules, zinc bound to metallothioneins (the major cellular zinc storage proteins), and a pool of “free” zinc (
    <a>
     Oteiza, 2012
    </a>
    ). Although the total cellular amount of zinc is described to be in the high micromolar range, the concentration of “free” zinc is much lower (nano- to picomolar) because most zinc is bound to proteins with high affinity. However, under certain circumstances, e.g., oxidative stress, zinc may be released. Our measured K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    for zinc binding to the mCRY1/mPER2 complex in the lower nanomolar range suggests a dynamic, regulatory zinc-binding site that might be influenced by its environment within the cell.
   </p>
   <p>
    Interestingly, the zinc-coordinating residues and most other residues mediating CRY-PER interactions are conserved in vertebrate CRY and PER2 proteins, in PER1, and, to a minor extent, in PER3, which strongly suggests the existence of homologous CRY/PER complexes (
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Lacking the knowledge about the mCRY1-mPER2 zinc interface,
    <a>
     Okano et al. (2009)
    </a>
    generated a transgenic mouse line constitutively overexpressing mCRY1 with a C414A mutation. These mice showed a long 28 hr free-running period of locomotor activity rhythms and abnormal entrainment behavior, as well as symptoms of diabetes, including reduced β cell proliferation and insulin secretion (hypoinsulinemia) (
    <a>
     Okano et al., 2009
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Okano et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Okano et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Most likely, these dominant in vivo effects of the C414A mutation are due to disruption of the mCRY1-mPER2 zinc interface, demonstrating the importance of zinc-dependent mCRY1/mPER2 complex formation for circadian dynamics and metabolic regulation. Notably, mutations in mBMAL1 and mCLOCK also lead to hypoinsulinemia and defective β cell function, whereas mCRY1/mCRY2 double-knockout mice exhibit hyperinsulinemia and tissue-specific insulin resistance (
    <a>
     Barclay et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Marcheva et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, the mCLOCKΔ19 mutation leads to extended circadian periods, whereas
    <em>
     mCry1
     <sup>
      −/−
     </sup>
    </em>
    mice exhibit a period shortened by 1 hr (
    <a>
     King et al., 1997
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     van der Horst et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). Hence, the circadian and metabolic phenotypes of the mCRY1 C414A mutation are more similar to those resulting from mutations in the mCLOCK/BMAL1 complex than to mCRY knockouts. Our structure suggests that the intimate interaction of mPER2 with mCRY1 α22 interferes with repressive mCRY1 binding to the mCLOCK/BMAL1-E-box complex. Thus, we speculate that the weakened mPER2 interaction of the zinc-binding-deficient mCRY1(C414A) mutant protein (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A) leads to an enhanced transcriptional repression activity in vivo. We further propose that, in transgenic mice, the overexpressed mCRY1(C414A) mutant protein represses the mCLOCK/BMAL1 complex more strongly than endogenous WT mCRY1. This may cause the dominant phenotype of the mCRY1(C414A) mutation, which somewhat resembles the phenotypes of transgenic mice expressing weakened transcriptional activator complexes, including, for example, the mCLOCKΔ19 mutant protein.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our structure also shows that binding of FBXL3 or PER2 to CRY is mutually exclusive and suggests that PER2 stabilizes CRY1 by shielding it from FBXL3. Strikingly, neither mPER2 (this study) nor FBXL3 (
    <a>
     Xing et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) binds in close proximity of the AMPK phosphorylation site Ser71, suggesting that AMPK regulates PER2 and FBXL3 binding in a more indirect manner. Notably, Cys412 appears highly reactive in switching functions because it not only forms the intramolecular disulfide bond to Cys363 in apo-mCRY1 but also an intermolecular disulfide bond with FBXL3 in the CRY2/FBXL3 complex structure.
   </p>
   <p>
    Taken together, our crystal structure provides a more complete understanding of how mammalian CRY and PER proteins interact, how this interaction might be sensing and be regulated by cellular redox/metabolic states, and how the interplay with other clock components drives the circadian clock and metabolic processes. This will guide the design of new mutants, experiments, and small-molecule ligands to study or target macromolecular CRY/PER containing complexes in vivo.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Protein Purification and Crystallization
   </title>
   <p>
    mCRY1 and mPER2 proteins were recombinantly expressed as His-fusions in insect cells and
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    , respectively. For purification of the mCRY1/mPER2 complex (native and selenomethionine labeled), lysates were combined and copurified via Ni
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    affinity, anion exchange, and heparin and size-exclusion chromatography columns. For biochemical analysis, mCRY1 proteins were purified via Ni
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    affinity, anion exchange, heparin and size-exclusion columns, mPER2 proteins via Ni
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    affinity followed by tag cleavage, anion exchange, and size-exclusion chromatography.
   </p>
   <p>
    Crystals of the mCRY1/mPER2 complex grew at 20°C in 0.2 M MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and 12%–13% PEG3350. They contain one complex per asymmetric unit (space group P4
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    2
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    2).
   </p>
   <title>
    Data Collection, Structure Determination, and Refinement
   </title>
   <p>
    A 2.45 Å data set of a mCRY1/mPER2 crystal and a 2.8 Å data set of a selenomethione-labeled mCRY1/mPER2 crystal were collected at beamline PXII (SLS). The mCRY1/mPER2 complex structure was solved by molecular replacement with apo-mCRY1 (PDB ID 4K0R) as search model combined with selenium single-wavelength anomalous dispersion (SAD) phasing. Data collection and refinement statistics are summarized in
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Inductively Coupled Plasma Optical Emission Spectrometry
   </title>
   <p>
    We performed inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry (ICP-OES) using a Varian VISTA-RL spectrometer with a MicroMist nebulizer. Zinc binding was determined by measuring its specific emission at 213.857 nm.
   </p>
   <title>
    Pull-Down Experiments
   </title>
   <p>
    Clear lysates of
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    cells expressing His-tagged mPER2 (WT and mutants) were incubated with Ni-Sepharose 6 Fast Flow beads in presence of 25 mM imidazole for 1 hr. After washing and equilibration in lysis buffer with 70 mM imidazole, mPER2-bound Ni-beads were incubated with clear lysates of insect cells expressing untagged mCRY1 for 1 hr in order to pull down mCRY1. The beads were extensively washed before elution of the bound complex with 500 mM imidazole and analysis by SDS-PAGE.
   </p>
   <title>
    Native PAGE Analysis
   </title>
   <p>
    Purified proteins were incubated at a 1:1 molar ratio in a BIS-Tris Propane buffer (pH 7.0) at 4°C for at least 2 hr. Samples were analyzed on a native 4%–20% Novex Tris-Glycine gel and by SDS-PAGE.
   </p>
   <title>
    Circular Dichroism, Isothermal Titration Calorimetry, and Thermofluor
   </title>
   <p>
    Circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy using a Jasco J-810 spectropolarimeter and ITC experiments using a VP-ITC MicroCalorimeter were performed essentially as described in
    <a>
     Czarna et al. (2011)
    </a>
    . Thermofluor was performed as described in
    <a>
     Weir et al. (2010)
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    LC-ESI MS Analysis
   </title>
   <p>
    Purified WT and mutant mCRY1/mPER2 complexes were kept under reducing (4 mM DTT) or nonreducing (no DTT, aeration) conditions for 2 days. For removal of bound zinc, the protein complex was treated with 10 mM EDTA, and zinc-bound EDTA was removed by dialysis. LC-MS analyses were performed on a Bruker micrOTOF connected to an Agilent 1100 HPLC system equipped with a diode array detector.
   </p>
   <title>
    Luciferase Complementation Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    The luciferase complementation assay was performed essentially as described in
    <a>
     Kucera et al. (2012)
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Analysis of Disulfide Bridges in mCRY1
   </title>
   <p>
    mCRY1 disulfide bridges were analyzed essentially using a combined method from
    <a>
     Wu et al. (2000)
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Templeton et al. ( 2010)
    </a>
    . Free thiol groups in lysates of MYC-tagged mCRY1-expressing HEK293 cells were blocked with 50 mM NEM, excess NEM was removed by methanol precipitation, and disulfide bridges were then reduced with 20 mM DTT. After removal of DTT by methanol precipitation, arosen free thiol groups were modified by incubation with 300 μM Maleimide-PEG. Samples were then analyzed by western blotting using an anti-MYC antibody.
   </p>
   <title>
    Live-Cell Zinc-Binding Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Human U2-OS cells stably expressing mCRY1 and mPER2 as split-luciferase hybrid proteins were kept for at least 1 week in zinc-depleted medium prior to zinc ion addition. Bioluminescence of reconstituted luciferase was recorded for several days.
   </p>
   <title>
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn-Binding Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    HEK293 cells were cultured for 5 days in zinc-free medium before transfection with equal amounts of plasmid DNA encoding either WT or mutant epitope-tagged mCRY1 or mPER2. Lysates with overexpressed V5-tagged mPER2 constructs were incubated with anti-V5 antibody and equivalent amounts of Protein G PLUS-agarose beads overnight. Beads were washed, mixed with lysates overexpressing mCRY1 or control lysates, and incubated for 3 hr with 35 μM
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    ZnCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    radionuclide at room temperature. After washing,
    <sup>
     65
    </sup>
    Zn binding was determined by scintillation counting in a Wallac 1440 DSA system.
   </p>
   <p>
    The
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    section, which provides detailed information about all experimental procedures, including protein purification, crystallization, structure determination, in vitro interaction studies (ITC, native gels, and pull-down), circular dichroism, thermofluor, LC-ESI-MS, and atomic absorption spectroscopy (ICP-OES), as well as cell-based studies (luciferase complementation assays, zinc-binding assays, and disulfide bond formation), is included in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Information
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Author Contributions
   </title>
   <p>
    I.S., S.R., T.W., R.K., A.K., and E.W. designed experiments; I.S., S.R., T.W., R.K., C.B., and A.G. performed experiments; I.S., J.R.P., and C.B. solved the structure; I.S., S.R., T.W., R.K., J.R.P., C.B., A.K., and E.W. analyzed data; and I.S., A.K., and E.W. wrote the paper.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The coordinates and structure factors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank under the accession code
    <a>
     4ct0
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Tables S1 and S2.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (183 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (9113 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Auld, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.S. Auld
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Zinc coordination sphere in biochemical zinc sites
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biometals, 14 (2001), pp. 271–313
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Barclay et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.L. Barclay, A. Shostak, A. Leliavski, A.H. Tsang, O. Jöhren, H. Müller-Fielitz, D. Landgraf, N. Naujokat, G.T.J. van der Horst, H. Oster
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         High-fat diet-induced hyperinsulinemia and tissue-specific insulin resistance in Cry-deficient mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab., 304 (2013), pp. E1053–E1063
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chaves et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I. Chaves, K. Yagita, S. Barnhoorn, H. Okamura, G.T.J. van der Horst, F. Tamanini
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional evolution of the photolyase/cryptochrome protein family: importance of the C terminus of mammalian CRY1 for circadian core oscillator performance
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 26 (2006), pp. 1743–1753
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Czarna et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Czarna, H. Breitkreuz, C.C. Mahrenholz, J. Arens, H.M. Strauss, E. Wolf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Quantitative analyses of cryptochrome-mBMAL1 interactions: mechanistic insights into the transcriptional regulation of the mammalian circadian clock
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 286 (2011), pp. 22414–22425
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Czarna et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Czarna, A. Berndt, H.R. Singh, A. Grudziecki, A.G. Ladurner, G. Timinszky, A. Kramer, E. Wolf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structures of Drosophila cryptochrome and mouse cryptochrome1 provide insight into circadian function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 153 (2013), pp. 1394–1405
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Eckel-Mahan and Sassone-Corsi, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Eckel-Mahan, P. Sassone-Corsi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Metabolism control by the circadian clock and vice versa
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 16 (2009), pp. 462–467
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Edgar et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.S. Edgar, E.W. Green, Y. Zhao, G. van Ooijen, M. Olmedo, X. Qin, Y. Xu, M. Pan, U.K. Valekunja, K.A. Feeney,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Peroxiredoxins are conserved markers of circadian rhythms
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 485 (2012), pp. 459–464
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Eide et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.J. Eide, E.L. Vielhaber, W.A. Hinz, D.M. Virshup
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The circadian regulatory proteins BMAL1 and cryptochromes are substrates of casein kinase Iepsilon
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 17248–17254
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Evans et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.C. Evans, D.P. Huddler, J. Jiracek, C. Castro, N.S. Millian, T.A. Garrow, M.L. Ludwig
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Betaine-homocysteine methyltransferase: zinc in a distorted barrel
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure, 10 (2002), pp. 1159–1171
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gatfield and Schibler, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Gatfield, U. Schibler
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Physiology. Proteasomes keep the circadian clock ticking
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 316 (2007), pp. 1135–1136
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Griffin et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.A. Griffin Jr., D. Staknis, C.J. Weitz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Light-independent role of CRY1 and CRY2 in the mammalian circadian clock
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 286 (1999), pp. 768–771
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hirano et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Hirano, K. Yumimoto, R. Tsunematsu, M. Matsumoto, M. Oyama, H. Kozuka-Hata, T. Nakagawa, D. Lanjakornsiripan, K.I. Nakayama, Y. Fukada
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FBXL21 regulates oscillation of the circadian clock through ubiquitination and stabilization of cryptochromes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 152 (2013), pp. 1106–1118
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hirota et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Hirota, J.W. Lee, P.C. St John, M. Sawa, K. Iwaisako, T. Noguchi, P.Y. Pongsawakul, T. Sonntag, D.K. Welsh, D.A. Brenner,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of small molecule activators of cryptochrome
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 337 (2012), pp. 1094–1097
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hitomi et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Hitomi, L. DiTacchio, A.S. Arvai, J. Yamamoto, S.-T. Kim, T. Todo, J.A. Tainer, S. Iwai, S. Panda, E.D. Getzoff
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional motifs in the (6-4) photolyase crystal structure make a comparative framework for DNA repair photolyases and clock cryptochromes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 106 (2009), pp. 6962–6967
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huang et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Huang, Y. Chelliah, Y. Shan, C.A. Taylor, S.-H. Yoo, C. Partch, C.B. Green, H. Zhang, J.S. Takahashi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structure of the heterodimeric CLOCK:BMAL1 transcriptional activator complex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 337 (2012), pp. 189–194
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ilbert et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Ilbert, P.C. Graf, U. Jakob
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Zinc center as redox switch—new function for an old motif
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Antioxid. Redox Signal., 8 (2006), pp. 835–846
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         King et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.P. King, M.H. Vitaterna, A.M. Chang, W.F. Dove, L.H. Pinto, F.W. Turek, J.S. Takahashi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The mouse Clock mutation behaves as an antimorph and maps within the W19H deletion, distal of Kit
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genetics, 146 (1997), pp. 1049–1060
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Koike et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Koike, S.-H. Yoo, H.-C. Huang, V. Kumar, C. Lee, T.-K. Kim, J.S. Takahashi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Transcriptional architecture and chromatin landscape of the core circadian clock in mammals
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 338 (2012), pp. 349–354
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kucera et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Kucera, I. Schmalen, S. Hennig, R. Öllinger, H.M. Strauss, A. Grudziecki, C. Wieczorek, A. Kramer, E. Wolf
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Unwinding the differences of the mammalian PERIOD clock proteins from crystal structure to cellular function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 109 (2012), pp. 3311–3316
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kume et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Kume, M.J. Zylka, S. Sriram, L.P. Shearman, D.R. Weaver, X. Jin, E.S. Maywood, M.H. Hastings, S.M. Reppert
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         mCRY1 and mCRY2 are essential components of the negative limb of the circadian clock feedback loop
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 98 (1999), pp. 193–205
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lamia et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.A. Lamia, U.M. Sachdeva, L. DiTacchio, E.C. Williams, J.G. Alvarez, D.F. Egan, D.S. Vasquez, H. Juguilon, S. Panda, R.J. Shaw,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         AMPK regulates the circadian clock by cryptochrome phosphorylation and degradation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 326 (2009), pp. 437–440
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lamia et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.A. Lamia, S.J. Papp, R.T. Yu, G.D. Barish, N.H. Uhlenhaut, J.W. Jonker, M. Downes, R.M. Evans
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cryptochromes mediate rhythmic repression of the glucocorticoid receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 480 (2011), pp. 552–556
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Marcheva et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Marcheva, K.M. Ramsey, E.D. Buhr, Y. Kobayashi, H. Su, C.H. Ko, G. Ivanova, C. Omura, S. Mo, M.H. Vitaterna,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Disruption of the clock components CLOCK and BMAL1 leads to hypoinsulinaemia and diabetes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 466 (2010), pp. 627–631
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Maret, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Maret
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New perspectives of zinc coordination environments in proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Inorg. Biochem., 111 (2012), pp. 110–116
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Miyazaki et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Miyazaki, M. Mesaki, N. Ishida
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nuclear entry mechanism of rat PER2 (rPER2): role of rPER2 in nuclear localization of CRY protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 21 (2001), pp. 6651–6659
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Müller and Carell, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Müller, T. Carell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural biology of DNA photolyases and cryptochromes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol., 19 (2009), pp. 277–285
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         O’Neill and Reddy, 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.S. O’Neill, A.B. Reddy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Circadian clocks in human red blood cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 469 (2011), pp. 498–503
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         O’Neill et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.S. O’Neill, G. van Ooijen, L.E. Dixon, C. Troein, F. Corellou, F.-Y. Bouget, A.B. Reddy, A.J. Millar
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Circadian rhythms persist without transcription in a eukaryote
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 469 (2011), pp. 554–558
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Okano et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Okano, M. Akashi, K. Hayasaka, O. Nakajima
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Unusual circadian locomotor activity and pathophysiology in mutant CRY1 transgenic mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Neurosci. Lett., 451 (2009), pp. 246–251
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Okano et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Okano, K. Hayasaka, M. Igarashi, H. Iwai, Y. Togashi, O. Nakajima
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Non-obese early onset diabetes mellitus in mutant cryptochrome1 transgenic mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Eur. J. Clin. Invest., 40 (2010), pp. 1011–1017
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Okano et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Okano, K. Hayasaka, M. Igarashi, Y. Togashi, O. Nakajima
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Characterization of age-associated alterations of islet function and structure in diabetic mutant cryptochrome 1 transgenic mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Diabetes Investigation, 4 (2013), pp. 428–435
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Oteiza, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.I. Oteiza
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Zinc and the modulation of redox homeostasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Free Radic. Biol. Med., 53 (2012), pp. 1748–1759
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ozber et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Ozber, I. Baris, G. Tatlici, I. Gur, S. Kilinc, E.B. Unal, I.H. Kavakli
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of two amino acids in the C-terminal domain of mouse CRY2 essential for PER2 interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         BMC Mol. Biol., 11 (2010), p. 69
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Templeton et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.J. Templeton, M.-S. Aye, J. Rady, F. Xu, J.V. Cross
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Purification of reversibly oxidized proteins (PROP) reveals a redox switch controlling p38 MAP kinase activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PLoS ONE, 5 (2010), p. e15012
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tomita et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Tomita, K. Miyazaki, Y. Onishi, S. Honda, N. Ishida, K. Oishi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Conserved amino acid residues in C-terminus of PERIOD 2 are involved in interaction with CRYPTOCHROME 1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochim. Biophys. Acta, 1803 (2010), pp. 492–498
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         van der Horst et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.T. van der Horst, M. Muijtjens, K. Kobayashi, R. Takano, S. Kanno, M. Takao, J. de Wit, A. Verkerk, A.P. Eker, D. van Leenen,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mammalian Cry1 and Cry2 are essential for maintenance of circadian rhythms
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 398 (1999), pp. 627–630
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.A. Wang, Y.V. Yu, G. Govindaiah, X. Ye, L. Artinian, T.P. Coleman, J.V. Sweedler, C.L. Cox, M.U. Gillette
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Circadian rhythm of redox state regulates excitability in suprachiasmatic nucleus neurons
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 337 (2012), pp. 839–842
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Weir et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.R. Weir, F. Bonneau, J. Hentschel, E. Conti
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural analysis reveals the characteristic features of Mtr4, a DExH helicase involved in nuclear RNA processing and surveillance
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 107 (2010), pp. 12139–12144
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wu et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.H. Wu, J.A. Thomas, J. Momand
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         p53 protein oxidation in cultured cells in response to pyrrolidine dithiocarbamate: a novel method for relating the amount of p53 oxidation in vivo to the regulation of p53-responsive genes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 351 (2000), pp. 87–93
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Xing et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Xing, L. Busino, T.R. Hinds, S.T. Marionni, N.H. Saifee, M.F. Bush, M. Pagano, N. Zheng
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SCF(FBXL3) ubiquitin ligase targets cryptochromes at their cofactor pocket
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 496 (2013), pp. 64–68
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yagita et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Yagita, F. Tamanini, M. Yasuda, J.H.J. Hoeijmakers, G.T.J. van der Horst, H. Okamura
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleocytoplasmic shuttling and mCRY-dependent inhibition of ubiquitylation of the mPER2 clock protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 21 (2002), pp. 1301–1314
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ye et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Ye, C.P. Selby, N. Ozturk, Y. Annayev, A. Sancar
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemical analysis of the canonical model for the mammalian circadian clock
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 286 (2011), pp. 25891–25902
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yoo et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.-H. Yoo, J.A. Mohawk, S.M. Siepka, Y. Shan, S.K. Huh, H.-K. Hong, I. Kornblum, V. Kumar, N. Koike, M. Xu,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Competing E3 ubiquitin ligases govern circadian periodicity by degradation of CRY in nucleus and cytoplasm
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 152 (2013), pp. 1091–1105
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Young and Kay, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.W. Young, S.A. Kay
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Time zones: a comparative genetics of circadian clocks
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Genet., 2 (2001), pp. 702–715
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.E. Zhang, Y. Liu, R. Dentin, P.Y. Pongsawakul, A.C. Liu, T. Hirota, D.A. Nusinow, X. Sun, S. Landais, Y. Kodama,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cryptochrome mediates circadian regulation of cAMP signaling and hepatic gluconeogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Med., 16 (2010), pp. 1152–1156
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <title>
      Supplemental References
     </title>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Adams et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.D. Adams, P.V. Afonine, G. Bunkóczi, V.B. Chen, I.W. Davis, N. Echols, J.J. Headd, L.W. Hung, G.J. Kapral, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66 (2010), pp. 213–221
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bergfors, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.M. Bergfors
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Crystallization: Techniques, Strategies, and Tips
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         (Second Edition)International University Line, La Jolla, CA (2009)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cowtan, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Cowtan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Buccaneer software for automated model building. 1. Tracing protein chains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 62 (2006), pp. 1002–1011
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         da Silva and Williams, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.J.R.F. da Silva, R.J.P. Williams
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Biological Chemistry of the Elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oxford University Press, Oxford (2001)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Emsley and Cowtan, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Emsley, K. Cowtan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 60 (2004), pp. 2126–2132
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goujon et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Goujon, H. McWilliam, W. Li, F. Valentin, S. Squizzato, J. Paern, R. Lopez
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A new bioinformatics analysis tools framework at EMBL-EBI
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 38 (Web Server issue) (2010), pp. W695–W699
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kabsch, 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Kabsch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Automatic processing of rotation diffraction data from crystals of initially unknown symmetry and cell constants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst., 26 (1993), pp. 795–800
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Krissinel and Henrick, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Krissinel, K. Henrick
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inference of macromolecular assemblies from crystalline state
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 372 (2007), pp. 774–797
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Maier et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Maier, S. Wendt, J.T. Vanselow, T. Wallach, S. Reischl, S. Oehmke, A. Schlosser, A. Kramer
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A large-scale functional RNAi screen reveals a role for CK2 in the mammalian circadian clock
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 23 (2009), pp. 708–718
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McCoy et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. McCoy, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve, P.D. Adams, M.D. Winn, L.C. Storoni, R.J. Read
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phaser crystallographic software
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst., 40 (2007), pp. 658–674
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Palmiter and Findley, 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.D. Palmiter, S.D. Findley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cloning and functional characterization of a mammalian zinc transporter that confers resistance to zinc
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 14 (1995), pp. 639–649
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pattison and Cousins, 1986
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.E. Pattison, R.J. Cousins
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Kinetics of zinc uptake and exchange by primary cultures of rat hepatocytes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Am. J. Physiol., 250 (1986), pp. E677–E685
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Provencher and Glöckner, 1981
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.W. Provencher, J. Glöckner
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Estimation of globular protein secondary structure from circular dichroism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 20 (1981), pp. 33–37
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sievers et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Sievers, A. Wilm, D. Dineen, T.J. Gibson, K. Karplus, W. Li, R. Lopez, H. McWilliam, M. Remmert, J. Söding,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Syst. Biol., 7 (2011), p. 539
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Terwilliger et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.C. Terwilliger, P.D. Adams, R.J. Read, A.J. McCoy, N.W. Moriarty, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve, P.V. Afonine, P.H. Zwart, L.W. Hung
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Decision-making in structure solution using Bayesian estimates of map quality: the PHENIX AutoSol wizard
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 65 (2009), pp. 582–601
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Waterhouse et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.M. Waterhouse, J.B. Procter, D.M.A. Martin, M. Clamp, G.J. Barton
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Jalview Version 2—a multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbench
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioinformatics, 25 (2009), pp. 1189–1191
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>