<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22087277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3210151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-18421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Extracellular Matrix Proteins</subject><subject>Protein Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomacromolecule-Ligand Interactions</subject><subject>Protein Folding</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Analysis Tools</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome-Wide Association Studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Autoimmune Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Crohn Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gastroenterology and Hepatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</subject><subj-group><subject>Crohn Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Protein Characterization of a Candidate Mechanism SNP for Crohn's Disease: The Macrophage Stimulating Protein R689C Substitution</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Candidate SNP for Crohn's Disease: MSP Arg689Cys</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorlatova</surname><given-names>Natalia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>Kinlin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>Lipika R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Araj</surname><given-names>Rawan Hanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galkin</surname><given-names>Andrey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Turko</surname><given-names>Illarion</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herzberg</surname><given-names>Osnat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute for Bioscience and Biotechnology Research, University of Maryland, Rockville, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>National Institute for Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Cell Biology and Molecular Genetics, University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Griffith University, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>jmoult@umd.edu</email> (JM); <email>osnat@umd.edu</email> (OH)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JM OH. Performed the experiments: NG KC LRP AG IT. Analyzed the data: NG LRP IT JM OH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NG KC RHA. Wrote the paper: JM OH.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e27269</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Gorlatova et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>High throughput genome wide associations studies (GWAS) are now identifying a large number of genome loci related to risk of common human disease. Each such locus presents a challenge in identifying the relevant underlying mechanism. Here we report the experimental characterization of a proposed causal single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in a locus related to risk of Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis. The SNP lies in the MST1 gene encoding Macrophage Stimulating Protein (MSP), and results in an R689C amino acid substitution within the &#x003b2;-chain of MSP (MSP&#x003b2;). MSP binding to the RON receptor tyrosine kinase activates signaling pathways involved in the inflammatory response. We have purified wild-type and mutant MSP&#x003b2; proteins and compared biochemical and biophysical properties that might impact the MSP/RON signaling pathway. Surface plasmon resonance (SPR) binding studies showed that MSP&#x003b2; R689C affinity to RON is approximately 10-fold lower than that of the wild-type MSP&#x003b2; and differential scanning fluorimetry (DSF) showed that the thermal stability of the mutant MSP&#x003b2; was slightly lower than that of wild-type MSP&#x003b2;, by 1.6 K. The substitution was found not to impair the specific Arg483-Val484 peptide bond cleavage by matriptase-1, required for MSP activation, and mass spectrometry of tryptic fragments of the mutated protein showed that the free thiol introduced by the R689C mutation did not form an aberrant disulfide bond. Together, the studies indicate that the missense SNP impairs MSP function by reducing its affinity to RON and perhaps through a secondary effect on <italic>in vivo</italic> concentration arising from reduced thermodynamic stability, resulting in down-regulation of the MSP/RON signaling pathway.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Until recently, information on which variants within the human genome contribute to increased risk of common human disease was fragmentary and often statistically weak. New chip based technologies are now providing relatively unbiased and reliable information on which single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are significantly associated with altered risk for a number of common diseases. The current generation of GWAS typically includes several thousand individuals with the disease of interest and a similar number of control individuals without the disease (for example <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Consortium1">[1]</xref>). These studies, and more recently, meta-studies combining data from a number of individual experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Franke1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Teslovich1">[3]</xref> have already led to identification of up to a 100 risk associated loci for some individual diseases. These new data open up the possibility of a deeper understanding of the nature of complex trait disease and consequential advances in treatment, diagnosis, prognosis and prophylaxis. Identification of the mechanism underlying each risk locus is non-trivial, since a typical microarray contains complementary oligos for only 500,000 to a million common SNPs (those with a population allele frequency greater than 1&#x00025;), while the number of known common SNPs is more than 10 times this (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/</ext-link>). It is thus unlikely that a sampled (tag) SNP found to be associated with altered disease risk (a &#x02018;marker&#x02019; SNP) is in fact playing a direct role in the disease mechanism. Rather, because of incomplete recombination within the population, the presence of a marker SNP will be correlated with the presence of the genetic variant actually affecting <italic>in vivo</italic> function, through linkage disequilibrium (LD). For any given marker associated with increased disease risk, each of the SNPs in LD is a candidate for involvement in the disease mechanism. The range of LD varies widely across the genome, and thus the number of candidate SNPs does also, from approximately 100 to of the order of 10,000 in the highly linked MHC region of chromosome 6 (Pal and Moult, unpublished).</p><p>It is likely that, in each locus, no more than one of the many candidate SNPs is involved in disease mechanism. It is also possible that in any given locus none of the identified candidate SNPs is the mechanism for a number of reasons. A mechanism SNP may directly influence phenotype and hence disease risk through a number of known processes, such as amino acid substitutions altering <italic>in vivo</italic> protein function, altered mRNA level via effects on transcription factor binding, microRNA action, message half-life or splicing, and changed translational efficiency through effects on mRNA structure and codon efficiency. Although most disease related loci encompass one or more genes, some are in so-called gene deserts, suggesting additional mechanisms may exist. At present, the relevance of each mechanism is unknown. Also unknown is the distribution of impact levels on protein function &#x02013; how common are subtle changes in gene function versus major changes? The best understood mechanisms are those arising from non-synonymous variants (missense and nonsense single base variants, changing an amino acid in a coding region or truncating the polypeptide chain), which may alter <italic>in vivo</italic> activity of the affected protein by effects on folding and thermodynamic stability, ligand and partner binding, catalysis, allosteric regulation, and post-translational modification. In previous work, we have developed two machine-learning methods for identifying which missense variants have a high impact on protein function. One of these methods makes use of a set of features of protein three-dimensional structure to identify those variants that significantly decrease protein thermodynamic stability, and we have shown that this is the major mechanism in monogenic disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue1">[4]</xref>. The second method makes use of the extent of local sequence conservation and the nature of an amino acid substitution to identify variants that affect <italic>in vivo</italic> function by any missense mechanism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue2">[5]</xref>. The methods have been validated by analysis of a set of variants causative of the monogenic disease phenylketonuria (Shi, Sellers &#x00026; Moult, In press) and a set of common SNPs that have been investigated experimentally <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-AllaliHassani1">[6]</xref>. Application of these methods to missense SNPs in the human genome has shown that approximately a quarter have high impact on protein function <italic>in vivo</italic>, with decrease in protein thermodynamic stability again playing the major role <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue2">[5]</xref>. The high incidence of these high impact SNPs suggests they are likely to play a significant role in common disease. To investigate this possibility, we have now applied the methods to GWAS results from a Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (WTCCC) study of seven common diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Consortium1">[1]</xref> and follow-up studies. The analyses show that about one third of all loci have at least one missense SNP predicted to have a large impact on protein function, and these represent possible molecular mechanisms for those loci. These results support a major role for high impact non-synonymous SNPs.</p><p>Here we present an experimental study of possible molecular mechanisms for a predicted high impact missense SNP in macrophage stimulating protein (MSP, also known as hepatocyte growth factor like protein (HGF-like), associated with a disease related locus for Crohn's disease on chromosome 3. This SNP has earlier been identified as associated with inflammatory bowel disease in a more focused gene centric study UC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Goyette1">[7]</xref>. Recently, the same SNP was reported as associated with the chronic liver disease primary sclerosing cholangitis, a disease that affects 2.4&#x02013;7.5&#x00025; of individuals with inflammatory bowel disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Melum1">[8]</xref>.</p><p>Crohn's disease (CD) and ulcerative colitis (UC) are chronic inflammatory bowel diseases, with a genetic component, and a relatively high heritability of 50&#x02013;60&#x00025; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Sofaer1">[9]</xref>. A series of GWAS and meta GWAS have so far identified 71 and 47 susceptibility loci for CD and UC, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Franke1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Anderson1">[10]</xref>. Genes in these loci span widely distributed functions, but a number are involved in the inflammatory response and in particular in autophagy. As described later, analysis of the locus on chromosome 3, first identified in a GWA study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Consortium1">[1]</xref> identifies a single high impact non-synonymous SNPs in the MST1 gene, resulting in substitution of Arg689 by Cys in the MSP &#x003b2; chain.</p><p>MSP is a component of a signaling pathway that regulates aspects of the innate immune response to infection and cellular stress. MSP and its receptor, RON receptor tyrosine kinase, are involved in macrophage chemotaxis and activation. Macrophage function in normal cell proliferation, adhesion, motility and apoptosis is well documented, and their activity is elevated in many solid tumors. Such elevated activity correlates with metastasis and poor cancer prognosis. Hence, the MSP/RON signaling pathways have been proposed as a potential cancer therapeutic target <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Kretschmann1">[11]</xref>.</p><p>MSP is a serum protein that circulates in the blood as an inactive single-chain precursor (pro-MSP) comprising two chains, &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Wang1">[12]</xref>. Cleavage of the Arg483-Val484 peptide bond yields the mature active MSP &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; heterodimer, linked by a disulfide bond between Cys468 and Cys588. The &#x003b1; chain (MSP&#x003b1;) contains four kringle domains and the &#x003b2; chain (MSP&#x003b2;) adopts a trypsin-like serine protease fold, but lacks the catalytic triad and proteolytic activity. Matriptase-1, a type II transmembrane serine protease expressed on epithelial cells and macrophages, has been shown to specifically cleave and activate pro-MSP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Bhatt1">[13]</xref>.</p><p>The mature form of RON contains two chains (&#x003b1; and &#x003b2;) linked by a disulfide bond. The &#x003b1; chain is entirely extracellular and encodes for the N-terminal half of a Sema domain, a domain unique to the RON/MET subfamily of receptor tyrosine kinases. The &#x003b2; chain comprises an extracellular polypeptide region that includes the C-terminal half of the Sema domain, a PSI domain (acronym for plexin, semaphorins, integrins) and four immunoglobulin-like domains, IPT<sub>1</sub> through IPT<sub>4</sub>. A single transmembrane segment followed by an intracellular tyrosine kinase domain complete the &#x003b2; chain. A gene-focused study has found two non-synonymous SNPs (R523Q and G1335R) of RON to be associated with increased risk of CD and UC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Beckly1">[14]</xref>.</p><p>Several studies established that MSP&#x003b2; binds to the RON Sema domain with high affinity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Danilkovitch1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Waltz1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Wang2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Angeloni1">[18]</xref>. Competitive ELISA experiments showed that MSP&#x003b1; binds weakly to RON Sema-PSI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Angeloni1">[18]</xref> whereas competition experiments with <sup>125</sup>I radiolabeled MSP indicated that MSP&#x003b1; did not bind to RON in intact cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Wang2">[17]</xref> and co-immunoprecipitation assays failed to detect MSP&#x003b1; binding to a RON construct that contained the Sema-PSI and a portion of the ensuing IPT<sub>1</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Ma1">[19]</xref>. By comparison, the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chains of the MSP homolog, HGF, exhibit a reverse trend in the binding affinities to the HGF receptor, MET, which is a homolog of RON <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Matsumoto1">[20]</xref>. A proposed 3-D model based on a combined small-angle X-ray scattering and cryo electron tomography study suggested the interactions of both the HGF &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chains with the MET Sema domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Gherardi1">[21]</xref>. By analogy, it is possible that both &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chains of MSP interact with RON Sema even though the binding of MSP&#x003b1; is weak.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Candidate SNP analysis</title><p>The initial WTCCC GWA Study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Consortium1">[1]</xref> identified nine loci where tag SNPs are significantly associated with increased risk of Crohn's disease. One of these is on chromosome 3, and contains three marker SNPs. Two of these markers are in introns in bassoon (presynaptic cytomatrix protein, BSN, and the third is a synonymous SNP in that gene. The linkage disequilibrium region for chromosome 3 locus, in 3p21, spans 20 genes, an unusually high number. Penetrance analysis finds a total of 148 candidate SNPs, seven of which are non-synonymous (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0027269-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Candidate non-synonymous mechanism SNPs in the Chromosome 3 locus associated with increased risk of Crohn's disease.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0027269-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0027269.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNP ID</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substitution</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Profile Impact<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stability Impact<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs34762726</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A741T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs2005557</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3863A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;0.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs13068038</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCDC36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D430E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;1.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs34823813</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNF123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R854H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;1.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs13072748</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VLLR9392</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R5K</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;1.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs13077498</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C3ORF62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E110K</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;2.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3197999</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MST1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R689C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;0.52</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>Profile and stability impact scores are the outputs from the sequence profile and structure stability support vector machines respectively. Positive scores reflect an assignment of a low or negligible impact on <italic>in vivo</italic> protein function, negative scores an assignment of high impact on protein function. The higher the absolute score, the higher the confidence of the assignment. Scores &#x0003e;|0.5| are considered high confidence. NA indicates there is inadequate sequence or structure information available to make an assignment. (See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Methods</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue2">[5]</xref> for details). Only the SNP in MST1 is assigned a high impact on protein function.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All but two of the non-synonymous SNPs have high confidence profile based assignments of a low impact on <italic>in vivo</italic> function. No assignment is available for the A741T in BSN, but this gene is an unlikely candidate on biological grounds, since it is involved in neuronal development, and only expressed in brain. The single high confidence high impact assignment is for rs3197999 in MST1, resulting in the substitution of an arginine by a cysteine, at position 689 of MSP. This SNP is in almost complete LD with the marker (R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.95). The sequence profile analysis classifies this substitution as high impact on protein function, with a high confidence support vector machine (SVM) score (&#x02212;1.13), primarily determined by the facts that close orthologs all have an arginine at this position and no homolog has a cysteine. In contrast, the structure method classifies the change as benign (high confidence SVM score of 0.52). Thus the initial computational analysis suggests this SNP is the only known high impact non-synonymous candidate in the chromosome 3 locus, and impacts the function of MSP <italic>in vivo</italic> through some mechanism unrelated to protein stability. The MSP R689C substitution lies on the surface of the MSP &#x003b2;-chain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref>. The computational results may reflect a role for this residue in a number of processes that could be disrupted by the amino acid substitution and so contribute to Crohn's disease susceptibility. Principle among these are a reduction in binding affinity to RON Sema, structural perturbation resulting from an incorrect disulfide bond formed with the newly introduced cysteine, or impaired activation of pro-MSP by matriptase-1. To examine the contributions of these effects, we undertook to characterize the MSP&#x003b2; and its interaction with RON extra cellular domain constructs <italic>in vitro</italic> using well-purified proteins. Although the computational analysis classified the substitution as not affecting protein stability, and the surface location supported that analysis, we nevertheless also measured the change in protein stability resulting from the substitution to directly determine any contribution from this factor.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Thermostability of MSP&#x003b2;</title><p>DSF is a useful technique for rapid assessment of protein thermal stability. With this approach, the proteins are subjected to gradually increasing temperature and the difference between the melting temperatures (T<sub>m</sub>) of two samples being compared is measured using a fluorescent dye (SYPRO Orange was used in the current study) whose emission properties change upon interaction with unfolded protein. MSP&#x003b2; has a single glycosylation site and was produced in <italic>Drosophilae melanogaster</italic> Schneider 2 (S2) cells, which may yield a different glycosylation pattern than that produced in human cells, and hence different protein stability. To determine whether the trend of thermal stability change of the wild-type and MSP&#x003b2; R689C remain the same upon changes in glycosylation, the proteins were deglycosylated and their thermal stabilities were examined in addition to those of the glycosylated proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The T<sub>m</sub> values (the midpoint of the melting curves) were calculated as the maximum of the first derivative of the melting curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g001">Fig. 1 A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>MSP&#x003b2; thermal stability monitored by DSF.</title><p>Four representative experiments are shown, one for each MSP&#x003b2;: Wild-type glycosylated, wild-type deglycosylated, glycosylated R689C, and deglycosylated R689C. The melting curves were measured by heating the samples at a rate of 2&#x000b0;C per minute (B). The T<sub>m</sub> values were calculated as the maximum of the first derivative of the melting curves (A). The first derivative values (dF/dT) are normalized and given in &#x00025;, where 100&#x00025; corresponds to the highest peak of the entire experiment set. The fluorescence values are on an arbitrary scale (AU). <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t002">Table 2</xref> provides the T<sub>m</sub> values. The R689C variant melts at approximately 2.5 K lower temperature than the wild type for the deglycosylated protein and 1.6 K lower for the glycosylated form.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g001"/></fig><p>The melting curves of the glycosylated proteins reveal a clear decrease in the T<sub>m</sub> value of the mutant protein compared with wild-type MSP&#x003b2; (&#x00394;T<sub>m</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.6 K, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t002">Table 2</xref>). The glycosylation status of MSP&#x003b2; strongly influences the thermal stability of the protein. The melting curves of both deglycosylated wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; show a striking decrease in the T<sub>m</sub> values compared with their glycosylated counterparts (&#x00394;T<sub>m</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.8 K for wild-type and 4.7 K for R689C MSP&#x003b2;, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t001">Table 1</xref>). The destabilizing effect of the R689C mutation is more pronounced with the deglycosylated MSP&#x003b2;s (&#x00394;T<sub>m</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 K) than it is with the glycosylated proteins.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0027269-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Melting temperatures of wild-type and R689C MSP &#x003b2;-domain.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0027269-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0027269.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>m</sub> (&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref> (&#x000b0;C)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT: glycosylated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R689C: glycosylated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R689C dimer: glycosylated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT: deglycosylated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R689C: deglycosylated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>The standard deviations were calculated from four independent melting curves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Together, the DSF data show that MSP&#x003b2; R689C is destabilized compared with wild type MSP&#x003b2;. However, the stability decrease is likely too small an effect to have a significant impact in <italic>in vivo</italic> protein function. Examination of data for proteins where both &#x00394;T<sub>m</sub> and &#x00394;&#x00394;G data are available, such as barnase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Axe1">[23]</xref>, subtilisin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Pantoliano1">[24]</xref>, Plasminogen activator kringle domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Kelley1">[25]</xref>, and T4 lysozyme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Baase1">[26]</xref>, shows a 1 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> change in free energy difference between the folded and unfolded states typically corresponds to a 3 to 4 K change in melting temperature. On this basis, for glycosylated MSP, the destabilization is probably in the range 0.5 to 0.8 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In contrast to this, monogenic disease causing mutations that act in a manner consistent with destabilization typically have a loss of stability of at least 2 to 3 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue1">[4]</xref>. The simplest model of the relationship between loss of stability and lower effective <italic>in vivo</italic> protein activity through increased concentration of the unfolded species supports an exponential relationship between the amount of destabilization and the expected change in concentration of unfolded protein, such that whereas a typical monogenic disease causing mutation increases the concentration of unfolded protein by approximately 100 fold, the destabilization resulting from this SNP is expected to cause an increase of approximately 3 fold. Nevertheless, the MSP variant may still have a modest effect on <italic>in vivo</italic> protein concentration.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>R689C MSP&#x003b2; free cysteine assignment</title><p>As explained in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Methods</xref>, TPS chromatography coupled with trypsin digestion and mass-spectrometry analyses was employed to identify free cysteines in MSP&#x003b2; R689C. The recombinant MSP&#x003b2; was engineered following the strategy employed for the crystal structure determination, including 19 amino acids of the linker to the &#x003b1;-chain, to enable formation of the physiologically relevant five disulfide bonds: Cys468-Cys588, Cys507-Cys523, Cys527-Cys562, Cys602-Cys667, Cys657-Cys685. Another cysteine, Cys672, is located in close proximity to the Cys468-Cys588 disulfide bond connecting the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chains. To avoid an aberrant disulfide bond, Cys672 was mutated into Ser. Thus, if all disulfide bonds formed correctly in the R689C MSP&#x003b2; mutant, only the peptide that includes Cys689 would be detected. Trypsin cleaves peptides primarily after arginine residues. The arginine-flanked peptide sequence that spans Cys689 is: Arg687-Ser688-Cys689-Trp690-Pro691-Ala692-Val793-Phe694-Thr-695-Arg696. Only a single major peptide of R689C MSP&#x003b2; was eluted from the TPS column. The peptide was sequenced by mass spectrometry as: Ser-Cys-Trp-Ala-Val-Phe-Thr-Arg, confirming that Cys689 did not form an aberrant disulphide bond. Thus, there is no evidence of an incorrect intramolecular disulfide bond.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Analysis of MSP&#x003b2;-RON interaction by SPR</title><p>Binding of the wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; (including 19 amino acid of the MSP &#x003b1;-chain) to four immobilized extracellular variants of RON were measured by Surface Plasmon Resonance (SPR). The SPR data complement previous co-immunoprecipitation studies that concluded that MSP&#x003b2; binds to the RON Sema domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Angeloni1">[18]</xref>. In addition, the current study define <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> values under the SPR experimental conditions for both wild type and mutant MSP&#x003b2;. Representative binding sensorgrams are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g002">Figure 2</xref>. The curves show that both wild type and R689C MSPs bind to RON Sema, Sema-PSI, Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>, and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>. The binding curves were fitted globally to a 1&#x02236;1 Langmuir kinetic model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t003">Table 3</xref>), yielding a 10&#x02013;13 fold tighter binding for the wild-type MSP&#x003b2; (13.5&#x02013;21.2 nM) compared with the mutant MSP&#x003b2; (148&#x02013;233 nM). Because the on and off binding rates were quite high, <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> values were also calculated using an equilibrium model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Consistent with the kinetic model, the equilibrium model yielded a 7&#x02013;8 fold tighter binding for the wild-type MSP&#x003b2; (16.4&#x02013;32.0 nM) compared with the MSP&#x003b2; R689C (139&#x02013;244 nM). In addition, the binding data show that the protein-protein interaction may be attributed primarily to the RON Sema domain alone with no significant contribution of the PSI and the four IPT domains, consistent with the reported 90&#x00025; inhibition of MSP&#x003b2; binding to immobilized full length RON by Sema or Sema-PSI using competitive ELISA experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Angeloni1">[18]</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Sensorgrams of wild-type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; binding to immobilized RON extracellular domain constructs.</title><p>The binding curves in each sensogram correspond to increasing concentrations of the analyte in 2-fold dilution steps: 4, 8, 16, 32, 64, 128, 256, and 512 nM. The eight experiments correspond to immobilized: (A,E) RON Sema. (B,F) RON Sema-PSI. (C,G) RON Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>. (D,H) RON Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>. The response units (RU) were corrected for nonspecific binding relative to a blank flow cell surface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone-0027269-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>SPR equilibrium analysis of binding to immobilized binding to immobilized RON-Sema.</title><p>(A) Wild-type and (B) R689C MSP&#x003b2;. The inserts show the Scatchard plots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0027269-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>SPR binding kinetics of wild-type and R689C MSP &#x003b2;-chain to the RON domains.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0027269-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0027269.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analyte</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>on</sub>(M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7; s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>off</sub>(s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (nM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (nM)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">construct<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02236;1 Langmuir</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equilibrium model</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt MSP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SP-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPI-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPI<sub>4</sub>-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R689C MSP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SP-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPI-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPI<sub>4</sub>-RON</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.0</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p>abbreviations: S &#x02013; Sema, SP &#x02013; Sema-PSI, SPI &#x02013; Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>, SPI<sub>4</sub> &#x02013; Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The SPR MSP&#x003b2;/RON binding affinity is approximately 100-fold tighter than that between the homologous MET Sema-PSI and HGF&#x003b2; as measured using the same SPR technique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Holmes1">[27]</xref>. In contrast, the MET Sema-PSI SPR studies showed 10-fold tighter binding affinity to a HGF&#x003b1; construct than to HGF&#x003b2;. An analogous SPR study of MSP&#x003b1; binding to RON domains has not been reported; however, ELISA studies suggested that MSP&#x003b1; binding affinity for RON is over 50-fold weaker than that of MSP&#x003b2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Danilkovitch1">[15]</xref>. The apparent low contribution of MSP&#x003b1; to RON binding implies that the 10-fold reduced RON binding affinity of MSP&#x003b2; R689C cannot be masked by the RON/MSP&#x003b1; interaction.</p><p>To further examine the RON/MSP&#x003b2; interaction, competition SPR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Nieba1">[28]</xref> experiments measured capture of monomeric MSP&#x003b2; from pre-equilibrated Sema/MSP&#x003b2; and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>/MSP&#x003b2; analyte mixtures to immobilized RON Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The results confirmed that the Sema domain alone competes with the RON Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> for MSP&#x003b2; binding. The calculated dissociation constants for wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t003">Table 3</xref>) were consistent with those calculated from the direct SPR binding experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0027269-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>SPR competition assays.</title><p>(A&#x02013;D) Bindings to immobilized RON-Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>4</sub> of mixtures containing MSP&#x003b2; with varying concentrations of RON-Sema or RON-Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>4</sub>. (E&#x02013;H) The dependence of free MSP&#x003b2; concentrations on RON concentration in the solution mixtures. The free MSP&#x003b2; concentrations were determined from the measured relative response based on a calibration curve.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g004"/></fig><p>Together, the SPR binding experiments show that the R689C MSP&#x003b2; exhibits approximately 10-fold lower binding affinity to its receptor compared with the wild type MSP&#x003b2;. The reduced affinity might impair the biological function of the MSP/RON signaling system.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Structural consequences of the R689C mutation</title><p>The crystal structure of MSP&#x003b2; shows that Arg689 is located on a surface loop, fully exposed to solvent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref>. However, a symmetry-related molecule packs close to Arg689 in the crystals such that the side chain of Arg689 stacks against the side chain of Trp593 on a neighboring molecule, generating an energetically favorable &#x003c0;-&#x003c0; interaction that contributes to crystal stability. MSP&#x003b2; exists as monomers in solution, thus such an inter-molecular interaction is unlikely. Instead, the structure reveals that Arg689 side-chain orientation may readily adjust to form an intra-molecular salt bridge between the Arg689 and Glu648 side chains and concomitantly form a hydrogen bond between the guanidinium group and the backbone carbonyl of Gly649 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Both Glu648 and Gly649 reside on a loop adjacent to the Arg689 loop, thus these interactions may contribute to protein stability. In contrast, a cysteine at position 689 cannot form analogous interactions, which may explain the modest reduction in protein stability associated with the R689C MSP&#x003b2;.</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Side chain conformation of Arg689 in the MSP&#x003b2; crystal and modeled structures.</title><p>In the crystal structure (yellow), the side chain is involved in inter molecular crystal contacts, and in the modeled conformation (cyan) it forms an intra molecular salt bridge with Glu648 and a hydrogen bond with Gly649 backbone carbonyl. These interactions, if present or partly present in solution, may contribute the modest change in proteins stability introduced by the R689C substitution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g005"/></fig><p>A model of the MSP&#x003b2;/RON-Sema complex was generated using the structures of the individual proteins super positioned on the HGF&#x003b2;/MET-Sema <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Stamos1">[29]</xref>, as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">methods</xref> section. This model places Arg689 outside the protein-protein interface, with the guanidinium group minimally 11 &#x000c5; away from the carboxylate of Glu149 on RON Sema, the closest residue on the receptor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Based on the model, substitutions at this position are unlikely to affect protein-protein affinity. Yet, the SPR studies showed that the R689C MSP&#x003b2; exhibited approximately 10-fold reduced affinity towards RON constructs compared with the wild-type MSP&#x003b2;.</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Model of the structure of MSP&#x003b2;/RON Sema complex.</title><p>Arg689 and the location of the &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; cleavage site are highlighted in magenta color. The molecular surfaces are shown in transparent colors. The model was built by super positioning the crystal structures of MSP&#x003b2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref> (PDB entry 1ASU) and RON-Sema-PSI (Chao and Herzberg, unpublished) on the crystal structure of the HGF&#x003b2;/MET-Sema-PSI complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Stamos1">[29]</xref> (PDB entry 1SHY). In this model, Arg689 is not directly involved in the RON/MSP interface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g006"/></fig><p>A site directed mutagenesis study of a different MSP variant, R683Q, found no MSP/RON binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Danilkovitch1">[15]</xref>. The MSP&#x003b2;/RON-Sema model places Arg683 at the protein-protein interface, by analogy with HGF&#x003b2;'s Arg695. However, whereas the HGF Arg695 interacts with a MET tyrosine residue (Tyr125), the tyrosine counterpart on RON is an alanine residue (Ala128), which cannot participate in a guanidinium-aromatic interaction. Indeed, many of the interface residues are not conserved between MET Sema and Ron Sema or between HGF&#x003b2; and MSP&#x003b2;, consistent with the mutual exclusivity of the RON/MSP and MET/HGF pairing specificities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Gaudino1">[30]</xref>. Together, the SPR binding studies and the mutagenesis information support the notion that the protein-protein interfaces of the two systems resemble but are not identical to one another. Therefore, accurate mapping of the relationship between the Arg689 mutation site and the MSP&#x003b2;/RON Sema interface requires the structure determination of the MSP&#x003b2;/RON Sema complex.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>MSP activation</title><p>The extracellular serine protease domain of the macrophage transmembrane protease, matriptase-1, activates pro-MSP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Bhatt1">[13]</xref> by specifically cleaving the &#x003b1;-&#x003b2; single polypeptide chain between Arg483 and Val484 to generate &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chains that are linked by a single disulfide bond between Cys468 and Cys588. The Arg483-Val484 peptide has been cleaved in the crystal structure and Val484 is buried in the protein core. Because the exact position of the Arg483-Val484 peptide on the protein surface prior to cleavage is unknown, the adjacent Gly486, positioned on the MSP&#x003b2; surface, is also highlighted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g006">Figure 6</xref>. This illustrates that Arg689 is located remotely from the activation site, and thus the substitution by a cysteine is not likely to impair the peptide bond cleavage directly. Nevertheless, the transient MSP/matriptase interface formed during proteolysis might span large surface area and engage Arg689 such that the R689C substitution might interfere with this interaction and compromise MSP activation. Therefore, we investigated the cleavage by matriptase-1 of both wild type and mutant MSP&#x003b2;, both of which contain the fused 19 C-terminal amino acid of MSP&#x003b1;. The cleaved and uncleaved proteins migrate the same distance on a SDS-PAGE gel under non-reducing conditions. In contrast, SDS-PAGE analysis under reducing conditions breaks the disulfide bonds and discriminates between the uncleaved &#x003b2;-chain and the shorter cleaved &#x003b2; chain that now lacks the MSP&#x003b1; 19 amino acid fragment. The experiment shows that incubation of the wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; variants with matriptase-1 as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">methods</xref> section followed by SDS-PAGE analysis under reducing conditions yields cleaved wild-type and mutant proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027269-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Thus, the substitution does not interfere with MSP activation.</p><fig id="pone-0027269-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027269.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>MSP&#x003b2; SDS-PAGE performed at reducing conditions to assess cleavage by matriptase-1.</title><p>Samples of MSP&#x003b2; fused to the 19 C-terminal amino acids of MSP&#x003b1; before and after 4 hrs incubation with matriptase-1 at 37&#x000b0;C were applied. Lane 1 &#x02013; wild type MSP&#x003b2;; Lane 2 &#x02013; wild type MSP&#x003b2; after incubation with matriptase-1; Lane 3 &#x02013; R689C MSP&#x003b2;; Lane 4 &#x02013; R689C MSP&#x003b2; after incubation with matriptase-1; M &#x02013; molecular weight markers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Disulfide bridge formation and intramolecular interactions</title><p>Finally, there are two other potential consequences of the R689C mutation. First, as MSP is an extracellular protein, the free cysteine might form an inter molecular disulfide bond to generate MSP dimers that could interfere with binding to RON. SDS-PAGE under non-reducing conditions of a sample that was stored at 4&#x000b0;C for over six months revealed small amounts of MSP&#x003b2; dimers. This dimeric protein was purified by gel filtration chromatography and its thermal stability was shown by DSF to be 1.5 K lower than that of the monomeric MSP&#x003b2; R689C (T<sub>m</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;68.7&#x000b0;C). The dimeric MSP&#x003b2; binding affinities towards RON constructs were unimpaired and were actually comparable with those of wild type MSP&#x003b2; (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.7&#x02013;4.9 nM), perhaps owing to avidity effects. Investigation of the presence of MSP dimers in individuals carrying the R689C mutation would be required to determine whether dimerization plays a role <italic>in vivo</italic>. Nevertheless, these results suggest that even if dimers were formed, RON binding would not be impaired.</p><p>Second, it remains unknown whether MSP&#x003b2; interacts closely with any of the &#x003b1; chain domains, and which of the MSP domains mediates the physiological dimerization of RON. If the Arg689 plays a role in such interactions, the R689C mutation might have a negative effect on function. Studies of the entire activated MSP containing both the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; chain and its effect on RON dimerization would be required to shed light on these issues. Clearly, the cellular system is more complex than that studied <italic>in vitro</italic>; nevertheless, the different properties of the mutant MSP&#x003b2; compared with the wild type MSP&#x003b2; are significant and might contribute to the impaired biological function.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Computational analysis of the GWAS results for the chromosome 3 Crohn's disease associated locus identifies the SNP resulting in the MSP&#x003b2; R689C amino acid substitution as the only known viable missense candidate for involvement in disease mechanism in the locus. Computational impact analysis provides evidence that R689C is expected to have a significant effect on the <italic>in vivo</italic> function of the protein through some mechanism other than thermodynamic destabilization. Further support for the involvement of that SNP comes from its association with disease risk in a targeted gene study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Goyette1">[7]</xref>. These results alone provide suggestive evidence for a role of the SNP in the disease, but the substitution might have an insignificant effect on <italic>in vivo</italic> function; or a mechanism other than missense, such as an effect on expression or translation, could be involved in this locus; or an unknown genetic variant in LD with the marker might be responsible. A number of possible functional impacts at the protein level have been examined. The results show that the substitution does not lead to non-native disulfide bond formation or impairment of the activation by matriptase-1. There is also a modest reduction in protein stability that might play a minor role. The major finding is that the substitution reduces the binding affinity to the RON receptor tyrosine kinase by an amount likely to seriously affect signaling: Assuming the <italic>in vivo</italic> concentration of RON and MSP are well below the <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> value of the complex, the lower affinity will result in an order of magnitude lower concentration of the signaling complex, likely reducing the normal function of the MSP/RON signaling pathway substantially. This in turn is likely to alter the inflammatory response, particularly the level of macrophage activity. Some Crohn's patients exhibit lower than normal macrophage response, providing further circumstantial evidence for such a mechanism.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Identification of candidate non-synonymous SNPs</title><p>As noted earlier, association studies identify those SNPs included in a microarray (tag SNPs) that are associated with an increased risk of disease. A marker may itself be involved in disease mechanism, or more probably, is in LD with one or more mechanism SNPs. Thus, given a set of marker SNPs in a susceptibility locus, we require the set of possible mechanism candidates. The availability of linkage disequilibrium data in Hapmap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Altshuler1">[31]</xref> provides a basis for obtaining such a list. A common approach is to extract all SNPs in strong LD with one or more markers in a locus from Hapmap LD information. This method omits viable candidates less strongly linked to the markers. A more rigorous approach is to impute the likely genotypes in each individual in the study for each Hapmap SNP not included in the microarray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Marchini1">[32]</xref>. Since the genotypes of SNPs in weak LD with the markers cannot be imputed with certainty, the resulting probability of altered SNP frequency is underestimated. Imputation also requires the full data for individuals to be included in the study, which is not always easily available. We have introduced an alternative approach, designed to be easily applied to any dataset, and to produce an inclusive set of candidates. The method selects as candidates all SNPs for which the penetrance (the probability of having the disease, given the presence of a particular SNP) is as high or higher than that of the marker SNPs in a locus. That is:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027269.e001"/></disp-formula>where P(D|c) is the probability of an individual having the disease, given they carry the candidate allele &#x02018;c&#x02019;, and P(D|m) is the probability of an individual having the disease, given they carry the marker allele. Penetrances are calculated from Hapmap data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Altshuler1">[31]</xref> and the population frequencies of the marker and candidate SNPs. In addition, any SNP for which the linkage disequilibrium correlation r<sup>2</sup>&#x0003e;&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.8 is included.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Identification of high impact non-synonymous candidate SNPs</title><p>Identification of SNPs that significantly destabilize the folded structure of a protein molecule <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue1">[4]</xref>. A set of structural effects, such as reduction in hydrophobic area, over-packing, backbone strain, and loss of electrostatic interactions, is used to represent the impact of single residue mutations on protein stability. A SVM was trained on a set of mutations causative of monogenic disease (extracted from an early version of the Human Gene Mutation Database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Krawczak1">[33]</xref>) and a control set of non-disease causing mutations. In jack-knifed testing, the method identifies 74&#x00025; of disease mutations with a false positive rate of 15&#x00025;. The apparent false negative rate includes both true false negatives (cases where stability is involved, and the method classification is incorrect) and cases where the contribution to disease arises from some factor other than stability. When only higher confidence assignments are included (those with an SVM score &#x0003c;&#x02212;0.5), the false positive rate is 11&#x00025;. Use of the method to evaluate a set of <italic>in-vitro</italic> mutagenesis data with the SVM established that the majority of monogenic disease mutations affect protein stability by 1 to 3 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue1">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Identification of high impact SNPs through amino acid sequence conservation properties: The extent of family sequence conservation and types of residue observed at a non-synonymous SNP position are considered. The more restricted the amino acid, the more likely that a different or unusual residue at that position will be deleterious to protein function. A SVM is also used to identify high impact substitutions in this model, using the same disease and control datasets as for the stability method. In jack-knifed testing, the method identifies 80&#x00025; of disease mutations with a false positive rate of 10&#x00025; (for high confidence assignments, 16&#x00025; and 6&#x00025; false negative and false positive rates, respectively). This method has the advantage that it does not require knowledge of structure and so can be applied to a larger fraction of SNPs. It has the disadvantage that it provides no direct insight into the nature of the impact on protein function. (See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Yue2">[5]</xref> for a full description).</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Production and purification of recombinant RON extracellular domain constructs</title><p>The extracellular region of the human MST1R gene was amplified from the pMSCVneo-hRON-2HA clone (kindly provided by Dr. Pamela A. Hankey, Penn State University) and was ligated into a BglII/AgeI digested pMT/BiP/V5-HisA vector for secreted expression as a C-terminal non-cleavable His<sub>6</sub>-tagged recombinant protein in <italic>Drosophilae melanogaster</italic> Schneider 2 (S2) cells (Drosophila Expression System, Invitrogen). The putative furin cleavage site in the RON Sema domain (Lys305-Arg306-Arg307-Arg308-Arg309-Gly310-Ala311) was mutated to a thrombin (Lys305-Leu306-Val307-Pro308-Arg309-Gly310-Ser311) or a TEV protease (Glu304-Lys305-Arg306-Tyr307-Arg308-Gln309-Gly310) cleavage site. The recombinant proteins contain two residues (Arg23 and Ser24) at the N-terminus and eight amino acids (Thr684, Gly685, and His686-His691) at the C-terminus, derived from the expression vector. Four different RON constructs were engineered: Sema (Glu25-Gly524), Sema-PSI (Glu25-Pro568), Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub> (Glu25-Glu683), and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> (Glu25-Ser956). The sequences of all expression clones were confirmed by DNA sequencing.</p><p><italic>Drosophilae melanogaster</italic> S2 cells were transfected with the RON expression vectors and pCoPuro, and stable transfectants resistant to puromycin were selected. The amount of protein in the conditioned serum free media (HyClone SFX) was determined by Western blot analysis with the Penta-His monoclonal Antibody (Qiagen) and clonal selection of stable transfectants was conducted to obtain clones with improved expression levels. For large-scale expression, stable S2 cells were grown in shaker flasks at 28&#x000b0;C and protein expression from the metallothionin promoter was induced by the addition of 0.6 mM CuSO<sub>4</sub>. The cells were removed by centrifugation &#x0223c;4&#x02013;5 days post induction and the cell-free conditioned medium was applied directly onto a Chelating Sparse Fast Flow column, pre-equilibrated in MilliQ water (GE Health Sciences) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Lehr1">[34]</xref>. The resin was washed with phosphate buffered saline followed by 0.5 M NaCl to remove nonspecifically bound proteins and contaminants. The bound protein was eluted with 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, containing 50&#x02013;500 mM Imidazole and fractionated sequentially with 45&#x00025; and 80&#x00025; ammonium sulfate. The eluted protein was purified using the Sephacryl S200 size exclusion chromatography (GE Health Sciences) in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 0.10 M NaCl, 0.5 mM ethylene-diamine-tetra-acetic acid (EDTA). Purification of the RON Sema-PSI-IPT1<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> required an additional ion-exchange chromatographic step using Source 30Q.</p><p>Protein purity and identity were monitored by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and western analysis using the Penta-His monoclonal antibody (Qiagen). The concentration of RON Sema, Sema-PSI, Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub> and Sema-PSI-IPT1<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> were determined using the extinction coefficients of 27,235 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 42,745 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 44,485 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and 67,695 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. The protein yields per liter of conditioned medium were &#x0223c;1 mg, &#x0223c;1.5 mg, &#x0223c;2.5 mg, and 0.2 mg, respectively. Size exclusion chromatography and MiniDawn TREOS multiangle light scattering (Wyatt Technology) indicated that the protein was monomeric. Matrix-assisted laser desorption time-of-flight (MALDI-TOF) spectrometric analysis of the RON recombinant proteins gave MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;56,444&#x000b1;313 Da for Sema (&#x0223c;&#x00394;1957 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;54,487 Da), 64,039&#x000b1;162 Da for Sema-PSI (&#x0223c;&#x00394;4710 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;59,329 Da), 77,689&#x000b1;2 35 Da for Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub> (&#x0223c;&#x00394;5789 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;71,908 Da) and 108,971&#x000b1;366 Da for IPT1<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>. (&#x0223c;&#x00394;8308 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;100,663 Da). The higher molecular masses are attributed to post-translational modifications. The NetNGlyc web server predicts 8 potential N-glycosylation sites for the amino acid sequence Asn-Xaa-Ser/Thr, four on the Sema domain and one on each IPT domain (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetNGlyc/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetNGlyc/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Production and purification of recombinant wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2;</title><p>The recombinant human MSP&#x003b2; was contracted from the MSP cDNA (clone ID: 5190966, Open Biosystems) following the design strategy employed for the protein production that yielded the crystal structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref> except that the protein for the current study was produced in S2 cells. The recombinant MSP&#x003b2; was cloned into AvaI/PmeI sites of the pMT/BiP/V5-HisC vector (Invitrogen). It includes the adjoining N-terminal 19 amino acid residues of the &#x003b1;-chain (residues Phe465-Gly711). Cys672 was mutated to a serine (Quick Change&#x02122;<sub>,</sub> Stratagene) to prevent formation of a wrong disulphide bond owing to the unpaired Cys672, which is located close to two other cysteine residues that form a disulfide bond <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref>. This variant will be referred to as the wild type protein. The mutation, R689C, associated with CD and UC was engineered as well. The wild type and mutant MSP&#x003b2; constructs were confirmed by DNA sequencing.</p><p>Drosophila S2 cells (Invitrogen) were transfected with the MSP&#x003b2; wild type or R689C expression vectors and pCoBlast, and stable transfectants resistant to blasticidin were selected. For protein production, stable transfectants were grown in SFX medium supplemented with 20 mM L-glutamine. Protein expression was induced with 0.5 mM CuSO4. The cells were removed by centrifugation 4 days post induction. The conditioned medium was consecutively passed through Chelex 100 (BioRad) and QSepharose FF (GE Health Sciences) resins to remove Cu<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>, DNA, and some contaminating proteins. The QSepharose flow-through fraction was concentrated with QuixStand Cross flow concentrator (Amersham Biosciences) and applied on Talon Co<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-chelated Sepharose resin (Clontech), equilibrated with 50 mM potassium phosphate (pH 7.5), 0.5 M NaCl and 10 mM Imidazole. The His-tagged MSP&#x003b2; was eluted by the above buffer containing 150 mM Imidazole and further purified on Superdex 200 HR column (GE Health Sciences) equilibrated in 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), and 100 mM NaCl. Size exclusion chromatography and multiangle light scattering showed that the protein existed in solution as monomers.</p><p>Protein concentrations were determined by using molar extinction coefficient at 280 nm of 50,920 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The purification yielded &#x0223c;2 mg MSP&#x003b2; from 1 liter of conditioned medium. MALDI-TOF spectrometric analysis of the wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; recombinant proteins gave MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;29,260&#x000b1;33 Da (&#x0223c;&#x00394;916 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;28,344) and 29,370&#x000b1;42 Da (&#x0223c;&#x00394;1096 Da greater than the calculated MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;28,274), respectively. MSP&#x003b2; has a single potential N-glycosylation site at Asn615. Thus, the difference in molecular mass is consistent with post-translational modification at a single glycosylation site containing 6&#x02013;7 sugar units.</p><p>Both wild type and mutant MSP&#x003b2; were treated with the glycoamidase PNGase F to removed the N-glycosyl group. The recombinant PNGase F from <italic>Elizabethkingia miricola</italic> (ATTC 33958D) was produced in house as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Loo1">[35]</xref>. A solution containing 100&#x02236;1 ratio of MSP&#x003b2; and PNGase F in 50 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.5) was incubated for 3 h at 37&#x000b0;C. The deglycosylated MSP&#x003b2; was purified by size-exclusion chromatography on Superdex 200 HR column in 20 mM MES buffer (pH 6.0) and 100 mM NaCl. The MALDI-TOF analyses yielded MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;28,260&#x000b1;18 Da and MW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;28,362&#x000b1;22 Da for the wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2;, respectively, consistent with the theoretical molecular mass of the non-glycosylated proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Differential Scanning Fluorimetry</title><p>The DSF experiments were performed using a Mastercycler ep realplex quantitative real-time (RT) PCR system (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany). The MSP&#x003b2; samples were subjected to heating as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Vedadi1">[36]</xref>. Briefly, protein stock solutions (0.5 mg/mL) in 10 mM Na<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>HEPES buffer (pH 7.3), 150 mM NaCl, were mixed with freshly diluted Sypro Orange (10&#x000d7;) (Invitrogen, Paisley, Scotland, U.K.) to generate 20 &#x000b5;L reaction solutions in a Fast Optical 96-well plate (Applied Biosystems). After sealing the plate with an optical adhesive film (Applied Biosystems) and centrifugation, the sample were monitored in the RT-PCR instrument as follows. The heating protocol comprised a pre-warming step at 30&#x000b0;C for 120 s and a subsequent heating gradient from 30 to 90&#x000b0;C at 2&#x000b0;C/min steps. Data were collected using a ROX dye (Applied Biosystems) calibration detection settings. The melting curves were obtained for the glycosylated and deglycosylated forms MSP&#x003b2; wild type and R689C. The melting temperature (T<sub>m</sub>) of each melting curve was calculated as the maximum of the first derivative of the curve. The average T<sub>m</sub> value of each protein was determined from four distinct melting curves.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Free cysteine identification in R689C MSP&#x003b2;</title><p>Thiopropyl Sepharose 6B (TPS) reacts with proteins containing free thiol groups under non-reducing conditions to form disulfide bonds, allowing the separation of peptides containing reduced thiol groups from those containing disulfide bonds. TPS chromatography coupled with trypsin digestion and mass-spectrometry analyses identified the free cysteine in MSP&#x003b2; R689C as follows. MSP&#x003b2; R689C, covalently bound to TPS beads (GE Life Sciences) in 50 mM NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub> buffer (pH 7.7), was treated with trypsin (Sigma-Aldrich) at 1&#x02236;25 (w/w) enzyme/substrtate ratio for 40 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Following proteolysis, the TPS beads were washed with buffer containing 50 mM NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub> (pH 7.7) and 150 mM NaCl to remove non-specifically bound cleavage fragments. The bound peptides were eluted from the column in the presence of 10 mM DTT. The eluted fractions were treated with 50 mM iodoacetamide for 60 min at room temperature. Small fraction aliquots were then mixed with equal volumes of 10 mg/mL &#x003b1;-cyano-4-hydroxycinnamic acid dissolved in 50&#x00025; acetonitrile and 0.1&#x00025; TFA, and spotted onto an ABI 01-192-6-AB target plate. Mass spectrometry (MS) analysis was performed using an AB4700 Proteomics Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Framingham, MA, USA). MS-mode acquisitions consisted of 1,000 laser shots averaged over 20 sample positions. For MS/MS-mode acquisitions, 3,000 laser shots were averaged over 30 sample positions for post-source decay fragments. Automated combined acquisition of MS and MS/MS data was controlled with the 4000 Series Explorer software 3.0. Data analysis was performed with the GPS Explorer software 3.5 utilizing Mascot 2.0 (MatrixScience, London, UK) as the search engine. During searching, the mass tolerance was 0.08 Da for the precursor ions and 0.2 Da for the fragment ions. Because of the presence of the R689C mutation, data analysis was also performed manually using the monoisotopic masses of tryptic peptides predicted for MSP&#x003b2; R689C by the PeptideMass software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ca.expasy.org/tools/peptide-mass.html">http://ca.expasy.org/tools/peptide-mass.html</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>Surface Plasmon Resonance</title><p>Binding of wild type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; to the various extracellular RON domain combinations was measured using a Biacore T100 (GE Health Sciences). Purified Sema, Sema-PSI, Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>, and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>4</sub> were covalently coupled in a random orientation through their primary amine groups to the carboxymethylated dextran matrix of a CM5 sensor chip (Series S; GE Health Sciences) according to the manufacturer protocol. All proteins were diluted to a concentration of 15 &#x000b5;g/mL in 10 mM Na<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>Acetate (pH 4.0 for Sema and Sema-PSI or pH 5.0 for Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub> and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>). Three RON variants were immobilized on three sensor chip flow cells with matrix volume concentration of 10&#x02013;20 fM. For reference, the fourth flow cell was treated only with the surface-activating reagents N-hydroxysuccinimide/N-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)-N&#x02032;-ethylcarbodiimide (NHS/EDC). After protein immobilization, the chip surfaces were blocked by 1 M ethanolamine (pH 8.5) and unbound proteins were removed by washing with 50 mM NaOH. Two sensor chips were required to immobilize the four RON variants, thus two of the variants were included twice. One chip included Sema, Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>, and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> and the second chip included Sema-PSI, Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1</sub>, and Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>.</p><p>Binding assays were performed in a running buffer comprising 10 mM Na<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>HEPES (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, and 0.005&#x00025; Surfactant P20 (GE Health Sciences) at 25&#x000b0;C. To reduce non-specific binding, the immobilized chips were equilibrated with the running buffer, supplemented with 0.2 mg/mL bovine serum albumin, at a flow rate of 10 &#x000b5;L/min for several hours, followed by priming with the running buffer alone. To characterize binding kinetics of the wild-type MSP&#x003b2;, concentrations of the protein ranging from 5 to 500 nM, were prepared by step dilution and injected over the RON surfaces for 2 min at a 50 &#x000b5;L/min flow rate. Each injection was followed by a 2-min dissociation period. For the experiments with the MSP&#x003b2; R689C, the concentrations ranged between 32 and 2000 nM. All injections were performed using the Wizard &#x0201c;Customized Application&#x0201d; program in an automated mode. At the end of each cycle, the sensor chip surfaces were regenerated by a 0.5 min injection of 25 mM NaOH followed by a 2 min wash with running buffer.</p><p>Competition SPR experiments probed the MSP&#x003b2;/RON interaction further following a previously published approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Nieba1">[28]</xref>. The experiments measured the binding of free MSP&#x003b2; (wild-type and R689C) from a pre-equilibrated RON Sema/MSP&#x003b2; or Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>/MSP&#x003b2; analyte mixtures to covalently immobilized Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>. MSP&#x003b2; concentrations close to the calculated <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> values (10 nM for wild-type MSP&#x003b2; or 35&#x02013;100 nM for MSP&#x003b2; R689C) were mixed with increasing concentrations (0.1&#x02013;10,000 nM) of Sema- or Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub> RON and pre-equilibrated for at least 30 minutes. The pre-equilibrated complexes were sequentially injected into the sensor chip to detect free MSP&#x003b2; binding to the immobilized RON. The concentration of unbound MSP&#x003b2; was calculated from calibration curves, where the initial binding rate of an analyte was plotted against the analyte concentration. For the calibration, the initial binding rates were determined from the set of binding sensorgrams for 1.5&#x02013;12.5 nM (wild-type) or 4&#x02013;62.5 nM (R689C) MSP&#x003b2; to the immobilized Sema-PSI-IPT<sub>1&#x02013;4</sub>. Each curve was fitted in the early association phase, defining linear correlation between the SPR signal and the analyte concentration. This calibration was used to determine the free MSP&#x003b2; concentrations in the RON/MSP&#x003b2; mixtures, which were then plotted against the soluble RON concentrations and globally fitted to a solution affinity model, yielding the affinity equilibrium constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) in solution.</p><p>Kinetic data were analyzed using the BIAevaluation software, version 3.1 (BIAcore). All binding curves were corrected for background and bulk refractive index contribution using the reference flow cell and buffer alone. The sets of binding curves were globally fitted with a non-linear least squares algorithm, using single-exponential functions (Langmuir monovalent binding model). Kinetic parameters (<italic>k</italic><sub>on</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>off</sub>) and equilibrium dissociation constants (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) were determined based on at least two experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s3h"><title>Proteolytic activation of MSP</title><p>The wild-type and R689C MSP&#x003b2; proteins used in this study contain the C-terminal 19 amino acids of the MSP&#x003b1; fused to the N-terminus of the &#x003b2;-chain, including Cys468 of MSP&#x003b1; that forms an inter chain disulfide bond with Cys588 on the &#x003b2; chain. The specific proteolysis of the Arg483-Val484 peptide bond that activates MSP yields an &#x003b1; chain peptide that is linked to the &#x003b2;-chain only by the disulfide bond. Cleavage of both the wild type and R689C proteins by matriptase-1 was performed as follows. Samples containing 2 &#x000b5;L (500 nG) of MSP&#x003b2; and 10 &#x000b5;L of 100 nM matriptase-1 (EnzoLife Sciences International, USA) were incubated for 4 h at 37&#x000b0;C at substrate to enzyme molecular ratio of 20&#x02236;1. Wild type and mutant MSP&#x003b2; incubated in the absence of matriptase-1 served as controls. The proteolytic products were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (Invitrogen) under reduced conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s3i"><title>Structure modeling</title><p>A comparative model of the MSP&#x003b2; in complex with RON Sema-PSI was built based on the available crystal structures of MSP&#x003b2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Carafoli1">[22]</xref> (PDB entry 1ASU), RON Sema-PSI (Chao and Herzberg, unpublished), and the crystal structure of the homologous protein complex HGF&#x003b2;/MET Sema-PSI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Stamos1">[29]</xref> (PDB entry 1SHY) (HGF&#x003b2; and MSP&#x003b2; share 43&#x00025; sequence identity, and the Sema-PSI domains of MET and RON share 29&#x00025; sequence identity). The model was built by super positioning the individual protein structures on their respective homologs within the HGF&#x003b2;/MET Sema-PSI complex, using the interactive computer graphics program COOT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027269-Emsley1">[37]</xref>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants R21-DA027024, R01-GM087922, R01LM007174 (URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/oer.htm">http://grants.nih.gov/grants/oer.htm</ext-link>). RHA was a recipient of an HHMI (Howard Hughes Medical Institute) undergraduate student award. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0027269-Consortium1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>WTCC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controls.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>447</volume>             <fpage>661</fpage>             <lpage>678</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17554300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Franke1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Radford-Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide meta-analysis increases to 71 the number of confirmed Crohn's disease susceptibility loci.</article-title>             <source>Nature genetics</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>1118</fpage>             <lpage>1125</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21102463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Teslovich1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teslovich</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Musunuru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmondson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Biological, clinical and population relevance of 95 loci for blood lipids.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>466</volume>             <fpage>707</fpage>             <lpage>713</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Yue1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Loss of protein structure stability as a major causative factor in monogenic disease.</article-title>             <source>Journal of molecular biology</source>             <volume>353</volume>             <fpage>459</fpage>             <lpage>473</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16169011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Yue2"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Identification and analysis of deleterious human SNPs.</article-title>             <source>Journal of molecular biology</source>             <volume>356</volume>             <fpage>1263</fpage>             <lpage>1274</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16412461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-AllaliHassani1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allali-Hassani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasney</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Senisterra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A survey of proteins encoded by non-synonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms reveals a significant fraction with altered stability and activity.</article-title>             <source>The Biochemical journal</source>             <volume>424</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>26</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19702579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Goyette1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goyette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brant</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Gene-centric association mapping of chromosome 3p implicates MST1 in IBD pathogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>131</fpage>             <lpage>138</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Melum1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weismuller</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotthardt</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide association analysis in primary sclerosing cholangitis identifies two non-HLA susceptibility loci.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>17</fpage>             <lpage>19</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Sofaer1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sofaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Crohn's disease: the genetic contribution.</article-title>             <source>Gut</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>869</fpage>             <lpage>871</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8344571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Anderson1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Amato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Meta-analysis identifies 29 additional ulcerative colitis risk loci, increasing the number of confirmed associations to 47.</article-title>             <source>Nature genetics</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>246</fpage>             <lpage>252</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Kretschmann1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kretschmann</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyob</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Buys</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Welm</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The macrophage stimulating protein/Ron pathway as a potential therapeutic target to impede multiple mechanisms involved in breast cancer progression.</article-title>             <source>Curr Drug Targets</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1157</fpage>             <lpage>1168</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20545605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Wang1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Skeel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Proteolytic cleavage and activation of pro-macrophage-stimulating protein by resident peritoneal macrophage membrane proteases.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Invest</source>             <volume>97</volume>             <fpage>720</fpage>             <lpage>727</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8609228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Bhatt1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Welm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farady</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Coordinate expression and functional profiling identify an extracellular proteolytic signaling pathway.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>5771</fpage>             <lpage>5776</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17389401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Beckly1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckly</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Geremia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Two-stage candidate gene study of chromosome 3p demonstrates an association between nonsynonymous variants in the MST1R gene and Crohn's disease.</article-title>             <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>500</fpage>             <lpage>507</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18200509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Danilkovitch1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilkovitch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Interaction of macrophage-stimulating protein with its receptor. Residues critical for beta chain binding and evidence for independent alpha chain binding.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>29937</fpage>             <lpage>29943</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10514476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Waltz1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waltz</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Air</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Flick</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Functional characterization of domains contained in hepatocyte growth factor-like protein.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>30526</fpage>             <lpage>30537</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Wang2"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Breathnach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Godowski</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Takehara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Macrophage stimulating protein (MSP) binds to its receptor via the MSP beta chain.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>16999</fpage>             <lpage>17004</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9202013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Angeloni1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angeloni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilkovitch-Miagkova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miagkov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>The soluble sema domain of the RON receptor inhibits macrophage-stimulating protein-induced receptor activation.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>279</volume>             <fpage>3726</fpage>             <lpage>3732</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Ma1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Padhye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Inhibition of MSP-RON signaling pathway in cancer cells by a novel soluble form of RON comprising the entire sema sequence.</article-title>             <source>Int J Oncol</source>             <volume>36</volume>             <fpage>1551</fpage>             <lpage>1561</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20428780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Matsumoto1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Date</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Cooperative interaction between alpha- and beta-chains of hepatocyte growth factor on c-Met receptor confers ligand-induced receptor tyrosine phosphorylation and multiple biological responses.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>273</volume>             <fpage>22913</fpage>             <lpage>22920</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9722511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Gherardi1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gherardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petoukhov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Youles</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Structural basis of hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor and MET signalling.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>4046</fpage>             <lpage>4051</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Carafoli1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carafoli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chirgadze</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gherardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Crystal structure of the beta-chain of human hepatocyte growth factor-like/macrophage stimulating protein.</article-title>             <source>Febs J</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>5799</fpage>             <lpage>5807</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16279944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Axe1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Axe</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fersht</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>An irregular beta-bulge common to a group of bacterial RNases is an important determinant of stability and function in barnase.</article-title>             <source>Journal of molecular biology</source>             <volume>286</volume>             <fpage>1471</fpage>             <lpage>1485</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10064710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Pantoliano1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pantoliano</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitlow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Large increases in general stability for subtilisin BPN' through incremental changes in the free energy of unfolding.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>7205</fpage>             <lpage>7213</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2684274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Kelley1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Effect of residue 65 substitutions on thermal stability of tissue plasminogen activator kringle-2 domain.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>4047</fpage>             <lpage>4054</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2502177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Baase1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baase</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tronrud</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Lessons from the lysozyme of phage T4.</article-title>             <source>Protein science : a publication of the Protein Society</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>631</fpage>             <lpage>641</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20095051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Holmes1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deakin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carafoli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Insights into the structure/function of hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor from studies with individual domains.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Biol</source>             <volume>367</volume>             <fpage>395</fpage>             <lpage>408</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17258232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Nieba1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieba</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluckthun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Competition BIAcore for measuring true affinities: large differences from values determined from binding kinetics.</article-title>             <source>Anal Biochem</source>             <volume>234</volume>             <fpage>155</fpage>             <lpage>165</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8714593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Stamos1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchhofer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Crystal structure of the HGF beta-chain in complex with the Sema domain of the Met receptor.</article-title>             <source>Embo J</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>2325</fpage>             <lpage>2335</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15167892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Gaudino1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaudino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Follenzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naldini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Collesi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>RON is a heterodimeric tyrosine kinase receptor activated by the HGF homologue MSP.</article-title>             <source>The EMBO journal</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>3524</fpage>             <lpage>3532</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8062829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Altshuler1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peltonen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dermitzakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Integrating common and rare genetic variation in diverse human populations.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>467</volume>             <fpage>52</fpage>             <lpage>58</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20811451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Marchini1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Howie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McVean</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A new multipoint method for genome-wide association studies by imputation of genotypes.</article-title>             <source>Nature genetics</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>906</fpage>             <lpage>913</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Krawczak1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krawczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeysinghe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Human gene mutation database-a biomedical information and research resource.</article-title>             <source>Human mutation</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>45</fpage>             <lpage>51</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10612821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Lehr1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehr</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Elefante</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikly</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>A modified metal-ion affinity chromatography procedure for the purification of histidine-tagged recombinant proteins expressed in Drosophila S2 cells.</article-title>             <source>Protein Expr Purif</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>362</fpage>             <lpage>368</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10910726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Loo1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Patchett</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Using secretion to solve a solubility problem: high-yield expression in Escherichia coli and purification of the bacterial glycoamidase PNGase F.</article-title>             <source>Protein Expr Purif</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>90</fpage>             <lpage>98</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11812228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Vedadi1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vedadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niesen</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Allali-Hassani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorov</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><name><surname>Finerty</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Chemical screening methods to identify ligands that promote protein stability, protein crystallization, and structure determination.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>15835</fpage>             <lpage>15840</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17035505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027269-Emsley1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics.</article-title>             <source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>2126</fpage>             <lpage>2132</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>