<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC2286729
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Directed discovery of bivalent peptide ligands to an SH3 domain
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     The
     <em>
      Caenorhabditis elegans
     </em>
     SEM-5 SH3 domains recognize proline-rich peptide segments with modest affinity. We developed a bivalent peptide ligand that contains a naturally occurring proline-rich binding sequence, tethered by a glycine linker to a disulfide-closed loop segment containing six variable residues. The glycine linker allows the loop segment to explore regions of greatest diversity in sequence and structure of the SH3 domain: the RT and n-Src loops. The bivalent ligand was optimized using phage display, leading to a peptide (PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L) with 1000-fold increased affinity for the SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain over that of a natural ligand. NMR analysis of the complex confirms that the peptide loop segment is targeted to the RT and n-Src loops and parts of the β-sheet scaffold of this SH3 domain. This binding region is comparable to that targeted by a natural non-PXXP peptide to the p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     SH3 domain, a region not known to be targeted in the Grb2 SH3 domain family. PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L may aid in the discovery of additional binding partners of Grb2 family SH3 domains.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     SH3 domain, signal transduction, phage display, combinatorial library, peptide ligand, bivalent ligand, NMR spectroscopy, non-PXXP binding site
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results and Discussion
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Design and identification of tight binding bivalent ligands to SEM-5 SH3 domain
    </title>
    <p>
     A Fuse-5 phage-displayed random peptide library (PPPVP PRGGGGCXXXXXXC, where X represents the 20 naturally occurring amino acids) was screened to select for a peptide sequence showing high-affinity binding interactions with the SEM-5 C terminal SH3 domain. The peptide library links a naturally occurring proline-rich region via a tetra-glycine linker to a disulfide-constrained, randomized loop. Members of the library allow us to explore regions of greatest sequence and structural diversity among SH3 domains: the n-Src and RT loops. The length of the glycine linker was selected to allow the loop residues to completely interact with the regions adjacent to the polyproline pocket on the SH3 domain and to reach one of the non-PXXP binding sites. The cysteine residues allow the formation of a disulfide bond to restrict the conformational space sampled by each loop sequence. This minimizes the loss in conformational entropy of the ligand upon binding to the receptor domain.
    </p>
    <p>
     The phage selection converged to a single sequence, PPPVPPRGGGGCLYTRYWC (PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L), after multiple rounds of biopanning. Phage eluted at pH 2 converged to a single amino acid sequence after round 3, while phage eluted at pH 3 converged to that same sequence after round 4. The resulting peptide was chemically synthesized and its binding to fluorescein-labeled SEM-5 SH3 domain was determined by fluorescence anisotropy. The [=7139453 PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L protein] peptide bound to its target protein [=P29355 SEM-5 SH3 protein] with a
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      <em>
       d
      </em>
     </sub>
     of [=7139446 48 nM kd] (Table 1
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        1).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
      </span>
     </a>
     ). This represents ~1000-fold enhancement in affinity over the mSos polyproline peptide segment alone: Ac-PPPVPPR-amide (190 μM;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Nguyen et al. 1998
     </xref>
     ), and is the highest affinity of a selected peptide to any SH3 domain yet reported.
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Determination of K
        <sub>
         d
        </sub>
        values for SEM-5•peptide complexes
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Thermodynamic analysis of peptide ligands to the SEM-5 SH3 domain
    </title>
    <p>
     The free energy contributions of bivalent molecules has been defined by
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Jencks (1981)
     </xref>
     as Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     °
     <sub>
      AB
     </sub>
     = Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       i
      </em>
     </sup>
     <sub>
      A
     </sub>
     + Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       i
      </em>
     </sup>
     <sub>
      B
     </sub>
     + Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       s
      </em>
     </sup>
     , where AB represents the bivalent ligand, and A and B the individual binding fragments. The term Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       s
      </em>
     </sup>
     accounts for changes in translational and rotational entropy as a result of connecting the two fragments. The binding affinities for the [=Q62245 mSos proline-rich sequence protein] alone PPPVPPR (herein termed mSos;
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      <em>
       d
      </em>
     </sub>
     = [=7139421 190 μM kd]) (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Nguyen et al. 1998
     </xref>
     ) and PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L (0.048 μM), result in free energies of binding of −5.1 and −10.01 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     , respectively (Table 1
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        1).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The binding free energies of the tether plus loop, G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L and the loop alone (termed L), are −7.9 and −8.24 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     , respectively. The G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     linker may decrease the affinity of G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L over L due to a reduction in the conformation space it can sample on binding compared to that sampled when free in solution. The sum of binding free energies of the individual fragments (mSos and G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L) is −13.0 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     , whereas the bivalent ligand (PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L) bound to the domain with a free energy of only −10.01 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     (Table 1
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        1).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The positive Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       s
      </em>
     </sup>
     (3 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     ) for the bivalent ligand indicates that it binds less well than expected from the binding free energy of the two components. The length of the linker may not be appropriate, resulting in weaker binding than expected.
    </p>
    <p>
     The sequence Ac-PPPVPPRGGGCLYTRYWCGRK-amide (PP-G
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     -L) was chemically synthesized to investigate the effect of linker length on the bivalent ligand affinity for the SH3 domain. The peptide [=7139468 PP-G
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     -L protein], in which the glycine linker was shortened by one residue, bound more tightly to the [=P29355 SH3 domain protein] (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      <em>
       d
      </em>
     </sub>
     = [=7139473 25 nM kd]) that the longer PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L ligand (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      <em>
       d
      </em>
     </sub>
     = 48 nM). The increased binding affinity can be attributed to the reduced conformational space sampled by the PP-G
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     -L conformers, due to the reduced conformational ensemble associated with the shorter glycine segment.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     NMR spectroscopy maps peptide interactions to the surface of the SH3 domain
    </title>
    <p>
     The binding interactions of the mSos proline-rich peptide, PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L, and L peptides were mapped to surface residues of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain in 2D
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H HSQC NMR-based chemical shift and line width perturbation studies. The relatively weak interaction between the SH3 domain and the mSos peptide results in a protein–peptide complex that is in fast exchange on the NMR time scale, as evidenced by chemical shift perturbations. However, the selective broadening of the SH3 domain amide (NH) cross-peaks upon titration with PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L and L peptides demonstrate relatively stronger binding of these peptides to the SH3 domain, producing a protein–peptide complex that is in intermediate exchange on the NMR timescale (Fig. 1
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="f1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H-
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N HSQC spectra of SH3 domain alone (black contours) and with PP-G
       <sub>
        4
       </sub>
       -L (red contours; molar ratio of ligand to protein, ~1.5 : 1). Black peaks alone indicate that the resonances from the complex (red) have been significantly broadened.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     SH3 residues that are affected by binding of the mSos peptide line the binding site observed in the crystal structure of this complex (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Lim et al. 1994b
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Ferreon et al. 2003
     </xref>
     ), while the binding of the PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L peptide affects not only this binding site, but also extends its effects to some residues in β-strands b, c, and d as well as residues of the n-Src and RT loops (Figs. 2A,B
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     and 3A,C
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     ). We used 2D
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H-
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N HSQC NMR spectroscopy to investigate the binding interactions of the loop peptide (L) to the SH3 domain, to determine which residues of the SH3 domain specifically interact with the loop residues on the PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L peptide. Surprisingly, a common set of residues on the RT loop (G171, E172, and L173), β-strand b (N185, K186), β-strand c (W191 and W192), and β-strand d (I202 and F203) were perturbed by the poly-proline sequence (mSos) and L peptides (Figs. 2A,C
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     and 3B,C
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     ). Similar observations have been previously reported for the Grb2 C-terminal SH3 domain where the binding site of a non-PXXP fragment of SLP-76 peptide was observed to partially overlap with the PXXP motif binding site (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Kami et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ). We used NMR spectroscopy to analyze competitive binding between mSos and the L peptide to the SEM-5 SH3 domain to ascertain the mode of binding of the bivalent ligand (PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     L). Significant chemical shift perturbations were observed for residues that line the mSos binding site on the SH3 domain when a 1:1 complex is formed between the two. The subsequent addition of L peptide to this 1:1 mSos•SH3 domain complex causes line broadening of the residues that interact with the L peptide, without causing any further chemical shift perturbations (data not shown). The results suggest cobinding of the two peptides on the surface of the SH3 domain, without any evidence of competition for the mSos binding site.
    </p>
    <fig id="f2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Graphical representation of chemical shift and line width perturbations of SEM-5 SH3 domain residues by m-Sos (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ), PPG4L (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ), and L (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) peptides. The perturbations observed in the side chain atoms are depicted in blue. Regions of higher perturbation on the SEM-5 SH3 domain are shown with horizontal red bars for all three peptides. The non-PXXP binding sites for Grb2 and p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       are indicated by green and magenta bars, respectively, in (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ). The weighted chemical shift differences for SEM-5 SH3 domain titration with mSos are calculated as the square root of [(Δω
       <sub>
        H
       </sub>
       )
       <sup>
        2
       </sup>
       + 0.5(Δω
       <sub>
        N
       </sub>
       )
       <sup>
        2
       </sup>
       ], where Δω
       <sub>
        H
       </sub>
       and Δω
       <sub>
        N
       </sub>
       are changes in proton and nitrogen chemical shifts in ppm units.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Ribbon diagrams of SEM-5 SH3 domain color coded to specify the regions of interactions with mSos (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ), LGT-E-D3 (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ), and PPG4L (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) peptides. Color coding from gold to orange to red indicates increasing perturbation or binding interactions of the domain residues with the respective peptides.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We compared the residues on C-terminal SEM-5 SH3 domain that are significantly perturbed (more than 30% reduction in signal intensity) by the addition of non-PXXP loop peptide, L (residues colored red in Fig. 3B
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     ) to the non-PXXP peptide binding sites on other SH3 domains (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Kami et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ). Kami et al. reported binding of non-PXXP peptides to Grb2 (a SEM-5 homolog), p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and Pex13p SH3 domains (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Kami et al. 2002
     </xref>
     ). Each peptide mapped to a distinctive site on their respective SH3 domains, but with some common chemical shift perturbations. The L peptide-binding site on the SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain is nearly identical with that reported for the non-PXXP region of p47
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     peptide bound to the p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     SH3 domain and is distinct from SLP-76 binding to homologous Grb2 SH3 domain despite perturbations of some common residues (Figs. 3C
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     and 4B,C
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      ▶
     </xref>
     ). Surprisingly, a portion of the L peptide binding site is distinct from that reported for the homologous Grb2 SH3 domain, although they display an overlapping set of chemical shift perturbations. This particular site has not been reported for a member of the Grb2 adaptor protein family. The L peptide may prove a useful reagent in mapping a new molecular partner for the SEM-5 adaptor protein.
    </p>
    <fig id="f4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Comparison of the non-PXXP peptide binding sites on SH3 domains. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Sequence alignment of the SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain with SH3 domains sequences that bind non-PXXP peptides. The secondary structure elements above refer to the SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain. The residues that are broadened substantially by the L peptide (&gt;30% reduction in signal intensity on peptide addition) for the SEM-5 domain (red) are compared with cross-saturation results reported for the other domains (red;
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        Kami et al. 2002
       </xref>
       ). (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Mapping of non-PXXP binding regions (based on the sequence alignment) for SEM-5 and p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       SH3 domains on the structure of SEM-5 C terminal SH3 domain. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Mapping of non-PXXP binding regions for SEM-5 and Grb2 SH3 domains on the structure of SEM-5 C terminal SH3 domain. The regions colored red and green are non-PXXP binding regions unique to SEM-5, p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       and Grb2 C terminal SH3 domains, respectively; regions in gold are common non-PXXP binding regions for both the SH3 domains.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Conclusions
    </title>
    <p>
     We have developed a bivalent peptide library using the Fuse5 phage display system that links the proline-rich region of mSos via a poly-glycine linker to a disulfide-constrained, randomized loop, allowing us to explore additional binding sites on the SH3 domain. Increased binding affinity to the SH3 domain is observed for the bivalent peptide sequence PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L versus its individual monovalent components. Chemical shift and line width perturbation studies by NMR spectroscopy reveal additional binding interactions of the SH3 domain with the PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L peptide compared to mSos alone. We observed that the binding affinity is further enhanced by shortening the length of the poly-glycine linker, from four glycine residues (PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L) to three (PP-G
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     -L). The increase in the conformational ensemble associated with each additional glycine residue probably leads to an energetically unfavorable entropic contribution to binding, denoted by Δ
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     <sup>
      <em>
       s
      </em>
     </sup>
     = 3 kcal mole
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     for the binding of PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L to the SH3 domain. The L peptide-binding site is comparable to that for a non-PXXP peptide to the p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     SH3 domain; a site that has yet to be identified for the Grb2 family of signal transduction adaptor proteins. The PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L and L peptides may provide a useful tool to further elaborate the molecular interactions of the Grb2 adaptor protein family. Ultimately, this methodology could be applied to the development of therapeutic agents such as antioncogenic compounds.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Materials and methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Construction of phage display library
    </title>
    <p>
     The DNA oligo: 5′-B-C TAT TCT CAC TCG GCC GAC GGG GCT GGT ACC ATG CCT CCC CCT GTT CCT CCT CGT GGT GGT GGT GGT TGC NNK NNK NNK NNK NNK NNK TGC GGT GGA TCC GCC GCT GGG GCC GAA ACT GTT GAA-3′ was used to prepare a Fuse-5 phage display library encoding -PPPVPPRGGGGCXXXXXXC-peptide sequences following an established protocol (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Scott and Smith 1990
     </xref>
     ). (5′-B: biotinylated 5′ end; “N” represents an equal mixture of the deoxynucleotides G, A, T, and C; “K” represents an equal mixture of G and T; and X represents a mixture of all 20 naturally occurring amino acids). The oligo was double stranded, with a single primer oligo: 5′-B-TTTCAACAGTTTCGGCCCCAG-3′ using a thermal cycler and, digested with BglI, and the oligo ends and undigested oligos were removed by incubating with streptavidin-agarose beads (Gibco-BRL, Cat.#15942-014) for 30 min at 25°C, followed by microcentrifugation at 2500 rpm for 2 min. The library of DNA fragments was cloned into the SfiI sites of the Fuse-5 vector and transfected into
     <em>
      Escherichia coli
     </em>
     strain DH5α. The resulting library contained 1.2 × 10
     <sup>
      8
     </sup>
     unique clones. (Oligo Synthesis: Keck Foundation Biotechnology Resource Laboratory, Yale University School of Medicine).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     SEM-5 protein expression, purification, and phage display library selection
    </title>
    <p>
     The C-terminal SEM-5 SH3 domain (residues 155–214) was expressed and purified as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Lim et al. 1994a
     </xref>
     ). We biotinylated SEM-5 SH3 using N-(hydroxysuccinamide)-NHS-LC-Biotin (Pierce, Cat. #21335) as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Smith 1985
     </xref>
     ). ESI mass spectrometry confirmed incorporation of 1~3 biotins per Sem 5 molecule. For library selection, streptavidin magnesphere paramagnetic particles (SA-PMPs; Promega Cat. #Z5481) were rinsed three times with Tris-buffered saline (TBS; 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 0.15 M NaCl). Biotinylated SH3 (100 μg) was added to 0.6 mg SA-PMPs in 600 μL TBS and incubated at 4°C for 18 h. The SA-PMPs were then incubated with 10 μmole of biotin at 4°C for 4 h to block unbound sites. The library phage virions (input = 10
     <sup>
      12
     </sup>
     cfu) were added and incubated with the beads in 700 μL TBS at 4°C for 18 h. The SA-PMPs were then washed with TBS-Tween (0.5%) 700 μL 6X at 4°C to remove unbound phage. The bound phage were eluted with 400 μL glycine-HCl (100 mM Glycine-HCl, pH adjusted with HCl 1 mg/mL BSA, 0.1 mg/mL phenol red) at pH 5, 4, 3, and 2 for 20 min at 4°C. Tris buffer (1 M Tris, pH 9.1) was used for neutralization. The pH eluates were transfected into ER2537 F′(NEB)
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     cells for library expansion. RF DNA from a single clone was sequenced at each enrichment cycle.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Peptide synthesis and purification
    </title>
    <p>
     The following sequences were synthesized:
    </p>
    <sec>
     <ul>
      <li>
       <sec>
        mSos peptide: Ac-PPPVPPR-amide,
       </sec>
      </li>
      <li>
       <sec>
        PP-G
        <sub>
         4
        </sub>
        -L: Ac-PPPVPPRGGGGCLYTRYWCGRK -amide
       </sec>
      </li>
      <li>
       <sec>
        PP-G
        <sub>
         3
        </sub>
        -L: Ac-PPPVPPRGGGCLYTRYWCGRK -amide
       </sec>
      </li>
      <li>
       <sec>
        G
        <sub>
         4
        </sub>
        -L: Ac-GGGGCLYTRYWCGRK-amide
       </sec>
      </li>
      <li>
       <sec>
        L: Ac-CLYTRYWCGRK -amide.
       </sec>
      </li>
     </ul>
    </sec>
    <p>
     PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L peptide was obtained from the original library selection, and PP-G
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     -L and L peptides were modified peptides from the original library selection. All peptides were synthesized with Fmoc/tBu solid-phase peptide synthesis (ABI 431A). The N termini of the peptides were acetylated, and an amide group was added to the C terminus of each peptide. Peptides (200 μg/mL) were oxidized in 10–100 mM Tris (pH 8.0) with 10–20 μM CuCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     . Peptides were purified by RP-HPLC on a C18 column and their identities confirmed to be monomers by ESI mass spectrometry. The mass results are given in Table 1
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        1.
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
      </span>
     </a>
     . The peptides were oxidized to form disulfide bridges in 100 mM Tris (pH 8.0) and 10 μM Cu
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     at 25°C for 4 h.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Binding affinity
    </title>
    <p>
     The SEM-5 SH3 domain was labeled at Cys209 using a thiol-reactive reagent (fluorescein-5-maleimide) as described by the manufacturer (Molecular Probes, cat. no. F-150). This site occurs on the opposite face of the SH3 domain from the proline-rich binding surface. Fluorescence measurements were performed at 25°C in HEPES buffer at pH 7.5 (20 mM HEPES, 50 mM NaCl) using a Beacon fluorescence polarization spectrometer (PANVERA). The excitation and emission wavelength were 490 and 525 nm, respectively.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     NMR analysis
    </title>
    <p>
     All NMR spectra were collected at 25°C on a Varian UnityPlus 750 MHz or 600 MHz instruments using a triple resonance probe equipped with a pulsed-field gradient. Sequential assignments are reported elsewhere (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Ferreon et al. 2003
     </xref>
     ). Titrations of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled SEM-5 C-terminal SH3 domain with the mSos, PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L, and L peptides were monitored using
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H-
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N HSQC spectra. The final ligand : peptide molar ratio was ~2 : 1 for the mSos, ~1.5 : 1 for PP-G
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -L, and ~2 : 1 for L peptide. All spectra were recorded as 64 × 2048 complex matrices with 16 scans per
     <em>
      t
     </em>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     point. Spectral widths of 2400 and 7500 Hz were employed in D
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     and D
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , respectively. The NMR spectra were processed using NMRPipe software (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Delaglio et al. 1995
     </xref>
     ). Peak heights measured with NMRView were used for the titrations.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Notes
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     Article and publication are at http://www.proteinscience.org/cgi/doi/10.1110/ps.03470504.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
