<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2009.06.051
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    The Non-canonical Hop Protein from Caenorhabditis elegans Exerts Essential Functions and Forms Binary Complexes with Either Hsc70 or Hsp90
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      Hsp
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      heat shock protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      TPR
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      tetratricopeptide repeat
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CeHop
     </span>
     ,
     <em>
      Caenorhabditis elegans
     </em>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      SHR
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      steroid hormone receptor
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      ORF
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      open reading frame
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      RNAi
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      RNA interference
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      DAPI
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      4′-6-diamidino-2-phenylindole
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      SPR
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      surface plasmon resonance
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Hsc
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      heat shock cognate
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      NGM
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      nematode growth medium
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      PBS
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      phosphate-buffered saline
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      Hsp90
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Hsc70
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Hop
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      TPR domain
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      gonad development
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Hop (
    <em>
     H
    </em>
    sp70/Hsp90-
    <em>
     o
    </em>
    rganizing
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    rotein) has been described as a cofactor in a multichaperone complex with the cytosolic chaperones heat shock protein (Hsp) 90 and Hsp70.
    <a>
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
    </a>
    Albeit not acting as a chaperone itself, Hop is required for the efficient activation of steroid hormone receptors (SHRs) by the Hsp70–Hsp90 system.
    <a>
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
    </a>
    Hop has been shown in multiple experiments to bind to an initial complex of SHR with Hsp70 and the chaperone Hsp40.
    <sup>
     <a>
      3
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      4
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      5
     </a>
    </sup>
    The main purpose of the interaction between Hsp70, Hop, and Hsp90 is to promote substrate transfer from Hsp70 to Hsp90, which occurs in the ternary complex under ATP hydrolysis by Hsp70.
    <a>
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
    </a>
    Subsequent activation of the SHR requires ATP hydrolysis by Hsp90 and the exchange of the protein complex Hsp40·Hsp70·Hop for other cofactors, namely, p23 and FKBP51/52.
    <sup>
     <a>
      7
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      8
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      9
     </a>
    </sup>
   </p>
   <p>
    The binding of Hop to the C-terminal amino acids IEEVD of Hsp70 is mediated by its tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) 1 domain.
    <sup>
     <a>
      10
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      11
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      12
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      13
     </a>
    </sup>
    The TPR2A domain of Hop provides the main interaction site for the C-terminal MEEVD motif of Hsp90, which allows the formation of the ternary Hsp90·Hop·Hsp70 complex in yeast and human systems.
    <sup>
     <a>
      12
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      14
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      15
     </a>
    </sup>
    In addition to TPR1 and TPR2A, all characterized Hop proteins contain a putative third TPR domain without an assigned function (TPR2B) and two linker domains: one between TPR1 and TPR2A, called DP1, and one at the C-terminus of the protein, called DP2. The DP1 domain is absent in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    .
    <a>
     <sup>
      16
     </sup>
    </a>
    It is intriguing that the putative homologue of Hop in the genome of
    <em>
     Caenorhabditis elegans
    </em>
    does not contain a coding sequence for the Hsp70-binding TPR1/DP1 domain despite a strong homology throughout the TPR2A, TPR2B, and DP2 domains. We observed that a Hop protein lacking the TPR1 domain can only be detected in the genomes of
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    and its close relatives
    <em>
     Caenorhabditis briggsae
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     Caenorhabditis remanei
    </em>
    , besides a few other mostly unconfirmed homologues of lower eukaryotes (
    <em>
     Cryptosporidium hominis
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     Schistosoma japonicum
    </em>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Apart from being analyzed in mammalian cell culture, Hop has been analyzed in yeast, where a homologue of Hop, termed Sti1, is found.
    <a>
     <sup>
      17
     </sup>
    </a>
    Sti1 strongly inhibits the ATPase activity of yeast Hsp90
    <a>
     <sup>
      18
     </sup>
    </a>
    in stark contrast to the mammalian homologue, which does not inhibit the hydrolysis of human Hsp90.
    <a>
     <sup>
      19
     </sup>
    </a>
    For the Hsp90·Sti1 complex, the mechanism of ATPase inhibition has been investigated. Interaction with Sti1 prevents a crucial conformational change in Hsp90, which has been shown to be essential for the ATP-hydrolyzing reaction,
    <a>
     <sup>
      20
     </sup>
    </a>
    albeit mechanistic details regarding the binding sites involved in ATPase inhibition have not been performed. Functional analysis in yeast shows that although the protein seems to be not essential in
    <em>
     sti1
    </em>
    knockout strains, synthetic phenotypes that result in growth defects and lethality exist.
    <sup>
     <a>
      21
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      22
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      23
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      24
     </a>
    </sup>
    Genes that show synthetic lethality with
    <em>
     sti1
    </em>
    knockout strains include the Hsp40 homologue
    <em>
     ydj1
    </em>
    ;
    <sup>
     <a>
      23
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      24
     </a>
    </sup>
    the Hsp90 cochaperones
    <em>
     sba1
    </em>
    ,
    <sup>
     <a>
      21
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      24
     </a>
    </sup>
    <em>
     cpr7
    </em>
    ,
    <a>
     <sup>
      24
     </sup>
    </a>
    and
    <em>
     cdc37
    </em>
    ;
    <a>
     <sup>
      22
     </sup>
    </a>
    and the genes for KIN28, CDC7, CEP3, and EPS1, some of which were identified in large-scale genomewide screens.
    <sup>
     <a>
      25
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      26
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      27
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      28
     </a>
    </sup>
    Moreover, deletion of
    <em>
     sti1
    </em>
    in yeast reduces the activity of two heterologous Hsp90 targets, namely glucocorticoid receptor and v-Src.
    <sup>
     <a>
      17
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      21
     </a>
    </sup>
    For several of these synergistic effects, the reasons have not been determined, leaving the cellular function of Sti1, in part, unclear.
   </p>
   <p>
    We aimed to address the function of the Hop homologue from
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    and further attempted to understand to what extent the current biochemical knowledge about Hop/Sti1 applies to this exotic variant. Our results describe the first organismal function of Hop in a metazoan and address the mechanism of interaction between the
    <em>
     Caenorhabditis elegans
    </em>
    Hop homologue R09E12.3 (CeHop), Hsp70, and Hsp90.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Hop proteins show specific domain loss in nematodes
   </title>
   <p>
    A homologue of Hop in the nematode
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    has been identified by genome sequencing and automated annotation of open reading frames (ORFs).
    <a>
     <sup>
      29
     </sup>
    </a>
    The closest homologue of human Hop in
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    is encoded by the gene
    <em>
     R09E12.3
    </em>
    . The predicted ORF lacks sequences for the TPR1 domain and encodes a 340-amino-acid protein that resembles a truncated version of the 543-amino-acid human protein (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    a). Nevertheless, alignment of different Hop proteins detects a strong sequence homology in the sequences of the TPR2A, TPR2B ,and DP2 domains (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    b), hinting strongly at a conserved function of the remaining domains.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="C. elegans Hop resembles a truncated homologue of Hop/Sti1. (a) Domain ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
         Hop resembles a truncated homologue of Hop/Sti1. (a) Domain comparison of Hop-homologous proteins from
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          Saccharomyces cerevisiae
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          Drosophila melanogaster
         </em>
         , and
         <em>
          Homo sapiens
         </em>
         shows that the TPR1 domain of Hop is absent in the nematode protein. TPR domains are depicted in dark gray, whereas linker domains (DP domains) are depicted in light gray. (b) Sequence alignment of Hop proteins from
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          H. sapiens
         </em>
         ,
         <em>
          D. melanogaster
         </em>
         , and
         <em>
          S. cerevisiae
         </em>
         . Identities are emphasized in black, whereas similarities are emphasized in gray. Alignments were generated using ClustalW software, and visualization of alignment results was performed using the Boxshade program.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1457 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We were interested to see how common this domain organization is among Hop-like proteins. In the public genome databases, only a few other Hop proteins that share the domain organization of the gene
    <em>
     R09E12.3
    </em>
    can be found. Based on today's sequence availability, only about 2% of the sequenced Hop genes encode a truncated Hop protein (data not shown). Most of these are encoded by nematode genomes, namely
    <em>
     C. briggsae
    </em>
    and other close relatives of
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    It has been observed in eukaryotic proteins that loss of domains is sometimes accompanied by the emergence of another protein that, in turn, could be complemented by complex formation. We therefore searched the
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    genome for proteins that encode TPR motifs similar to the lost TPR1 domain, using TPR1 from yeast and human Hop proteins as bait in the searches (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). The strongest homology was found for TPR2B of
    <em>
     R09E12.3
    </em>
    itself, while other proteins identified were the homologues of the well-described Hsp90 cochaperones CNS1, SGT1, and CHIP. Therefore, we conclude that the loss of the TPR1 domain in the gene
    <em>
     R09E12.3
    </em>
    is not compensated for by another protein, while the remaining domains of CeHop form a protein with a close homology to other eukaryotic Hop proteins.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Hop-like TPR domains can be identified in
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
           Sti1-1 (2–105) (%Id/%H
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           Sti1-2A (262–362) (%Id/%H)
          </th>
          <th>
           Sti1-2B (395–490) (%Id/%H)
          </th>
          <th>
           hHop-1 (3–105) (%Id/%H)
          </th>
          <th>
           hHop-2A (226–326) (%Id/%H)
          </th>
          <th>
           hHop-2B (363–460) (%Id/%H)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            C. elegans
           </em>
           hit 1
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3b (35/60)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3a (42/65)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3b (45/64)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3b (41/62)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3a (52/75)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3b (64/81)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            C. elegans
           </em>
           hit 2
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (32/59)
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (36/52)
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (32/45)
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (37/56)
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3b (29/56)
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (34/57)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            C. elegans
           </em>
           hit 3
          </td>
          <td>
           Pph-5 (34/58)
          </td>
          <td>
           Pph-5 (32/48)
          </td>
          <td>
           T12D8.8 (32/49)
          </td>
          <td>
           Pph-5 (36/53)
          </td>
          <td>
           Chn-1 28/51
          </td>
          <td>
           Chn-1 36/56
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            C. elegans
           </em>
           hit 4
          </td>
          <td>
           ZK370.8 34/49
          </td>
          <td>
           Chn-1 30/61
          </td>
          <td>
           Pph-5 32/50
          </td>
          <td>
           T12D8.8 29/51
          </td>
          <td>
           Sgt-1 (30/50)
          </td>
          <td>
           T12D8.8 (32/49)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            C. elegans
           </em>
           hit 5
          </td>
          <td>
           T12D8.8 (32/55)
          </td>
          <td>
           F52H3.5 (29/48)
          </td>
          <td>
           Chn-1 (28/46)
          </td>
          <td>
           C34B2.5 (27/50)
          </td>
          <td>
           Dnj-28 (28/48)
          </td>
          <td>
           Pph-5 (36/58)
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        BLAST searches of the
        <em>
         C. elegans
        </em>
        proteome were performed with the isolated TPR domains of Sti1 and Hop, as indicated by amino acid positions below the TPR name.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         a
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          Id, identity; H, homology.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    The 38-kDa Hop homologue is ubiquitously expressed in
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
   </title>
   <p>
    The observation of a TPR1-depleted Hop protein raises questions about the functionality of the gene product. Therefore, we were interested in analyzing the expression of the Hop homologue of
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    . A polyclonal antibody was generated against recombinant CeHop and was used to determine the size of the expressed protein in
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    extracts. The translated CeHop was detectable at the predicted size in wildtype nematodes under normal growth conditions (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    a) and matched the size of the recombinant protein. Thus, CeHop is expressed constitutively and deletion of TPR1 is observable also at the protein level, excluding any major posttranscriptional or posttranslational modifications of the gene product.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="CeHop participates in the development of the gonads. (a) Coomassie-stained gel ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         CeHop participates in the development of the gonads. (a) Coomassie-stained gel (lane 1 + lane 2) and Western blot analysis against recombinant His
         <sub>
          6
         </sub>
         -CeHop and endogenous Hop (lane 3 + lane 4). Recombinant protein was loaded in lanes 1 and 3, whereas whole worm extracts were loaded in lanes 2 and 4. The antibody was raised against CeHop and used as outlined in
         <a>
          Materials and Methods
         </a>
         . (b) The ectopic expression of EYFP under the control of the CeHop promoter is predominant in intestinal tissues and can be detected in several other tissues at lower levels. Tissues are labeled as Pm (pharyngeal muscle cells), Bwm (body-wall muscle cells), Sp (spermathecae), and Int (intestinal cell ring). (c) Light microscopy image of adult hsf-1(sy441)/R09E12.3(RNAi) and hsf(sy441)/control(RNAi) worms. (d–g) DAPI staining of the gonads was performed in
         <em>
          N2
         </em>
         and
         <em>
          hsf-1(sy441)
         </em>
         nematodes treated either with control RNAi or with RNAi against CeHop (R09E12.3). While
         <em>
          hsf-1(sy441)
         </em>
         /
         <em>
          control
         </em>
         (d) and
         <em>
          N2
         </em>
         /
         <em>
          R09E12.3(RNAi)
         </em>
         (g) developed normally,
         <em>
          hsf-1(sy441)
         </em>
         /
         <em>
          R09E12.3(RNAi)
         </em>
         developed malformed gonad arms (e; arrows) or no gonad arms (f; arrows). (h) DAPI staining of
         <em>
          hsf-1(sy441)
         </em>
         /
         <em>
          R09E12.3(RNAi)
         </em>
         germline cells. Oocytes emerging from the distal gonad show bivalent chromosomes (arrows). Spermatheca is marked with a triangle.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1286 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In order to confirm constitutive expression and to investigate which tissues actually express the Hop homologue, we fused the 1.5-kb promoter region of the gene to YFP and generated stable
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    lines by microinjection. We could detect expression from this construct in all major tissues at normal growth temperature (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    b). A particularly strong expression was observed in the intestine, pharynx, spermathecae, and body-wall muscle cells.
   </p>
   <title>
    The truncated CeHop protein is required for the development of fertility
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we were interested to find an organismal function for the TPR1-depleted CeHop. Thus, we performed RNA interference (RNAi) experiments to characterize knockdown phenotypes. Upon knockdown of CeHop/R09E12.3 in wildtype nematodes (
    <em>
     N2
    </em>
    Bristol), we were unable to observe phenotypes consistent with results obtained in large genomic screens
    <a>
     <sup>
      30
     </sup>
    </a>
    and publicly shared information
    <a>
     ‡
    </a>
    . However, when using the strain
    <em>
     PS3551
    </em>
    (
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    ), which shows an impaired heat shock response amid the homozygote early truncation allele
    <em>
     sy441
    </em>
    in the gene for the heat shock transcription factor HSF-1, we observed a sterility phenotype with a penetrance of 100% when subjected to RNAi-mediated knockdown of CeHop (
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    ). Interestingly, these nematodes still developed to adult size (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    c). No sterility was observed when
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    was grown on bacteria expressing control RNAi (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 2.
        </span>
        <p>
         Phenotypic description of RNAi experiments directed against CeHop
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Strain
          </th>
          <th>
           RNAi construct
          </th>
          <th>
           Phenotype
          </th>
          <th>
           Propensity (%)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            N2
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           Control
          </td>
          <td>
           Wild type
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            N2
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3
          </td>
          <td>
           Wild type
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            hsf-1(sy441)
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           Control
          </td>
          <td>
           Wild type
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            hsf-1(sy441)
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           R09E12.3
          </td>
          <td>
           Sterile
          </td>
          <td>
           100
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Only one gonad misformed
          </td>
          <td>
           20
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Both gonads misformed
          </td>
          <td>
           52
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           One gonad missing
          </td>
          <td>
           10
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Both gonads missing
          </td>
          <td>
           0
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Both gonads wildtype-like
          </td>
          <td>
           18
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Experiments were performed by feeding RNAi starting with L1 larvae, as described previously. Phenotypes were scored based on
        <em>
         n
        </em>
        = 50 worms per experiment. A detailed description of changes within the gonad arms was performed after DAPI staining of the animals.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To more specifically identify the processes of CeHop involvement, we performed 4′-6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining of sterile nematodes in order to characterize the developmental status of gonad arms. We observed that the growth of the gonads during the development of
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    is hampered (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    d–g). Even though
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    reached adult size, none had developed the wildtype U-shaped gonad structure. A large fraction of the nematodes had shortened arms of the distal or proximal gonad (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    e); a smaller fraction was lacking one gonad arm (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    f,
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). Additionally,
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    developed endomitotic oocytes in the uterus (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    e, arrows). Despite the endomitotic oocytes and the drastically shortened distal gonad arms, other features of the gonad were found to be in place. Development of oocytes emanating from the distal gonad arm showed the characteristic pattern of six bivalent chromosomes distal to the spermatheca (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    h). Sperm-filled spermathecae were observed in some nematodes, although many
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    appear to develop only small, oddly shaped spermathecae and a few sperms. Based on these RNAi experiments, we conclude that the TPR1-depleted Hop protein exerts cellular functions that can be uncovered as synthetic phenotype in
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    and might particularly be required during the development of fertility.
   </p>
   <title>
    CeHop binds to Hsp90 and inhibits its ATPase activity
   </title>
   <p>
    Having shown that this exotic Hop homologue is widely expressed and participates in organismal processes, we aimed to understand its biochemical properties, as the deletion of TPR1 could affect all proposed biochemical functions of Hop. We therefore investigated whether the ability of this protein to interact with Hsp90 is compromised. First, we tested its interaction with Hsp90 by coimmunoprecipitation after addition of His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -CeHop to whole animal extracts. His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -CeHop was pulled down by Ni-NTA matrices, and attached proteins were analyzed by Western blot analysis. Indeed, we observed an interaction of Hsp90 when His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -CeHop was added, while control experiments in the absence of His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -CeHop did not result in the pulldown of Hsp90 (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    a).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="CeHop binds to Hsp90 and inhibits its ATPase activity. (a) His6-CeHop was used ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         CeHop binds to Hsp90 and inhibits its ATPase activity. (a) His
         <sub>
          6
         </sub>
         -CeHop was used to precipitate Hsp90 from worm extracts. Recombinant
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
         Hsp90 was loaded in lane 1 as control. Ni-NTA agarose pulldowns from worm extracts were performed with (lane 2) and without (lane 3) prior addition of His
         <sub>
          6
         </sub>
         -CeHop. The presence of Hsp90 was analyzed by Western blot analysis using a cross-reactive antibody raised against yeast Hsp90. In lane 4, Hsp90 was detected in untreated worm extracts. (b) The binary binding isotherm (black curve) of CeHop with chip-bound Hsp90 was fitted to SPR signals (●) that were plotted against analyte concentrations. Error bars indicate ± SD. (c) Binding to an Hsp90-bound chip was monitored in the presence of 1 μM CeHop and titrated amounts of competing free Hsp90 (●) and a mutant lacking the C-terminal MEEVD motif, respectively (○). The SPR signal is plotted against the concentration of the ligand. (d) Hop inhibits the ATPase activity of
         <em>
          C. elegans
         </em>
         Hsp90. CeHop was added to ATPase assay mixtures containing 2 μM Hsp90 (●) or 2 μM Hsp90-ΔMEEVD (○) at the indicated end concentrations.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (310 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In order to quantify the binding behavior of CeHop to Hsp90, we purified
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    Hsp90 from recombinant
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    cultures and determined the binding affinities using a surface plasmon resonance (SPR)-based binding assay. The calculated dissociation constant was 204 ± 22 nM for direct titrations (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    b), and a similar value was obtained in competition experiments (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    c). In agreement with data for other eukaryotic systems, the binding of CeHop to Hsp90 was critically dependent on the MEEVD motif at the C-terminus of Hsp90, as a mutant lacking the MEEVD motif did not show competition with chip-coupled Hsp90 (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    c).
   </p>
   <p>
    We next tested whether CeHop binding has an effect on the ATP turnover rate of Hsp90.
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    Hsp90 was found to hydrolyze ATP with a turnover rate of 0.8 min
    <sup>
     − 1
    </sup>
    , slightly higher than that of yeast Hsp90 (
    <em>
     k
    </em>
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    = 0.4 min
    <sup>
     − 1
    </sup>
    ) and far higher than that of human Hsp90 (
    <em>
     k
    </em>
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    = 0.03 min
    <sup>
     − 1
    </sup>
    ). Addition of increasing concentrations of CeHop to Hsp90 has a strong inhibitory effect (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    d) on the Hsp90 turnover rate. Again, no inhibition of ATPase activity was observed in a mutant lacking the MEEVD motif at the C-terminal end of Hsp90.
   </p>
   <p>
    These data imply that the mechanism of the
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    Hop homologue—at least regarding Hsp90—closely resembles the mechanism of the yeast homologue Sti1, which also acts as a potent inhibitor of the Hsp90 ATPase, while the human Hsp90 protein, with its significantly lower ATP turnover and noninhibitory Hop interaction, remains different.
   </p>
   <title>
    CeHop binds to Hsc70 in the absence of TPR1
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we were interested on whether the loss of TPR1 in CeHop compromises the binding of heat shock cognate (Hsc) 70. No distinction regarding the binding of the heat-inducible Hsp70 or the constitutively expressed Hsc70, which share a sequence identity in excess of 90%, has so far been made. Therefore, the constitutive Hsp70 protein Hsc70/
    <em>
     F26D10.3
    </em>
    /HSP-1 was purified from recombinant expression cultures. Hsc70 then was coupled to the chip surface for SPR studies to investigate CeHop binding. Indeed, upon addition of CeHop to the sensor surface, we observed an interaction between CeHop and chip-bound Hsc70 in direct binding assays (
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    a). The interaction was rather weak (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    = 2.7 ± 0.3 μM) compared to the affinity for Hsp90 but similar to published Hsp70·Hop complexes from yeast and human systems.
    <a>
     <sup>
      31
     </sup>
    </a>
    As the interaction of Hsc70 with CeHop does not involve the characterized Hsc70-binding site, we were interested on whether the IEEVD motif at the C-terminal end of Hsc70 is still responsible for this effect. Therefore, we generated an SPR chip by coupling the Hsc70 mutant Hsc70-ΔIEEVD to its surface and investigated the binding of CeHop to the sensor surface. Binding of CeHop was abolished, showing the specificity of the interaction and the requirement of the IEEVD motif for the interaction between CeHop and Hsc70 even in the absence of TPR1 (
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    a).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="CeHop binds weakly to Hsc70. (a) SPR signals (&amp;#9679;) on an Hsc70-bound chip were ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         CeHop binds weakly to Hsc70. (a) SPR signals (●) on an Hsc70-bound chip were plotted against titrated amounts of CeHop in the analyte. The isotherm was fitted according to binary binding behavior (black curve). No change in SPR signals (○) was observed on an Hsc70-ΔIEEVD-coupled chip plotted against the concentration of CeHop in the analyte. (b) The ATPase activity of 4 μM Hsc70 is plotted with increasing concentrations of CeHop present in the reaction mixture as indicated. No change in activity was observed.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (148 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Having seen binding between Hsc70 and CeHop, we were interested to see whether CeHop influences the turnover of Hsc70. Purified Hsc70 was found to hydrolyze ATP with a turnover rate of 0.3 min
    <sup>
     − 1
    </sup>
    . No influence on the ATP turnover of Hsc70 was detected, even at CeHop concentrations far above the determined binding constant (
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    b).
   </p>
   <p>
    Therefore, we conclude that the TPR1-depleted Hop homologue from
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    surprisingly is still capable of binding Hsc70, potentially via the other TPR domains, but fails to stimulate the ATPase activity of Hsc70. This implies that the interaction between these two proteins might functionally not be comparable to the observed interaction of yeast Ssa1 and Sti1/Hop.
    <a>
     <sup>
      31
     </sup>
    </a>
   </p>
   <title>
    Binding of Hsp90 to CeHop competes with Hsc70 binding
   </title>
   <p>
    The apparent complexity of the binary binding of CeHop to either Hsc70 or Hsp90 raised the important question of whether a ternary complex, as proposed in yeast or mammals previously, can be formed even in the absence of the Hsp70-binding site TPR1. We therefore tested whether Hsp90 can compete for the binding of Hop to Hsc70 using the SPR interaction assay. Hsc70 was coupled to the sensor surface and binding of CeHop was observed upon injection, as reported previously (see
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    a). Maintaining constant concentrations of CeHop during the injections, we added increasing concentrations of Hsp90 to the injection solution in order to preform Hsp90-CeHop complexes. Addition of higher concentrations of Hsp90 fully abolished the binding of CeHop to Hsc70 (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). An increase in the concentration of CeHop required proportionally increased amounts of Hsp90 to suppress binding (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). Again, deletion of the MEEVD motif from Hsp90 precludes its binding to CeHop and prevents the inhibitory effect of Hsp90 on the formation of Hsp90-CeHop complexes (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). These results imply that Hsp90 binding to CeHop efficiently prevents binding of CeHop to Hsc70 and, therefore, Hsc70 and Hsp90 apparently compete for binding to the
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    Hop homologue.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="CeHop-Hsp90 interaction competes with CeHop&amp;ndash;Hsc70. Competition assays between ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609007694-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         CeHop-Hsp90 interaction competes with CeHop–Hsc70. Competition assays between Hsp90 and Hsc70 binding to CeHop were performed by using a chip coupled with Hsc70. Change in SPR was monitored upon titration of Hsp90 in the presence of 2 μM (●), 1 μM (○), and 0.5 μM (▪) CeHop in the injection solution, and binary binding isotherms (black lines) were fitted to data points. A reduction in binding signal with increasing concentrations of Hsp90 is interpreted as a competition between Hsc70 and Hsp90 for the cochaperone CeHop. No change in SPR is observed after titration of Hsp90-ΔMEEVD in the presence of 1 μM CeHop (□).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (91 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Regulation of Hsp90 requires both TPR domains of CeHop
   </title>
   <p>
    The inability to simultaneously bind Hsc70 and Hsp90 to the two TPR domains of CeHop raises the question of potentially overlapping binding sites. We therefore aimed to analyze which domains of CeHop participate in the binding of Hsp90 and Hsc70. We individually purified TPR2A (N131-CeHop) and the C-terminal domain, including TPR2B (129C-CeHop). Both domains exhibited a stability similar to that of full-length CeHop, as judged from thermal transitions employing CD spectroscopy and urea transitions (data not shown).
   </p>
   <p>
    We first aimed to characterize the binding of the Hop fragments to Hsc70. Here, N131-CeHop did bind Hsc70 with a weak binding affinity, implying that this domain serves as an interaction site with Hsc70. 129C-CeHop as well showed a weak but unquantifiable interaction with Hsc70 (
    <a>
     Table 3
    </a>
    ). Neither fragment was able to influence ATP turnover by Hsc70 (
    <a>
     Table 3
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 3.
        </span>
        <p>
         Influence of CeHop TPR domains on the ATPase activities of Hsc70 and Hsp90
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
           Hsc70
           <hr/>
          </th>
          <th>
           Hsp90
           <hr/>
          </th>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <th>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (μM)
          </th>
          <th>
           ATPase influence
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (μM)
          </th>
          <th>
           ATPase influence
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CeHop
          </td>
          <td>
           2.7 ± 1.2
          </td>
          <td>
           No
          </td>
          <td>
           0.2 ± 0.05
          </td>
          <td>
           Inhibition
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           N131-CeHop
          </td>
          <td>
           &gt; 10
          </td>
          <td>
           No
          </td>
          <td>
           1.98 ± 0.3
          </td>
          <td>
           No
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           129C-CeHop
          </td>
          <td>
           &gt; 10
          </td>
          <td>
           No
          </td>
          <td>
           —
          </td>
          <td>
           No
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        The binding constants of Hsc70 and Hsp90 derived from SPR studies and the effect of the indicated fragment on ATP turnover are listed for CeHop and two individual purified TPR domains. During ATPase assays, N131-CeHop was used at concentrations of up to 20 μM, whereas 129C-CeHop was used at concentrations of up to 40 μM.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We next tested the binding behavior of the individual Hop domains towards Hsp90. N131-CeHop bound to Hsp90 with a—compared to CeHop—10-fold reduced affinity of 1.98 ± 0.3 μM (
    <a>
     Table 3
    </a>
    ). The isolated TPR2B domain 129C-CeHop did not bind Hsp90 (
    <a>
     Table 3
    </a>
    ). Interestingly, N131-CeHop also was unable to suppress the ATPase activity of Hsp90 at concentrations significantly higher than the binding constant of the TPR2A–Hsp90 complex (
    <a>
     Table 3
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    These findings indicate that, while both TPR domains have some affinity for Hsc70, the full-length CeHop is required for the high affinity binding of Hsp90 for CeHop. The 10-fold reduction in the affinity of N131-CeHop for Hsp90 and the lack of any regulation of the Hsp90 ATPase in complex with isolated TPR2A imply that the second TPR domain significantly contributes to the binding reaction and the functional interaction between CeHop and Hsp90.
   </p>
   <p>
    The combination of these results suggests that—contrary to findings in the yeast and mammalian multichaperone systems—the two chaperones bind competitively to CeHop and that weak binding of Hsc70 is disrupted in the presence of Hsp90.
   </p>
   <title>
    Hsp90 knockdown leads to Hop-like defects during gonad development
   </title>
   <p>
    Hop is not known to perform cellular functions independent of Hsp90 and Hsc70. Having established that the
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    homologue of Hop is able to bind to Hsc70 or Hsp90, we were interested to see whether RNAi knockdown can show involvement of either of the two chaperones in cellular effects seen during the knockdown of CeHop/R09E12.3. Therefore, RNAi experiments were performed using constructs targeted at Hsp90/
    <em>
     daf-21
    </em>
    and Hsc70/
    <em>
     hsp-1
    </em>
    in
    <em>
     N2
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    . Contrarily to
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     daf-21(RNAi)
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     hsp-1(RNAi)
    </em>
    are known to be arrested during larval development,
    <sup>
     <a>
      30
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      32
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      33
     </a>
    </sup>
    resulting in early larval arrest in the case of
    <em>
     N2
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     hsp-1(RNAi)
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     hsp-1(RNAi)
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     daf-21(RNAi)
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Table 4
    </a>
    ).
    <em>
     N2
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     daf-21(RNAi)
    </em>
    developed a protruding vulva phenotype and late larval arrest. In order to prevent early larval arrest phenotypes and to allow detection of phenotypes during gonad development, we started the knockdown at developmental stages of L1, L2, and L3 larvae. We did not observe features of the phenotypes described for
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    during knockdown of Hsc70, as either early larval arrest (starting with L1 or L2) or wildtype (starting with L3) phenotypes were observed. In
    <em>
     N2
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     daf-21(RNAi)
    </em>
    , we did observe a phenotype with limited similarity to
    <em>
     hsf-1(sy441)
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     R09E12.3(RNAi)
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Fig. 6
    </a>
    a,
    <a>
     Table 4
    </a>
    ). While the nematodes displayed late larval arrest and developed a protruding vulva, in particular, the shortened arms on either the proximal gonad or the distal gonad and the development of endomitotic oocytes were observable.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>