<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC2775176
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structural basis for recognition of H3K4 methylation status by the DNA methyltransferase 3A ATRX–DNMT3–DNMT3L domain
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     DNMT3 proteins are
     <em>
      de novo
     </em>
     DNA methyltransferases that are responsible for the establishment of DNA methylation patterns in mammalian genomes. Here, we have determined the crystal structures of the ATRX–DNMT3–DNMT3L (ADD) domain of DNMT3A in an unliganded form and in a complex with the amino-terminal tail of histone H3. Combined with the results of biochemical analysis, the complex structure indicates that DNMT3A recognizes the unmethylated state of lysine 4 in histone H3. This finding indicates that the recruitment of DNMT3A onto chromatin, and thereby
     <em>
      de novo
     </em>
     DNA methylation, is mediated by recognition of the histone modification state by its ADD domain. Furthermore, our biochemical and nuclear magnetic resonance data show mutually exclusive binding of the ADD domain of DNMT3A and the chromodomain of heterochromatin protein 1α to the H3 tail. These results indicate that
     <em>
      de novo
     </em>
     DNA methylation by DNMT3A requires the alteration of chromatin structure.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     DNA methyltransferase, histone modification, heterochromatin protein 1, crystal structure, NMR
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    DNA methylation is one of the principal epigenetic marks associated with a repressed chromatin state and gene silencing, and it regulates various physiological events such as X-chromosome inactivation, embryogenesis and genomic imprinting (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bird, 2002
    </xref>
    ). In mammals, cytosine methylation at the C5 position in CpG dinucleotides is the only covalent modification of genomic DNA under physiological conditions. The
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    establishment of DNA methylation patterns in early mammalian development involves the DNA methyltransferase (DNMT) 3 family members DNMT3A and DNMT3B, and the DNMT3-like non-enzymatic regulatory factor DNMT3L (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Goll &amp; Bestor, 2005
    </xref>
    ). DNMT3L has been shown to recognize unmethylated lysine 4 (Lys 4) of histone H3 (H3K4me0) through its alpha thalassaemia/mental retardation syndrome X-linked homologue (ATRX)–DNMT3–DNMT3L (ADD) domain, indicating that the DNMT3A–DNMT3L complex is targeted to chromatin containing H3K4me0 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Genome-wide analyses have also shown that the chromatin regions tagged with methylated H3K4 are protected from CpG methylation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Okitsu &amp; Hsieh, 2007
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In mammals,
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    DNA methylation in pericentric heterochromatin requires trimethylation of Lys 9 in histone H3 (H3K9me3) by H3K9 histone methyltransferases (HMTases), Suv39h1/2, and the subsequent binding of heterochromatin protein 1 (HP1) to H3K9me3 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Conversely, DNA methylation in euchromatic regions has been suggested to involve HMTase G9a, which catalyses monomethylation and dimethylation of H3K9 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Recently, G9a has been shown to interact directly with DNMT3A/B and to facilitate
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    DNA methylation in early embryonic gene promoters independently of its HMTase activity (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Thus, the mechanism of DNMT3 recruitment for
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    methylation might be different for heterochromatin and euchromatin regions, and a complex scheme of interplay between
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    DNA methylation and histone modifications has recently emerged. However, little is yet known about molecular mechanisms regulating the hierarchical order and/or cooperative action of these epigenetic traits.
   </p>
   <p>
    Here, we report the crystal structures of the ADD domain of DNMT3A (ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    ) in a ligand-free form and in complex with the peptide derived from the amino-terminal tail of histone H3 (H3 tail), and thereby provide structural insight into recognition of histone H3 by the ADD domain at atomic resolution. Together with biochemical data, the crystal structures have shown that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    binds specifically to H3K4me0. Our finding indicates that the ADD domains of the DNMT3 family have a decisive role in blocking DNMT activity in the areas of the genome with chromatin containing methylated H3K4. In addition, our biochemical and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) data have shown that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    competes with the chromodomain (CD) of heterochromatin protein 1α (HP1α; CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    ) for binding to the H3 tail. Considering the previous observations of the recruitment of DNMTs to chromatin that is mediated by HP1 proteins (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ), our results indicate that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    might promote the local chromatin structure conversion required for the catalytic activity of DNMT3A by temporarily displacing HP1α.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Crystal structure of the DNMT3A ADD domain
    </title>
    <p>
     The crystal structure of the ligand-free ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     was determined by using the multiple-wavelength dispersion method with intrinsic zinc atoms at a resolution of 2.3 Å (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1A
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S1A
     </a>
     online). The electron densities for four residues in a loop region (residues 577–580) and the carboxy-terminal five residues (residues 610–614) were not observed, indicating structural disorder in these regions. The overall structure of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     is similar to that of the ADD domains of DNMT3L (ADD
     <sub>
      3L
     </sub>
     ) and ATRX (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ), and is composed of two C
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     -type zinc fingers: GATA binding protein 1 (GATA1) and plant homeodomain (PHD)-type (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S1B
     </a>
     online). The histone-binding-surface character of DNMT3L seemed well conserved in the structure of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S1C
     </a>
     online).
    </p>
    <fig id="f1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Overall structures of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       in the unliganded and H3-bound forms. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Ribbon representation of the ligand-free ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       . Three zinc ions and cysteine residues forming CxxC motifs are shown as magenta spheres and multicoloured stick models, respectively. GATA1-like and PHD fingers are shown in orange and green, respectively. The green dotted line represents the disordered H3N loop. (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Crystal structure of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       (green) bound to the H3 tail (yellow). H3 peptide (residues 1–9) is shown as a ball-and-stick model. The disordered linker peptide that connects the carboxy-terminus of the peptide and the amino-terminus of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       is represented by a yellow dotted line. ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       , ADD domain of DNMT3A; GATA1, GATA binding protein 1; PHD, plant homeodomain.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Histone H3 binding ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
    </title>
    <p>
     We examined the binding of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     to the H3 tail using isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC). ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     binds to peptides with the sequences of the N-terminal 19 and 10 amino acids of histone H3 (designated as H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     and H3
     <sub>
      1–10
     </sub>
     , respectively) with high affinities. The dissociation constant,
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     , is 0.26 μM and 0.75 μM for H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     and H3
     <sub>
      1–10
     </sub>
     , respectively (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). To analyse the effect of the methylation of H3K4 on the interaction between ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and the H3 tail, we introduced analogues of non-methylated, dimethylated and trimethylated lysine at the position of Lys 4 in H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     according to a recently developed procedure (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ), and measured their affinities for ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     using ITC. The affinity of the H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     peptide harbouring an H3K4me0 analogue for ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     =0.57±0.05 μM) was slightly smaller than that of the native H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2A
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Nevertheless, the analogue peptide seemed to mimic the native peptide effectively (
     <a>
      supplementary information
     </a>
     online). Conversely, the H3K4me2 and H3K4me3 analogue peptides showed roughly 10-fold lower affinities for ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , with
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     values of 4.02±0.3 μM and 6.76±0.14 μM, respectively (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2B,C
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Hence, ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     specifically recognizes the non-methylated state of H3K4. Weaker binding to the H3 tail containing methylated H3K4 analogue is consistent with previous observations showing protection of H3K4 methylated regions from DNA methylation (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Okitsu &amp; Hsieh, 2007
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="f2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Calorimetric study of the binding of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       to H3
       <sub>
        1–19
       </sub>
       peptides containing non-methylated (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ), dimethylated (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) or trimethylated (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) H3K4 analogues. Δ
       <em>
        S
       </em>
       , Δ
       <em>
        H
       </em>
       and
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       values are the means of two experiments that used different peptide and protein concentrations. H3
       <sub>
        1–19
       </sub>
       , amino-terminal 19 amino acids of histone H3.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Dissociation constants of the interaction between ADD/CD and H3/H4-tail peptides determined by isothermal titration calorimetry measurements or nuclear magnetic resonance titration experiments
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
    <p>
     During the preparation of this paper, a work was published reporting that symmetrical methylation of Arg 3 in histone H4 (H4R3me2s) and its subsequent recognition by ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     are required for DNA methylation at the human
     <em>
      β-globin
     </em>
     locus, leading to silencing of the embryo-specific genes (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ). However, we could not reproduce the interaction between ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and the H4R3me2 s peptide under our experimental conditions (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ;
     <a>
      supplementary information
     </a>
     online).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Recognition of non-methylated H3K4 by ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
    </title>
    <p>
     We also determined the crystal structure of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     bound to the H3 tail (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1B
     </xref>
     ). In the ligand-free crystal structure, the N-terminus of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     is located in the vicinity of a putative histone-binding groove (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1A
     </xref>
     ). We then linked a peptide consisting of the N-terminal 20 residues of histone H3 to the N-terminus of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     by expressing an H3 peptide–ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     fusion protein (
     <a>
      supplementary information
     </a>
     online), obtained crystals suitable for X-ray diffraction experiments and determined the crystal structure of the linked complex at 2.3 Å resolution. The electron density map allowed us to build a model of the H3 peptide, except for the amino-acid residues from 10 to 16.
    </p>
    <p>
     As commonly observed in PHD fingers–H3 tail complexes, the extended H3 peptide fits into a shallow groove on the PHD-finger motif in ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , resulting in 721 Å
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     of total buried surface area (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3A
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S2
     </a>
     online). The segment from Arg 2 to Thr 6 forms intermolecular main-chain hydrogen bonds with strand β1 of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (residues 541–545), resulting in a continuous three-stranded antiparallel β-sheet. On binding to the H3 tail, a conformational change is induced in the H3 N-terminus recognition loop (H3N loop; residues 577–580) of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , which is disordered in the ligand-free form. The H3N loop is fixed by hydrogen bonds between the terminal amino group of the H3 tail and the main-chain carbonyl oxygen atoms of Ala 575, Ile 576 and Glu 578 of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3B
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S3
     </a>
     online). A 100-fold decreased affinity of the N-terminus acetylated H3 peptide to ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     indicated the importance of N-terminus recognition (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The overall structure of the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –H3 complex is similar to that of the ADD
     <sub>
      3 L
     </sub>
     –H3 complex, and the recognition mode of unmodified H3K4 is well conserved (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3C
     </xref>
     ;
     <a>
      supplementary Figs S2A,B and S3
     </a>
     online). However, the affinity of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     for the H3 peptide is about 10-fold higher than that of ADD
     <sub>
      3L
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The higher H3-binding affinity of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     might be attributable to the substitution of two residues, Ile 576 and Met 548, that are located at the histone interface of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     . A more detailed comparison is given in the
     <a>
      supplementary information
     </a>
     online.
    </p>
    <fig id="f3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Recognition of non-methylated H3K4 by ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       . Red dotted lines indicate hydrogen bonds (&lt;3.3 Å) between H3 and ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       residues. ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       and H3 residues are represented as ball-and-stick models in green and yellow, respectively. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) H3 peptide is shown with a
       <em>
        F
       </em>
       <sub>
        o
       </sub>
       −
       <em>
        F
       </em>
       <sub>
        c
       </sub>
       omit map contoured at 2.0 σ. (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) A close-up view of the recognition of the amino-terminus of the H3 tail by ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       . (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) A close-up view of the Lys 4 binding pocket of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       . ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       , ADD domain of DNMT3A.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     In the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –H3 tail structure, the side chain of H3R2 is fully exposed to solvent, as was previously observed in the DNMT3L–H3 complex structure (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ), implying that the methylation of H3R2 does not affect the affinity between H3 and ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S4
     </a>
     online)
     <sub>
      .
     </sub>
     We examined the effect of asymmetrical dimethylation of H3R2, which is depleted from the active mammalian promoter and negatively correlated with H3K4me3 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ), on the binding of H3 to ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     using ITC. The H3
     <sub>
      1–15
     </sub>
     peptide carrying asymmetrically dimethylated H3R2 bound to ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     with an affinity of 0.74 μM. This value is similar to the
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     value for the unmodified H3 peptide, indicating that the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –H3 interaction is independent of the methylation status of H3R2.
    </p>
    <p>
     The interaction surface of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     observed in the linked complex was consistent with that identified by NMR chemical-shift perturbation using the isolated H3 tail and ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S5
     </a>
     online), indicating that the interactions between ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and the H3 tail in the crystal are not artificially generated by the covalent link between them.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Mutually exclusive H3 binding of DNMT3A and HP1
    </title>
    <p>
     Several studies have showed that DNMTs are recruited to chromatin through interactions with chromo shadow domains (CSDs) of HP1 proteins (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Honda &amp; Selker, 2008
     </xref>
     ). The CD of HP1 proteins, which specifically binds to methylated H3K9, is indispensable for maintaining the condensed chromatin structure in heterochromatin regions. The model of the ternary complex of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     and H3 tail, which was built on the basis of the crystal structures of the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –H3 and CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     –H3 (Protein Data Bank entry; 3FDT) complexes (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S6
     </a>
     online), indicated that binding of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     to the H3 tail might block ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     binding, and vice versa, through steric occlusion of the H3 segment from Gln 5 to Thr 6. The H3 main chain from Ala1 to Thr 6 is covered with ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , whereas CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     binds to the main chain from Gln 5 to Arg 8.
    </p>
    <p>
     We next examined whether ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     bind simultaneously or exclusively to H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     containing H3K9me2 or H3K9me3 analogue using glutathione-
     <em>
      S-
     </em>
     transferase (GST) pulldown assays. The complexes of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     and ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     with K9me2/3 H3 tail were both observed (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4A
     </xref>
     , lane 5, and
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4B
     </xref>
     , lane 5), but the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     –H3 tail ternary complex was not seen (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4A
     </xref>
     , lanes 6–9 and
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4B
     </xref>
     , lanes 6–9). A twofold molar excess of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     efficiently inhibited binding of K9me2 H3
     <sub>
      1–19
     </sub>
     to CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4A
     </xref>
     , lane 7). However, a 10-fold molar excess of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     was needed to compete for roughly half of the peptide bound to ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4B
     </xref>
     , lane 9). The mutually exclusive binding of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     and ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     to the H3 peptide was also shown by a competitive NMR titration experiment. The
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H–
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N correlation spectrum of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labelled CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     in the presence of the non-labelled K9me3 H3 peptide showed a cross-peak pattern, indicating CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     –H3 tail complex formation (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4C
     </xref>
     , left panel). On titration of non-labelled ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , the cross-peak pattern shifted back to that of unliganded CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     in a slow exchange regime of an NMR timescale (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4C
     </xref>
     , right panel). In the presence of twofold molar excess of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     , most of the cross-peaks of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labelled CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     are superimposable onto those of the free-form protein (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S7A
     </a>
     online). The absence of direct interaction between ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     was confirmed by adding unlabelled ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     into
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labelled CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S7B
     </a>
     online). Reciprocally,
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H–
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N correlation experiments using
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labelled ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     showed that H3 binding of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     was perturbed by CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     , albeit less efficiently. Additions of 21-fold and 10-fold molar excesses of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     were required for dissociation of roughly 50% of the complexes of ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     with the H3K9me2 and H3K9me3, respectively (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4D,E
     </xref>
     ). The
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     values of CD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     for H3K9me3 and H3K9me2 were estimated to be 3.6±1.3 μM and 7.0±3.2 μM, respectively, from the signal intensity ratio between the H3-bound and unliganded
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labelled ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     domains observed in the titration experiment. Although the interaction between ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     and CSDs of HP1β has been previously observed in a GST pulldown assay (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      None
     </xref>
     ), the ADD
     <sub>
      3A
     </sub>
     –H3 tail complex formation was not inhibited by the addition of CSD
     <sub>
      HP1α
     </sub>
     in our NMR titration experiments and GST pulldown competition assays (data not shown).
    </p>
    <fig id="f4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Competitive binding of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       and CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       to the H3 tail. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) GST pulldown assay analysed by SDS–PAGE and CBB staining. The GST–CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       bound to H3 K9me2 peptide in the absence of ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       (lane 5) and was competed out by adding ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       (lanes 6–9). (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Reciprocal experiment of (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) using GST–ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       , the H3 K9me3 peptide and CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       . (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       )
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H–
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N HSQC spectra of the
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N-labelled CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       in the ligand-free (green) and H3 K9me3-bound (red) forms are superimposed (left panel). The CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       –H3 K9me3 complex was titrated with unlabelled ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       (right panel). The cross-peak positions of
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N-labelled CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       shifted from those of the H3-bound form to those of the free form during the titration. Selected spectral regions (i)–(iv) are magnified. (
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ,
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       ) Reciprocally,
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N-labelled ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       in complex with H3K9me2 (
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ) or H3K9me3 peptide (
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       ) was titrated by unlabelled CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       . ADD, ATRX–DNMT3–DNMT3L; ADD
       <sub>
        3A
       </sub>
       , ADD domain of DNMT3A; CBB, coomassie brilliant blue; CD
       <sub>
        HP1α
       </sub>
       , chromodomain of HP1α; GST, glutathione-
       <em>
        S-
       </em>
       transferase; HP1α, heterochromatin protein 1α; SDS–PAGE, sodium dodecyl sulphate–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Our structural and biochemical data clearly showed that the DNMT3A ADD domain specifically interacts with non-methylated H3K4, indicating a role of targeting DNMT activity to regions of chromatin lacking methylated H3K4. Conversely, it has previously been suggested that HP1 proteins promote DNA methylation in heterochromatic regions by interacting with both methylated H3K9 and DNMTs. Therefore, it is intriguing that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    and CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    are not able to bind simultaneously to the H3 tail: Our NMR and GST pulldown analyses indicate that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    can effectively dissociate CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    from the H3 tail, which is probably due to the higher H3 tail binding affinity of ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    =0.25 μM) than that of CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    =1.3 μM;
    <a>
     <span>
      Table 1
     </span>
    </a>
    ). DNMT enzymatic activity has been shown to be inhibited by nucleosomal structure and linker histones
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    , despite the association of DNA methylation with repressive chromatin loci, indicating that temporal local loosening of condensed chromatin might be required for DNA methylation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). The HP1 proteins are thought to be essential for maintenance of the heterochromatin structure (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Schulze &amp; Wallrath, 2007
    </xref>
    ), as indicated by the observations that a point mutation within the H3 tail binding surface of CD of HP1 causes loosening of heterochromatin structure (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ) and that tethering of HP1 to euchromatic regions leads to their heterochromatinization in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Recently, disruption of the interaction between the HP1β CD and K9me3 H3 tail has been shown to alter chromatin structure and facilitate H2AX phosphorylation in response to DNA damage (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Thus, it is assumed that the dissociation of HP1 from the H3 tail might cause loosening of chromatin structures. HP1 proteins have been shown to be dynamically mobile and they are continuously exchanged in chromatin in the cells (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Therefore, once DNMT3A has been recruited to the chromatin complex, it is possible that ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    competitively binds to H3 tails harbouring K9me2 or K9me3, displacing the HP1 proteins. Nevertheless, HP1 proteins that are released from the H3 tail might stay in the chromatin complex through interactions between their CSDs and chromatin-binding proteins (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Together with the indication that relatively loose chromatin structure is required for DNMT enzymatic activity, it is tempting to speculate that H3 tail binding of ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    might facilitate dissociation or rearrangement of HP1, which causes local loosening of heterochromatin structure at sites of
    <em>
     de novo
    </em>
    methylation. The affinity of ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    to the K4me0 H3 tail is markedly higher than that of the ADD from DNMT3L (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    =3.4 μM;
    <a>
     <span>
      Table 1
     </span>
    </a>
    ), despite high sequence identity (54–55%). The affinity of the DNMT3L ADD domain for the H3 tail is comparable with those of CDs of HP1α, HP1β and HP1γ for the K9me3 H3 tail (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    =13, 3 and 7 μM, respectively;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     None
    </xref>
    ;
    <a>
     <span>
      Table 1
     </span>
    </a>
    for CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    ). Thus, although the ADD domains of both DNMT3A and DNMT3L reside in the same DNMT3A–DNMT3L complex, they might have functionally distinct roles.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Methods
   </title>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Protein expression and purification.
    </strong>
    The human ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    (residues 476–614) and the H3 tail (residues 1–20): ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    fusion proteins were each bacterially expressed and purified using GST affinity and gel filtration column chromatography. The human HP1α CD (CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    , residues 15–78) was bacterially expressed as a GST fusion. Detailed information about expression vectors and protein preparation is provided in the
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Histone H3 peptide preparation and
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
     binding assays.
    </strong>
    The H3 peptide was expressed in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    as a GST-fusion protein and purified. Detailed information about GST-peptide purification and
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    binding assays is available in the
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Structure determination.
    </strong>
    Crystals of ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    were obtained in a hanging drop containing 2.0 μl protein solution mixed with 1.0 μl reservoir solution that contained 17% PEG 8000, 100 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.5, and 200 mM MgSO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    . Crystals of H3-fused ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    were grown under the conditions of 10% PEG 2000 monomethyl ether and 100 mM Bis–Tris, pH 5.5. X-ray diffraction data sets were collected on the beamline BL-5A at the Photon Factory, Japan, at a temperature of 100 K in cryoprotectant solution containing 20% ethylene glycol. Data processing and structure determination are described in detail in the
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     NMR spectroscopy.
    </strong>
    NMR spectra were recorded at 19°C in 10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.0, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 10%(v/v) D
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O on a Bruker AVANCE 700. Spectra were processed using NMRpipe and analysed using Sparky (
    <a>
     http://www.cgl.ucsf.edu/home/sparky
    </a>
    ). NMR spectra for ligand-free and H3-bound forms were made on the assumption of minimum chemical-shift perturbation. The same comparisons were also made for CD
    <sub>
     HP1α
    </sub>
    . Detailed information about NMR experiments is provided in the
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Coordinates.
    </strong>
    The structures of ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    and the H3 tail–ADD
    <sub>
     3A
    </sub>
    complex have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank (accession codes 3A1A and 3A1B).
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Supplementary information
    </strong>
    is available at
    <em>
     EMBO reports
    </em>
    online (
    <a>
     http://www.emboreports.org
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     supplementary information
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (846K, pdf)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>