<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC2440593
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Direct Binding of Integrin αvβ3 to FGF1 Plays a Role in FGF1
 Signaling*
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     Integrins play a role in fibroblast growth factor (FGF) signaling through
 cross-talk with FGF receptors (FGFRs), but the mechanism underlying the
 cross-talk is unknown. We discovered that [=P05230 FGF1 protein] directly bound to soluble and
 cell-surface [=2566390 integrin αvβ3 protein] (
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     about [=6509751 1
 μ
     <span>
      m kd]
     </span>
     ). Antagonists to αvβ3 (monoclonal antibody 7E3 and
 cyclic RGDfV) blocked this interaction. αvβ3 was the predominant,
 if not the only, integrin that bound to FGF1, because FGF1 bound only weakly
 to several β1 integrins tested. We presented evidence that the CYDMKTTC
 sequence (the specificity loop) within the ligand-binding site of β3
 plays a role in FGF1 binding. We found that the integrin-binding site of FGF1
 overlaps with the heparin-binding site but is distinct from the FGFR-binding
 site using docking simulation and mutagenesis. We identified an FGF1 mutant
 (R50E) that was defective in integrin binding but still bound to heparin and
 FGFR. R50E was defective in inducing DNA synthesis, cell proliferation, cell
 migration, and chemotaxis, suggesting that the direct integrin binding to FGF1
 is critical for FGF signaling. Nevertheless, R50E induced phosphorylation of
 FGFR1 and FRS2α and activation of AKT and ERK1/2. These results suggest
 that the defect in R50E in FGF signaling is not in the initial activation of
 FGF signaling pathway components, but in the later steps in FGF signaling. We
 propose that R50E is a useful tool to identify the role of integrins in FGF
 signaling.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Materials
    </title>
    <p>
     Recombinant soluble αvβ3 was synthesized in CHO K1 cells using
 the soluble αv and β3 expression constructs provided by Tim
 Springer (Center for Blood Research, Boston) and purified by
 nickel-nitrilotriacetic acid affinity chromatography as described
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ). K562 erythroleukemia
 cells that express human integrin α1(α1-K562) were provided by Roy
 Lobb (Biogen, Cambridge, MA). K562 cells that express human
 αvβ3(αvβ3-K562)
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      25
     </xref>
     ) were provided by Eric
 Brown (University of California, San Francisco). K562 cells that express human
 α2, α3, or α4 have been described
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ). K562 cells expressing
 human integrin α6(α6-K562 cells) were generated as described for
 other K562 transfectants. Briefly, we transfected human α6 cDNA in
 pBJ-neo vector (provided by Vito Quaranta) and selected for G418 resistance.
 Stable transfectants were cloned for high expressers by cell sorting. Chinese
 hamster ovary (CHO) cells that express WT β1 or the β1–3-1
 mutant have been described
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Plasmid Construction, Protein Expression, and Purification of the WT
 and Mutant FGF1
    </title>
    <p>
     The human FGF1 cDNA was amplified using PCR with human placenta library as
 a template. A BglII restriction site was introduced at the 5′ end and an
 EcoRI site at the 3′ end of the cDNA fragment with following primers:
 5′-GCAGATCTTTTAATCTGCCTCCAGGGAAT-3′ and
 5′-GCGAATTCTTAATCAGAAGAGACTGGCAG-3′. The resulting fragments were
 digested with BglII and EcoRI and then subcloned into the BamHI/EcoRI sites of
 the pGEX-2T (Amersham Biosciences) vector. Site-directed mutagenesis was
 performed using the QuickChange method
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ). The presence of the
 mutations was verified by DNA sequencing. The WT FGF1 and its mutants were
 expressed in
     <em>
      Escherichia coli
     </em>
     BL21 (DE3) and purified by glutathione
 affinity chromatography as described by the manufacturer's instructions (GE
 Healthcare). To remove endotoxin, GST-FGF1 fusion protein on
 glutathione-agarose was extensively washed with 1% Triton X-114 in PBS. WT,
 the R50E mutant, and the 3xA (E101A/Y108A/N109A) FGF1 mutant were further
 purified using a heparin-Sepharose column (Amersham Biosciences) after
 removing the GST tag by thrombin. The 4xE (K127E/K128E/K133E/R134E) mutant was
 purified by gel filtration. The FGF1 preparations were more than 90%
 homologous in SDS-PAGE.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Synthesis of the FGFR1 D2D3 Fragment
    </title>
    <p>
     A DNA fragment encoding amino acid residues 140–365 of the
 immunoglobulin-like D2 and D3 domains of FGFR1 was amplified by PCR with the
 full-length human FGFR1 cDNA in the pcDNA3 vector (gift from Ann Hanneken, the
 Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA) as a template. A BamHI restriction
 site was introduced at the 5′ end and an XhoI site at the 3′ end
 of the cDNA fragment with the following primers:
 5′-GCGGATCCACAGATAACACCAAACCAAACC-3′,
 5′-GCCTCAGTCACCTCTCTTCCAGGGCTTCC-3′. The resulting cDNA fragment
 was subcloned into the BamHI/XhoI sites of the vector pET21a, and transformed
 into BL21 (DE3). The protein was expressed as an insoluble protein and
 refolded as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     ).
 The refolded protein was purified by affinity chromatography on
 heparin-Sepharose to enrich the properly folded protein. Bound protein was
 eluted with 1
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     NaCl.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Surface Plasmon Resonance (SPR) Analysis
    </title>
    <p>
     <em>
      Heparin-FGF Interaction
     </em>
     —Biotinylated heparin (Sigma) in
 Biacore HBS-EP buffer (0.01
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     Hepes, pH 7.4, 0.15
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     NaCl, 3 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     EDTA, and 0.0005% of surfactant P20) was immobilized by
 a streptavidin sensor chip (Biacore SA Chip) by injecting at 2 μl/min for
 15 min. One response unit difference represents about 1 pg/mm
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     of
 the analytes on the surface matrix of the sensor chip. 5-Fold serially diluted
 WT, R50E, and 3xA ranging from 800 n
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     to 51.2 p
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     and
 2-fold serially diluted 4xE ranging from 1.6 μ
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     to 50
 n
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     in HBS-EP were injected at 50 μl/min for 3 min.
    </p>
    <p>
     <em>
      Integrin-FGF Interaction
     </em>
     —Soluble αvβ3 was
 immobilized on the CM5 sensor chip using a standard amine coupling procedure
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
     ). The WT and R50E FGF1
 were individually 2-fold serially diluted from 8 μ
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     to 125
 n
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     in HBS-P buffer (0.01
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     Hepes, pH 7.4, 0.15
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     NaCl, and 0.0005% of surfactant P20) with 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     of
 Mn
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     , and the 3xA FGF1 was 2-fold serially diluted from 6
 μ
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     to 93.75 n
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     in the same buffer. Samples were
 injected at 50 μl/min for 1.8 min. The HBS-P buffer with 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     of
 Mn
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     was then injected at 50 μl/min for 3 min to allow the bound
 FGF1s to dissociate from the integrin.
    </p>
    <p>
     <em>
      FGF1-FGFR1 D2D3 Interaction
     </em>
     —About 1500 response units of
 FGFR1 D2D3 was immobilized to a sensor chip CM5 by using a standard amine
 coupling method. WT or mutant FGF1 was 2-fold serially diluted from 800 to 50
 n
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     in HBS-P buffer containing 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     of Mn
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     and injected at a flow rate 30 μl/min for 3 min. The same buffer was
 injected at the same flow rate for 3 min to measure the dissociation of the
 bound FGF1 from FGFR1 D2D3.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Docking Simulation
    </title>
    <p>
     In the AutoDock 3.05 program, the ligand is presently compiled to a maximum
 size of 1024 atoms. The solvent-exposed Mg
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     octahedral vertex was
 left empty in the model during docking calculations. Atomic solvation
 parameters and fractional volumes were assigned to the protein atoms by using
 the AddSol utility, and grid maps were calculated by using Auto-Grid utility
 in AutoDock 3.05. A grid map with 127 × 127 × 127 points and a
 grid point spacing of 0.603 Å included the whole metal ion-dependent
 adhesive site-containing face of the I-like domain of β3 and the
 β-propeller domain containing repeats 2–4, which are large enough
 to accommodate the FGF1 structure. Kollman “united-atom” charges
 were used. AutoDock 3.05 uses a Lamarckian genetic algorithm (LGA) that
 couples a typical Darwinian genetic algorithm for global searching with the
 Solis and Wets algorithm for local searching. The LGA parameters were defined
 as follows: the initial population of random individuals had a size of 50
 individuals; each docking was terminated with a maximum number of 1 ×
 10
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
     energy evaluations or a maximum number of 27,000 generations,
 whichever came first; mutation and crossover rates were set at 0.02 and 0.80,
 respectively. An elitism value of 1 was applied, which ensured that the top
 ranked individual in the population always survived into the next generation.
 A maximum of 300 iterations per local search was used. The probability of
 performing a local search on an individual was 0.06, whereas the maximum
 number of consecutive successes or failures before doubling or halving the
 search step size was 4. This set of parameters was used for all dockings.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Integrin Binding Assays
    </title>
    <p>
     Cell adhesion and soluble integrin binding assays were performed as
 described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ).
 Native or heat-denatured (70 °C for 10 min) FGF in 0.1
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     carbonate buffer, pH 9.4, was incubated in a polystyrene 96-well non-tissue
 culture plate overnight at 4 °C. Unbound FGF was removed, and 200 μl of
 0.1% BSA in PBS was added and incubated for 60 min at room temperature. The
 wells were washed with PBS, and soluble integrin αvβ3 in 50 μl
 in Hepes-Tyrode's buffer supplemented with 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     Mn
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     was
 added to the wells and incubated at room temperature for 60 min. Then
 non-bound soluble integrin was removed by rinsing the wells with the same
 buffer. Horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated anti-His tag mouse IgG was
 added to the wells and incubated for 60 min. Non-bound antibodies were removed
 by rinsing the wells with the same buffer, and bound integrins were quantified
 by measuring the absorbance at 450 nm developed from adding the substrate
 3,3′,5,5′-tetramethylbenzidine of HRP.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     DNA Synthesis
    </title>
    <p>
     DNA synthesis was measured by BrdUrd incorporation. Balb 3T3 cells were
 plated on sterile coverslips in 6-well culture plates and serum-starved in
 DMEM supplemented with 0.4% FCS for 48 h. They were stimulated with 5 ng/ml WT
 FGF1 and its mutants for 24 h in the presence of 5 μg/ml heparin. BrdUrd
 (10 μg/ml) was added to the medium for the last 6 h of the incubation.
 Cells were then fixed with 70% ethanol and incubated with 2
     <span>
      n
     </span>
     HCl.
 After the medium was neutralized with 0.1
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     borate buffer (pH 0.5),
 the cells were incubated with anti-BrdUrd antibody (Pharmingen).
 BrdUrd-incorporated cells were stained with HRP-conjugated secondary antibody
 (Bio-Rad) and metal-enhanced 3,3′-diaminobenzidine substrate kit
 (Pierce). 3,3′-Diaminobenzidine-positive and -negative cells were
 counted from the digital images of three independent fields.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Proliferation Assay Using BaF3 Cells Expressing the Human FGFR1c
 Isoform
    </title>
    <p>
     Mouse pro-B BaF3 cells that express human FGFR1c (BaF3-FR1c, kindly
 provided by David Ornitz, Washington University, St. Louis) were maintained in
 a medium containing 0.5 ng/ml IL-3 as described
 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      31
     </xref>
     ). For proliferation
 assays, cells were maintained with WT or mutant FGF1 instead of IL-3, and cell
 proliferation was measured by MTS assays.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Western Blot Analysis
    </title>
    <p>
     NIH3T3 or Balb 3T3 cells were grown to confluence and starved in DMEM
 supplemented with 0.4% FCS for 24 h before FGF1 treatment. The starved cells
 were treated with WT or mutant FGF1 (5 ng/ml) in the presence of 5 μg/ml
 heparin for 10–15 min at 37 °C. Afterward, cells were washed twice
 with ice-cold PBS, and lysed with the lysis buffer (20 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     Tris-HCl,
 pH 8.0, 120 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     NaCl, 5 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     EDTA, 0.5% Triton X-100, 1
 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     dithiothreitol,
 10 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     NaF, 1 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     Na
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     VO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , 10
 μg/ml aprotinin). Protein concentrations in the cell lysates were
 determined using the Bradford protein assay (Bio-Rad). Equal amounts of cell
 proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE in a 10% polyacrylamide gel and Western
 blotting. The first antibodies were anti-FGFR1, anti-phospho-FGFR1
 (Tyr-653/Tyr-654, BIOSOURCE), anti-FRS2α (Santa Cruz Biotechnology,
 Santa Cruz, CA), anti-phospho-FRS2α (Tyr-196), anti-p44/42 ERK1/2 MAPK,
 anti-phospho-p44/42 ERK1/2 MAPK (Thr-202/Tyr-204), anti-AKT, or
 anti-phospho-AKT antibody (Cell Signaling Technology, Inc, Danvers, MA). Bound
 antibodies were detected with HRP-conjugated anti-mouse or anti-rabbit IgG,
 and ECL Western blotting detection reagents (Pierce).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     In Vitro Wound Healing Assay
    </title>
    <p>
     Balb 3T3 cells were plated into 6-well cell culture plates. Cells were
 allowed to grow in DMEM containing 10% FCS overnight, and then cells were
 washed with serum-free medium and starved for 24 h. A scratch was made across
 the cell layer using a pipette tip. After washing with serum-free medium
 twice, DMEM containing 10 ng/ml WT or mutant FGF1 together with 5 μg/ml
 heparin was added to the cells. The wounded areas were quantified by using
 ImageJ.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Chemotaxis
    </title>
    <p>
     A polycarbonate filter of 8 μm pore size of the Transwell insert was
 coated with 10 μg/ml fibronectin (Sigma) overnight at 4 °C. After
 washing, the insert was placed into a 24-well cell culture plate, and the
 lower portion of the plate was filled with 600 μl of serum-free DMEM
 containing 5 ng/ml WT or mutant FGF1. Balb 3T3 cells (10
     <sup>
      5
     </sup>
     cells/filter) were plated on the filter and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h,
 and cells were visualized by crystal violet staining (0.5% crystal violet in
 50 m
     <span>
      m
     </span>
     borate, pH 9.0, and 2% ethanol). The uncoated side of each
 filter was wiped with a cotton swab to remove cells that had not migrated
 through the filter. Chemotaxed cells were counted from the digital images of
 the stained cells, determining the mean number of cells counted per field.
 Results are expressed as means ± S.E. of the relative cell number with
 nonstimulated cells set as 100.
    </p>
    <p>
    </p>
    <p>
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    RESULTS
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     FGF1 Specifically Binds to Integrin
    </em>
    α
    <em>
     v
    </em>
    β
    <em>
     3
    </em>
    —We tested whether FGF1 directly
 interacts with integrins
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    . We found that recombinant soluble
 αvβ3 bound to immobilized WT FGF1 in a dose-dependent manner but
 did not bind to heat-denatured FGF1 in ELISA-type integrin binding assays
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). These
 results suggest that FGF1 binds to integrin αvβ3, and this
 interaction requires an intact three-dimensional structure of FGF1. EDTA and
 mAb 7E3 (anti-β3) blocked the binding of soluble αvβ3 to FGF1,
 suggesting that binding to FGF1 is cation-dependent and specific to
 αvβ3 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). An SPR analysis of the FGF1-αvβ3
 interaction showed that FGF1 binds to αvβ3 at a high affinity (see
 below).
   </p>
   <fig id="fig1" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 1.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Direct binding of FGF1 to integrin αvβ3.
      </strong>
      <em>
       a,
      </em>
      recombinant soluble αvβ3 bound to WT FGF1 but not to heat-denatured
 FGF1. Wells of 96-well microtiter plates were coated with WT or heat-denatured
 FGF1 at the indicated concentrations, and the remaining protein-binding sites
 were blocked with BSA. Recombinant soluble αvβ3 was added to the
 wells and incubated for 1 h at room temperature. Bound αvβ3 was
 determined by using HRP-conjugated anti-His
      <sub>
       6
      </sub>
      antibody and
 peroxidase substrate at
      <em>
       A
      </em>
      <sub>
       450
      </sub>
      . Data are shown as means
 ± S.E. of triplicate experiments.
      <em>
       b,
      </em>
      effects of antibodies and
 EDTA on the binding of soluble αvβ3 to FGF1. The ELISA-type
 integrin-binding assay was performed as described above. Soluble
 αvβ3 was incubated with 10 μg/ml 7E3 or control mouse IgG for 10
 min on ice prior to adding to the wells. Concentrations of MgCl
      <sub>
       2
      </sub>
      and EDTA are 10 and 5 m
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      , respectively. BSA was used as a negative
 control. Data are shown as means ± S.E. of triplicate experiments.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      ,
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      &lt; 0.05,
      <em>
       n
      </em>
      = 3 by
      <em>
       t
      </em>
      test.
      <em>
       c,
      </em>
      adhesion of K562 cells that express different integrins to FGF1.
 Wells of 96-well microtiter plates were coated with FGF1, and the remaining
 protein-binding sites were blocked with BSA. Cells were added to the wells and
 incubated for 1 h at 37 °C in Hepes-Tyrode's buffer containing 1
 m
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      MnCl
      <sub>
       2
      </sub>
      , and bound cells were quantified after removing
 unbound cells by using phosphatase assays. Data are shown as means ±
 S.E. of triplicate experiments.
      <em>
       d,
      </em>
      inhibition of cell adhesion to
 FGF1 by anti-integrin antibodies. Adhesion assay was performed as described in
      <em>
       c
      </em>
      . Cells were incubated with 10 μg/ml control mouse IgG, mAb 7E3
 (anti-β3, function blocking), or KH72 (anti-α5) for 30 min on ice
 prior to adding to the wells. Data are shown as means ± S.E. of
 triplicate experiments.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      ,
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      &lt; 0.05 to control IgG,
      <em>
       n
      </em>
      = 3 by
      <em>
       t
      </em>
      test.
      <em>
       e,
      </em>
      inhibition of
 αvβ3-FGF1 interaction by cyclic RGDfV, a specific antagonist to
 αvβ3. Adhesion assay was performed as described in
      <em>
       c.
      </em>
      Cyclic RGDfV was used at 10 μ
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      , and DMSO, in which stock cyclic
 RGDfV was solubilized, was used as a control.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      ,
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      =
 0.0024 betweenαvβ3-K562 (αvβ3-K)/DMSO
 andαvβ3-K562/cyclic RGDfV.
      <em>
       f,
      </em>
      binding of
 theβ1–3-1 mutant to FGF1. Adhesion assay was performed as described
 in
      <em>
       c.
      </em>
      Cells were incubated with 10 μg/ml control mouse IgG or mAb
 AIIB2 (anti-β1, function blocking). Data are shown as means ± S.E.
 of triplicate experiments.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      ,
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      &lt; 0.05 to DMSO,
      <em>
       n
      </em>
      = 3 by
      <em>
       t
      </em>
      test.
      <em>
       g,
      </em>
      effect of FCS to
 αvβ3-FGF1 interaction. Adhesion assay was performed as described in
      <em>
       c.
      </em>
      Assays were performed in the absence and presence of FCS (10%).
 Data are shown as means ± S.E. of triplicate experiments.
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
    We next tested whether cell-surface αvβ3 binds to FGF1. We found
 that K562 erythroleukemic cells (α5β1
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    ) expressing
 exogenous αvβ3(αvβ3-K562,
 α5β1+/αvβ3+) cells adhered to FGF1, but mock-transfected
 K562 cells showed only weak adhesion to FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). This
 suggests that FGF1 binds to αvβ3, but not to α5β1, on
 the cell surface under the current assay conditions. mAb 7E3 blocked, but mAb
 KH72 (anti-α5) did not significantly block, the adhesion of
 αvβ3-K562 cells to FGF1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Consistent with this finding, cyclic RGDfV, which is
 an antagonist specific to αvβ3
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     32
    </xref>
    ), blocked the adhesion of
 αvβ3-K562 cells to FGF1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). K562 cells that express several β1 integrins
 only weakly adhered to FGF1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). These results suggest that αvβ3 is a
 predominant, if not the only, integrin that binds to FGF1 in our assay
 conditions.
   </p>
   <p>
    Because FGF1-αvβ3 interaction is blocked by mAb 7E3 that has
 been mapped in the ligand-binding site of the β3 subunit
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     33
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     34
    </xref>
    ), and blocked by cyclic
 RGDfV, it is suggested that FGF1 binds to the ligand-binding site of
 αvβ3. We previously reported that a small disulfide-linked loop in
 the I-like domain of β3 plays a critical role in determining ligand
 specificity of αvβ3
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ). To test if FGF1 binding
 requires the specificity loop of αvβ3, we used a β1 mutant in
 which a disulfide-linked loop of β1 (the specificity loop, residues
 187–193) was swapped with the corresponding amino acid residues of
 β3 (the CYDMKTTC sequence) (the β1–3-1 mutation)
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ).
 αvβ1–3-1 has been shown to bind to several αvβ3
 ligands, including vitronectin, fibrinogen, von Willebrand factor
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     35
    </xref>
    ), and a viral surface
 protein (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     36
    </xref>
    ). Nevertheless
 function-blocking anti-β1 mAbs such as AIIB2 blocked ligand binding to
 αvβ1–3-1
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ). We found that CHO cells
 that express β1–3-1 (β1–3-1-CHO) strongly adhered to
 FGF1, whereas those expressing WT β1 (β1-CHO) did not
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ).
 Furthermore, anti-β1 mAb AIIB2 effectively blocked the binding of
 β1–3-1-CHO cells to FGF1. This suggests that the specificity loop
 is critical for FGF1 binding to αvβ3 and that FGF1 interacts with
 αvβ3 in a manner similar to those of known αvβ3 ligands
 (
    <em>
     e.g.
    </em>
    vitronectin). These results also suggest that αvβ1
 and αvβ5 that are expressed in parent CHO and β1-CHO cells do
 not appear to be important for FGF1 binding.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    It is possible that integrin αvβ3 may not interact with FGF1 in
 the presence of plasma adhesive proteins, because they may compete with FGF
 for binding to αvβ3. We found that the presence of 10% fetal bovine
 serum did not suppress αvβ3-specific cell adhesion to FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). This
 consistent with the previous reports that integrin-binding sites in
 serum-adhesive proteins are cryptic (see “Discussion”).
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Generation of Integrin-binding Defective FGF1 Mutants
    </em>
    —To
 localize the integrin-binding site in FGF1, we used a docking simulation
 program and site-directed mutagenesis. AutoDock is a set of docking tools
 widely used for predicting the pose of small ligands bound to receptors
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    ), and the methods are
 being extended to predict protein-protein complex poses
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     38
    </xref>
    ). We performed 50 dockings
 of the FGF1-integrin αvβ3 interaction, each one starting with a
 random initial position and orientation of FGF1 (PDB code 1AXM) with respect
 to the integrin αvβ3 headpiece (PDB code 1L5G). The results were
 clustered together by positional root mean square distance into families of
 similar poses (data not shown). Many of the docking poses clustered well with
 the lowest docking energy, 26.1 kcal/mol (cluster 1). These results predict
 that the docking pose of cluster 1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ) may represent the most probable stable FGF1 pose upon
 binding to αvβ3. This model predicts that the integrin-binding
 interface of FGF1 with integrin αvβ3 is distinct from the
 FGFR-binding site (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     39
    </xref>
    ) but is
 close to or overlapping with the heparin-binding site
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <fig id="fig2" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 2.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Identification of the integrin-binding site in FGF1.
      </strong>
      <em>
       a,
      </em>
      model of FGF1-integrin interaction. Docking simulation of the interaction
 between FGF1 (PDB code 1AXM) and integrin αvβ3 (PDB code 1L5G) was
 performed as described under the “Experimental Procedures” using
 AutoDock3. Model a of 1AXM was used for docking. The headpiece of 1L5G was
 used as a receptor. The pose in the cluster 1 with the lowest docking energy
 -26.3 kcal/mol is shown. This pose represents the most stable pose of FGF1
 when FGF1 interacts with integrin αvβ3.
      <em>
       b,
      </em>
      positions of
 amino acid residues that are selected for mutagenesis at the predicted
 interface between FGF1 and αvβ3. Several amino acid residues within
 the predicted integrin-binding site in FGF1 were selected for mutagenesis.
      <em>
       c,
      </em>
      positions of the amino acid residues (E102A, Y109A, and N110A) at
 the FGFR-binding site selected for mutagenesis. Note that the predicted
 integrin-binding site is distinct from the FGFR-binding site.
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    We introduced several mutations within the predicted integrin-binding site
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    and
    <a>
     <span>
      Table 1
     </span>
    </a>
    ) to localize the
 integrin-binding site in FGF1. We tested the ability of the mutants to bind to
 αvβ3 in ELISA-type binding assays. The Arg-50 to Glu (R50E)
 mutation effectively reduced the binding of soluble αvβ3 to FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Mutating
 positively charged residues (Lys-127, Lys-128, Lys-133, and Arg-134) in the
 predicted integrin-binding site to Glu in combination diminished the binding
 of soluble αvβ3 to FGF1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). Mutating all these residues simultaneously to Glu
 (designated the 4xE mutation) effectively diminished integrin binding. We
 predicted that Glu-102, Tyr-109, and Asn-110 are located in the FGFR-binding
 site from the FGF1-FGFR-2 complex structure
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     39
    </xref>
    ) and mutagenesis data of
 FGF2 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     40
    </xref>
    ). Mutating these
 residues to Ala individually or simultaneously (designated 3xA mutant) did not
 affect integrin binding (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ), whereas the 3xA mutation effectively suppressed the
 binding to FGFR1 (below).
   </p>
   <fig id="fig3" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 3.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Effect of FGF mutations on the binding to integrin αvβ3.
      </strong>
      <em>
       a,
      </em>
      R50E mutation of FGF1 reduced its binding to
 integrinαvβ3. Amino acid residues in the integrin-binding site or
 in the FGFR-binding site were mutated individually or in groups. WT FGF1 and
 the R50E mutant were coated to a plastic plate at various concentrations as
 indicated, and the binding of soluble αvβ3 was determined as
 described in
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       None
      </xref>
      .
 The results show that the R50E mutation reduced αvβ3 binding.
      <em>
       b,
      </em>
      summary of the effects of FGF1 mutations on integrin binding. The
 results suggest that mutations in the predicted integrin-binding site of FGF1
 reduced the binding of solubleαvβ3 to FGF1, but mutations in the
 FGFR-binding site did not.
      <em>
       c
      </em>
      and
      <em>
       d,
      </em>
      binding of WT FGF1
 (
      <em>
       c
      </em>
      ) and R50E FGF1 (
      <em>
       d
      </em>
      ) to αvβ3 in SPR. Soluble
 αvβ3 was immobilized on a CM5 sensor chip. WT and R50E FGF1 were
 individually 2-fold serially diluted from 8 μ
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      to 125
 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      in HBS-P buffer with 1 m
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      of Mn
      <sup>
       2+
      </sup>
      , and the
 3xA FGF1 was 2-fold serially diluted from 6 μ
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      to 93.75
 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      in the same buffer. 4xE did not show any binding to integrin
 (data not shown).
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <sec>
    <a>
     <img/>
    </a>
    <sec>
     <sec>
      <a>
       TABLE 1
      </a>
     </sec>
     <sec>
      <span>
       <strong>
        Amino acid residues at the predicted interface between FGF1 and integrin
 αvβ3
       </strong>
       Amino acid residues of FGF1 or αvβ3 that are
 within a 6-Å distance from αvβ3 or FGF1, respectively, were
 selected
      </span>
      <strong>
       ...
      </strong>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    We assessed the ability of the FGF1 mutants to bind to αvβ3 in
 surface plasmon resonance (SPR) using a sensor chip immobilized with soluble
 αvβ3. WT [=P05230 FGF1 protein] bound to [=2566390 αvβ3 protein] at a high affinity
 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [=6509751 1.1 μ
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    )
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). The [= R50E protein]
 mutant showed much lower
    <em>
     R
    </em>
    <sub>
     max
    </sub>
    value and enhanced off-rate
 to αvβ3, whereas it has a
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    value to
 [=2566390 αvβ3 protein] ([= 1.31 μ
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ) similar to WT FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). The ability
 of the [= 3xA mutant protein] to bind to [=2566390 αvβ3 protein] was intact
 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [= 0.18 μ
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ), but the 4xE mutant did not
 show binding affinity to αvβ3 (data not shown)). These results are
 consistent with those obtained by ELISA-type binding assays.
   </p>
   <p>
    We assessed the ability of these [=P05230 FGF1 protein] mutants to interact with the [=P11362 FGFR1 protein]
 fragment (domains 2 and 3, or FGFR1 D2D3) in SPR using a sensor chip
 immobilized with FGFR1 D2D3. WT FGF1 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [=6509819 30 p
    <span>
     m]
    </span>
    )
 and [= R50E FGF1 protein] (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [= 14 p
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ) had similar affinity
 to FGFR1 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). The [= 4xE mutant protein] showed low affinity to [=P11362 FGFR1 protein]
 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    5.5 μ
    <span>
     m
    </span>
    ; data not shown). The [= 3xA mutant protein]
 has a much lower affinity (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [= 0.41 m
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    )
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <fig id="fig4" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 4.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Effect of FGF mutations on the binding to FGFR and heparin.
      </strong>
      <em>
       a–c,
      </em>
      binding of WT (
      <em>
       a
      </em>
      ), R50E (
      <em>
       b
      </em>
      ), and 3xA
 (
      <em>
       c
      </em>
      ) FGF1 mutant to FGFR1 D2D3 fragment in SPR. FGFR1 D2D3 was
 immobilized to a CM5 sensor chip. WT or mutant FGF1 was 2-fold diluted
 serially from 800 to 50 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      .
      <em>
       K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
      </em>
      is calculated as
 30 p
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for WT FGF1, 14 p
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for R50E, 5.5 μ
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for 4xE, and 0.41 m
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for 3xA.
      <em>
       d,
      </em>
      binding of R50E to
 heparin-Sepharose. We incubated partially purified WT and mutant FGF1 with
 heparin-Sepharose and eluted with increasing concentrations of NaCl. Eluted
 proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and proteins stained with Coomassie
 Brilliant Blue.
      <em>
       e
      </em>
      and
      <em>
       f,
      </em>
      binding of WT FGF1 (
      <em>
       e
      </em>
      ) and
 R50E FGF1 (
      <em>
       f
      </em>
      ) to heparin in SPR. Biotinylated heparin was immobilized
 to a streptavidin sensor chip. 5-fold serially diluted WT, R50E, and 3xA
 ranging from 800 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      to 51.2 p
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      , and 2-fold serially
 diluted 4xE ranging from 1.6 μ
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      to 50 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      in HBS-EP
 were injected at 50 μl/min for 3 min.
      <em>
       K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
      </em>
      is calculated
 as 16.6 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for WT FGF1, 66 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for R50E, and 11.5
 n
      <span>
       m
      </span>
      for 3xA. 4xE did not show any binding to heparin (data not
 shown).
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
    We assessed the ability of the mutants to bind to heparin-Sepharose. WT
 FGF1, and the R50E and 3xA mutants, bound strongly to heparin-Sepharose and
 required 1.2
    <span>
     m
    </span>
    NaCl for elution, but the 4xE mutant did not show
 affinity to heparin (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). In SPR [= R50E protein] (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ) had slightly lower affinity to [=28304 heparin protein]
 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [= 66 n
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ) than WT [=P05230 FGF1 protein] (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [=6509859 16.6 n
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ) (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ), whereas the slightly reduced affinity of R50E to
 heparin did not affect its ability to induce FGFR1 activation and ERK1/2
 activation (see below). The [= 3xA mutant protein] (data not shown) showed affinity to
 [=28304 heparin protein] (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    [= 11.5 n
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    ) similar to that of WT
 FGF1, but the 4xE did not show any affinity to heparin (data not shown).
   </p>
   <p>
    These results are consistent with the prediction that in mutations in the
 predicted integrin-binding site in FGF1 compromised integrin binding and
 heparin binding, but those in the FGFR-binding site affected FGFR binding but
 did not affect integrin binding. The R50E mutation was unique in that it
 reduced integrin binding and induced minimal effect on heparin or FGFR
 binding. Thus we propose that the R50E mutant is useful to determine the
 potential role of integrin αvβ3 in FGF signaling. The 4xE mutation
 was defective in integrin, heparin, and FGFR1 binding and could be used as a
 control together with the 3xA mutant. Positions of these mutations in FGF1 are
 shown in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Effect of the Mutations on FGF-induced DNA Synthesis and Cell
 Migration
    </em>
    —We examined the effect of the FGF1 mutations on
 FGF1-induced DNA synthesis in Balb 3T3 cells. The R50E, 4xE, and 3xA mutants
 induced much lower BrdUrd incorporation than WT FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ), suggesting
 that these mutants are defective in inducing DNA synthesis.
   </p>
   <fig id="fig5" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 5.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Integrin-binding defective FGF1 mutants are defective in FGF
 signaling.
      </strong>
      <em>
       a,
      </em>
      DNA synthesis. Balb 3T3 cells were plated on
 coverslips in 6-well culture plates, serum-starved for 48 h, and stimulated
 with 5 ng/ml WT or mutant FGF1s in the presence of 5 μg/ml heparin for 24
 h. BrdUrd was added to the medium for the last 6 h of the incubation.
 BrdUrd-positive cells were counted. Results are shown as means ± S.E.
 of triplicate experiments.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      , the BrdUrd incorporation was lower in
 cells treated with R50E (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      = 0.0003), 4xE (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      = 0.019), and
 3xA (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      = 0.003) than with WT FGF1. We used 2-way analysis of variance
 for statistical analysis. Similar results were obtained using NIH3T3 cells.
      <em>
       FCS
      </em>
      , 10% FCS was added to the medium as a positive control.
      <em>
       b,
      </em>
      proliferation of BaF3 cells that express human FGFR1c (BaF3-FR1c).
 BaF3-FR1c cells were maintained for 48 h with WT or mutant FGF1 at indicated
 concentrations instead of IL-3, and cell proliferation was measured by MTS
 assays. Results are shown as means ± S.E. of triplicate experiments.
      <em>
       c, in vitro
      </em>
      scratch wound healing. Confluent serum-starved Balb 3T3
 cells were scratched. After washing with serum-free medium, the cells were
 incubated in DMEM containing 5 μg/ml heparin and 5 ng/ml WT or mutant FGF1s
 for 24 h at 37 °C. The rate of wound healing was quantified by using
 ImageJ.
      <em>
       d,
      </em>
      chemotaxis. The bottom of the polycarbonate filter of the
 Transwell apparatus was coated with fibronectin. The lower chamber contained
 serum-free DMEM containing 5 ng/ml WT or the mutants of FGF1. Balb 3T3 cells
 (10
      <sup>
       5
      </sup>
      cells/filter) were plated on filter and incubated 37 °C
 for 24 h, and the cells were stained with crystal violet. The cells that
 migrated to the bottom side of the membrane were counted. Results are
 expressed as means of the number of chemotaxed cells in three fields.
      <sup>
       *
      </sup>
      , the number of chemotaxed cells was lower with R50E (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      =
 0.026), 4xE (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      = 0.0004), and 3xA (
      <em>
       p
      </em>
      = 0.0078) than with WT
 FGF1. We used 2-way analysis of variance for statistical analysis.
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
    To test the ability of the FGF1 mutants to induce cell proliferation, we
 used BaF3 mouse pro-B cells that express human FGFR1c (designated BaF3-FGFR1c)
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     41
    </xref>
    ), which have been used to
 sensitively detect cell proliferation that is dependent on exogenous FGF1. We
 found that WT FGF1 robustly induced proliferation of BaF3-FGFR1c cells,
 whereas the R50E, 4xE, and 3xA mutants did not induce detectable cell
 proliferation (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). This is consistent with the results that these
 mutants were defective in inducing DNA synthesis.
   </p>
   <p>
    Because FGF1 is a potent inducer of cell migration and chemotaxis
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     42
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     43
    </xref>
    ), we tested the ability of
 the mutants to induce cell migration. Using scratch wound healing assays with
 Balb 3T3 cells, we found that although WT FGF1 closed the wound by 59% in 24
 h, the R50E, 4xE, and 3xA mutants did not close the wound in this time frame
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). We found
 that the R50E, 4xE, and 3xA mutants induced much lower chemotaxis than WT FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    ). These
 results suggest that these mutants are defective in inducing cell
 migration.
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Effect of the Integrin-binding Defective Mutations on FGF1
 Signaling
    </em>
    —Next we studied whether these FGF1 mutants induce FGF
 signaling inside the cells. The binding of FGF to FGFR leads to tyrosine
 phosphorylation of the docking protein FRS2α, which functions as a major
 mediator of signaling via FGFR
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     1
    </xref>
    –
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    ).
 This results in recruitment of multiple Grb2-Sos complexes leading to
 activation of the Ras/MAPK signaling pathway
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     44
    </xref>
    ). The mitogenic action of
 the FGFs is mediated in part by the activation of ERK1/2
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     45
    </xref>
    ). WT FGF1 induced
 phosphorylation of FGFR1, FRS2α, AKT (protein kinase B), and ERK1/2. The
 4xE and 3xA mutants showed little or no ability to induce FGFR1, FRS2α,
 or ERK1/2 activation as compared with WT FGF1 and the R50E mutant
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 6
    </xref>
    ), which is consistent
 with the finding that the 4xE and 3xA mutants are defective in binding to
 FGFR1. Notably, the R50E mutant induced FGFR1, FRS2α, AKT, and ERK1/2
 activation to the similar extent of WT FGF1
 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 6
    </xref>
    ). These results suggest
 that the integrin-binding defective R50E FGF1 mutant can induce the initial
 FGFR activation and subsequent FGF signaling and that the slightly reduced
 heparin binding to this mutant did not affect it.
   </p>
   <fig id="fig6" position="float">
    <label>
     FIGURE 6.
    </label>    <caption>
     <p>
      <strong>
       Effect of FGF1 mutations on FGF signaling.
      </strong>
      <em>
       FCS
      </em>
      , 10% FCS.
 Serum-starved NIH3T3 cells were stimulated with WT or mutant FGF1s (5 ng/ml)
 in the presence of 5 μg/ml heparin for 10 min at 37 °C. For FGFR
 phosphorylation (
      <em>
       p-FGFR1
      </em>
      ), phosphorylated FGFR1 was first
 immunoprecipitated from lysates (750 μl, total 2.6 mg of protein) using
 anti-phospho-Tyr antibodies and then blotted using anti-FGFR1 antibodies.
 Whole FGFR1 in cell lysates were detected with anti-FGFR1. For FRS2α,
 ERK1/2, and AKT, cell lysates were analyzed by Western blotting with
 antibodies against phospho-FRS2α, FRS2α, phospho-ERK1/2, ERK1/2,
 phospho-AKT, and AKT, respectively. Results with the 4xE mutant were very
 similar to those with the 3xA mutant (data not shown).
     </p>
    </caption>
   </fig>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    DISCUSSION
   </title>
   <p>
    Although it has been reported that integrins play a critical role in FGF
 signaling (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     13
    </xref>
    ), the specifics
 governing their interaction in this process are still unclear. In this study,
 we showed that integrin αvβ3 directly bound to FGF1 at an affinity
 comparable with those of known integrin ligands. Heat denaturation of FGF1
 destroyed integrin binding, and the amino acid residues of FGF1 that are
 critical for integrin-binding were discontinuous, indicating that proper
 folding of FGF1 is required for integrin binding. Because mAb 7E3 and cyclic
 RGDfV blocked the FGF1-αvβ3 interaction, it is suggested that FGF1
 binds to the ligand-binding site of αvβ3. We showed that the
 specificity loop plays a role in the binding of FGF1 to αvβ3,
 suggesting that FGF1 binds to αvβ3 in a manner similar to that of
 other αvβ3 ligands tested
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     27
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     35
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     36
    </xref>
    ). We showed that 10% fetal
 bovine serum did not suppress αvβ3-mediated cell adhesion to FGF1.
 This is consistent with the reports that integrin-binding sites are cryptic in
 fibrinogen (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     46
    </xref>
    ), fibronectin
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     47
    </xref>
    ), and vitronectin
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     48
    </xref>
    ). These findings suggest
 that the observed FGF1 binding to αvβ3 may happen in biological
 body fluid. It has been proposed that productive integrin-ligand interactions
 require ligand “activation” (
    <em>
     e.g.
    </em>
    by immobilization and
 proteolysis) in addition to activation of integrins
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     46
    </xref>
    ). We recently showed that
 αvβ3 binds to the C-terminal fragment of the fibrinogen
 γ-chain but not to whole fibrinogen in solution
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     49
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    We localized critical amino acid residues of FGF1 for binding to
 αvβ3 using docking simulation and mutagenesis. We found that the
 integrin-binding site overlaps with the heparin-binding site. These findings
 suggest that docking simulation and mutagenesis are useful tools for studying
 how integrins bind to protein ligands. The R50E mutation affected integrin
 binding, although its effect on heparin and FGFR binding was minimal,
 suggesting that this mutation primarily affected integrin binding. The R50E
 mutant did not induce cell proliferation and migration, whereas R50E induced
 FGF1 signaling (FGFR1 phosphorylation, FRS2α phosphorylation, and
 ERK1/2). This suggests that the integrin binding may not be required for the
 early activation of ERK1/2 but is required for the later steps in FGF
 signaling that leads to cell proliferation and migration. Indeed it has been
 reported that that transient ERK1/2 activation is not integrin-dependent and
 not related to cell proliferation, but that sustained ERK1/2 activation is
 integrin-dependent and directly related to cell cycle entry
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     50
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     51
    </xref>
    ). The R50E mutant of FGF1
 may be a useful tool to study the role of integrins in FGF signaling. Further
 studies in this direction are under way.
   </p>
   <p>
    We showed that WT [=P05230 FGF1 protein] free in solution had a
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    of [=6509751 1.1
 μ
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    to [=2566390 αvβ3 kd] and a
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    of around [= 1
 p
    <span>
     m kd]
    </span>
    to [=P11362 FGFR1 protein]. It is thus expected that FGF1 will bind preferentially
 to FGFR on the cell surface. We expect that the binding of FGF1 to FGFR will
 facilitate the binding of FGF1 to αvβ3 because FGF1 is concentrated
 on the cell surface through binding to FGFR. Our results predict that the
 integrin-binding site of FGF1 would be still exposed upon binding to FGFR. The
 results in this study suggest that integrin αvβ3 is a major, if not
 the only, integrin that binds to FGF1. It has been reported that
 αvβ3 is detectable in NIH3T3 cells
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     52
    </xref>
    ) and that αvβ3
 is markedly induced when the Ras-ERK1/2 pathway is activated by Raf oncogene
 in NIH3T3 cells (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     53
    </xref>
    ). The R50E
 mutation is close to the FGF1-FGFR1 domain D2 interface as shown in the
 crystal structure of the FGF1-FGFR1 complex (PDB code 1EVT). We showed that
 the R50E mutation did not affect the binding of FGF1 to FGFR1 D2D3. Also we
 showed that this mutant induced phosphorylation of FGFR1 and FRS2α and
 activation of ERK1/2 and AKT. It is thus unlikely that the R50E mutation
 suppressed FGFR binding. We propose that the primary defect in the R50E mutant
 is in its ability to bind to integrins.
   </p>
   <p>
    In current models of the role of integrins in growth factor signaling,
 integrins interact with ECM ligands, and the resulting integrin-mediated
 signaling merges with growth factor-mediated signaling
 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     54
    </xref>
    ). The present results
 suggest that the direct binding of FGF to integrin αvβ3 is critical
 for proper FGF signaling and that FGF1 itself acts as an integrin ligand. If
 this is the case, it is likely that integrin-FGFR cross-talk may be mediated
 by direct binding of FGF to integrins and FGFR. We showed that FGF1 binds to
 integrins in the presence of 10% serum, consistent with the previous reports
 that integrin-binding sites in major serum adhesive proteins (
    <em>
     e.g.
    </em>
    fibrinogen) are cryptic in solution as discussed above. We propose that
 FGF-integrin interaction occurs in body fluids. Also, we propose that FGF may
 be concentrated on the cell surface through high affinity binding to FGFR.
 This would facilitate FGF-integrin interaction on the cell surface. Because
 FGFR and integrins bind to distinct sites in FGF1, FGFR binding to FGF would
 not block FGF-integrin interaction. Thus we expect that FGF may interact with
 integrins on the cell surface under physiological conditions even if the
 affinity of αvβ3 to FGF in solution in SPR is low
 (
    <em>
     K
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
    </em>
    1 μ
    <span>
     m
    </span>
    ). We showed that an
 integrin-binding defective FGF1 mutant (R50E) was defective in inducing cell
 proliferation and migration. Taken together, we propose that the direct
 FGF-integrin interaction on the cell surface is biologically relevant. The
 present results, however, do not rule out the possibility that ECM-integrin
 interaction is required for FGF signaling. Integrin antagonists or
 down-regulation of integrins block both integrin-ECM and integrin-FGF
 interactions, and do not distinguish the two interactions in FGF signaling.
 The R50E mutant of FGF1 is thus an important tool that selectively blocks
 FGF1-integrin interaction in FGF signaling.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Notes
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
     This work was supported, in whole or in part, by National
 Institutes of Health Grants
 CA113298 and CA093373 (to Y.
 T.). The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the
 payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked
 “
     <em>
      advertisement
     </em>
     ” in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734
 solely to indicate this fact.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
