<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.05.007
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Rif1 and Rif2 Shape Telomere Function and Architecture through Multivalent Rap1 Interactions
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The
    <em>
     Saccharomyces cerevisiae
    </em>
    repressor-activator protein 1 (Rap1) serves as a general transcriptional activator at about 300 genomic loci (
    <a>
     Lieb et al., 2001
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Shore and Nasmyth, 1987
    </a>
    ). At the two
    <em>
     HM
    </em>
    silent mating type loci, Rap1 acts as a repressor of gene expression (gene silencing). Telomere-bound Rap1 is required for different aspects of telomere homeostasis, including telomere length regulation, inhibition of telomere end resection, protection from telomere fusion, and inhibition of undesired activation of the DNA damage checkpoint (reviewed in
    <a>
     Wellinger and Zakian, 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Budding yeast telomere repeats are, on average, 300 bp in length, largely double-stranded, and capable of binding 15–20 Rap1 molecules per telomere (
    <a>
     Gilson et al., 1993
    </a>
    ). The sequence-specific DNA-binding protein Rap1 recognizes the double-stranded TG
    <sub>
     1-3
    </sub>
    DNA moiety directly (
    <a>
     Longtine et al., 1989
    </a>
    ) and recruits the Rap1-interacting factors 1 and 2 (Rif1 and Rif2, respectively). Rif1 and Rif2 associate directly with the Rap1 C-terminal domain (Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    ) in yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) experiments (
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore 1997
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The different protective and regulatory roles of telomeres are not provided by Rap1 alone but in conjunction with other proteins that assemble a “capping” structure, also referred to as the telosome (
    <a>
     Wright et al., 1992
    </a>
    ). The mammalian capping complex is known as shelterin (reviewed in
    <a>
     de Lange, 2005
    </a>
    ). In budding yeast, the protective telomere cap is composed of Rap1-Rif1-Rif2, Ku70-Ku80, and the Cdc13-Stn1-Ten1 (CST) complex. The CST complex associates at the telomeric single-stranded 3′ overhang, preventing its degradation during S phase (
    <a>
     Vodenicharov and Wellinger, 2006
    </a>
    ). The Ku70-Ku80 complex is a ubiquitous DNA end-binding factor that protects telomeres from resection in nondividing cells (
    <a>
     Vodenicharov et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Complexes of Rap1-Rif1-Rif2, being the major protein components that bind double-stranded TG
    <sub>
     1-3
    </sub>
    repeats, serve in central aspects of telomere homeostasis.
   </p>
   <p>
    The capping structure that forms through Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 assembly at telomeres is the focus of this study. Wild-type (WT) telomere length is thought to be maintained by a feedback mechanism that controls telomerase action through an inhibitory signal whose strength is proportional to the amount of bound Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 molecules (
    <a>
     Marcand et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). Consequently, loss of Rif1 or Rif2 results in elongated telomeres. Rif1 and Rif2 prevent telomeres from inadvertent recognition as a DNA double-strand break (DSB), thus contributing to telomere capping. Rif2 and Rap1 inhibit both nuclease access and nonhomologous end-joining (NHEJ) at telomeres (
    <a>
     Marcand et al., 2008
    </a>
    ), whereas the loss of Rif1 does not affect NHEJ and only slightly increases single-stranded DNA generation at telomeres (
    <a>
     Marcand et al., 2008
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Bonetti et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Instead, Rif1 reinforces the CST complex, given that Rif1 is required for cell viability specifically when CST activity is reduced (
    <a>
     Anbalagan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). However, both Rif1 and Rif2 carry out nonoverlapping roles in preventing G2/M checkpoint activation at telomeric DNA ends that are flanked by only short arrays of TG
    <sub>
     1-3
    </sub>
    repeats (
    <a>
     Ribeyre and Shore, 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In vitro, Rap1 molecules bind TG
    <sub>
     1-3
    </sub>
    repeats in an independent fashion, and there is no obvious crosstalk between individual Rap1 units (
    <a>
     Williams et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). No novel property emerges once multiple Rap1 sites are juxtaposed, as judged by the absence of cooperative binding (
    <a>
     Gilson et al., 1993
    </a>
    ). Yet, in vivo, arrays of TG
    <sub>
     1-3
    </sub>
    Rap1-binding sites confer telomere capping properties once approximately 4–5 (or perhaps even fewer) Rap1-binding sites are present (
    <a>
     Ribeyre and Shore, 2012
    </a>
    ). It has been unclear what allows double-stranded arrays of Rap1-binding sites to act as a protective telomeric cap once a certain number of Rap1-binding sites are present. Why the proteinaceous cap is recruited to telomeres, but not to individual Rap1 sites, is a crucial question.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    The focus of our study was to characterize the protein-protein interaction scaffold underlying the
    <em>
     S. cerevisiae
    </em>
    telomere-capping complex comprised of Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2. We set out to examine how these interactions form a capping structure on telomeric DNA and how they contribute to telomere homeostasis in vivo.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Rif2 Interacts through Distinct Epitopes with Two Adjacent Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    Domains
   </title>
   <p>
    First, we examined Rif2 and its complex with Rap1. The structures of Rif2 (residues 66–380) alone (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A) and full-length Rif2 (1–395) in complex with the Rap1 C-terminal domain (Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    : 672–827) were solved by X-ray crystallography (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B) and refined at a 2.9 and 3.3 Å resolution, respectively. In comparing Rif2 in complex with Rap1 and alone, no significant conformational changes are observed in Rif2. The structure of Rif2 identifies it as a member of the ATPase family associated with diverse cellular activities (AAA+) that exist in oligomeric or monomeric form (
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    A and S1B available online). We find that Rif2 is monomeric in solution (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Crystal Structure of Rif2 and the Full-Length Rif2-Rap1RCT Complex(A) Cartoon ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (995 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rif2 Structurally Belongs to AAA+ Family, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;1(A) Comparison of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1557 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The Rif2 AAA+ structure consists of two lobes (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A), an α-helical domain composed of six helices (α0 and α6–α10) and an additional strand-conserved E family (ASCE) domain found as an insertion between α0 and α6. The defining feature of AAA+ proteins is the structurally conserved NTPase domain (ASCE domain), which contains Walker A (or P loop) and B motifs (reviewed in
    <a>
     Erzberger and Berger, 2006
    </a>
    ). Most AAA+ proteins function by linking ATP-mediated conformational changes within an oligomeric assembly to specific chemomechanical motions that direct the translocation or remodeling of target substrates. However, an increasing number of AAA+ proteins that are monomeric and not active as ATPases or do not even bind ATP have been identified. In the case of Rif2, the ATP-binding site within its AAA+ domain is degenerate (
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    B and S1C), and isolated Rif2 shows no measurable ATP hydrolysis (data not shown). We cannot rule out the importance of this site for ligand binding or posttranslational modification, given that mutations in the nucleotide-binding groove exhibited mild phenotypes in telomere length regulation and G2/M checkpoint response in vivo (
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    D and S1E). The Rif2 C terminus (371–395, referred to as Rif2
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A) does not contain discernible secondary structure elements and is found to be stabilized by packing interactions within the Rif2 crystal lattice.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    In the Rif2-Rap1 complex structure (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B), we found that each Rif2 molecule binds to two different Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    molecules through two independent interfaces: the Rif2 AAA+ domain (Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    ) and an N-terminal extension peptide comprising residues 36–48 (subsequently referred to as the Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    -binding module [Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    ]). Conversely, one Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    binds two Rif2 molecules (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F). The Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    -Rap1 interaction is directed towards the N-terminal face of Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    . Rap1 residues F708 and P705 interact with Rif2 residues L79, F342, and V350, participating in extended hydrophobic interactions (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). A pronounced salt bridge is formed between Rif2 E347 and Rap1 R747 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). The interfaces between Rap1 H709 with Rif2 T346, as well as those between Rap1 R747 with Rif2 E347 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C), are consistent with previous mapping attempts (
    <a>
     Feeser and Wolberger, 2008
    </a>
    ). An additional minor interface is provided by Rif2
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    , which we found sandwiched between the Rif2 α-helical bundle and the ASCE domain (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B, 1D, and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    A). Hydrogen bonding interactions were observed between Rif2 L386, Q382, and A375 and Rap1 Q715, D742, and R747, respectively (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D). The second Rap1-binding interface is formed by Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , which attaches as a helix in a Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    surface cleft formed by helices α3 through α6 (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B and 1E). The RBM peptide sequence could be assigned despite medium resolution and was validated by selenomethionine labeling in combination with mutagenesis (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    B–S2D). Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    residues L42 and L44 bind to the Rap1 hydrophobic cleft provided by Rap1 residues L736, L755, L762, and A733 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E). Interestingly, the Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    epitope and the Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    domain from one Rif2 molecule are unable to simultaneously engage with the same Rap1 molecule (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F); the observed distance between the last visible residue in Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    (K48) and the first visible residue of the Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    domain (P61) comprises more than 60 Å in the crystal, whereas the maximally calculated root mean square (rms) end-to-end distance of the interjacent 14-residue linker (48–61) is only 42 Å (
    <a>
     Miller and Goebel, 1968
    </a>
    ). Therefore, the Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    epitope originates from a second Rif2 molecule in the crystal lattice located ∼28 Å from the nearest Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rif2&amp;nbsp;Utilizes Multivalent Binding Domains to Interact with Rap1, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (893 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    A Single Rif2 Molecule Is Able to Bind Two Separate Rap1 Molecules In
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    in Solution
   </title>
   <p>
    The crystal structure indicated that the RBM and AAA+ interfaces of the same Rif2 molecule do not bind to a common Rap1 molecule, but, rather, they bind to two different Rap1 molecules. Furthermore, it predicts that Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    /Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    are able to autonomously bind Rap1. We used isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) to independently validate the Rap1- and Rif2-binding mode observed in the crystal (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    G–1I). In solution, a Rif2 RBM epitope containing residues 30–49 bound Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    with an affinity of ∼30 μM, as measured by ITC (stoichiometry N = 1.1 ± 0.2) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    G). A Rif2 construct without the RBM-epitope, but retaining the AAA+ interface (Rif2 66–395), bound Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    with an affinity of ∼50 μM (N = 1.05 ± 0.02) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    H). Thus, the two isolated RBM and AAA+ interfaces have comparable affinities (Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    , 30 ± 20 μM, versus Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    , 50 ± 30 μM) despite the fact that the Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    interface is considerably larger (Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    , 729 Å
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    , versus Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    , 1280 Å
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E versus
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C–1D). If both interfaces were to bind the same Rap1 molecule, the two dissociation constant (K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    ) values would be expected to potentiate each other, resulting in a significantly higher overall affinity (by orders of magnitude) (
    <a>
     Borsi et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). On the other hand, if the two interfaces were to function independently, no significant change in overall affinity would be expected. Full-length Rif2, carrying both the RBM and the AAA+ interfaces, showed a Rap1-binding affinity of ∼30 μM (N = 1.0 ± 0.2) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    I). Given that both Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    -binding reactions have similar affinities and amplitudes, we interpret the full-length Rif2 titration as a 2(Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    ):2(Rif2 full-length) complex (or multiples thereof) with N ≈ 1. This is consistent with the Rif2 RBM and AAA+ interfaces binding Rap1 independently of each other in solution, each contacting a different Rap1 molecule. Thus, a single Rif2 molecule in solution is able to bind one Rap1 molecule through Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    while holding a second Rap1 in
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    through Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    . Conversely, it is also true that one Rap1 molecule binds simultaneously to two Rif2 molecules in a nonoverlapping fashion (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B, 1F, and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    E).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    Serves as a Rap1-Binding and Tetramerization Module
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we turned our attention to Rif1 and examined its mode of Rap1 binding. Using limited proteolysis, we were able to map the Rif1 carboxyl-terminal Rap1-binding domain to residues 1,857–1,916 (data not shown), designated as Rif1 carboxyl-terminal domain (Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). Subsequently, we crystallized Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    , determined its structure by ab initio methods, and obtained a refined model at a 1.94 Å resolution (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    is composed of two antiparallel Rif1 dimers, tetramerizing along a pseudo-2-fold symmetry axis. Structure-based sequence alignment revealed that the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain is conserved from yeast to humans (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A). The tetramerization interface of the two dimers utilizes four prominent salt bridges formed by residues R1895 and E1906 from the opposing helix α4 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). Using multiangle light scattering (MALS), we confirmed that Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    is also tetrameric in solution, the measured molecular weight (MW) being 93 kDa for a Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    -containing fragment (1,709–1,916) and 23.5 kDa for the monomer (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B). Intradimer packing proceeds in canonical knobs-into-holes fashion, largely driven by internal hydrophobic interactions (L1883, I1886, L1894, L1898, and L1905) and surface salt bridges (K1867 to E1897 and R1876 to D1882) (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and 2C). We find that this interface is important for tetramerization, given that an arginine mutation of residue L1905, which is highly conserved across the eukaryotic orthologs (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A), led to a significant reduction in apparent molecular weight in size-exclusion chromatography (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B). The observed molecular weight of Rif1 L1905R (residues 1,709–1,916) by MALS was 35 ± 2 kDa (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B), indicating an equilibrium between a monomer (23.5 kDa) and a dimer (47 kDa) with no apparent sign of tetramerization.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Crystal Structures of the Rif1CTD Tetramer and the Rif1RBM-Rap1RCT Complex(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1521 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rap1-Binding Modules in Rif1, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;2(A) Structure-based sequence ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (752 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In a previously published Y2H assay, a larger Rif1 construct (1,614–1,916) carrying the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain was reported to bind Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    ). Mutation of E1906K within this construct showed 4-fold reduced binding to Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    . However, the diminished interaction due to the E1906K mutation in Rif1 was rescued by a compensatory D727A mutation in Rap1 (identified as the
    <em>
     rap1-12
    </em>
    allele) (
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    ). On the basis of the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    structure from this study, E1906 is located at the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    interdimer interface (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D) where it is only partially solvent accessible. Additionally, we found that mutation of residues L1905R (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B) and R1895E (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D), located at the intradimer and interdimer interfaces, respectively, showed reduced Rap1 binding in a Y2H assay (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Although the Rap1-binding defect for L1905R was pronounced, the defect seen with Rif1 R1895E was slightly less severe. The structure demonstrates that L1905 is fully buried in the interface and, thereby, unlikely to bind Rap1 directly (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B), although its mutation to arginine interferes with tetramerization, as judged by size-exclusion chromatography (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B). Therefore, the defect in Rap1 binding seen in the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    mutants is most likely an indirect consequence of tetramerization, possibly because tetramerization is required for assembling the Rap1-binding interface.
   </p>
   <title>
    A Short Rif1 Peptide Provides a Second Rap1 Binding Site
   </title>
   <p>
    In our Y2H mutational scanning analysis, we noticed that mutating the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain in a construct spanning residues 1,709–1,916 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A) did not lead to the complete loss of Rap1 binding (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Therefore, we examined conserved Rif1 residues outside the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain in search of additional, previously uncharacterized Rap1-binding sites. Sequence alignments of Rif1 orthologs from diverse yeast species revealed a conserved 20-amino-acid motif (1,752–1,772) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    F). Mutation of conserved residues within this motif (I1760R, I1762R, or I1764R) abolished Rif1-Rap1 binding in Y2H assays (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    G). ITC experiments using a Rif1 construct including both the conserved Rif1 1,752–1,772 peptide and the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain showed an interaction with Rap1 at a K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of ∼20 μM (N = 0.99 ± 0.02) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    H). Mutating the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    still yielded a detectable ITC interaction with an estimated K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of ∼50 μM (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    C–S3D). However, a fragment without the conserved peptide motif (1,766–1,916) only carrying the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain displayed no detectable binding to Rap1 in ITC (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    C–S3D). The conserved Rif1 region comprises residues 1,752–1,772 and, hence, appears to be the major Rap1-binding epitope within Rif1, whereas the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain serves as a tetramerization platform and as a secondary, comparably weaker Rap1-binding site in solution.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Next, we set out to study the molecular details of the Rif1 1,752–1,772 peptide interaction with Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    . This Rif1 peptide, which, in analogy to Rif2, was named the Rap1-binding module (Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    ), cocrystallized with Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    and allowed structural analysis of the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    complex at a 1.6 Å resolution (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    I). In the crystal, we found three Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    molecules in the asymmetric unit complexed by three Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    peptides, resulting in an overall 1:1 stoichiometry. The electron density of Rif1 1,760–1,766 was observed for the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    peptide in the structure. Strikingly, the crystal revealed that Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    binds Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    as a linear peptide at a location identical to that found for Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    I and
    <a>
     1
    </a>
    B). Like Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    binds through extended hydrophobic interactions with Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    binding mediated by residues I1760, I1762, I1764, and F1765 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    I). Secondary structure prediction and limited proteolysis experiments (data not shown) suggest that Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    connects to the tetrameric Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain through an unstructured linker (residues 1,773–1,856) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). Because of the presence of 84 residues between the RBM and CTD domains, this linker is expected to span about 110 Å. Altogether, these data imply that a Rif1 tetramer may bind to more than one (most likely four) Rap1 molecules in solution, in line with the observed stoichiometry in ITC (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    H) (each Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    tetramer is expected to bind four Rap1 molecules, giving rise to an apparent
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    1:1 stoichiometry).
   </p>
   <title>
    Interconnecting Rap1-Rif1 and Rap1-Rif2 Complexes through Overlapping and Nonoverlapping Binding Sites
   </title>
   <p>
    Our structural studies reveal that the RBM domains of Rif1 and Rif2, in complex with Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    , fully overlap structurally and, thus, are mutually exclusive. Yet, as judged by the structure, the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    interfaces do not overlap (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A), and the Rif2 RBM and AAA+ interfaces most likely engage two different Rap1 molecules. Furthermore, this is supported by published data (
    <a>
     Feeser and Wolberger, 2008
    </a>
    ), which can now be rationalized by our structures; mutation of a Rap1 surface residue R747, which we found at the Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    interface (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C), diminished the Rap1-Rif2 interaction by Y2H without affecting the Rap1-Rif1 interaction. The same study demonstrated that mutation of the published Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    -binding site on Rap1 (Rap1, D727) reduced Rap1-Rif1-binding in a Y2H assay but retained the Rap1-Rif2 interaction. This indicated that the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    -binding site on Rap1 is also nonoverlapping with both the Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    or Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    interaction sites (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). Altogether, these data suggest that three of the four Rap1-binding interfaces utilized by Rif1 and Rif2 are nonoverlapping.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rif1 and Rif2 Interlink Rap1 on Telomeric Repeats(A) Left, on Rap1RCT, the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (569 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Although we did not observe a direct interaction between Rif1 and Rif2 by solution pulldown or Y2H assays (data not shown), the modular nature of these nonoverlapping binding sites nonetheless endows Rif1 and Rif2 with the capacity to simultaneously bind to a common Rap1 molecule, giving rise to a Rif1-Rif2-Rap1 ternary complex bridged by Rap1 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
   <title>
    Rif1 and Rif2 Interconnect Rap1 Units on DNA Arrays
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we examined if such an interconnection of neighboring complexes may be facilitated on DNA arrays in vitro, where cognate, juxtaposed Rap1-binding sites are expected to generate high local Rap1 concentrations, potentially leading to stable higher-order complexes. Rap1 binds to its cognate recognition site in a noncooperative manner (
    <a>
     Gilson et al., 1993
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Williams et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Binding occurs independently of the occupancy of adjacent sites, and there was no detectable crosstalk between neighboring Rap1 units on telomeric DNA. We set out to test whether Rif1 and Rif2 serve to interconnect Rap1 units on DNA.
   </p>
   <p>
    In electromobility shift assays (EMSA) we used a
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P-labeled 270 bp telomere DNA fragment (Tel270) carrying 14 predicted Rap1-binding sites (
    <a>
     Gilson et al., 1994
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Williams et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). When Tel270 was incubated with increasing amounts of Rap1, we observed characteristic laddering due to stochastic binding of Rap1 to these 14 sites (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    A). Then, we loaded Rap1 onto Tel270 and subsequently challenged the Rap1-Tel270 complex with unlabeled specific competitor DNA. Under these conditions, no Rap1 displacement from Tel270 was observed (data not shown). Given the slow dissociation rate of Rap1 from its cognate binding site (k
    <sub>
     off
    </sub>
    ≫1 hr) (
    <a>
     Williams et al., 2010
    </a>
    ) and its reduced stability after 1 hr (see
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B), we could not pursue equilibrium-based approaches. Therefore, we examined the distribution of Rap1 when incubated simultaneously with labeled Tel270 substrate and unlabeled specific competitors carrying one (Tel19), two (Tel31), or four (Tel80) Rap1-binding sites (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lanes 3–6). This experimental setup allows us to measure a kinetic parameter, the association rate (or “on”-rate), of Rap1 to arrays of different sizes. The amounts of specific competitor DNA were adjusted such that Tel19, Tel31, and Tel80 provided an equivalent concentration of 240 nM Rap1 recognition sites per experiment, whilst having one, two, or four Rap1 sites per competitor duplex, respectively. Rap1 was held at 80 nM with Tel270 present at 1 nM (equivalent of 14 nM Rap1-binding sites). All experiments were carried out in the presence of poly(dIdC), quenching nonspecific DNA interactions. In EMSA, Rap1 now partitioned away from Tel270 towards the excess of unlabeled substrate. The extent of partitioning was independent of the number of binding sites per competitor DNA (Tel19, Tel31, or Tel80) (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, compare fully occupied Rap1-Tel270 in lane 3 with the partially saturated DNA ladders in lanes 4–6), demonstrating that Rap1 exhibits no preference for arrays over single binding sites, as is expected for noncooperative Rap1-DNA binding.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rap1 Molecules on Arrays of TG1-3 Repeats Are Connected by Rif1 and Rif2, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (636 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Next, we used this assay to investigate whether the addition of Rif1 and Rif2 may favor Rap1 binding to arrays of binding sites and whether any such preference might be dependent on the multivalent Rap1-binding motifs in Rif1 and Rif2. Full-length Rif2 and Rif1 (1,709–1,916, containing both the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and the Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domains) were now included in the experiment (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lanes 7–10; note that Rif1 and Rif2 exhibit no Tel270 binding under the conditions used, lane1). Rap1 partitioning was assessed between labeled Tel270 (14 nM Rap1 sites) and unlabeled Tel80 (240 nM Rap1 sites) (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 10) in the presence of 80 nM Rif2 and 160 nM Rif1. The result showed that Rap1 partitioned between Tel270 (14 sites) and the excess of Tel80 (4 sites) in a manner similar to what was observed with Rap1 alone (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, compare lanes 10 and 6), revealing a distinct ladder on Tel270. Thus, the Tel80 array with four Rap1 sites effectively competed with Tel270 for binding Rap1 in the presence of Rif1 and Rif2. However, when partitioning was carried out between Tel270 and Tel31 with two Rap1 sites (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 9) or between Tel270 and Tel19 with one Rap1 site (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 8) distinct laddering (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 10) disappeared. Then, we repeated the experiment with Tel19 at different time points (10 min and 1 hr), all of which revealed a qualitative difference for partitioning between Tel270 and Tel19 in the presence, or absence of Rif1 and Rif2 (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B). Rather than competing Rap1 off Tel270, giving rise to free Tel270 DNA and lower Rap1 occupancy, the Rif1-Rif2-Rap1 complexes remained bound to Tel270 under these conditions, revealing a broad distribution of higher molecular weight intermediates (see
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    C for detailed explanation). Thus, Tel80 (four sites), Tel31 (two sites), and Tel19 (one site), showing a decreasing number of Rap1-binding sites per molecule but providing the same total number of binding sites per reaction, progressively failed to sequester Rap1 from Tel270 in the presence of Rif1 and Rif2. We conclude that Rif1 and Rif2 enable Rap1, in the biologically relevant time frame of the ∼90 min generation cycle of dividing yeast cells, to associate with arrays of cognate recognition sites preferentially over individual binding sites, a feature not observed in the absence of Rif1 and Rif2.
   </p>
   <title>
    The
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    -Binding Modules in Rif1 and Rif2 Are Required for Array-Specific Rap1-DNA Interactions
   </title>
   <p>
    Because Rif1 and Rif2 do not bind DNA in the absence of Rap1 in our experimental conditions (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 1), we went on to test whether multivalent long-range Rap1-binding interactions in Rif1 and Rif2 mediate preferential recruitment of Rif1-Rif2-Rap1 to arrays. We used the same experimental setup as in
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, comparing Rap1 partitioning between Tel270 and Tel19 in the presence of WT Rif1 and Rif2, or various mutants defective in binding neighboring Rap1 units in
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). Our reasoning was that when the Rap1
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    -binding modules of Rif1 and Rif2 are compromised, preferential binding of Rap1 to arrays in the presence of Rif1 and Rif2 would be lost. This would give rise to band-shift patterns similar to those observed for Rap1 alone. We found that mutation in either the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    (I1762R-I1764R) or the Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM/AAA+
    </sub>
    (E347R-L44R-V45E) motif resulted in a clear loss of preferential binding to Tel270 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C, compare lane 8 with lanes 2 and 4), as indicated by the characteristic laddering previously seen for Rap1 in the absence of Rif1 and Rif2 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B, lane 4). The effect observed when Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM/AAA+
    </sub>
    motifs were both mutated was only slightly more pronounced than when testing one WT and one mutant version of these proteins in combination (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C, compare lane 6 with lanes 2 and 4). Therefore, our data suggest that the preferential binding of Rap1-Rif1-Rif2 assemblies to arrays in vitro requires the long-range Rap1-binding modules (Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM/AAA+
    </sub>
    ) identified in solution. This provides support for the idea that, in Rif1 and Rif2, both Rap1
    <em>
     trans-
    </em>
    binding modules stabilize the protein assembly on arrays of Rap1-binding sites, consistent with the formation of an interlinked scaffold.
   </p>
   <title>
    The Multivalent Rap1-Binding Sites in Rif1 and Rif2 Function at Telomeres In Vivo
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we assessed whether the multivalent Rap1-binding motifs in Rif1 and Rif2 are needed for Rif1- and Rif2-mediated telomere homeostasis in yeast. As a first step, we examined Rif1 and Rif2 recruitment to native telomeres. Alleles encoding Rif1 (I1762R-I1764R, conserved among yeast species) (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    F), Rif1 (L1905R, highly conserved across all eukaryotes) (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A), Rif2 (E347R), and Rif2 (L44R-V45E) mutant proteins (referred to hereafter as Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    , Rif2
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    , and Rif2
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    [
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    A], respectively) were constructed with a C-terminal Myc tag at their endogenous locus for chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP). Western blot analysis indicated that all four mutants are expressed at levels identical to their WT counterparts (
    <a>
     Figures S5
    </a>
    B–S5C). ChIP at telomeres on chromosomes VI-R and XV-L showed a
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    110- and 130-fold enrichment of WT Rif1 protein, respectively (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). In contrast, both Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    proteins showed more than 100-fold reduced telomere localization (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). We note that a Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM/CTD
    </sub>
    double mutant has telomere occupancy similar to the single mutants (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A), indicative of a possible background level of Rif1 binding.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Detailed Comparison of Rif1RBM, Rfi2RBM, and Sir3RBM, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;4(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (788 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Functional Analysis of Rap1-Binding Modules in Rif1 and Rif2 In&amp;nbsp;Vivo(A and B) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (777 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    ChIP analysis of WT Rif2 at telomeres revealed a ∼7- and 10-fold enrichment on chromosomes VI-R and XV-L, respectively (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B). We observed that Rif2
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    mutants reproducibly showed reduced binding to about 50% and 30% of that seen in the
    <em>
     RIF2
    </em>
    WT strain, and a slight additional decrease was observed in a strain expressing the Rif2
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM/AAA+
    </sub>
    double mutant protein, perhaps to background levels (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B). These in vivo results are particularly remarkable for Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    , which showed a clear defect in tetramerization, and Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    exhibited weaker Rap1 binding than Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    in vitro. Given that Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    does not aggregate in vitro (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    B) and is expressed at WT levels in cells (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    B), the Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    phenotype is a consequence of impaired Rap1 binding due to defects in tetramerization. In conclusion, all Rap1-binding interfaces in Rif1 (RBM and CTD) and Rif2 (RBM and AAA+) are functional in vivo, where they are required for efficient recruitment of Rif1 and Rif2 to telomeres.
   </p>
   <title>
    Rap1-Binding Modules in Rif1-Rif2 Are Required for Wild-Type Telomere Length Regulation
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we tested whether decreased Rif1 or Rif2 telomere occupancy, due to mutation of the multivalent long-range Rap1-binding modules, was sufficient to elicit a biological response strong enough to interfere with telomere homeostasis. Rif1 and Rif2 negatively regulate telomere length in a telomerase-dependent manner (
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Levy and Blackburn, 2004
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ). Deletion of
    <em>
     RIF1
    </em>
    gives rise to an approximate 300 bp increase in average telomere TG tract length (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C) (
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    ). Whereas telomere elongation for
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    and
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      CTD
     </em>
    </sub>
    was pronounced (∼150 bp), the phenotypes did not correspond to that of a full
    <em>
     RIF1
    </em>
    deletion (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). A Rif1 mutant strain lacking its entire Rap1 binding C terminus (
    <em>
     rif1_ΔC
    </em>
    ) also gave rise to an intermediate telomere length phenotype, very similar to that seen for the
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    single mutant (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <p>
    Loss of
    <em>
     RIF2
    </em>
    also results in a telomere elongation phenotype, though one that is less pronounced than that seen for the loss of
    <em>
     RIF1
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ). We found that
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    and
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      AAA+
     </em>
    </sub>
    strains had non-WT telomeres with TG tract length increases of
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    50 bp in comparison to the WT strain (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D). In conclusion,
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    ,
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      CTD
     </em>
    </sub>
    ,
    <em>
     rif2
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    , and
    <em>
     rif2
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      AAA+
     </em>
    </sub>
    , defective in Rap1 binding and telomere localization, also show defects in telomere length regulation.
   </p>
   <title>
    Rap1-Binding Modules in Rif1-Rif2 Are Required for Antagonizing SIR-Mediated Silencing
   </title>
   <p>
    The Rif1 and Rif2 capping complex antagonizes transcriptional silencing of genes placed in the vicinity of telomeres, also known as telomere position effect (TPE) (
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Gottschling et al., 1990
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Kyrion et al., 1993
    </a>
    ). Telomeric silencing utilizes most of the genes (
    <em>
     SIR2
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     SIR3
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     SIR4
    </em>
    ) required for silencing of the
    <em>
     HM
    </em>
    loci (
    <a>
     Aparicio et al., 1991
    </a>
    ). Deletion of
    <em>
     RIF1
    </em>
    , and to a lesser extent
    <em>
     RIF2
    </em>
    , triggers increased telomeric silencing (
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ), presumably because Sir and Rif proteins compete for binding to the Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    domain at telomeres. This notion of competitive interplay between Sir and Rif proteins at telomeres is strongly supported by earlier Y2H analysis (
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ), although the detailed molecular basis of this effect is currently unknown.
   </p>
   <p>
    Using X-ray crystallography,
    <a>
     Chen et al., 2011
    </a>
    previously observed that a Sir3 peptide (Sir3
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    ) binds the Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    domain. Now, our results show that the Rap1-binding motifs in Sir3, Rif1, and Rif2 occupy the same binding groove on Rap1 (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    E). On the basis of structural superposition, Sir3
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    within this Rap1 RBM-binding groove are fully overlapping and, hence, mutually exclusive (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    F–4G). Surprisingly, the secondary structure motifs of the RBM domains used for Rap1 binding differ, as does the directionality of the protein chains, revealing an unexpected structural plasticity. This was not anticipated on the basis of sequence analysis and precluded prior recognition of Rif1 and Rif2 RBM motifs (see
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    H–S5I).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    To ask whether the Rif1 and Rif2 scaffold competes through its RBM domains with Sir3 for binding Rap1 in vivo, we used standard reporter genes placed at a truncated telomere (
    <em>
     telVII-L::URA3
    </em>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    H, see
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for a detailed description). The
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    mutant strain was found to exhibit a 100-fold increase in
    <em>
     URA3
    </em>
    repression (as measured by the fluoroorotic acid [FOA] growth assay), an effect similar to that seen in a
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    Δ strain, and indicative of increased Sir3 activity at the locus. Similarly, mutations in the RBM motif of Rif2 (
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    ) gave rise to a TPE phenotype comparable to that of
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    Δ cells. The
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    <em>
     /rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    double mutant showed a greater than additive increase in
    <em>
     URA3
    </em>
    repression (
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    10
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    -fold), indicating that the RBM domains of Rif1 and Rif2 synergistically antagonize telomeric silencing. We note that the TPE effects of
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    and
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    cannot be explained by an indirect effect acting through telomere length, given that, in otherwise WT cells, an increase of &gt;600 bp is required to affect TPE (
    <a>
     Kyrion et al., 1993
    </a>
    ), whereas the length change in all mutants is considerably smaller (
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    , 150 bp;
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    , 50 bp;
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    <em>
     / rif2
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    , 200–300 bp) (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    C–4D and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    E). Thus, the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    motifs are required to antagonize silencing and function synergistically in competing with Sir3 for the Rap1-binding groove in vivo.
   </p>
   <p>
    Next, we asked if modulating silencing requires only the RBM domains or whether all Rap1-binding interfaces in Rif1 and Rif2 are needed for competition with SIR proteins. We focused on Rif1, which had the most pronounced effects on silencing (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    H) (
    <a>
     Wotton and Shore, 1997
    </a>
    ;
    <a>
     Feeser and Wolberger, 2008
    </a>
    ). Silencing assays at telomeres revealed a comparable magnitude of silencing effects for
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      CTD
     </em>
    </sub>
    and
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    mutant strains (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    I). This observation correlates with the similar decrease of Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    mutant proteins in their telomere occupancies, as measured by ChIP (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). Thus, silencing changes in
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    mutants are primarily caused by reduced Rif1 telomere occupancy because of an impaired Rap1 interaction. Furthermore, we conclude that all Rap1-binding domains tested in Rif1 (Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    ) and Rif2 (Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    ) are simultaneously needed for modulating telomeric silencing in vivo.
   </p>
   <title>
    Mutations of Rap1-Binding Interfaces in Rif2, but Not in Rif1, Trigger the G2/M Checkpoint at Telomeric DSBs
   </title>
   <p>
    Defects in replication, repair, or telomere capping trigger a G2/M checkpoint arrest (reviewed in
    <a>
     Lisby and Rothstein, 2004
    </a>
    ). We used a single-cell assay to assess the role of the Rif1 and Rif2 scaffold in inhibiting the G2/M checkpoint activation triggered by an HO-endonuclease-induced DSB flanked by 80 bp telomere tracts (TG80) (
    <a>
     Michelson et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). WT Rif1 and Rif2 are required for the prevention of short TG80 telomeric tracts from initiating a DNA-damage response that arrests the cell cycle, each deletion mutant giving rise to a transient G2/M delay of about 1 hr after HO-induced cleavage (
    <a>
     Ribeyre and Shore, 2012
    </a>
    ). Using our Rif1 and Rif2 mutants, we found that
    <em>
     rif2
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      AAA+
     </em>
    </sub>
    caused a G2/M arrest (∼1 hr) comparable to that seen in the
    <em>
     rif2
    </em>
    Δ strain (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A), whereas mutations in the Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    domain (
    <em>
     rif2
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    ) led to a slightly shorter arrest of 30–45 min (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). Thus, both long-range Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    interfaces, used for Rap1 binding and telomere recruitment, are needed for the prevention of inappropriate G2/M checkpoint activation at short telomeres in vivo.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Influence of Rif1 and Rif2 Mutants on G2/M Arrest at Telomeric DSBs(A) Mutations ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (523 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Summary of In Vivo Assays for Mutants of Rif1 and Rif2
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
           G2/M Arrest Assay
           <hr/>
          </th>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
          </th>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <th>
          </th>
          <th>
           Genotype
          </th>
          <th>
           Average Restart Time (hr)
          </th>
          <th>
           Phenotype Similar to (WT/Δ)
          </th>
          <th>
           Telomere Length
          </th>
          <th>
           Silencing Deficiency (TPE)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Controls
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           4.1
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif2Δ
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           5.1
          </td>
          <td>
           Δ
          </td>
          <td>
           ++
          </td>
          <td>
           ++
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rif2
           <sub>
            AAA+
           </sub>
           -Rap1 Interface
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif2-E347R
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           5.1
          </td>
          <td>
           Δ
          </td>
          <td>
           +
          </td>
          <td>
           ND
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rif2
           <sub>
            RBM
           </sub>
           -Rap1 Interface
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif2-L44R-V45E
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.7
          </td>
          <td>
           Δ
          </td>
          <td>
           +
          </td>
          <td>
           ++
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Controls
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           4.1
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif1Δ
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.9
          </td>
          <td>
           Δ
          </td>
          <td>
           +++
          </td>
          <td>
           +++
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rif1
           <sub>
            RBM
           </sub>
           -Rap1 interface
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif1-I1762R-I1764R
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.3
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           +
          </td>
          <td>
           +++
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rif1
           <sub>
            CTD
           </sub>
           -Rap1 interface
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif1-L1905R
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.2
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           +
          </td>
          <td>
           +++
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Rif1
           <sub>
            RBM/CTD
           </sub>
           -Rap1 interface
          </td>
          <td>
           <em>
            rif1-I1762R-I1764R-L1905R
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           4.3
          </td>
          <td>
           WT
          </td>
          <td>
           +
          </td>
          <td>
           ND
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        +, increase; ND, not determined.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    When testing the Rif1 mutants in the G2/M assay, we found that the single
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    or
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      CTD
     </em>
    </sub>
    mutant strains did not significantly delay cell-cycle progression (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B), although
    <em>
     rif1
    </em>
    Δ did. This was observed despite the fact that the Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    mutant proteins appear to be practically absent at normal, undamaged telomeres and display clear phenotypes in telomere length regulation and transcriptional silencing. Thus, we examined in detail whether Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    or Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    mutant proteins are recruited to telomeric DSBs despite their compromised Rap1 binding. Before HO-mediated DSB formation at the duplicated TG80 arrays, WT Rif1 is clearly detectable, whereas Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    or Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    binding appears considerably lower (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). The reduced presence of Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    is in line with our observation of decreased recruitment of these mutants to native telomeres (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). Following HO cutting, additional WT Rif1 is recruited to both TG80 ends, perhaps partly because they are actively elongated. Surprisingly, Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    were also readily detectable at the HO-cut TG80 ends (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C), albeit at lower levels in comparison to the Rif1 WT protein. The fold increase of WT Rif1 and Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    (or Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    ) at the TG80 tracts before and after HO induction was comparable (
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    5-fold). A Rif1
    <sup>
     *
    </sup>
    <sub>
     RBM/CTD
    </sub>
    double mutant, expected to be further compromised in Rap1 binding, was, nonetheless, recruited to the TG80 ends and showed a WT G2/M checkpoint response, (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    B and 5C). Although they are defective in telomere binding, length regulation, and silencing, the
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      RBM
     </em>
    </sub>
    and
    <em>
     rif1
     <sup>
      *
     </sup>
    </em>
    <sub>
     <em>
      CTD
     </em>
    </sub>
    mutant strains exhibit a separation-of-function phenotype with respect to their G2/M checkpoint role allowing for Rap1-independent recruitment to telomeric DSBs (see
    <a>
     Figures S6
    </a>
    A–S6B for further characterization and discussion of Rif1 G2/M separation of function).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rif2-Independent Recruitment of Rif1 to Telomeric DSBs, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;5(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (271 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In summary, we have observed that Rif1 and Rif2 bestow specific binding of Rap1 to arrays of Rap1 binding sites in vitro in a manner dependent on the Rif1 and Rif2 multivalent long-range Rap1-binding interactions identified by structural means. We found that these multivalent interactions are all required for Rif1 and Rif2 telomere binding and modulating telomeric silencing in vivo. In the case of Rif1, defects in the long-range Rap1-binding modules had no discernable effect on Rif1-mediated G2/M checkpoint inhibition, although other phenotypes related to telomere length regulation and silencing were detected.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <title>
    Model for Rap1-Rif1-Rif2 Assembly at Telomeric Arrays
   </title>
   <p>
    The structural and biochemical findings reported here allow us to define the principal structural building blocks of the higher-order telosome assembly at double-stranded Rap1-binding site repeats.
   </p>
   <title>
    Rap1-Rif2: Interconnecting Neighboring Rap1 Units
   </title>
   <p>
    Rif2 can bind individual Rap1 molecules either through its AAA+ or RBM interfaces, both of which have comparable affinity. When neighboring Rap1 molecules are spaced in close proximity, Rif2 is expected to be able to interconnect two Rap1 molecules in
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    using both interfaces connected through a flexible linker. A hypothetical model of such an assembly, assuming Rap1-binding sites are set apart by 19 bp, is shown in
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A. Because of the length restriction of the Rif2 flexible linker connecting the RBM and AAA+ domains (spanning a maximal length of 42 Å), Rif2-Rap1
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    binding is expected to be dependent on the DNA spacing and the radial orientation between Rap1-binding sites. The system is most likely expected to be plastic, given that Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    is connected to the remainder of Rap1 through a flexible linker (∼70 Å to maximally 90 Å in length) and Rap1 binding may induce distortion of the DNA (
    <a>
     Gilson et al., 1993
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Model of the Rap1-Rif1-Rif2 Assembly at Telomeres(A) Rif2-Rap1 binding in trans ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1500 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Rap1-Rif1: Interconnecting Distal Rap1 Units
   </title>
   <p>
    The Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    epitope is attached to its Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    domain via a
    <em>
     ∼
    </em>
    110 Å linker. Although Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    appears to be the major Rap1-binding site in our in vitro assay, Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    plays only an accessory role. However, we observed in vivo that both the RBM and CTD domains are of equal importance in telomere homeostasis. On the basis of molecular modeling, we estimate that Rif1, with its four RBM domains coupled to its tetramerization CTD domain, can interlink up to four neighboring Rap1 units over 30 bp of spacing between Rap1-binding sites (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B). Thus, the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    tetramer with its predicted end-to-end distance of 2 × 110 Å is expected to bridge Rap1 molecules over longer distances in comparison to Rif2.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Mixed Rap1-Rif1 and Rap1-Rif2 Interconnections
   </title>
   <p>
    Although the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    interfaces on Rap1 are directly overlapping, the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    or Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    interfaces are not mutually exclusive with those of Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    and Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    (structural studies
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     2
    </a>
    , and
    <a>
     3
    </a>
    A and mutagenesis by
    <a>
     Feeser and Wolberger, 2008
    </a>
    ). This allows Rap1, once its RBM-binding groove is occupied by either Rif1 or Rif2, to bind neighboring Rif2 or Rif1 molecules through the AAA+ or CTD interfaces, respectively (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <title>
    The Velcro Model for Telomere Organization
   </title>
   <p>
    Now, we provide the biochemical, biophysical, and structural characterization of Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 binding to telomeric arrays. In vitro, a higher-order interlinked scaffold exists when reconstituting Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 on a native telomeric DNA substrate (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and 3C). Such interlinking also appears to operate in vivo. The Rif1 RBM domain is the main Rap1-binding site, although the CTD domain has a lower Rap1 affinity, providing
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    binding through tetramerization. However, in vivo, neither one alone suffices as a Rap1-binding module for telomere recruitment of Rif1. Similarly for Rif2, mutation of either Rap1-binding site (Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    or Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    ) was equivalent to the disruption of both sites simultaneously. Altogether, this suggests that multivalent weak Rap1-binding modules provided by Rif1 and Rif2 serve in stabilizing telosome formation in vivo. Furthermore, the observed Rap1 preference for arrays in the presence of Rif1 and Rif2 in vitro provides a biochemical rationale for the preferential binding of Rap1-Rif1-Rif2 to telomeres in vivo.
   </p>
   <p>
    The exact spatial organization and local concentrations of Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 on telomeres is unknown. On the basis of our data, we propose a model where interactions (
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    A–6C) identified by structural means, characterized in solution, and found to bestow array-specific Rap1 binding to telomeric DNA would predict a high propensity for Rap1-Rif1-Rif2 to form a molecular Velcro, in which Rap1 units become interlinked in a Rif1- and Rif2-dependent manner in vivo. Rap1 affinities provided by Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , and Rif2
    <sub>
     AAA+
    </sub>
    appear balanced (20–50 μM), in principle allowing a stochastic combination of the different possible binding modes. We favor a model where Rap1, Rif1, and Rif2 form a heterogeneous assembly rather than a defined stoichiometric complex (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D), given that this may be better adapted to accommodate the irregular DNA spacing found at telomeric Rap1 site arrays in budding yeast (see also
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Rif1 and Rif2 Form a Multivalent Velcro on Telomeric Rap1 Repeats, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867413005722-figs7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (724 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The Velcro-like binding mode utilizing arrays of weak binding sites confers plasticity to structures such as the telosome, allowing them to undergo disassembly and reformation in every S phase while providing stability in the other phases of the cell cycle.
   </p>
   <title>
    Higher-Order Architectures Serving a Biological Function
   </title>
   <p>
    The structural and functional characterization of Rif1 and Rif2 enabled us to dissect the molecular contribution of this scaffold to telomere homeostasis. Mutations in any of the Rap1-binding modules in Rif1 and Rif2 resulted in defects in Rif1 and Rif2 telomere recruitment (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B) and, as a consequence, defective telomere length regulation (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    C and 4D). Similarly, mutations in the Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    , Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    , and Rif2
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    motifs gave rise to transcriptional silencing effects. In silencing, we find, surprisingly, that the structural RBM motifs constituting an important part of the Velcro architecture directly and functionally compete with Sir3 for binding to Rap1. Thus, the Velcro is not only an array-specific recruitment mechanism but also a functional architecture. Although it is speculative at this point, a more direct role of the Velcro in sterically protecting telomeres from nucleases or regulating telomere length through limiting telomerase access (
    <a>
     Gallardo et al., 2011
    </a>
    ) deserves further attention in the future.
   </p>
   <title>
    Organizing DNA Arrays
   </title>
   <p>
    This work provides insights into how genomic arrays (telomeric Rap1-binding sites) are packaged through array-specific complexes, such as Rif1 and Rif2, into higher-order structures, which are, in turn, required for telomere function. Genome sequences in many organisms often contain a large number of repeated units that bind pleiotropic transcription factors. The multivalent long-range interaction network observed herein, and the resulting Velcro architecture, would allow dedicated protein complexes to bring novel biological functions specifically to these repeated DNA domains.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Protein Expression and Purification
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     S. cerevisiae
    </em>
    Rap1 and Rif1 constructs were expressed in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    , and full-length Rif2 was produced in insect cells. Expression and purification procedures are outlined in the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystallization and Structure Determination
   </title>
   <p>
    Rif2 was solved by single-wavelength anomalous dispersion. The Rif2-Rap1 complex structure was solved by molecular replacement with the Rif2 structure and that of the Rap1 C-terminal domain. The Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    was solved by ab initio methods. Details for crystallization, data collection, structure determination, and refinement statistics are given in
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    and the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Biochemical Assays
   </title>
   <p>
    Isothermal calorimetry, DNA substrate preparation, and analysis by EMSA are outlined in the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Cellular Assays
   </title>
   <p>
    Y2H experiments were performed as outlined in
    <a>
     Hardy et al., 1992
    </a>
    , and the telomere blots and G2/M assay performed are described in
    <a>
     Ribeyre and Shore, 2012
    </a>
    . For experimental details and the design of silencing assays, please refer to the
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The models and structure factors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank with the PDB under accession numbers
    <a>
     4BJ1
    </a>
    (Rif2
    <sub>
     66-380
    </sub>
    ),
    <a>
     4BJ5
    </a>
    (Rif2
    <sub>
     1-395
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    ),
    <a>
     4BJ6
    </a>
    (Rif2
    <sub>
     35-395
    </sub>
    ),
    <a>
     4BJT
    </a>
    (Rif1
    <sub>
     RBM
    </sub>
    -Rap1
    <sub>
     RCT
    </sub>
    ), and
    <a>
     4BJS
    </a>
    (Rif1
    <sub>
     CTD
    </sub>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Tables S1–S3.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (137 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (6584 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Anbalagan et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Anbalagan, D. Bonetti, G. Lucchini, M.P. Longhese
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Rif1 supports the function of the CST complex in yeast telomere capping
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PLoS Genet., 7 (2011), p. e1002024
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Aparicio et al., 1991
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        O.M. Aparicio, B.L. Billington, D.E. Gottschling
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Modifiers of position effect are shared between telomeric and silent mating-type loci in S. cerevisiae
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 66 (1991), pp. 1279–1287
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bonetti et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Bonetti, M. Clerici, N. Manfrini, G. Lucchini, M.P. Longhese
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The MRX complex plays multiple functions in resection of Yku- and Rif2-protected DNA ends
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PLoS ONE, 5 (2010), p. e14142
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Borsi et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V. Borsi, V. Calderone, M. Fragai, C. Luchinat, N. Sarti
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Entropic contribution to the linking coefficient in fragment based drug design: a case study
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Med. Chem., 53 (2010), pp. 4285–4289
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chen et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Chen, R. Rai, Z.R. Zhou, J. Kanoh, C. Ribeyre, Y. Yang, H. Zheng, P. Damay, F. Wang, H. Tsujii,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A conserved motif within RAP1 has diversified roles in telomere protection and regulation in different organisms
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 18 (2011), pp. 213–221
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         de Lange, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. de Lange
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Shelterin: the protein complex that shapes and safeguards human telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 19 (2005), pp. 2100–2110
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Erzberger and Berger, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.P. Erzberger, J.M. Berger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Evolutionary relationships and structural mechanisms of AAA+ proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct., 35 (2006), pp. 93–114
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feeser and Wolberger, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.A. Feeser, C. Wolberger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural and functional studies of the Rap1 C-terminus reveal novel separation-of-function mutants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 380 (2008), pp. 520–531
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gallardo et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Gallardo, N. Laterreur, E. Cusanelli, F. Ouenzar, E. Querido, R.J. Wellinger, P. Chartrand
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Live cell imaging of telomerase RNA dynamics reveals cell cycle-dependent clustering of telomerase at elongating telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 44 (2011), pp. 819–827
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gilson et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Gilson, M. Roberge, R. Giraldo, D. Rhodes, S.M. Gasser
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distortion of the DNA double helix by RAP1 at silencers and multiple telomeric binding sites
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Biol., 231 (1993), pp. 293–310
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gilson et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Gilson, T. Müller, J. Sogo, T. Laroche, S.M. Gasser
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAP1 stimulates single- to double-strand association of yeast telomeric DNA: implications for telomere-telomere interactions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 22 (1994), pp. 5310–5320
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gottschling et al., 1990
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.E. Gottschling, O.M. Aparicio, B.L. Billington, V.A. Zakian
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Position effect at S. cerevisiae telomeres: reversible repression of Pol II transcription
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 63 (1990), pp. 751–762
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hardy et al., 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.F. Hardy, L. Sussel, D. Shore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A RAP1-interacting protein involved in transcriptional silencing and telomere length regulation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 6 (1992), pp. 801–814
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         König et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. König, R. Giraldo, L. Chapman, D. Rhodes
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The crystal structure of the DNA-binding domain of yeast RAP1 in complex with telomeric DNA
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 85 (1996), pp. 125–136
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kyrion et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Kyrion, K. Liu, C. Liu, A.J. Lustig
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RAP1 and telomere structure regulate telomere position effects in Saccharomyces cerevisiae
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 7 (7A) (1993), pp. 1146–1159
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Levy and Blackburn, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.L. Levy, E.H. Blackburn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Counting of Rif1p and Rif2p on Saccharomyces cerevisiae telomeres regulates telomere length
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 24 (2004), pp. 10857–10867
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lieb et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.D. Lieb, X. Liu, D. Botstein, P.O. Brown
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Promoter-specific binding of Rap1 revealed by genome-wide maps of protein-DNA association
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Genet., 28 (2001), pp. 327–334
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lisby and Rothstein, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Lisby, R. Rothstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         DNA damage checkpoint and repair centers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Cell Biol., 16 (2004), pp. 328–334
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Longtine et al., 1989
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.S. Longtine, N.M. Wilson, M.E. Petracek, J. Berman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A yeast telomere binding activity binds to two related telomere sequence motifs and is indistinguishable from RAP1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Genet., 16 (1989), pp. 225–239
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Marcand et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Marcand, E. Gilson, D. Shore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A protein-counting mechanism for telomere length regulation in yeast
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 275 (1997), pp. 986–990
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Marcand et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Marcand, B. Pardo, A. Gratias, S. Cahun, I. Callebaut
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Multiple pathways inhibit NHEJ at telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 22 (2008), pp. 1153–1158
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Matot et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Matot, Y.V. Le Bihan, R. Lescasse, J. Pérez, S. Miron, G. David, B. Castaing, P. Weber, B. Raynal, S. Zinn-Justin,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The orientation of the C-terminal domain of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae Rap1 protein is determined by its binding to DNA
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 40 (2012), pp. 3197–3207
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Michelson et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.J. Michelson, S. Rosenstein, T. Weinert
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A telomeric repeat sequence adjacent to a DNA double-stranded break produces an anticheckpoint
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 19 (2005), pp. 2546–2559
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Miller and Goebel, 1968
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.G. Miller, C.V. Goebel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dimensions of protein random coils
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 7 (1968), pp. 3925–3935
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ribeyre and Shore, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Ribeyre, D. Shore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anticheckpoint pathways at telomeres in yeast
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 19 (2012), pp. 307–313
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shore and Nasmyth, 1987
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Shore, K. Nasmyth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Purification and cloning of a DNA binding protein from yeast that binds to both silencer and activator elements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 51 (1987), pp. 721–732
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vodenicharov and Wellinger, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.D. Vodenicharov, R.J. Wellinger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         DNA degradation at unprotected telomeres in yeast is regulated by the CDK1 (Cdc28/Clb) cell-cycle kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 24 (2006), pp. 127–137
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vodenicharov et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.D. Vodenicharov, N. Laterreur, R.J. Wellinger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Telomere capping in non-dividing yeast cells requires Yku and Rap1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 29 (2010), pp. 3007–3019
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wellinger and Zakian, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.J. Wellinger, V.A. Zakian
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Everything you ever wanted to know about Saccharomyces cerevisiae telomeres: beginning to end
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genetics, 191 (2012), pp. 1073–1105
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Williams et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.L. Williams, D.L. Levy, S. Maki-Yonekura, K. Yonekura, E.H. Blackburn
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Characterization of the yeast telomere nucleoprotein core: Rap1 binds independently to each recognition site
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 285 (2010), pp. 35814–35824
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wotton and Shore, 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Wotton, D. Shore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel Rap1p-interacting factor, Rif2p, cooperates with Rif1p to regulate telomere length in Saccharomyces cerevisiae
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 11 (1997), pp. 748–760
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wright et al., 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.H. Wright, D.E. Gottschling, V.A. Zakian
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Saccharomyces telomeres assume a non-nucleosomal chromatin structure
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 6 (1992), pp. 197–210
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <title>
      Supplemental References
     </title>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Adams et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.D. Adams, P.V. Afonine, G. Bunkóczi, V.B. Chen, I.W. Davis, N. Echols, J.J. Headd, L.W. Hung, G.J. Kapral, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66 (2010), pp. 213–221
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bricogne, 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Bricogne
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Direct phase determination by entropy maximization and likelihood ranking: status report and perspectives
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 49 (1993), pp. 37–60
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chen et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V.B. Chen, W.B. Arendall 3rd, J.J. Headd, D.A. Keedy, R.M. Immormino, G.J. Kapral, L.W. Murray, J.S. Richardson, D.C. Richardson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular crystallography
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66 (2010), pp. 12–21
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Collaborative Computational Project, Number 4, 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Collaborative Computational Project, Number 4
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The CCP4 suite: programs for protein crystallography
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 50 (1994), pp. 760–763
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         delaFortelle and Bricogne, 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. delaFortelle, G. Bricogne
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Maximum-likelihood heavy-atom parameter refinement for multiple isomorphous replacement and multiwavelength anomalous diffraction methods
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Methods Enzymol., 276 (1997), pp. 472–494
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Emsley et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Emsley, B. Lohkamp, W.G. Scott, K. Cowtan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Features and development of Coot
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66 (2010), pp. 486–501
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Holm and Rosenström, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Holm, P. Rosenström
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dali server: conservation mapping in 3D
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 38 (Web Server issue) (2010), pp. W545–W549
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         James et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. James, J. Halladay, E.A. Craig
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genomic libraries and a host strain designed for highly efficient two-hybrid selection in yeast
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genetics, 144 (1996), pp. 1425–1436
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Joosten et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.P. Joosten, J. Salzemann, V. Bloch, H. Stockinger, A.C. Berglund, C. Blanchet, E. Bongcam-Rudloff, C. Combet, A.L. Da Costa, G. Deleage,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PDB_REDO: automated re-refinement of X-ray structure models in the PDB
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst., 42 (2009), pp. 376–384
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kabsch, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Kabsch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         XDS
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66 (2010), pp. 125–132
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McCoy et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. McCoy, R.W. Grosse-Kunstleve, P.D. Adams, M.D. Winn, L.C. Storoni, R.J. Read
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phaser crystallographic software
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Appl. Cryst., 40 (2007), pp. 658–674
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Puglisi et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Puglisi, A. Bianchi, L. Lemmens, P. Damay, D. Shore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distinct roles for yeast Stn1 in telomere capping and telomerase inhibition
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 27 (2008), pp. 2328–2339
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rodríguez et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.D. Rodríguez, C. Grosse, S. Himmel, C. González, I.M. de Ilarduya, S. Becker, G.M. Sheldrick, I. Usón
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystallographic ab initio protein structure solution below atomic resolution
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Methods, 6 (2009), pp. 651–653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ruault et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Ruault, A. De Meyer, I. Loïodice, A. Taddei
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Clustering heterochromatin: Sir3 promotes telomere clustering independently of silencing in yeast
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 192 (2011), pp. 417–431
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sheldrick, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.M. Sheldrick
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A short history of SHELX
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. A, 64 (2008), pp. 112–122
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Smart et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        O.S. Smart, T.O. Womack, C. Flensburg, P. Keller, W. Paciorek, A. Sharff, C. Vonrhein, G. Bricogne
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Exploiting structure similarity in refinement: automated NCS and target-structure restraints in BUSTER
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 68 (2012), pp. 368–380
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vonrhein et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Vonrhein, C. Flensburg, P. Keller, A. Sharff, O. Smart, W. Paciorek, T. Womack, G. Bricogne
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Data processing and analysis with the autoPROC toolbox
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 67 (2011), pp. 293–302
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Xue et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Xue, M.D. Rushton, L. Maringele
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel checkpoint and RPA inhibitory pathway regulated by Rif1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PLoS Genet., 7 (2011), p. e1002417
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2013 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>