<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2010.10.035
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    A mammalian insulysin homolog is regulated by enzyme IIAGlc of the glucose transport system in Vibrio vulnificus
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      PEP
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      phosphoenolpyruvate
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      PTS
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      phosphoenolpyruvate:sugar phosphotransferase system
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      EI
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      enzyme I of the PTS
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      HPr
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      histidine-containing phosphocarrier protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <sup>
      Glc
     </sup>
     ,
     <span>
      glucose-specific enzyme IIA of the PTS
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      TFA
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      trifluoroacetic acid
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      HPLC
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      high performance liquid chromatography
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      vIDE
     </span>
     ,
     <em>
      Vibrio vulnificus
     </em>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      EDTA
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      EGTA
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      ethylene glycol tetraacetic acid
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      NEM
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      N-ethylmaleimide
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      TPEN
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      N,N,N′,N′-tetrakis(2-pyridylmethyl)ethylenediamine
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      MALDI-TOF
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      PBS
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      phosphate-buffered saline
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      TCBS agar
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      thiosulfate citrate bile salts sucrose agar
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <sup>
      Glc
     </sup>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Insulysin
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Phosphoenolpyruvate:sugar phosphotransferase system
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Protein–protein interaction
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <em>
      Vibrio vulnificus
     </em>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     Vibrio vulnificus
    </em>
    is a Gram-negative bacterium that is found in estuarine waters and frequently contaminates seafood. Strains of
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    are classified into three biotypes based on their biochemical characteristics and those belonging to biotype 1 are responsible for the majority of human infections
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . Biotype 2 strains are primary eel pathogens, while the biotype 3 appears to be emerged by recombination between biotypes 1 and 2 genomes and causes human wound infection
    <a>
     [2]
    </a>
    . Primary septicemia is the most lethal infection caused by
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    , with an average mortality rate exceeding 50%. Predisposing factors for severe
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    infection include chronic liver disease, elevated serum iron levels, low gastric acid, immunosuppression, and diabetes
    <a>
     [3]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [4]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [5]
    </a>
    . Most septic patients die of fulminant septicemia within 48 h after infection, implying that
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    cells subvert host innate immune responses upon infection.
   </p>
   <p>
    The bacterial phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP):sugar phosphotransferase system (PTS) participates in several physiological processes, in addition to its role in coupling phosphorylation to translocation of numerous sugars across the cytoplasmic membrane
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    . The PTS is composed of two general proteins, enzyme I (EI) and histidine-containing phosphocarrier protein (HPr), and a set of sugar-specific proteins collectively known as enzymes II. EI and HPr mediate phosphoryl transfer from PEP to enzyme II, which finally phosphorylates PTS sugar substrates during uptake. Therefore, the ratio of the phosphorylated forms of the PTS components increases in the absence and decreases in the presence of a PTS sugar. Roles of the PTS have been most extensively studied in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    , and these roles include regulation of chemotaxis by EI
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    , regulation of glycogen phosphorylase by HPr
    <a>
     [7]
    </a>
    , and sequestration of the global repressor Mlc by glucose-specific enzyme IICB to induce expression of the PTS proteins in the presence of PTS sugars
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [10]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [11]
    </a>
    . In addition, glucose-specific enzyme IIA (IIA
    <sup>
     Glc
    </sup>
    ) plays multiple roles such as regulation of adenylyl cyclase, inducer exclusion of non-PTS sugars to preferentially consume glucose, inhibition of glycerol kinase activity, and regulation of fermentation/respiration switch protein
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Although the PTS has never been documented in
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    , we postulated that it might play important roles in
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    physiology. We therefore set out to isolate a protein(s) that interacts with and is regulated by IIA
    <sup>
     Glc
    </sup>
    in
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    because all of the regulatory roles of the PTS reported to date are mediated through the direct interaction of the PTS components with their target proteins, and because IIA
    <sup>
     Glc
    </sup>
    is the key regulatory component among Gram-negative bacterial PTSs
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [14]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and methods
   </title>
   <title>
    2.1. Strains, plasmids and culture media
   </title>
   <p>
    Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    .
    <em>
     V. vulnificus
    </em>
    strains were cultured in Luria-Bertani medium containing 2.5% NaCl (LBS) and all
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    strains except BL21(DE3) derivatives were grown in M9 medium supplemented with 2% casamino acids and 1% glycerol. BL21 (DE3) strains were grown in LB medium.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>