<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC3642377
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    The interplay between RPGR, PDEδ and Arl2/3 regulate the ciliary targeting of farnesylated cargo
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     <strong>
      Defects in primary cilia result in human diseases known as ciliopathies. The retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator (RPGR), mutated in the most severe form of the eye disease, is located at the transition zone of the ciliary organelle. The RPGR-interacting partner PDEδ is involved in trafficking of farnesylated ciliary cargo, but the significance of this interaction is unknown. The crystal structure of the propeller domain of RPGR shows the location of patient mutations and how they perturb the structure. The RPGR·PDEδ complex structure shows PDEδ on a highly conserved surface patch of RPGR. Biochemical experiments and structural considerations show that RPGR can bind with high affinity to cargo-loaded PDEδ and exposes the Arl2/Arl3-binding site on PDEδ. On the basis of these results, we propose a model where RPGR is acting as a scaffold protein recruiting cargo-loaded PDEδ and Arl3 to release lipidated cargo into cilia.
     </strong>
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     ciliary trafficking, retinitis pigmentosa, RPGR, Arl2/Arl3, PDEδ
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    INTRODUCTION
   </title>
   <p>
    The cilium is a microtubule-based hair-like sensory organelle found on almost all human cells. Defects in the structure or function of cilia result in several human diseases collectively defined as ciliopathies. Ciliopathies include polycystic kidney disease, nephronophtisis, Bardet–Biedl syndrome (BBS) and various retinal degeneration syndromes [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     1
    </xref>
    ]. Retinitis pigmentosa is a genetically heterogenous eye disease causing the progressive degeneration of photoreceptor cells, in which the outer segments are specialized forms of cilia in the retina. The disorder is characterized by night blindness, progressive loss of the peripheral visual field leading to complete blindness [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     2
    </xref>
    ]. Some retinitis pigmentosa patients manifest more ciliopathy phenotypes as abnormal sperm development, respiratory tract infections and hearing defects [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    The retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator (RPGR) gene is involved in the most severe form of the disease, X-linked retinitis pigmentosa [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ]. In photoreceptors, RPGR localizes to the connecting cilium (CC) of rod and cones [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. RPGR was also found in primary cilia of other cell types and the transition zone of motile cilia [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     2
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ]. Knockout of RPGR in mice showed degeneration of rod and cone photoreceptor cells [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ]. In addition, lack of RPGR is associated with opsin mislocalization pointing to an involvement of RPGR in regulation of ciliary trafficking [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    The
    <em>
     RPGR
    </em>
    gene encodes several isoforms sharing an amino-terminal domain homologous to the RanGEF regulator of chromosome condensation 1 (RCC1), referred to as RCC1-like domain (RLD), and was thus predicted to also have GEF activity. One of the two main isoforms is the widely expressed RPGR
    <sup>
     1–19
    </sup>
    consisting of 19 exons encoding a protein of 815 amino acids where exons 2–11 comprise the RLD [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     10
    </xref>
    ]. A carboxy-terminal CAAX box, specific for geranylgeranylation, was shown to be essential for the localization and function of the protein [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     11
    </xref>
    ]. By alternative splicing, the RPGR
    <sup>
     ORF15
    </sup>
    isoform is generated, which has a highly repetitive acidic terminal exon, referred to as ORF15. While this exon is identified as a mutational hotspot in RPGR patients [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     12
    </xref>
    ], most of the more severe patient mutations are localized in the RLD underscoring the physiological importance of this domain [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     13
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    RPGR interacts via its RCC-like domain with a variety of cilia-related proteins, such as nephrocystin6 (NPHP6/CEP290), RPGRIP1 and nucleophosmin, and microtubule-associated proteins, such as IFT88, dynein, kinesin II and with PDEδ [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     10
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    The phosphodiesterase 6 delta subunit is a ubiquitous and highly conserved prenyl-binding protein that was originally identified by co-purification with the prenylated catalytic subunits of PDE6 and hence its name [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     14
    </xref>
    ]. It has been shown that PDEδ is a solubilizing and shuttling factor for several prenylated membrane-associated proteins, like Ras, RheB, the catalytic subunits of phosphodiesterases and rhodopsin kinase (GRK1), and recently the inositol polyphosphate 5-phosphatase E [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ]. The small G proteins Arl2 and Arl3 allosterically regulate the release of farnesylated cargo from PDEδ in a GTP-dependent manner [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ]. Nevertheless, the interplay of RPGR, PDEδ, Arl2/Arl3 and farnesylated cargo is not known.
   </p>
   <p>
    To gain insights into the structure and function of RPGR and the interplay between its interacting partners, we determined the X-ray crystal structures of RPGR alone and in complex with PDEδ. Structural and biochemical analysis show that RPGR binds to the open conformation of PDEδ, which in contrast to the Arl2/3-bound closed conformation allows farnesylated cargo binding. Furthermore, the RPGR-binding site on PDEδ is not overlapping with the Arl2/Arl3 allosteric binding site suggesting the formation of a transient, fast dissociating quaternary complex. On the basis of these data, we propose a model where RPGR is recruiting PDEδ-bound farnesylated cargo at the transition zone (or CC) where the ciliary Arl3·GTP is releasing the cargo and hence targeting the farnesylated cargo into cilia.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    RESULTS
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Overall structure of RPGR
    </title>
    <p>
     Owing to the difficulty to obtain the full-length 815 residue main RPGR isoform, we designed a shorter RPGR construct consisting of amino acids 1–392 comprising the RLD (referred to as RPGR from now on). Almost all RPGR patient mutations
     <sup>
      1–19
     </sup>
     as well as the presently described protein interaction sites are located within the RLD. This construct was crystallized and the crystal structure was solved at a resolution of 1.7 Å by molecular replacement using the RCC1 structure (PDB code 1A12) as a search model.
    </p>
    <p>
     As expected, RPGR shows an RCC1-like seven bladed propeller similar to the homologous RCC1 protein (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1A
     </xref>
     ). Each blade is formed by one repeat unit and consists of four antiparallel β-strands where the inner strands surround a central tunnel filled with water molecules. The structure shows the characteristic 2+2 arrangement of the first/last β-sheet with two strands from the N-terminal and two from the C-terminal half repeat, similar to RCC1 and unlike the WD40 propeller fold that has a 3+1 arrangement. The four molecules found in the asymmetric unit superimpose well (r.m.s.d. of 0.32, 0.37 and 0.29 Å). Compared with RCC1, the connecting loops show different conformations, and the positions of the β-sheets slightly differ (r.m.s.d. of 1.8 Å) (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S1A
     </a>
     online). RPGR lacks the N-terminal extension, which is required in RCC1 for DNA binding. In addition, the RCC1 β-hairpin extension, referred to as β-wedge required for its GEF activity, is not found in RPGR; however, an unstructured loop between blades B3 and B4 is found instead (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S1B
     </a>
     online). Surface representation of RCC1 shows a doughnut-like structure. In contrast to RCC1, the tunnel shaft of the RLD propeller in RPGR is closed on one side, where Tyr199, Tyr200, Arg96 and Asp344 are involved in the tunnel closure.
    </p>
    <fig id="f1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Overall structure of RPGR. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Structure of the RLD domain of RPGR shown in ribbon representation. Blades are numbered (B1–B7), as indicated, as are the N and C termini. (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Close-up view of the RPGR tunnel opening, showing the conserved cysteine and histidine ring in ball and stick representation and their residue number. Mutations of the Cys/His ring residues found in RP patients are indicated by asterisks. (
       <strong>
        C–D
       </strong>
       ) Surface presentation of RPGR where conserved residues &gt;90% are shown in red, residues with 60% are shown in white and residues with &lt;20% are in blue (as demonstrated by the colour scale below). Two patches with the highest sequence conservation are at the top of the RPGR molecule, patch 1 (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) and at the side of the protein, patch 2 (
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ), as indicated. Patient mutations located on the surface are boxed. The relative orientations of the two views are indicated schematically above by the ribbons. RLD, RCC1-like domain; RP, retinitis pigmentosa; RPGR, retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     A ring of six highly conserved cysteine residues and another ring of six histidines in close proximity surround the RPGR tunnel entrance (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1B
     </xref>
     ). Two cysteine residues (C250R/Y and C302R/Y) and a histidine (H98Q) are mutated in patients with retinitis pigmentosa (RP). The cysteine and histidine residues most likely have a structural role stabilizing the protein fold. Indeed, purification of the proteins containing such patient mutations showed the protein to be partly insoluble and degraded suggesting that mutations of the Cys/His ring destabilize the structure (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S2
     </a>
     online). Sequence alignment of RPGR from different vertebrates shows that the propeller surface is highly conserved, with two surface patches with the highest conservation located at the top of the molecule as viewed from the Cys/His ring (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1C
     </xref>
     , patch1) and at one side of the molecule (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1D
     </xref>
     , patch2).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Patient mutations and PDEδ interaction
    </title>
    <p>
     Mapping the patient mutations to the RPGR structure shows that they are distributed over the entire molecule and are not restricted to particular regions. Many of the mutations are located in the β-strands, most likely contributing to the integrity of the propeller structure, as shown above for the cysteine mutations. In
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1C,D
     </xref>
     , we map all the surface mutations that are likely to be involved in the binding of RPGR-interacting proteins. Surprisingly, only some of these residues (R127G, F130C and P235S) are highly conserved among vertebrates (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 1C,D
     </xref>
     ). One particularly interesting interactor is PDEδ as it is involved in ciliary trafficking of farnesylated cargo proteins and is regulated by the small G proteins Arl2 and Arl3, the latter of which is a
     <em>
      bona fide
     </em>
     ciliary protein [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ]. We thus wanted to investigate the effect of patient mutations on RPGR binding to PDEδ. The affinity of RPGR to a fluorescently labelled Cy5-PDEδ determined by a fluorescence-based polarization experiment is 500 nM (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S3
     </a>
     online). This dissociation constant is in line with that reported before using a glutathione
     <em>
      S
     </em>
     -transferase (GST)-tagged PDEδ [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      19
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
    <p>
     Unlike the Cys mutants mentioned above, the surface patient mutants could be purified. To analyse the effect of mutations on the interaction with PDEδ, we performed GST pull-down assays. RPGR mutants were pulled down by GST-PDEδ similarly to wild-type RPGR (
     <a>
      supplementary Figs S3,S4
     </a>
     online). Densitometric analysis (data not shown) of the bands showed no significant differences (&lt;3%) between wild-type and mutant proteins. In addition, we determined and compared the binding affinities using surface plasmon resonance. As expected, we did not observe significant changes in affinities compared with wild-type RPGR (data not shown). From this, we conclude that the patient mutations located at the surface of RPGR are not involved in the RPGR–PDEδ interaction.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Structure of RPGR in complex with PDEδ
    </title>
    <p>
     To further investigate the RPGR–PDEδ interaction, we set out to solve the crystal structure of the RPGR–PDEδ complex. Good diffracting crystals were obtained with a construct of RPGR comprising amino acids 8–368, by mixing equimolar amounts of RPGR
     <sup>
      8–368
     </sup>
     and PDEδ. The crystals belonged to space group C2 and diffracted to 1.9 Å. Using the RPGR structure as a search model for molecular replacement, we could identify one molecule of RPGR in the asymmetric unit. For the PDEδ molecule, a solution could only be found by using the PDEδ ‘open' conformation model from the PDEδ·cargo complex (PDB code 3T5G), and not the closed conformation from the PDEδ·Arl2 complex (PDB code 1KSH). This and an ambiguous electron density in the open farnesyl-binding pocket (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2A,B
     </xref>
     ) imply a conformation-specific binding of PDEδ to RPGR (see below) [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ].
    </p>
    <fig id="f2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Structure of RPGR·PDEδ complex. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ,
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Slice through the electrostatic surface presentation of PDEδ in either the complex with farnesylated cargo (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       , PDB code 3T5G) or with Arl2•GppNHp (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       , PDB code 1KSH) to show the hydrophobic pocket in the open (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) and closed (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) conformations with the farnesyl moiety modelled into the closed pocket. (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) Ribbon representation of RPGR in cyan in complex with PDEδ in grey. (
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ) Ribbon representation of PDEδ (grey) and RPGR as surface representation similar to the position in
       <xref ref-type="fig">
        Fig 1D
       </xref>
       (slightly rotated towards the viewer). PDEδ binds to conserved patch1 (encircled) of RPGR. (
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       ) Schematic diagram showing the residues involved in the interface between RPGR (cyan) and PDEδ (grey) where solid lines represent nonpolar interactions and dotted lines show polar interactions. (
       <strong>
        F
       </strong>
       ) The interface residues Arg48 of PDE and Glu216 of RPGR are shown as ball and stick presentation. GST pull-down experiments using wt and mutant PDE(R48E) (upper) and wt and mutant RPGR(E216R) (lower) are shown on the right side. GST, glutathione
       <em>
        S
       </em>
       -transferase; RPGR, retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     PDEδ binds to one of the two most highly sequence-conserved patches (patch1) of RPGR, with a buried surface area of 1632 Å
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2C,D
     </xref>
     ). This side is topologically similar to where Ran binds to RCC1. Residues involved in complex formation are summarized in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2E
     </xref>
     . Except for the W64-I30 and K51 (aliphatic side chain)–Y200 interactions, the interface is mostly formed by polar interactions. As expected from our pull-down-binding studies, patient mutations of RPGR are not located in but rather away from the interface (c
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S3B
     </a>
     online).
    </p>
    <p>
     To verify the interface of the crystallized RPGR·PDEδ complex, one residue each from PDEδ and RPGR located in the interface, Arg48 and Glu216, respectively, were mutated by charge reversal. Indeed, both the PDEδ(R48E) and the RPGR(E216R) mutations completely abolished interaction of both proteins as analysed by GST pull-down experiments (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 2F
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     RPGR interaction with cargo-loaded PDEδ
    </title>
    <p>
     PDEδ solubilizes and shuttles farnesylated cargo between membranes and is involved in their ciliary targeting. It is not known, however, how cargo bound to PDEδ is targeted to cilia. RPGR localization in the transition zone/CC makes it a potential candidate for recruiting cargo-loaded PDEδ. We thus wanted to study the connection between RPGR, PDEδ and cargo, and if RPGR would be able to recruit cargo-bound PDEδ. As PDEδ is in the open conformation in both structures, we can superimpose RPGR·PDEδ on the structure of the PDEδ·F-RheB (for farnesylated RheB) cargo complex using PDEδ as a reference molecule. We could obtain a ternary complex model without any steric clashes (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3A
     </xref>
     ). We then wanted to test if the ternary complex can indeed be formed in solution. To do so, we performed GST pull-down experiments using GST-PDEδ, RPGR and F-RheB. Indeed, the pull-down experiment indicated the presence of a ternary 1:1:1 complex (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3B
     </xref>
     ). In addition, fluorescence-based polarization experiments using Cy5-labelled PDEδ showed a stepwise increase in the polarization signal after stepwise addition of RPGR and F-RheB (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3C
     </xref>
     ), confirming the existence of a ternary complex. Finally, a fluorescence polarization-based stopped-flow experiment using fluorescein-labelled F-RheB to study the kinetics of the PDEδ interaction with RheB in the presence and absence of RPGR showed no effect of RPGR for neither the dissociation nor association rate constants of the F-RheB/PDEδ interaction (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S5
     </a>
     online), which is in line with the observation that RPGR binds PDEδ in the ‘open' but not the ‘closed' conformation.
    </p>
    <fig id="f3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       The interplay between RPGR, PDEδ and RheB or Arl2/3. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Superimposition of the PDEδ·F-RheB (farnesylated F-RheB) on the RPGR·PDEδ complex with RheB in yellow, RPGR in cyan and PDEδ in grey (using PDEδ as a reference molecule). (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) GST pull-down experiments using GST-PDEδ, RPGR and/or F-RheB as indicated. (
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) Fluorescence polarization experiments using 0.25 μM Cy5-labelled PDEδ where 10 μM of RPGR and F-RheB, respectively, were added at the indicated time points. (
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ) Superimposition of Arl2•GppNHp on the RPGR·PDEδ complex with Arl2•GppNHp in green, RPGR in cyan and PDEδ in grey (using PDEδ as a reference molecule). (
       <strong>
        E–G
       </strong>
       ) Gel filtration and SDS–PAGE analysis of mixtures containing equal amounts of RPGR (
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       –
       <strong>
        G
       </strong>
       ), wild-type (
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       ,
       <strong>
        F
       </strong>
       ) or double mutant (F94A/I98A) (
       <strong>
        G
       </strong>
       ) PDEδ and Arl3•GppNHp (
       <strong>
        E
       </strong>
       ) or Arl2•GppNHp (
       <strong>
        F
       </strong>
       ,
       <strong>
        G
       </strong>
       ). Elution profiles for the controls are shown in
       <a>
        supplementary Fig S7
       </a>
       online. PAGE analysis of the numbered elution fractions are shown below the elution profiles. GST, glutathione
       <em>
        S
       </em>
       -transferase; RPGR, retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     The interplay between RPGR, PDEδ and Arl2 or Arl3
    </title>
    <p>
     We recently reported that Arl2 and Arl3 regulate the binding of farnesylated cargo to PDEδ [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ]. We thus wanted to know if and how Arl2/Arl3 affects the RPGR·PDEδ interaction. By superimposing the crystal structure of RPGR·PDEδ on that of PDEδ·Arl2•GppNHp, we can show that Arl2 binding does not sterically overlap with the RPGR-binding site and that a ternary complex of RPGR·PDEδ·Arl2•GppNHp should in principle be structurally feasible (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3D
     </xref>
     ). On the other hand, the conformation of PDEδ in complex with RPGR is in the ‘open' conformation, contrary to the closed conformation reported for PDEδ·Arl2•GppNHp. This suggests that Arl2/3 binding to PDEδ might affect the RPGR–PDEδ interaction. To investigate this, we performed pull-down experiments using GST-PDEδ as bait and Arl2/3 and RPGR as prey. Increasing amounts of either Arl2 or Arl3 in the GppNHp-bound conformation are seen displacing RPGR from the complex with GST-PDEδ as shown in
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S6A,B
     </a>
     online. This seems to suggest that the two conformations of PDEδ are mutually exclusive for either Arl2/Arl3 or RPGR binding. However, as the binding sites of Arl2/3 and RPGR are non-overlapping, in the structural model (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3D
     </xref>
     ), it is more likely that Arl2/3 allosterically displaces RPGR via the formation of an intermediate ternary complex. To investigate this, we used size exclusion chromatography. Equal amounts of RPGR, PDEδ and Arl3•GppNHp were incubated and applied to a gel filtration column. The elution profile and PAGE analysis showed the appearance of three peaks (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3E
     </xref>
     ). The first peak contained high amounts of the ternary RPGR·PDEδ·Arl3 complex followed by the binary PDEδ·Arl3 complex and free Arl3•GppNHp (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3E
     </xref>
     ), as confirmed by control elusion profiles for the individual proteins and the binary complexes (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S7
     </a>
     online). In contrast to Arl3•GppNHp, a ternary complex could not be identified by using Arl2•GppNHp. Here, the three peaks represent the binary RPGR·PDEδ complex, the PDEδ·Arl2 complex and free Arl2•GppNHp (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3F
     </xref>
     ). This is most likely owing to the fast dissociation of RPGR·PDEδ·Arl2 complex.
    </p>
    <p>
     The pull-down experiments (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S6A,B
     </a>
     online) had shown that Arl2 also displaces PDEδ from RPGR, which suggest that Arl2 is also acting allosterically and that the difference between Arl2 and Arl3 is a difference in quantity rather than quality. Previously, we have shown that Arl2 and Arl3 are unable to allosterically release farnesylated cargo from a PDEδ(F94A/I98A) double mutant but rather form a stable ternary PDEδ·cargo·Arl2/3 complex [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ]. This indicates that Arl2·GTP (and Arl3·GTP) binding does not change the conformation of PDEδ from an open to a closed conformation, and that correspondingly such a mutant should be able to stably bind to both Arl2·GTP and RPGR. Using this mutant, a stable ternary complex of RPGR, PDEδ and Arl2•GppNHp could indeed be separated by gel filtration (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 3F
     </xref>
     ). This confirms the presence of two distinct binding sites for Arl2 and RPGR on PDEδ and the formation of an intermediate, fast dissociating transient ternary complex. While a ternary complex could not be identified by pull-down experiments using His-Arl3/2 as bait with RPGR and wt PDEδ as prey, such a complex was formed using the PDEδ(F94A/I98A) double mutant in the presence of Arl3•GppNHp, supporting the allosteric control of Arl3 (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S6C
     </a>
     online). A minor band corresponding to RPGR being pulled down using His-Arl3 on nickel beads in the absence of PDEδ could be seen (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S6C
     </a>
     online), but it was also seen in the absence of Arl3. Thus, we consider this to be nonspecific as we also did not observe direct binding between Arl3 and RPGR in solution in fluorescence polarization using fluorescently labelled mGppNHp-Arl3 and RPGR (data not shown) nor in size exclusion chromatography experiments (
     <a>
      supplementary Fig S7
     </a>
     online). From all of the above, we conclude that although Arl2/3 and RPGR bind to PDEδ using two different binding sites and can in principle form a ternary complex, the binding sites are allosterically coupled. Both, Arl2•GppNHp and Arl3•GppNHp decrease the affinity of RPGR to PDEδ, with Arl3 apparently forming a more stable ternary complex.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     RPGR as a scaffold for Arl3-mediated cargo release
    </title>
    <p>
     Finally, we wanted to investigate the regulatory role of Arl2/Arl3 on the RPGR·PDEδ·cargo ternary complex. By superimposing the structures of the three PDEδ complexes with Arl2•GppNHp, F-RheB and RPGR on the PDEδ template, we obtain a model of a quaternary complex of RPGR·PDEδ·cargo·Arl2/Arl3•GppNHp in which the four proteins, sterically, do not significantly interfere with each other, apart from the highly mobile N terminus of Arl2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4A
     </xref>
     ). This suggest that RPGR could function as a scaffold for the PDEδ-mediated, Arl3-controlled transport of farnesylated cargo into cilia. Using fluorescence polarization and a fluorescein-labelled F-RheB peptide, we could clearly demonstrate the formation of a ternary complex between the peptide, PDEδ and RPGR, indicated by the increase in polarization after addition of the proteins (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig 4B
     </xref>
     ). On addition of Arl3•GppNHp, the signal decreased indicating dissociation of the complex and release of F-RheB peptide. Although not relevant for ciliary transport, the same effect was also observed for Arl2 (data not shown).
    </p>
    <fig id="f4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Cargo release from the RPGR·PDEδ·F-RheB complex by Arl2/Arl3. (
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Superimposition of complexes of PDEδ with Arl2•GppNHp (green), F-RheB (yellow) and RPGR·in cyan using PDEδ (grey) as a reference molecule. (
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Fluorescence polarization experiments where 0.25 μM fluorescein-labelled F-RheB peptide were titrated by stepwise addition of PDEδ and RPGR, at the indicated time points, to final concentrations of 0.25, 0.5 and 10 μM for PDEδ and 1.5, 11.5 and 21.5 μM for RPGR. Following addition of 5 μM Arl3•GppNHp, a decrease of the polarization signal can be observed. RPGR, retinitis pigmentosa GTPase regulator.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    DISCUSSION
   </title>
   <p>
    RPGR mutations result in the most severe form of retinitis pigmentosa (X-linked RP), with 80% of the patient mutations located in this gene. In addition to retinal degeneration, a number of patients showed respiratory tract infections, hearing defects and abnormal sperm development as well. A recent study demonstrated that gene therapy using RPGR
    <sup>
     ORF15
    </sup>
    was successful to rescue retinal degeneration in dogs [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    ]. This underscores the role of RPGR in photoreceptors and perhaps other cilia. While a large number of interacting proteins have been identified, the function of RPGR is still elusive.
   </p>
   <p>
    As an approach to delineate the effect of patient mutations on the structure and possible function of RPGR, we have solved the three-dimesional structure of its propeller domain. We can show that a number of patient mutations are located in the structural core and are expected to destabilize the protein. While the surface shows two highly sequence-conserved patches, none of the mutations described so far are located in these patches, suggesting that they do not perturb a crucial interaction with a partner protein. We show that PDEδ is bound to one of the highest conserved surface patches where we cannot locate any of the patient mutations. This might indicate that the loss of this interaction is not tolerated [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     22
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    The crystal structure of the RPGR·PDEδ complex showed binding of RPGR to the PDEδ ‘open' conformation, and biochemical experiments confirmed the formation of a stable ternary complex of RPGR·PDEδ·F-RheB. As RPGR is located in the transition zone of cilia in general and the CC of photoreceptor cells in particular, this suggests a role for the RPGR RCC1 domain, as a docking platform for the delivery of farnesylated cargo, such as the catalytic subunits of PDE6 or the γ-subunit of transducin. We have shown earlier that Arl2/3 allosterically induce a conformational change of PDEδ into the closed binding conformation. As both cargo and RPGR favour the open conformation, this would also suggest how cargo and the binding of PDEδ to RPGR are simultaneously weakened by Arl2/3 in the GTP-bound conformation. Our structures and structural models show that the PDEδ allosteric site for Arl2 and Arl3 is exposed and indeed our biochemical studies revealed release of farnesylated cargo bound to the RPGR·PDEδ complex by Arl2/Arl3, and at the same time the weakening of the interaction between RPGR and PDEδ. Although the binding sites of RPGR and Arl2/3 are on distinct faces of PDEδ, they are allosterically coupled such that they can inhibit the binding of each other via an intermediate ternary complex from which one of the partners is released.
   </p>
   <p>
    Arl2 and Arl2 seem to be very similar in terms of biochemical and structural properties, and interact with the same set of effectors, such as BART, PDEδ and Unc119/HRG4. The identification of a more stable ternary complex between Arl3•GppNHp, wt PDEδ and RPGR, as compared with Arl2•GppNHp, is a further indication of differences in biochemical properties and biological function that were previously inferred from overexpression of GTPase-negative mutants and RNAi-knockdown studies [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     23
    </xref>
    ]. Previously, we and others have shown that the release of myristoylated ciliary cargo, such as GNAT1 and Cystin, from its complex with UNC119/HRG4 is only mediated by Arl3, although both Arl2 and Arl3 bind to UNC119 with similar affinities [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     24
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     25
    </xref>
    ]. As Arl3 is a ciliary protein, whereas Arl2 is not, it suggests that Arl3 has a very specific function in ciliary trafficking. Our studies reported here suggest that farnesylated ciliary cargo transported by PDEδ is specifically captured in the transition zone/CC by the scaffolding protein RPGR and released by Arl3GTP. For validating such a pathway, further biochemical, structural and cell biological analysis of these and other RPGR-containing interactions are required.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    METHODS
   </title>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Constructs and plasmids.
    </strong>
    C-terminal His-tagged human RPGR(amino acids 1–392), and full-length murine Arl2 and Arl3 were cloned in pET21d and pET20a vectors, respectively; the GST fusion of human PDEδ was cloned in pGEX4T5-TEV as described [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     26
    </xref>
    ]. For RPGR, a second construct comprising amino acids 8–368 with a C-terminal His-tag was cloned into pET21d.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Protein purification.
    </strong>
    Affinity chromatography followed by size exclusion chromatography was performed (for details see
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online). Cy5-labelled fully modified farnesylated RheB protein and fluorescein-labelled farnesylated carboymethylated RheB peptide was obtained as described before [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Structure.
    </strong>
    All crystals were obtained by the hanging drop vapour diffusion method, and microseeding was performed for optimization (for details for crystallization and structure determination please see
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online). For data collection and refinement statistics, see
    <a>
     supplementary Table S1
    </a>
    online.
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     <em>
      In vitro
     </em>
     pull-down assays.
    </strong>
    GST fusion protein (GST-PDEδ or mutants) were used for the pull-down assays following standard procedures (for details see
    <a>
     supplementary information
    </a>
    online).
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Fluorescence measurements.
    </strong>
    Fluorescence polarization measurements were carried out at 20 °C in a buffer containing 20 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and 2 mM β-ME. Data were recorded using a Fluoromax-4 spectrophotometer (Jobin Yvon, Munich, Germany)
   </p>
   <p>
    For kinetics measurements, the dissociation or association of fluorescein-labelled RheB peptide·PDEδ in the presence and absence of RPGR was followed by recording the polarization fluorescence in a stopped-flow apparatus (Applied Biophysics). The data were fitted to a single exponential function using Grafit 5.0
   </p>
   <p>
    <strong>
     Accession codes:
    </strong>
    The PDB access code for the RPGR structure is
    <a>
     4JHN
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     4JHP
    </a>
    for the RPGR-PDE complex.
   </p>
   <p>
    <a>
     Supplementary information
    </a>
    is available at EMBO
    <em>
     reports
    </em>
    online (
    <a>
     http://www.emboreports.org
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Supplementary Information:
    </strong>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (1.4M, pdf)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Review Process File:
    </strong>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (224K, pdf)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>