<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ccr.2011.01.018
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Angiopoietin-like 4 Protein Elevates the Prosurvival Intracellular O2−:H2O2 Ratio and Confers Anoikis Resistance to Tumors
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Significance
   </title>
   <p>
    <strong>
     We show here that elevated expression of ANGPTL4 is widespread in tumors, and tumor-derived ANGPTL4 confers anoikis resistance to tumors via autocrine adhesion mimicry. Our findings that ANGPTL4 hijacks integrin-mediated signaling to maintain an elevated, oncogenic O
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     <sup>
      −
     </sup>
     :H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ratio and, therefore, confers anoikis resistance to tumor cells suggest ANGPTL4 as an important player in redox-mediated cancer progression. Treating cancer cells with ANGPTL4-targeted RNAi or monoclonal antibodies imparts a significant decrease in in vivo tumor growth and induces apoptosis in cancer cell lines upon anoikis challenge. Our findings suggest that anticancer strategies focusing on redox-based apoptosis induction in tumors are viable.
    </strong>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    In response to stresses such as hypoxia and inflammation in the tumor microenvironment, tumor cells exploit various signaling molecules to sustain and promote their growth, invasiveness, and metastasis (
    <a>
     Singh et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). Aggressive tumor metastasis and invasiveness are the main cause of mortality in patients with cancer (
    <a>
     Fidler, 1999
    </a>
    ). The constitutive activation of intracellular signaling by these molecules in tumor cells leads to cellular changes, including increased proliferation and the ability for cells to grow beyond their original confined milieu, leading to metastasis (
    <a>
     Pani et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Westhoff and Fulda, 2009
    </a>
    ). Among these changes, the loss of dependence on integrin-mediated extracellular matrix contact for growth (i.e., anoikis resistance) is an essential feature of tumor cells. However, the mechanism by which anoikis resistance is acquired remains an unsolved problem in cancer biology.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although low levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS) regulate cellular signaling and play an important role in normal cell proliferation, recent studies show that tumors exhibit an excessive amount or persistent elevation of ROS (specifically the superoxide anion O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    ) and utilize a redox-based mechanism to evade death by anoikis (
    <a>
     Chiarugi, 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Giannoni et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pervaiz and Clément, 2007
    </a>
    ). Previous studies have indicated that ROS are involved in tumor initiation, progression, and maintenance. Furthermore, deregulated ROS production is also associated with an invasive tumor phenotype. Oncogenic and mitogenic Ras activity is superoxide dependent, and a sustained increase in ROS following the overexpression of Nox1 (the catalytic subunit of NADPH oxidase) leads to cell transformation and aggressive tumor metastasis (
    <a>
     Komatsu et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Suh et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). Elevated production of ROS following activation of the c-Met proto-oncogene leads to cell transformation and malignant growth (
    <a>
     Ferraro et al., 2006
    </a>
    ), and Rac-dependent redox signals increase the secretion of metalloproteinases and induce epithelial-mesenchymal transition (
    <a>
     Wu, 2006
    </a>
    ), two key features of invasive cancers. Thus, a clear understanding of the underlying redox-based anoikis escape mechanism and its connection to malignancy will provide insight into therapeutic interventions.
   </p>
   <p>
    The secreted protein angiopoietin-like 4 (ANGPTL4) was recently linked to tumor progression. ANGPTL4 was previously identified as a paracrine and, possibly, endocrine regulator of lipid metabolism (
    <a>
     Oike et al., 2005
    </a>
    ) and a target of peroxisome proliferators-activated receptors (PPARs) (
    <a>
     Kersten et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). ANGPTL4 is expressed in numerous cell types, such as adipocytes and hepatocytes, and is upregulated after fasting and hypoxia (
    <a>
     Belanger et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kersten et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). Importantly, ANGPTL4 undergoes proteolytic processing to release its C-terminal fibrinogen-like domain (cANGPTL4), which circulates as a monomer but whose function remains unclear. The N-terminal coiled-coil domain of ANGPTL4 (nANGPTL4) mediates ANGPTL4 oligomerization and binds to lipoprotein lipase to modulate lipoprotein metabolism (
    <a>
     Ge et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Emerging studies also implicate tumor-derived ANGPTL4 in cancer metastasis via its effect on endothelial integrity. However, whether ANGPTL4 promotes or inhibits vascular permeability and, thus, cancer metastasis remains controversial. Several previous studies suggest that ANGPTL4 can prevent metastasis by inhibiting vascular leakiness (
    <a>
     Galaup et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ito et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Conversely, ANGPTL4 is also implicated as a pro-angiogenic factor (
    <a>
     Le Jan et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Recent reports demonstrate that
    <em>
     ANGPTL4
    </em>
    is one of the most highly predictive genes associated with breast cancer metastasis to the lung (
    <a>
     Minn et al., 2005
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Padua et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). ANGPTL4 expression is upregulated in clear cell renal-cell carcinoma (
    <a>
     Le Jan et al., 2003
    </a>
    ) and oral tongue squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) (
    <a>
     Wang et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). In addition, tumor-derived ANGPTL4 has been shown to promote metastasis by disrupting vascular integrity (
    <a>
     Padua et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). The reasons for these conflicting results and the underlying mechanism of ANGPTL4 activity in tumor cells have not been clarified, hampering our understanding of its precise role in cancer metastasis. More importantly, the global expression pattern of ANGPTL4 in different types of tumors, to our knowledge, has yet to be fully investigated, and the pathological relevance of ANGPTL4 in cancer biology remains largely undefined. Thus, we set up to study the role of ANGPTL4 in tumor growth and metastasis.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Elevated Expression of ANGPTL4 in Various Tumor Types
   </title>
   <p>
    To examine the expression profile of ANGPTL4 in human tumors, we screened its expression pattern on two human tumor tissue arrays, which cover most of the common benign, malignant, and metastatic tumors originating from various anatomic sites. Using immunofluorescence (IF) with an anti-cANGPTL4 antibody, we observed widespread, elevated ANGPTL4 expression in all epithelial tumor samples when compared to the corresponding normal tissues, regardless of the anatomic sites of origin (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A; see
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    A and S1B available online). However, the IF signal level varied among different types of tumors. Notably, the expression of ANGPTL4 increased as tumors progressed from a benign state to an invasive/metastatic state (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    C). Next, we determined ANGPTL4 expression on three human skin tumorigenic lines (HSC, II-4, and A-5RT3), ten human SCC, and 13 basal cell carcinoma (BCC) biopsies by quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) and immunoblot analyses. Consistent with our prior results, we observed increased ANGPTL4 mRNA and protein levels in these epithelial tumor cells compared with the nontumorigenic human skin line HaCaT or cognate peri-tumor normal samples (PNSs), respectively (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B–1D). No difference was observed between normal skin biopsies (NSs) and PNSs (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    C and 1D). Interestingly, the three SCCs expressing the highest mRNA level of ANGPTL4 corresponded to an invasive prognosis (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C), underscoring our finding from tumor tissue arrays. In addition, polyclonal antibodies against either the N or C terminus of ANGPTL4 detected only cANGPTL4 in these tumor lines and SSCs (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B–1D;
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    D and S1E). To understand the reason for the increased expression of ANGPTL4 in tumor cells, we examined the expression of hypoxia-inducible factor 1 α (HIF1α) and PPARs in the SCCs. We found a concomitant upregulation of HIF1α with ANGPTL4 in SSCs than in PNSs (correlation coefficient = 0.88) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E;
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    F). No clear correlation was observed between the expression of ANGPTL4 and the three PPAR isotypes (
    <a>
     Figures S1
    </a>
    G–S1I). These results suggested that at least for SCCs, the elevated ANGPTL4 expression reflects the tumor's hypoxic microenvironment. As a protein that is secreted by tumor cells, ANGPTL4 may perform paracrine or autocrine function in tumors. Therefore, we sought to determine the source of ANGPTL4 in tumors. We isolated epithelial tumor and stromal tissues, the latter consisting mainly of fibroblasts, from SCCs and PNSs, using laser capture microdissection (LCM). qPCR and immunoblot analyses revealed that epithelial tumor cells, rather than tumor stroma, were the major contributor of ANGPTL4 in SCCs (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F). Furthermore, only a low, baseline level of ANGPTL4 expression was found in normal PNS stroma and epithelia, suggesting that ANGPTL4 may have an autocrine role in tumors.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Elevated Expression of ANGPTL4 in Various Tumor Types(A) ANGPTL4 expression ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (2133 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Suppression of ANGPTL4 Impairs Tumor Growth
   </title>
   <p>
    Next, we investigated the biological relevance of elevated ANGPTL4 expression to tumor growth via RNAi. Four sets of siRNAs targeting different segments of the
    <em>
     ANGPTL4
    </em>
    sequence were stably introduced into the metastatic skin tumor line A-5RT3 (
    <a>
     Mueller et al., 2001
    </a>
    ), and the subline with the highest knockdown efficiency (A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    ) was selected for subsequent studies. A nontargeting scrambled siRNA was also integrated into A-5RT3 (A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    ) as a negative control. ANGPTL4 mRNA and protein levels were suppressed by &gt;85% in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    as compared with the parental A-5RT3 or A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). The induction of interferon responses has been reported as a challenge to the specificity of some RNAi approaches (
    <a>
     Bridge et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). To test whether the RNAi-mediated silencing of ANGPTL4 was associated with interferon responses, we measured the expression of several key interferon response genes by qPCR. No induction of
    <em>
     OAS1
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     OAS2
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     MX1
    </em>
    , or
    <em>
     ISGF3γ
    </em>
    was detected in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells compared with either A-5RT3 or A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Suppression of ANGPTL4 Impairs Tumorigenicity(A) Relative ANGPTL4 mRNA and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1332 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    As expected, the injection of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells into immunodeficient mice induced large primary tumors (∼1000 mm
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    ) in all five mice at week 8, but A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors displayed a 90% reduction in tumor growth (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and 2C). A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumor growth was similarly reduced, albeit a 40% reduction, when mice were implanted with increasing number of tumor cells (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    B). To strengthen the above observations, we subcutaneously (s.c.) implanted B16F10 cells into ANGPTL4-knockout (KO) and control (wild-type [WT]) mice. WT and KO mice were maintained in a C57BL/6J background, and the B16F10 melanoma was derived from the same background. Notably, B16F10 tumor cells implanted in KO mice grew slower than those implanted in WT mice; at day 15, the average tumor volume in KO mice was ∼6-fold less than in WT mice (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). The injection of ANGPTL4-knockdown (B16F10
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    ) cells into KO mice induced little tumor growth and showed similar growth profile in WT mice compared to control B16F10 (B16F10
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    )-induced tumors in KO mice (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). Conversely, WT mice implanted with B16F10
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells and intravenously (i.v.) injected three times a week with recombinant N-terminal histidine-tagged cANGPTL4 showed greater tumor growth. The average tumor volume in cANGPTL4-treated mice was ∼3-fold larger than PBS-treated mice (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E;
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    C and S2D). B16F10
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumor growth was diminished in PBS-treated mice as compared to cANGPTL4-treated mice (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Next, we reasoned that treating mice injected with A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells with an antibody that interferes with the action of ANGPTL4 would recapitulate the observation made with A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells. To this end the monoclonal human cANGPTL4-directed antibody mAb11F6C4 was identified and produced for our immunotherapy experiment based on its superior k
    <sub>
     on
    </sub>
    , k
    <sub>
     off
    </sub>
    , and K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    values, as determined by surface plasmon resonance (SPR) (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    E and
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    ). Notably, inhibition of ANGPTL4 with mAb11F6C4 attenuated tumor growth in immunodeficient mice, compared with control IgG-treated mice (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    F and 2G). Immunoblot and IF analyses of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumor biopsies indicated reduced cell proliferation and enhanced cell apoptosis than A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    H and 2I). A qPCR-focused array of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumor biopsies further suggested increased expression of many pro-apoptotic genes, whereas expression of cell proliferation genes was diminished (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    F and
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). Together, these observations clearly support a tumor-promoting role for cANGPTL4.
   </p>
   <title>
    ANGPTL4-Deficient Tumor Cells Showed Increased Susceptibility to Anoikis
   </title>
   <p>
    Anchorage-independent growth or anoikis resistance of tumor cells, a hallmark of tumor malignancy (
    <a>
     Hanahan and Weinberg, 2000
    </a>
    ), was investigated by tumor colony formation in soft agar and anoikis assays (
    <a>
     Salmon, 1984
    </a>
    ). Underscoring our in vivo findings, the colony-forming potential of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells was undermined and formed fewer (∼85%) tumor colonies on soft agar than A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). Furthermore, A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    was more susceptible to anoikis, having 30% more apoptotic cells and enhanced caspase activities than A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells after 2 hr of anoikis (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and 3C). The addition of exogenous recombinant cANGPTL4 reduced the apoptotic index of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells in a dose-dependent manner (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D). Similarly, ANGPTL4 deficiency in human keratinocytes rendered these cells ∼50% more susceptible to anoikis when compared to control keratinocytes, suggesting that a low amount of ANGPTL4 was also necessary to confer anoikis resistance in normal epithelial cells (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    A). No difference in the apoptotic index was observed due to the deficiency of ANGPTL4 in adhered A-5RT3 cells or keratinocytes (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    B and S3C).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ANGPTL4 Interacts with Integrins &amp;#946;1 and &amp;#946;5 to Confer Tumor Cells Anoikis ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1697 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    ANGPTL4 Interacts with Integrins β1 and β5
   </title>
   <p>
    The mechanism by which ANGPTL4 mediates anoikis resistance is an unanswered question. Previous studies have revealed that anoikis is an integrin-dependent process (
    <a>
     Chiarugi, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Thus, we hypothesize that ANGPTL4 also exerts its role in tumor cells through integrins-mediated signaling. We examined if cANGPTL4 can interact with integrins. Indeed, SPR and ELISA results showed that ANGPTL4 specifically interacts with integrins β1 and β5, but not with β3 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    E and 3F), and these interactions were blocked by either mAb11F6C4 or integrin-specific antibodies (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G and 3H;
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    D–S3G). ANGPTL4 deficiency did not affect the expression of integrins β1, β3, and β5 (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    H). An in situ proximity ligation assay (PLA) detected ANGPTL4-integrin complexes in both A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells and tumors (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    I;
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    I), confirming that this interaction also exists in vivo. Further investigation revealed that integrin activation by ANGPTL4 binding triggered focal adhesion kinase (FAK) in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells and tumors, which were reduced by &gt;70% in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    J;
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    J). All of these findings were corroborated by results from immunodetection of FAK on tumor biopsies (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    K). Our findings suggest that ANGPTL4 secreted by epithelial tumor cells acts in an autocrine manner to hijack the integrin/FAK-regulated pathway, conferring anoikis resistance to tumors and, thus, sustaining tumor growth.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    ANGPTL4 Elevates the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    Level and Maintains a High O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    Ratio in Tumor Cells
   </title>
   <p>
    ROS can be regulated through integrin engagement, and an elevated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level allows tumor cells to avoid anoikis (
    <a>
     Pani et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pervaiz and Clément, 2007
    </a>
    ). In this regard we assessed whether ANGPTL4-integrin interaction regulates ROS production in tumor cells. Using electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy (EPR) in combination with 5-(diethoxyphosphoryl)-5-methyl-1-pyrroline-N-oxide (DEPMPO) spin trapping, we measured a decrease in the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    compared to A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B), suggesting that ANGPTL4 is vital in sustaining O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production in tumor cells. To determine the source of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    , similar experiments were performed using specific inhibitors that block the mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I and membrane-bound NADPH oxidase, which are two major producers of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    in mammalian cells (
    <a>
     Giannoni et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Treatment of tumor cells with rotenone, a mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I inhibitor (
    <a>
     Irani et al., 1997
    </a>
    ), did not alter cellular O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B), suggesting that this complex has little role in generating O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    in tumors. Further excluding mitochondria as the source of ANGPTL4-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    generation, qPCR analysis showed no change in the expression of selected genes in the methionine/homocysteine metabolic cycle (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    A), as previously studied in diabetic rodent hepatocytes (
    <a>
     Wang et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). In contrast the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level was abrogated by using two different NADPH oxidase inhibitors (
    <a>
     Ushio-Fukai and Nakamura, 2008
    </a>
    ), diphenylene iodonium (DPI) and apocynin (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B). ROS generated through the involvement of the small GTPase Rac1 and NADPH oxidase upon integrin engagement exert a mandatory role in transmitting a prosurvival signal that ensures that tumor cells escape from anoikis (
    <a>
     Giannoni et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Joneson and Bar-Sagi, 1998
    </a>
    ). Comparative immunoblot analyses of anti-cANGPTL4 immunoprecipitates from A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    - and A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumor lysates detected integrins β1 and β5, along with phosphorylated FAK and active GTP-bound Rac1, in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    -induced tumors, all of which were reduced in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    K). To further validate the relevance of Rac1 in ANGPTL4-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production, we transiently transfected A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    and A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells with dominant-negative Rac1 (T17N) and constitutively active Rac1 (G12V), respectively. We measured a diminished O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level in the former and, conversely, an obviously rescued O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production in the latter. The percentage of inhibition and recovery was consistent with the ∼65% transfection efficiencies, as estimated using a GFP-expressing vector. The requirement of Rac1 suggested a Rac1-engaged Nox (i.e., Nox1-3)-dependent mechanism for O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production. Because Nox 3 is expressed predominantly in the inner ear (
    <a>
     Paffenholz et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), we examined the expression of Nox1 and Nox2 in A-5RT3 (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B). Next, we performed Nox1 and Nox2 knockdown (Nox1 kd and Nox2 kd, respectively) in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    and A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    C), and measured the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level using EPR (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B). Results indicated that Nox1 NADPH oxidase is the predominant source of ANGPTL4-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    generation in tumor cells. The O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level was completely abolished by superoxide scavenger Tiron, which serves as a negative control for superoxide measurements (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B). These data were reproduced by a chemiluminescence assay using 2-methyl-6-(4-methoxyphenyl)-3, 7-dihydroimidazo[1,2-a]pyrazin-3-one hydrochloride (MCLA) (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C) (
    <a>
     Münzel et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Next, we measured the level of H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    in tumor cells in the presence of a specific catalase inhibitor, 3-amino-l, 2, 4-triazole (
    <a>
     Chance et al., 1979
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wagner et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    levels were higher in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    than A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D). Nox1 kd did not affect the H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    level, suggesting that ANGPTL4 modulated H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    production, linked to an unknown mechanism (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    D). Notably, the lower O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level and O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio were concurrent with 3-fold more apoptosis and enhanced caspase activities within 2 hr of anoikis in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    compared to A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    cells (Figures
    <a>
     3
    </a>
    B, 3C, and
    <a>
     4
    </a>
    A–4D). Accordingly, we observed a reduced O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors compared to A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    E and 4F), which was associated with increased apoptosis (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    H and 2I;
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ANGPTL4 Elevates O2&amp;minus; Level and Maintains a Relatively High O2&amp;minus;:H2O2 Ratio in ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (990 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To underscore the relevance of these findings to other cancers, similar experiments were performed using the breast cancer line MDA-MB-231, after using mAb11F6C4 to dose dependently neutralize endogenous cANGPTL4. We showed earlier that mAb11F6C4 was able to block cANGPTL4-integrin interaction (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    G and 3H;
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    D–S3G). Consistent with the above results, the inhibition of cANGPTL4 in MDA-MB-231 reduced the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    E–S4G), lowered the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    H), and enhanced apoptosis and caspase activities (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    I and S4J). Nox1 kd (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    K) but not Nox2 kd reduced ANGPTL4-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    E–S4G) with little effect on H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    production (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    L). Together, these findings indicate that ANGPTL4 protects tumor cells from anoikis via an NADPH oxidase-dependent O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    generation mechanism.
   </p>
   <title>
    ANGPTL4-Mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    Activates the Src, PI3K/PKBα, and ERK Survival Pathways
   </title>
   <p>
    Previous reports have shown that ROS produced via integrin engagement oxidizes and activates Src, which stimulates the ERK and PKBα prosurvival pathways (
    <a>
     Giannoni et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Giannoni et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pani et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). Both pathways regulate the subcellular localization or stability of BH3-only apoptotic proteins (e.g., Bad and Bim), which are essential for executing anoikis (
    <a>
     Bouillet and Strasser, 2002
    </a>
    ). Thus, we asked whether ANGPTL4-integrin engaged O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    generation employs these downstream signaling pathways to modulate tumor cell behavior. Immunoblot analyses revealed diminished expression of oxidized/activated Src, phosphorylated PKBα, and ERK1 in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors and A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A, and left panel of
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). Similar immunoblot analyses performed in the presence of DPI and with Nox1 kd cells revealed reduced Src, PKBα, and ERK1 activation, emphasizing the role of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    in their activities (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). The inhibition of PI3K by LY294002 and Wortmannin, a pivotal upstream mediator of PKBα, caused 4-fold more apoptosis of tumor cells upon anoikis challenge, reaching levels comparable to those of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). In addition, inhibition of MEK1/2, the upstream signal of ERK1, by PD98059 also resulted in an enhancement of apoptotic cell numbers, albeit to a lesser extent (∼50%) compared to PI3K inhibitors (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). These results suggest that the PI3K/PKBα and ERK1/2 downstream survival pathways are modulated and exploited by ANGPTL4 engagement in tumor cells, the former being the predominant pathway.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ANGPTL4-Mediated O2&amp;minus; Regulates Src and Promotes the PI3K/PKB&amp;#945; and ERK Survival ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1661 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The 14-3-3 adaptor protein is known to act downstream of the aforementioned survival pathways by sequestering pro-apoptotic Bad from the mitochondria to prevent apoptosis (
    <a>
     She et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). In agreement with these previous findings, the number of 14-3-3/Bad complexes and 14-3-3β/σ proteins was reduced by ∼70% in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    D–5F). The Na
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    /H
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    exchanger 1 (NHE), which positively influences cell proliferation by maintaining an alkaline intracellular environment (
    <a>
     Akram et al., 2006
    </a>
    ), was also diminished in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    D), indicating that NHE plays a subsidiary role in ANGPTL4-mediated tumor cell growth. Upon oxidant challenge in tumor cells, the induction of superoxide dismutase (SOD) expression is muted, allowing tumor cell proliferation (
    <a>
     Oberley, 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pervaiz and Clément, 2007
    </a>
    ). Indeed, we found that cytosolic Zn/CuSOD expression was enhanced in A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    -induced tumors (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    D), which contribute to a reduced O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio via an indirect but linked mechanism (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <title>
    ANGPTL4 Deficiency Abrogates O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    Production and Sensitizes Cancer Cells to Anoikis
   </title>
   <p>
    Our results revealed that the suppression of ANGPTL4, either by RNAi (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A–4C) or inhibition with mAb11F6C4 (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    E–S4G), results in a dose-dependent reduction of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    levels. To underscore the importance of ANGPTL4 in the regulation of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production, maintenance of a high O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio, and, hence, tumor survival, we examined the impact of reduced ANGPTL4 on anoikis in nine different cancer cell lines, in addition to A-5RT3 and MDA-MB-231 cells. Treatment with mAb11F6C4 resulted in a dose-dependent reduction of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    levels (40%–80% for 6 μg/ml mAb11F6C4) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A;
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    A), a reduction in the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio (70%–90% for 6 μg/ml mAb11F6C4) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B;
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    B), a 3- to 8-fold increase in the caspase activities (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    A;
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    A), and 30%–60% more apoptotic tumor cells (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    B;
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    B), all indicating weakened anoikis resistance. A higher percentage of apoptotic tumor cells was also observed using inducible RNAi against ANGPTL4 in the MDA-MB-231 line (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C). These findings indicate that ANGPTL4-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production for anoikis resistance may be a common feature in tumor cells. Taken together, our study showed that tumor-secreted ANGPTL4 interacted with integrins in an autocrine fashion to stimulate NADPH oxidase-dependent generation of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    , promoting a high O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio, and consequently activating downstream PI3K/PKBα and ERK activities (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ANGPTL4 Maintains a Relatively High O2&amp;minus;:H2O2 Ratio in Tumor CellsMeasurement of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (382 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Deficiency of ANGPTL4 Activates Caspase Activities and Induces Apoptosis upon ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (478 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ANGPTL4-Mediated Regulation of O2&amp;minus; Production in TumorsIn an autocrine manner, ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr8.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr8.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr8.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S1535610811000304-gr8.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig8" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (304 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    The loss of dependence on integrin-mediated ECM contact for growth (i.e., anoikis resistance) is an essential feature of tumor cells, but the mechanism by which anoikis resistance is acquired is a central problem in cancer biology. Our findings demonstrated that ANGPTL4-mediated integrin engagement activates ROS production, which leads to a prosurvival signal and sustained anchorage-related signals even in the absence of ECM and cell-cell contact. We showed that cANGPTL4 was detected and elevated in many human tumor cells and was predominantly secreted by proliferative tumor epithelial cells. cANGPTL4 specifically binds to integrins β1 and β5 on tumor cells and activates FAK and Rac1, which further stimulates NADPH oxidase-mediated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production via an autocrine pathway. However, it is conceivable that in tissues/organs, expressing high levels of cANGPTL4 in proximity to the tumor site may transmit a paracrine signal. Although integrins alone are not oncogenic, integrin-mediated signaling is often required to enable tumor survival and influence tumor growth (
    <a>
     Desgrosellier and Cheresh, 2010
    </a>
    ). The pro-oxidant intracellular environment led to redox-mediated activation of the Src machinery and, therefore, stimulated downstream PI3K/PKBα and ERK prosurvival pathways. This further triggered the 14-3-3 adaptor protein to sequester the pro-apoptotic Bad protein from mitochondria, conferring resistance to anoikis and favoring tumor survival and growth.
   </p>
   <p>
    The dysregulation of intracellular ROS levels, resulting in an excessive level or persistent elevation of ROS, has been linked to tumor growth, invasiveness, and metastasis. Indeed, elevated levels of ROS are detected in almost all cancers (
    <a>
     Liou and Storz, 2010
    </a>
    ). An elevated O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    or O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio is particularly important for cancer cells to sustain their tumorigenicity and metastatic potential (
    <a>
     Clément and Pervaiz, 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Pervaiz and Clément, 2007
    </a>
    ). We found that the disruption of ANGPTL4-mediated redox signaling via genetic and antibody-mediated suppression of ANGPTL4 essentially reduced the activities of FAK, Rac1, and O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production. These changes resulted in an increase in tumor cells' sensitivity to anoikis and impaired tumorigenesis. ANGPTL4-stimulated NADPH oxidase activity, leading to O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production, can be inhibited NADPH oxidase inhibitors, but not by the mitochondrial complex I inhibitor rotenone. This suggests that O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    was “purposely” and enzymatically produced by NADPH oxidase, rather than as a by-product of mitochondrial activity. Two survival pathways, the PKBα and ERK, which have been shown to exert anoikis-suppressing effects (
    <a>
     Westhoff and Fulda, 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhan et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), were complementarily employed by ANGPTL4 to confer resistance to anoikis in tumor cells.
   </p>
   <p>
    The tumor-promoting role of inflammation in the tumor microenvironment is well recognized (
    <a>
     Aggarwal and Gehlot, 2009
    </a>
    ). PPARγ and δ/β play major roles in the regulation of inflammation and are implicated in tumorigenesis (
    <a>
     Peters and Gonzalez, 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Murphy and Holder, 2000
    </a>
    ). Although no correlation between the expression of either PPARγ or δ/β, and their target gene ANGPTL4, was observed in our analysis of PNSs and SCCs, we cannot exclude their involvement and/or other oncogenic pathways or cell types in the tumor microenvironment, which enhanced the expression of cANGPTL4 in tumors. It is also conceivable that PPARs in cancer-associated fibroblasts play a more dominant role in the regulation of epithelial tumor growth. Indeed, PPARβ/δ-deficient fibroblasts can increase the proliferation of normal epithelial cells and SCCs via regulation of the interleukin-1 signaling pathway (
    <a>
     Chong et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). A dysregulated inflammatory response promotes tumorigenesis and malignancy by stimulating ROS production (
    <a>
     Aggarwal and Gehlot, 2009
    </a>
    ). Although not examined in this study, we cannot rule out the possibility that other mechanisms to produce O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    , such as cytosolic 5-lipooxygenase, may act in conjunction with ANGPTL4-stimulated NADPH oxidase activity to maintain an elevated intracellular O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    level for tumor growth (
    <a>
     Chiarugi and Fiaschi, 2007
    </a>
    ). Despite inconclusive findings from clinical trials on the effect of antioxidants on cancer (
    <a>
     Blot et al., 1993
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Omenn et al., 1994
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hennekens et al., 1996
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lee et al., 1999
    </a>
    ), our findings that the specific inhibition of ANGPTL4-mediated integrin signaling and intracellular O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    production induce tumor cell apoptosis suggest that anticancer therapeutics focusing on redox-based apoptosis induction remain an exciting and viable strategy.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Human Tumor Samples
   </title>
   <p>
    Human BCC biopsies and SCC biopsies along with their paired PNSs were provided by J.Y.P., S.H.T., and purchased from USA Asterand, plc., Detroit, MI. BCC samples, SCC samples, and PNSs, inclusive of epithelia and stroma, were subjected to protein and RNA extraction for immunoblotting and qPCR analyses, respectively. The study was approved by National Healthcare Group Domain-Specific Review Boards (NHG-DSRB). All the tumor samples had been de-identified prior to the analyses.
   </p>
   <title>
    Tumorigenicity Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    BALB/c athymic nude female mice (20–22 g), aged 5–6 weeks, and WT C57BL/6J female mice (20–25 g), aged 6–8 weeks, were purchased from A
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    STAR Biological Resources Centre (Singapore). C57BL/6J female WT and ANGPTL4-KO mice were used (
    <a>
     Koster et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). The animal studies were approved and carried out in compliance with the regulation from Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC0092), NTU. For nude mice experiments, 5 × 10
    <sup>
     5
    </sup>
    cells (A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    or A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    ) were injected s.c. into the interscapular region of each nude mouse (n = 5). The injection site was rotated to avoid site bias. The injected tumor cells were allowed to grow for 8 weeks. The xenograft tumors were externally measured with a Vernier caliper every other day, and tumor volume was estimated using the equation: V = (L × W
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    )/2, where L and W are the length of the major and minor axis of the tumor, respectively. To test the effect of the number of injected cells on tumorigenicity, nude mice were inoculated with 0.5 ×, 2 ×, and 8 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    or A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    cells as above. Experiments were terminated at week 4 according to IACUC protocol because tumor volume in the 8 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    inoculation group approached 3000 mm
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    For the antibody treatment, nude mice (n = 6) were implanted with A-5RT3 as above. One week postimplantation, 30 mg/kg/week of either mAb11F6C4 or isotype control IgG was i.v. administered for 4 weeks. The dose of antibody and delivery mode were consistent with studies using mAb14D12, another anti-ANGPTL4 mAb27 (
    <a>
     Desai et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). KO mice and cANGPTL-treated C57BL/6J mice studies were performed as previously described (
    <a>
     Sun and Lodish, 2010
    </a>
    ). Briefly, 1 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    B16F10
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    (scrambled control) or B16F10
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    (ANGPTL4 knockdown) cells were s.c. injected into the interscapular region of the indicated mice (n = 4–6). Mice were i.v. treated with either 3 mg/kg of cANGPTL4 or control PBS three times a week. Animals were monitored and tumor volumes measured as above. Mice were sacrificed at the end of the experiment, and tumors were harvested for further analyses.
   </p>
   <title>
    In Situ PLA
   </title>
   <p>
    Duolink in situ PLA (Olink Bioscience) was performed on tumor biopsies or cells as described (
    <a>
     Tan et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). The paired-primary antibodies used in the present study were rabbit anti-p(Y397)FAK and mouse anti-FAK antibodies, rabbit anti-pan-14-3-3 and mouse anti-BAD antibodies, and mouse anti-cANGPTL4 with either rabbit anti-β1, β3, or β5 integrin antibodies. As a negative control, PLA was performed using only anti-FAK, anti-pan-14-3-3, or anti-nANGPTL4 antibodies, respectively. Briefly, sections/cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min. The slides were washed twice with PBS, blocked for 1 hr at room temperature with 2% BSA in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100, followed by incubation with the indicated antibody pairs overnight at 4°C. PLA was performed as recommended by the manufacturer. Images were taken using an LSM710 confocal laser scanning microscope with a Plan-Apochromat 63×/1.40 Oil objective and ZEN 2008 software (Carl Zeiss).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Measurement of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    and H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
   </title>
   <p>
    Production of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    from tumor cells was measured using an O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    -sensitive luciferin derivative, MCLA (Invitrogen). Cells (5 × 10
    <sup>
     4
    </sup>
    ) were trypsinized, washed, lysed in Krebs buffer, and treated either individually or combinatorially for 0.5 hr with the following chemicals: 10 mM Tiron, 20 μM diphenyleneiodonium chloride (DPI) or 500 μM apocynin, 50 μM rotenone, and 3 or 6 μg/ml monoclonal human anti-cANGPTL4 antibody mAb11F6C4. MCLA (2 μM) was added, and the luminescent signal was recorded immediately thereafter for 1 min with a GloMax 20/20 Luminometer (Promega). Intracellular H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    was measured as previously described (
    <a>
     Wagner et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). We performed two control experiments to verify that we were measuring H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    . The specificity of the assay for H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    was verified with catalase, and the degradation of H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    or inhibition of the assay system by the sample was analyzed by determining the recovery of exogenously added H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    . The fold change in the O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    :H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ratio of A-5RT3
    <sub>
     ANGPTL4
    </sub>
    and mAb11F6C4-treated tumor cells was determined by direct comparison with the value of either A-5RT3
    <sub>
     CTRL
    </sub>
    or control IgG-treated tumor cells, which were arbitrarily assigned the value of one.
   </p>
   <title>
    Statistical Analyses
   </title>
   <p>
    Statistical significance between two groups was analyzed using unpaired nonparametric test (Mann-Whitney test) or with a Student's t test (SPSS, Inc.). All statistical tests were two sided. A p value of ≤0.05 was considered significant.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Six Figures, One Table, and Supplemental Experimental Procedures.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (2222 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Aggarwal and Gehlot, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.B. Aggarwal, P. Gehlot
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inflammation and cancer: how friendly is the relationship for cancer patients?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Pharmacol., 9 (2009), pp. 351–369
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Akram et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Akram, H. Teong, L. Fliegel, S. Pervaiz, M. Clément
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reactive oxygen species-mediated regulation of the Na
         <sup>
          +
         </sup>
         -H
         <sup>
          +
         </sup>
         exchanger 1 gene expression connects intracellular redox status with cells' sensitivity to death triggers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Death Differ., 13 (2006), pp. 628–641
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Belanger et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Belanger, H. Lu, T. Date, L.X. Liu, K.A. Vincent, G.Y. Akita, S.H. Cheng, R.J. Gregory, C. Jiang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hypoxia up-regulates expression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor γ angiopoietin-related gene (PGAR) in cardiomyocytes: role of hypoxia inducible factor 1α
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol., 34 (2002), pp. 765–774
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Blot et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.J. Blot, J.Y. Li, P.R. Taylor, W. Guo, S. Dawsey, G.Q. Wang, C.S. Yang, S.F. Zheng, M. Gail, G.Y. Li,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nutrition intervention trials in Linxian, China: supplementation with specific vitamin/mineral combinations, cancer incidence, and disease-specific mortality in the general population
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Natl. Cancer Inst., 85 (1993), pp. 1483–1491
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bouillet and Strasser, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Bouillet, A. Strasser
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         BH3-only proteins- evolutionarily conserved proapoptotic Bcl-2 family members essential for initiating programmed cell death
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Sci., 115 (2002), pp. 1567–1574
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bridge et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Bridge, S. Pebernard, A. Ducraux, A.L. Nicoulaz, R. Iggo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Induction of an interferon response by RNAi vectors in mammalian cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Genet., 34 (2003), pp. 263–264
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chance et al., 1979
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Chance, H. Sies, A. Boveris
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hydroperoxide metabolism in mammalian organs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Physiol. Rev., 59 (1979), pp. 527–605
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chiarugi, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Chiarugi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         From anchorage dependent proliferation to survival: lessons from redox signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         IUBMB Life, 60 (2008), pp. 301–307
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chiarugi and Fiaschi, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Chiarugi, T. Fiaschi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox signalling in anchorage-dependent cell growth
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell. Signal., 19 (2007), pp. 672–682
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chong et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.C. Chong, M.J. Tan, V. Philippe, S.H. Tan, C.K. Tan, C.W. Ku, Y.Y. Goh, W. Wahli, L. Michalik, N.S. Tan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of epithelial-mesenchymal IL-1 signaling by PPARβ/δ is essential for skin homeostasis and wound healing
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 184 (2009), pp. 817–831
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Clément and Pervaiz, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.V. Clément, S. Pervaiz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Intracellular superoxide and hydrogen peroxide concentrations: a critical balance that determines survival or death
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox Rep., 6 (2001), pp. 211–214
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Desai et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        U. Desai, E.C. Lee, K. Chung, C. Gao, J. Gay, B. Key, G. Hansen, D. Machajewski, K.A. Platt, A.T. Sands,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Lipid-lowering effects of anti-angiopoietin-like 4 antibody recapitulate the lipid phenotype found in angiopoietin-like 4 knockout mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 104 (2007), pp. 11766–11771
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Desgrosellier and Cheresh, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.S. Desgrosellier, D.A. Cheresh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Integrins in cancer: biological implications and therapeutic opportunities
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Cancer, 10 (2010), pp. 9–22
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ferraro et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Ferraro, S. Corso, E. Fasano, E. Panieri, R. Santangelo, S. Borrello, S. Giordano, G. Pani, T. Galeotti
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Pro-metastatic signaling by c-Met through RAC-1 and reactive oxygen species (ROS)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 25 (2006), pp. 3689–3698
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fidler, 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I.J. Fidler
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Critical determinants of cancer metastasis: rationale for therapy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol., 43 (Suppl) (1999), pp. S3–S10
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Galaup et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Galaup, A. Cazes, S. Le Jan, J. Philippe, E. Connault, E. Le Coz, H. Mekid, L.M. Mir, P. Opolon, P. Corvol,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Angiopoietin-like 4 prevents metastasis through inhibition of vascular permeability and tumor cell motility and invasiveness
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 103 (2006), pp. 18721–18726
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ge et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Ge, G. Yang, L. Huang, D.L. Motola, T. Pourbahrami, C. Li
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oligomerization and regulated proteolytic processing of angiopoietin-like 4
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 2038–2045
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Giannoni et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Giannoni, F. Buricchi, G. Grimaldi, M. Parri, F. Cialdai, M.L. Taddei, G. Raugei, G. Ramponi, P. Chiarugi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox regulation of anoikis: reactive oxygen species as essential mediators of cell survival
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Death Differ., 15 (2008), pp. 867–878
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Giannoni et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Giannoni, T. Fiaschi, G. Ramponi, P. Chiarugi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox regulation of anoikis resistance of metastatic prostate cancer cells: key role for Src and EGFR-mediated pro-survival signals
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 28 (2009), pp. 2074–2086
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hanahan and Weinberg, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Hanahan, R.A. Weinberg
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The hallmarks of cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 100 (2000), pp. 57–70
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hennekens et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.H. Hennekens, J.E. Buring, J.E. Manson, M. Stampfer, B. Rosner, N.R. Cook, C. Belanger, F. LaMotte, J.M. Gaziano, P.M. Ridker,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Lack of effect of long-term supplementation with beta carotene on the incidence of malignant neoplasms and cardiovascular disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         N. Engl. J. Med., 334 (1996), pp. 1145–1149
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Irani et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Irani, Y. Xia, J.L. Zweier, S.J. Sollott, C.J. Der, E.R. Fearon, M. Sundaresan, T. Finkel, P.J. Goldschmidt-Clermont
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mitogenic signaling mediated by oxidants in Ras-transformed fibroblasts
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 275 (1997), pp. 1649–1652
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ito et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Ito, Y. Oike, K. Yasunaga, K. Hamada, K. Miyata, S.I. Matsumoto, S. Sugano, H. Tanihara, Y. Masuho, T. Suda
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inhibition of angiogenesis and vascular leakiness by angiopoietin-related protein 4
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 63 (2003), pp. 6651–6657
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Joneson and Bar-Sagi, 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Joneson, D. Bar-Sagi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A Rac1 effector site controlling mitogenesis through superoxide production
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 17991–17994
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kersten et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Kersten, S. Mandard, N.S. Tan, P. Escher, D. Metzger, P. Chambon, F.J. Gonzalez, B. Desvergne, W. Wahli
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Characterization of the fasting-induced adipose factor FIAF, a novel peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor target gene
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 275 (2000), pp. 28488–28493
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Komatsu et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Komatsu, M. Kato, J. Nakayama, S. Miyagawa, T. Kamata
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NADPH oxidase 1 plays a critical mediating role in oncogenic Ras-induced vascular endothelial growth factor expression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 27 (2008), pp. 4724–4732
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Koster et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Koster, Y. Chao, M. Mosior, A. Ford, P. Gonzalez-DeWhitt, J. Hale, D. Li, Y. Qiu, C. Fraser, D. Yang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Transgenic angiopoietin-like (angptl)4 overexpression and targeted disruption of angptl4 and angptl regulation of triglyceride metabolism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Endocrinology, 146 (2005), pp. 4943–4950
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Le Jan et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Le Jan, C. Amy, A. Cazes, C. Monnot, N. Lamandé, J. Favier, J. Philippe, M. Sibony, J.M. Gasc, P. Corvol,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Angiopoietin-like 4 is a proangiogenic factor produced during ischemia and in conventional renal cell carcinoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Am. J. Pathol., 162 (2003), pp. 1521–1528
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lee et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I.M. Lee, N.R. Cook, J.E. Manson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Beta-carotene supplementation and incidence of cancer and cardiovascular disease: Women's Health Study
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Natl. Cancer Inst., 91 (1999), pp. 2102–2106
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liou and Storz, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.Y. Liou, P. Storz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reactive oxygen species in cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Free Radic. Res., 44 (2010), pp. 479–496
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Minn et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Minn, G.P. Gupta, P.M. Siegel, P.D. Bos, W. Shu, D.D. Giri, A. Viale, A.B. Olshen, W.L. Gerald, J. Massagué
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes that mediate breast cancer metastasis to lung
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 436 (2005), pp. 518–524
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mueller et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.M. Mueller, W. Peter, M. Mappes, A. Huelsen, H. Steinbauer, P. Boukamp, M. Vaccariello, J. Garlick, N.E. Fusenig
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tumor progression of skin carcinoma cells in vivo promoted by clonal selection, mutagenesis, and autocrine growth regulation by granulocyte colony-stimulating factor and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Am. J. Pathol., 159 (2001), pp. 1567–1579
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Murphy and Holder, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.J. Murphy, J.C. Holder
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PPARγ agonists: therapeutic role in diabetes, inflammation and cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Pharmacol. Sci., 21 (2000), pp. 469–474
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Münzel et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Münzel, I.B. Afanas'ev, A.L. Kleschyov, D.G. Harrison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Detection of superoxide in vascular tissue
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol., 22 (2002), pp. 1761–1768
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Oberley, 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.W. Oberley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anticancer therapy by overexpression of superoxide dismutase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Antioxid. Redox Signal., 3 (2001), pp. 461–472
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Oike et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Oike, M. Akao, Y. Kubota, T. Suda
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Angiopoietin-like proteins: potential new targets for metabolic syndrome therapy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Mol. Med., 11 (2005), pp. 473–479
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Omenn et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.S. Omenn, G. Goodman, M. Thomquist, J. Grizzle, L. Rosenstock, S. Barnhart, J. Balmes, M.G. Cherniack, M.R. Cullen, A. Glass,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The beta-carotene and retinol efficacy trial (CARET) for chemoprevention of lung cancer in high risk populations: smokers and asbestos-exposed workers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 54 (1994), pp. 2038s–2043s
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Padua et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Padua, X.H.F. Zhang, Q. Wang, C. Nadal, W.L. Gerald, R.R. Gomis, J. Massagué
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TGFβ primes breast tumors for lung metastasis seeding through angiopoietin-like 4
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 133 (2008), pp. 66–77
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Paffenholz et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Paffenholz, R.A. Bergstrom, F. Pasutto, P. Wabnitz, R.J. Munroe, W. Jagla, U. Heinzmann, A. Marquardt, A. Bareiss, J. Laufs,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Vestibular defects in head-tilt mice result from mutations in Nox3, encoding an NADPH oxidase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 18 (2004), pp. 486–491
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pani et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Pani, E. Giannoni, T. Galeotti, P. Chiarugi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Redox-based escape mechanism from death: the cancer lesson
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Antioxid. Redox Signal., 11 (2009), pp. 2791–2806
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pervaiz and Clément, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Pervaiz, M.V. Clément
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Superoxide anion: oncogenic reactive oxygen species?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol., 39 (2007), pp. 1297–1304
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Peters and Gonzalez, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.M. Peters, F.J. Gonzalez
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Sorting out the functional role(s) of PPARβ/δ in cell proliferation and cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochim. Biophys. Acta, 1796 (2009), pp. 230–241
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Salmon, 1984
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.E. Salmon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Human tumor colony assay and chemosensitivity testing
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Treat. Rep., 68 (1984), pp. 117–125
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         She et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Q.B. She, D.B. Solit, Q. Ye, K.E. O'Reilly, J. Lobo, N. Rosen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The BAD protein integrates survival signaling by EGFR/MAPK and PI3K/Akt kinase pathways in PTEN-deficient tumor cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 8 (2005), pp. 287–297
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Singh et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Singh, A. Sadanandam, R.K. Singh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Chemokines in tumor angiogenesis and metastasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Metastasis Rev., 26 (2007), pp. 453–467
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Suh et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y.A. Suh, R.S. Arnold, B. Lassegue, J. Shi, X. Xu, D. Sorescu, A.B. Chung, K.K. Griendling, J.D. Lambeth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell transformation by the superoxide-generating oxidase Mox1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 401 (1999), pp. 79–82
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sun and Lodish, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Sun, H.F. Lodish
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Adiponectin deficiency promotes tumor growth in mice by reducing macrophage infiltration
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PLoS ONE, 5 (2010), p. e11987
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tan et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.H. Tan, M. Pal, M.J. Tan, M.H.L. Wong, F.U. Tam, J.W.T. Teo, H.C. Chong, C.K. Tan, Y.Y. Goh, M.B.Y. Tang,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of cell proliferation and migration by TAK1 via transcriptional control of von Hippel-Lindau tumor suppressor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 284 (2009), pp. 18047–18058
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ushio-Fukai and Nakamura, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Ushio-Fukai, Y. Nakamura
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reactive oxygen species and angiogenesis: NADPH oxidase as target for cancer therapy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Lett., 266 (2008), pp. 37–52
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wagner et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.A. Wagner, C.B. Evig, K.J. Reszka, G.R. Buettner, C.P. Burns
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Doxorubicin increases intracellular hydrogen peroxide in PC3 prostate cancer cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Arch. Biochem. Biophys., 440 (2005), pp. 181–190
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Wang, K.S.L. Lam, J.B.B. Lam, M.C. Lam, P.T.Y. Leung, M. Zhou, A. Xu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Overexpression of angiopoietin-like 4 alters mitochondria activities and modulates methionine metabolic cycle in the liver tissues of db/db diabetic mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Endocrinol., 21 (2007), pp. 972–986
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Wang, B. Han, Z. Zhang, J. Pan, H. Xia
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Expression of angiopoietin-like 4 and tenascin C but not cathepsin C mRNA predicts prognosis of oral tongue squamous cell carcinoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biomarkers, 15 (2010), pp. 39–46
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Westhoff and Fulda, 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.A. Westhoff, S. Fulda
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Adhesion-mediated apoptosis resistance in cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Drug Resist. Updat., 12 (2009), pp. 127–136
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wu, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.S. Wu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The signaling mechanism of ROS in tumor progression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Metastasis Rev., 25 (2006), pp. 695–705
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhan et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Zhan, H. Zhao, Z.C. Han
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Signalling mechanisms of anoikis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Histol. Histopathol., 19 (2004), pp. 973–983
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2011 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>