<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2011.10.046
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Structural Basis and Sequence Rules for Substrate Recognition by Tankyrase Explain the Basis for Cherubism Disease
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    ADP-ribosylation of proteins or other acceptors is catalyzed by a family of 22 known or putative human ADP-ribosyltransferases, which use nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    ) as a source for transferring ADP-ribose onto their substrates, either as monomers or by constructing poly(ADP-ribose) chains (reviewed in
    <a>
     Amé et al., 2004
    </a>
    ; reviewed in
    <a>
     Hassa and Hottiger, 2008
    </a>
    ; reviewed in
    <a>
     Hottiger et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kleine et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Protein ADP-ribosylation reportedly occurs on aspartate, glutamate, asparagine, arginine, lysine, cysteine, phosphoserine, and diphthamide residues (reviewed in
    <a>
     Hottiger et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). As a large posttranslational modification of substantial negative charge, protein poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation (PARsylation) can influence protein fate through several mechanisms, including a direct effect on protein activity, recruitment of binding partners that recognize poly(ADP-ribose), or by affecting protein turnover.
   </p>
   <p>
    Tankyrase is a multidomain poly(ADP-ribose)polymerase (PARP) with an N-terminal region rich in ankyrin repeats, a sterile-alpha motif (SAM) domain that mediates Tankyrase oligomerization, and a C-terminal catalytic PARP domain (reviewed in
    <a>
     Hsiao and Smith, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Smith et al., 1998
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). The N-terminal ankyrin repeats cluster into five domains (“ankyrin repeat clusters,” ARCs), whose precise structures remain to be determined (
    <a>
     Seimiya and Smith, 2002
    </a>
    ). The human genome encodes two similar Tankyrases, TNKS and TNKS2 (PARP5/ARTD5 and PARP6/ARTD6). Both recruit a variety of substrates involved in a broad range of biological functions (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). Tankyrases recognize linear peptide motifs consisting minimally of six consecutive amino acids with high apparent degeneracy in sequence (the TNKS-binding motif, extended to 8 amino acids as shown below) (reviewed in
    <a>
     Hsiao and Smith, 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sbodio and Chi, 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Seimiya and Smith, 2002
    </a>
    ). This makes rationalization of known substrates and the prediction of additional substrates difficult. To date, TNKS-binding motifs have been validated or proposed in 17 proteins (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). In many of the studied systems, binding of target proteins by Tankyrase results in their PARsylation. Tankyrase targets some of its substrates for ubiquitylation and proteasome-dependent degradation, as observed for TERF1/TRF1 (
    <a>
     Chang et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Smith et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), AXIN (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2009
    </a>
    ), MCL1 (
    <a>
     Bae et al., 2003
    </a>
    ), and 3BP2 (see accompanying manuscript by
    <a>
     Levaot et al., 2011
    </a>
    [this issue of
    <em>
     Cell
    </em>
    ]). In the case of 3BP2, mutations in the TNKS-binding motif that abolish Tankyrase recognition underlie the human disease cherubism, a condition characterized by inflammatory lesions of the facial bone (see accompanying manuscript by
    <a>
     Levaot et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). These findings highlight the essential role of substrate targeting in Tankyrase biological function.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Functional Characterization of an Ankyrin Repeat Cluster(A) Domain organization ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1244 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Previously Identified and Proposed Tankyrase Binders
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Protein Name
          </th>
          <th>
           Function
          </th>
          <th>
           Reference(s)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Proven Tankyrase Binders/Substrates with Identified TNKS-Binding Motifs
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           TERF1/TRF1
          </td>
          <td>
           telomere binder and negative regulator of telomere length
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Cook et al., 2002
           </a>
           ,
           <a>
            Kaminker et al., 2001
           </a>
           ,
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           ,
           <a>
            Sbodio et al., 2002
           </a>
           and
           <a>
            Smith et al., 1998
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           AXIN1/2
          </td>
          <td>
           tumor suppressor in the Wnt signaling pathway
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Huang et al., 2009
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           LNPEP/IRAP
          </td>
          <td>
           integral-membrane aminopeptidase
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Chi and Lodish, 2000
           </a>
           ,
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           and
           <a>
            Sbodio et al., 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           NUMA1
          </td>
          <td>
           mitotic spindle regulator
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Chang et al., 2005a
           </a>
           ,
           <a>
            Chang et al., 2005b
           </a>
           and
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           MCL1
          </td>
          <td>
           apoptosis regulator
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Bae et al., 2003
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           TNKS1BP1/TAB182
          </td>
          <td>
           largely uncharacterized Tankyrase binder
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           and
           <a>
            Seimiya and Smith, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           EBNA1
          </td>
          <td>
           protein of Epstein Barr virus; functions in DNA replication and transcriptional regulation
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Deng et al., 2002
           </a>
           and
           <a>
            Deng et al., 2005
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           FNBP1/FBP17
          </td>
          <td>
           cytoskeletal regulator
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Fuchs et al., 2003
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           BLZF1
          </td>
          <td>
           regulator of protein transport; precise function unknown
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Zhang et al., 2011
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CASC3
          </td>
          <td>
           regulator mRNA biogenesis
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Zhang et al., 2011
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           3BP2
          </td>
          <td>
           signaling adaptor protein; mutated in cherubism
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Levaot et al., 2011
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Proposed Tankyrase Interactors with Putative TNKS-Binding Motifs
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           GRB14
          </td>
          <td>
           signaling adaptor
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Lyons et al., 2001
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           HOXB2
          </td>
          <td>
           homeobox transcription factor
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           PPP1R12C/MBS85
          </td>
          <td>
           polymorphic variant of the protein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 12C
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           TAX1BP1
          </td>
          <td>
           apoptosis regulator
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CACNA1S
          </td>
          <td>
           alpha 1S subunit of the voltage-dependent L-type calcium channel
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           USP25
          </td>
          <td>
           ubiquitin-specific protease
          </td>
          <td>
           (
           <a>
            Sbodio and Chi, 2002
           </a>
           )
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Proposed Tankyrase binders were identified by yeast-two-hybrid analysis; GRB14 was confirmed as an interactor by coimmunoprecipitation.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Here we uncover the structural and functional basis of how Tankyrases recognize their substrates and derive a comprehensive set of rules that explain the basis for cherubism disease and enable the accurate prediction of Tankyrase substrates.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    The TNKS2 N Terminus Contains Minimally Four Substrate-Binding Sites
   </title>
   <p>
    Previous work indicated that the N-terminal ankyrin repeat region of Tankyrase has five ARCs (
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Seimiya and Smith, 2002
    </a>
    ), each predicted to bind substrate (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). A bacterially expressed TNKS2 fragment containing the entire ankyrin repeat region (residues 20–800) bound a fluorescein-labeled 3BP2 substrate recruitment peptide (LPHLQRSPPDGQSFRS) with an apparent affinity of 0.5 ± 0.1 μM (using a one-site binding model;
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B, left). TNKS2 fragments corresponding to ARCs 1, 4, and 5 and a double-ARC construct comprising both ARCs 2 and 3 (but not ARCs 2 or 3 individually) were also solubly expressed and purified. ARCs 1, 4, and 5 each bound the 3BP2 peptide (dissociation constant [K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    ] = 6.9 ± 2.8 μM, 6.3 ± 1.2 μM, and 1.3 ± 0.2 μM, respectively;
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B, right). The ARC2-3 unit also bound the 3BP2 peptide (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 2.3 ± 0.3 μM), but we could not determine whether it contained one or two functional peptide-binding sites (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B, right). We concluded that there are four, or possibly five, functional substrate-binding sites in the TNKS2 N terminus, in agreement with previous work (
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Seimiya and Smith, 2002
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Structural Analysis of an ARC and Prediction of Its Peptide-Binding Pocket
   </title>
   <p>
    A boundary-optimized form of ARC4 was crystallized in apo- and 3BP2 peptide-bound forms, and X-ray crystal structures were determined by molecular replacement (see
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    available online for data collection and refinement statistics and
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details). ARC4 consists of a stack of five ankyrin repeats (
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    A and 1C), the central three of which (repeats 2–4) possess a characteristic ankyrin repeat architecture (loop–helix1–loop–helix2–loop). Ankyrin repeat 1 is cryptic in nature, with an atypically long helix1, whereas ankyrin repeat 5 has an atypically short helix1. As in other ankyrin repeat proteins, the terminal loops of each ankyrin repeat extend from the pair of hydrophobically packed, antiparallel helices, forming a sheet of β hairpins (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). The continuous succession of ankyrin repeats generates a concave surface at the “front” face of the ARC (according to the view shown in
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <p>
    Projection of residue conservation for ARCs 1–5 onto the ARC4 surface identified a conserved concave surface in the central region of the ARC (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D, left). Omission of ARC3 from the conservation analysis increased the degree of sequence conservation on the mapped surface (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D, right). As demonstrated below, the conserved region corresponds to the peptide-binding pocket, and its lack of conservation in ARC3 reflects the fact that ARC3 does not bind substrates.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Overview of the ARC4:3BP2 TNKS-Binding Motif Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    In the ARC4:3BP2 peptide complex, the 3BP2 peptide of sequence LPHLQ
    <span>
     RSPPDGQS
    </span>
    FRS (core binding motif as described below is underlined) adopts an extended conformation and binds to a pocket situated centrally to the ARC, perpendicular to its longitudinal axis (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A). The pocket is located within the peptide-binding site predicted by sequence conservation and is entirely formed by the central three ankyrin repeats (2–4). As such, the flanking ankyrin repeats, 1 and 5, likely serve as structural caps (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    B), as noted for other ankyrin repeat proteins (reviewed in
    <a>
     Forrer et al., 2003
    </a>
    ; reviewed in
    <a>
     Li et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). The anticipated shortness of linkers (0 to 9 residues) between autonomously folding ARCs (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C) likely limits the flexibility of an otherwise beads-on-a-string architecture.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Structural Representation of the ARC4:3BP2 Targeting Peptide Complex(A) Ribbon ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1143 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Domain Architecture of 3BP2 and Identified Tankyrase Targets and Capping ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (525 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Description of the TNKS2 ARC4:3BP2 TNKS-Binding Motif Interface
   </title>
   <p>
    The 8-residue 3BP2 core sequence
    <span>
     RSPPDGQS
    </span>
    is engaged by four groups of peptide-coordinating residues in ARC4: arginine at position 1 (R415
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    ) of the 3BP2 peptide is engaged by an “arginine cradle,” glycine at position 6 (G420
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    ) is engaged by an “aromatic glycine sandwich,” the central residues between the arginine and glycine (positions 2–5) are engaged by a ”central patch,” and two C-terminal residues (positions 7 and 8) are engaged by two C-terminal contact residues (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
   <p>
    Four TNKS2 side chains contribute to the extensive arginine cradle (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C): W591
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    packs against the nonpolar portion of the R415
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    side chain. F593
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    establishes a cation-π interaction, whereas E598
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and D589
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    form salt bridges with the guanidinium group of R415
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Two TNKS2 tyrosines, Y536
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and Y569
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , form the aromatic glycine sandwich (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). The absence of a side chain at G420
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    allows for a close approach of the peptide main chain to the ARC such that a hydrogen bond is formed between the main-chain carbonyl of G535
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and the main-chain amide of Q421
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at position 7.
   </p>
   <p>
    Nine residues comprise the central patch of the peptide-binding pocket (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    A). R525
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    forms a hydrogen bond with the side chain of S416
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at position 2, the main-chain carbonyl groups of S416
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    and P417
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at positions 2 and 3, respectively, and, via a water molecule, the main-chain amino and carbonyl groups of S416
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    . TNKS2 makes no contact with the solvent-exposed side chain of P417
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    ; however, P417
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    directs the peptide backbone toward a subpocket into which the side chain of P418
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at position 4 inserts. Within this subpocket, L560
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    confers hydrophobic contact, whereas the main chains of N565
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and H564
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and the side chain of S568
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    confer Van der Waals contact. The side chain of Y569
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    additionally coordinates P418
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    through a hydrogen bond to the main-chain carbonyl group.
   </p>
   <p>
    A subpocket of the central patch defined by F532
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , D521
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , S527
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , and R525
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    accommodates the D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    side chain at position 5. S527
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    forms a direct hydrogen bond with D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    , whereas D521
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and the main-chain amino group of R525
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and S527
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    form water-bridged hydrogen bonds to the D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    side chain. Similarly, S527
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , D556
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , and N565
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    collaborate in a water-bridged hydrogen-bonding network to the main-chain amino group of D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    . The N565
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    side chain also hydrogen bonds with the main-chain carbonyl group of D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    . Lastly, a water molecule bridges the Y536
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    and D419
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    side chains.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although the residues preceding the arginine at position 1 are poorly ordered and unlikely to contribute critical contacts, two C-terminally located amino acids of the peptide are directly coordinated by ARC4 side chains: the side chain of H571
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    hydrogen bonds with the main-chain carbonyl group of Q421
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at position 7, whereas the side chain of K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    hydrogen bonds with the side chain of S422
    <sup>
     3BP2
    </sup>
    at position 8 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). The structural order of the three C-terminal peptide residues is largely attributable to crystal contacts with no major direct contacts to the corresponding ARC.
   </p>
   <p>
    The four ARC4:3BP2 complexes present in the asymmetric unit are highly similar (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    B). A comparison of the apo- and peptide-bound forms of ARC4 demonstrates that the peptide-binding pocket is fully formed prior to peptide coordination (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Structural Features of the ARC4 Peptide-Binding Surface, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;2(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (654 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Validation of the ARC4-Peptide Interaction Surface by Mutagenesis
   </title>
   <p>
    To biochemically validate the ARC4:3BP2 structure, we introduced mutations into the peptide-binding pocket predicted to impair binding while preserving the ankyrin repeat fold. We produced and purified 14 well-folded ARC4 mutant derivatives (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    ) and performed fluorescence polarization (FP) assays to test each for substrate (3BP2) binding (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). As noted above, wild-type (WT) ARC4 bound the 3BP2 peptide with micromolar affinity (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 6.4 ± 0.6 μM) (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Probing the ARC4 Interaction Surface by Site-Directed Mutagenesis and Analyzing ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1036 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Validation of ARC4 Mutant Integrity, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;3(A) Coomassie-stained ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (312 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Mutation of arginine cradle residues (W591A, F593A, E598A, WFE591/593/598AAA, D589T) strongly impaired peptide binding to ARC4 so that a K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    could not be determined (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). Mutation of Y536, one of the glycine sandwich tyrosines (Y536A), had a weak effect on peptide binding (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 17.7 ± 3.5 μM), whereas mutation of Y569 (Y569A, YY536/569AA) abolished measurable peptide binding. TNKS2 residues coordinating the central positions 2–5 of the 3BP2 peptide also proved critical for peptide binding. An N565A mutation strongly reduced peptide binding (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 30.2 ± 8.9 μM), whereas the R525A, R525D, S527A, and a pocket-filling L560W mutation each reduced peptide binding below quantifiability. These results validate our structural observations and establish a set of residues critical for 3BP2 targeting peptide engagement by an ARC. Notably, despite the conservation of K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    as a basic residue (see
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C), its mutation to alanine had no measurable effect on 3BP2 peptide binding. As discussed below, K604 makes a more important contribution to binding of targeting peptides from other Tankyrase substrates.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Based on conservation of residues within the validated substrate-binding surface of ARC4, we can rationalize the peptide-binding function of the different ARCs: like ARC4, ARCs 1, 2, and 5 possess the required infrastructure for substrate binding, whereas ARC3 does not (see ARC alignment in
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). We therefore anticipated that the ARC2-3 construct discussed above contains only a single peptide-binding site formed by ARC2. Introduction of an L245W mutation into ARC2 (equivalent to the L560W mutation in ARC4) in the context of ARC2-3 (ARC2
    <sub>
     mut
    </sub>
    -3) abolished ARC2-3 binding to the 3BP2 peptide, confirming this prediction (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B). The TNKS2 N terminus therefore contains four functional 3BP2 peptide-binding sites. If one considers the presence of four sites within the TNKS2 N terminus that contribute similarly to peptide binding, the overall affinity of the penta-ARC construct (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B, left) is in agreement with the affinities of the individual ARCs (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B, right).
   </p>
   <title>
    ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 Display Redundancy for 3BP2 Binding
   </title>
   <p>
    The binding behavior of ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 toward 3BP2 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B) suggests that these ARCs may be functionally redundant for 3BP2 recognition. To test this prediction, we serially introduced inactivating L-to-W mutations (equivalent to the L560W mutation in ARC4) into each of the ARCs of TNKS2 in the context of the full ankyrin repeat region spanning all five ARCs (TNKS2(20–800);
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). Bacterially expressed His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -GST-TNKS2(20–800) efficiently recruited purified, recombinant full-length His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -3BP2 in a GST pull-down assay, whereas neither His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -GST alone nor the corresponding TNKS2 mutant with five mutated ARCs (xxxxx) bound 3BP2 (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D). In agreement with our prediction, all five single-ARC mutants (x2345, 1x345, 12x45, 123x5, 1234x) showed robust binding to 3BP2, demonstrating that no single ARC is critical for 3BP2 binding by Tankyrase (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <p>
    To determine whether any of the five ARCs is sufficient for 3BP2 recruitment in the context of the full TNKS2 N terminus, we mutated four out of five ARCs, leaving only a single ARC intact (1xxxx, x2xxx, xx3xx, xxx4x, xxxx5). As expected, ARC3 alone (xx3xx) did not bind 3BP2, whereas ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 alone did bind, but with reduced apparent affinities (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D). Reduced binding might reflect the simple reduction of the number of available binding sites and/or the loss of avidity effects.
   </p>
   <p>
    To extend our binding analysis to full-length Tankyrase, we coexpressed WT MYC-TNKS2 or a set of mutant derivatives with either WT FLAG-3BP2 or cherubism derivatives (murine R413Q and P416H) of FLAG-3BP2 in mammalian (HEK293T) cells (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    E). Following immunoprecipitation of WT FLAG-3BP2, we detected robust binding of TNKS2 and any of its single-ARC mutants but not TNKS2 xxxxx or xx3xx (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    E). The cherubic FLAG-3BP2 variants (murine R413Q or P416H) did not recruit Tankyrase detectably. These observations support a degree of functional redundancy across ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 for 3BP2 recruitment. A complete disabling of substrate recognition by Tankyrase in cells thus may require the inactivation of all four functional ARCs.
   </p>
   <title>
    ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 Display Similar Substrate Recognition Abilities, and TNKS-Binding Motifs Are Octapeptides
   </title>
   <p>
    We expanded our analysis from 3BP2 to other Tankyrase targets. Using the FP binding assay, we assessed ARC4 binding to proven or predicted targeting peptides from known or proposed Tankyrase substrates (3BP2, NUMA1, HOXB2, LNPEP, FNBP1, TNKS1BP1, a polymorphic variant of PPP1R12C, CACNA1S, MCL1, USP25, TERF1, AXIN1, TAX1BP1, EBNA1, and GRB14; see
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ) (reviewed in
    <a>
     Hsiao and Smith, 2008
    </a>
    ). All peptides except for those from TAX1BP1, EBNA1, GRB14, and nonpolymorphic PPP1R12C bound ARC4 with comparable (micromolar) affinities (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Determinants in TNKS-Binding Motifs for ARC4 Binding(A) Sequence alignment of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1186 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Binding analysis of other ARCs to the same panel of peptides revealed similar peptide-discriminating abilities with only slight differences in overall binding affinities. On average, ARC2 (i.e., ARC2-3) and ARC5 bound TNKS-binding motif peptides more strongly than ARC1 or ARC4 (Figures
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Among ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5, ARC1 was the weakest peptide binder, which may be rationalized by two phenylalanines in place of the tyrosines in the aromatic glycine sandwich (see sequence alignment in
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). This would abolish a hydrogen bond between the residue equivalent to Y569 in ARC4 with the substrate main chain (see
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C). Based on the hyperconservation of peptide-binding surface residues within each ARC across different species, we reason that the relative binding strength and function of each ARC will be conserved across life forms with Tankyrases that possess a penta-ARC organization (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Substrate Recognition Properties of the Different ARCs of TNKS2, Related to ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (829 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Nonlinear Regression Analysis of the Baseline-Corrected FP Data for Binding of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Figure S5.
        <p>
         Nonlinear Regression Analysis of the Baseline-Corrected FP Data for Binding of TNKS2 ARCs to the Indicated Peptides, Related to
         <a>
          Figures 4
         </a>
         and
         <a>
          S4
         </a>
        </p>
        <p>
         Data are from one experiment done in technical duplicate, except the data for TERF1 (ARC5), LNPEP (ARC2
         <sub>
          mut
         </sub>
         -3), CACNA1S (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), EBNA1 (1) (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), EBNA1 (2) (ARC2-3), and GRB14 (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), which include an additional experiment done in technical duplicate with a maximum ARC concentration of 150 μM. Error bars, SEM (where n &gt; 1 technical duplicate). See
         <a>
          Figure S4
         </a>
         A for a graphical summary of the data and
         <a>
          Table S2
         </a>
         for all K
         <sub>
          D
         </sub>
         .
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (747 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    TNKS-binding motifs are typically referred to as “hexapeptides,” and the limited overall sequence conservation outside a 6-amino-acid stretch suggested that the hexapeptide contains the chief determinants for Tankyrase binding (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). To revisit the actual extent of the TNKS-binding motif, we performed an alanine scan across a 9-amino-acid range for two prominent TNKS-binding motifs, 3BP2 and AXIN1. We then tested the effect of each mutation on ARC4 association in the FP assay (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). The WT 3BP2 peptide bound ARC4 with a K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    of 3.8 ± 0.4 μM. Mutation of the residues preceding the invariant arginine at position 1, Q-1A, and mutation of residues at positions 7 and 8 had little effect on ARC4 binding (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    values of 4.6 ± 1.1 μM, 3.9 ± 0.9 μM, and 3.8 ± 0.7 μM, respectively). Strikingly, mutation of the invariantly conserved R1 and G6 positions to alanine (R415A and G420A) abolished quantifiable binding of ARC4 to the peptide, similar to the GST pull-down results obtained with the TNKS-binding motif peptide of LNPEP (
    <a>
     Sbodio and Chi, 2002
    </a>
    ). Mutation of the less conserved peptide residues at positions 2–4 (S416A, P417A, P418) only had small effects (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    values of 5.7 ± 0.8 μM, 7.3 ± 1.1 μM, 8.8 ± 1.5 μM, respectively). The D419A mutation at position 5 resulted in a larger decrease in peptide affinity (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 70.0 ± 39.5 μM), indicating a more critical contribution of aspartate at this site. The binding determinants for 3BP2 therefore map to a hexapeptide stretch. In the case of AXIN1, however, binding to ARC4 was sensitive to mutations across an octapeptide region (positions 1 to 8;
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). As observed for 3BP2, the arginine and glycine residues at positions 1 and 6 were absolutely required for binding. Mutation of residues at positions 2, 3, 4, 5, and 8 resulted in less dramatic decreases in affinity, whereas mutation of the residue at position 7 had no negative effect on binding. Unlike for 3BP2, mutation of residue 8 weakened the ARC4-AXIN1 interaction about 2.3-fold (from 6.5 ± 1.4 μM to 15.1 ± 4.0 μM).
   </p>
   <p>
    In summary, the four functional ARCs display similar binding properties, and ARC-binding determinants map to a TNKS-binding motif of 8 amino acids. The highly conserved arginine and glycine residues at positions 1 and 6 of the binding motif are critical anchor residues essential for peptide binding to ARC4. The limited sampling of the alanine scan, however, did not fully explain the remarkable diversity of residues at other positions of functional TNKS-binding motifs (explored below).
   </p>
   <title>
    A Structural Comparison of Multiple TNKS-Binding Motif Peptides
   </title>
   <p>
    The variability of the central peptide residues in various Tankyrase ligands is striking (see
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). For example, the TNKS-binding motif peptide of MCL1 contains three consecutive proline residues (RPPPIGAE), whereas that of TERF1 lacks prolines altogether (RGCADGRD). To elucidate whether such diverse ligands employ the same binding mode for ARC interaction, we crystallized ARC4 bound to peptides from TERF1, MCL1, LNPEP, NUMA1, and FNBP1 (
    <a>
     Table S1. Data Collection and Refinement Statistics, Related to Figures 2 and 4
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Table S6. Peptides Used in This Study, Related to Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    ). All peptides bound in a similar configuration observed for the 3BP2-derived peptide (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D); notably, peptides without prolines adopted a geometry similar to proline-containing peptides. Thus, despite considerable variation in interaction motif sequence, all substrates investigated employ a common ARC-binding mode.
   </p>
   <p>
    Unfortunately, we were unable to obtain crystals for ARC4 bound to AXIN1/2, one of the most prominent Tankyrase targets (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2009
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). To probe whether AXIN1 employs an ARC-binding mode similar to that of the other targets analyzed, we investigated binding of the AXIN1-targeting peptide to the 14 ARC4 pocket mutants described above. Most of the mutations that impaired binding to the 3BP2 substrate peptide also perturbed binding to the AXIN1 peptide, arguing that a common binding mode is employed (compare
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    C). However, binding of the AXIN1 peptide was strikingly sensitive to mutation of the C-terminal contact residue K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    to alanine (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    C). Position 8 in the TNKS-binding motifs of AXIN1 and AXIN2 (and MCL1) is occupied by a conserved glutamate residue (versus a serine residue in 3BP2), which we predict forms a potent stabilizing salt bridge interaction (versus weaker hydrogen bond) with K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , as observed in the ARC4:MCL1 complex (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4D). Furthermore, in comparison to 3BP2, the ARC4-AXIN1 interaction was less sensitive to the R525A
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    mutation in the central patch (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    C). As R525
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    forms a stabilizing hydrogen bond to the polar side chain of substrate position 2 (S416 in the case of 3BP2), the presence of a nonpolar proline in position 2 of AXIN would render R525 more dispensable.
   </p>
   <p>
    Thus, although the overall binding mode of substrates to an ARC of Tankyrase is highly conserved, the relative importance of component interactions can differ markedly for different substrates.
   </p>
   <title>
    Defining Sequence Rules that Govern Substrate Recognition by Tankyrase
   </title>
   <p>
    To fully understand the binding determinants within the TNKS-binding motifs in Tankyrase substrates, we designed a peptide library based on the TNKS-binding motif of 3BP2. We serially exchanged each residue of the 8-amino-acid stretch RSPPDGQS in the fluorescently labeled peptide QRSPPDGQS for each of the 20 standard amino acids, obtaining 153 unique peptides. We then used the FP binding assay to test their binding to ARC4. The results (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     S6
    </a>
    A and
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    ) can be rationalized by our ARC:peptide structures.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Defining a Rule-Based Consensus for TNKS-Binding Motifs to Predict Tankyrase ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (693 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="A Rule-Based Consensus for the TNKS-Binding Motif, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;5(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (817 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    As expected, peptide recognition by ARC4 critically requires arginine and glycine residues at positions 1 and 6, respectively. The arginine cradle is specifically tuned for arginine with multiple residues collaborating in arginine coordination (see
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    B and 2C). The phi and psi peptide bond angles of glycine at position 6 are unique to glycine and cannot be adopted by any other amino acid, explaining why even alanine cannot substitute at position 6 (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <p>
    Positions 2 and 3 of the TNKS-binding motif display a broad amino acid tolerance. However position 3 poorly tolerated phenylalanine, and the rank order of the individual residues was different between the two positions. Consistent with the broad tolerance, the side chains at positions 2 and 3 of all peptides in the crystal structures introduced above (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D) always face solvent. We cannot rationalize why phenylalanine is unfavorable at position 3.
   </p>
   <p>
    The side chain at peptide position 4 is restricted to the small and/or hydrophobic amino acids proline, glycine, alanine, and cysteine. In the crystal structures, side chains at position 4 are always presented toward the peptide-binding pocket on the ARC. The space restraints imposed by the position-4 subpocket, and its hydrophobic nature, explain why only small and hydrophobic amino acids are tolerated at this position.
   </p>
   <p>
    Aspartic acid is strongly preferred at position 5 but can be substituted to a far lesser degree by glutamic acid, valine, glutamine, tyrosine, isoleucine, and cysteine. In all but one crystal structure, peptide position 5 is occupied by the highly preferred aspartate, as in 3BP2, establishing hydrogen bonds to S527
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    . The crystal structures of the ARC4:MCL1 complex provide an example wherein position 5 is adopted by a hydrophobic amino acid (isoleucine). A phenylalanine, F532
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , and the hydrophobic portion of R525
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    render the position-5 subpocket sufficiently hydrophobic to accommodate the less optimal nonpolar residues identified in the peptide screen (see
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <p>
    Position 7 of the TNKS-binding motif can be occupied by a wide range of amino acids. Surprisingly, proline was not allowed at this position, presenting a case for negative selection by the ARC against one particular amino acid.
   </p>
   <p>
    Position 8 tolerates all 20 amino acids; however, it presents a substantial preference for acidic residues (glutamate, aspartate) and least prefers basic residues (arginine, lysine). This is in full agreement with acidic residues in position 8 forming a salt bridge with K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    , as observed in the ARC4:MCL1 crystal structure (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <p>
    In summary, the findings of the positional scanning experiment support the binding mode we observe in the ARC4:peptide complex structures and can explain the ARC-binding behavior of most of the 16 confirmed or putative TNKS-binding motif peptides analyzed (see
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A). The experiment also demonstrates that all characterized cherubism mutations (R415P, R415Q, P418L, P418R, P418H, D419N, G420E, G420R) act by abolishing binding of the 3BP2 TNKS-binding motif to ARCs (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Lietman et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ueki et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). Our peptide library screen suggests a “superconsensus” for the 8-amino-acid TNKS-binding motif. To test whether this is the case, we generated a pair of 10-amino-acid peptides, the first one containing the TNKS-binding motif of 3BP2 and the second one an optimized TNKS-binding motif with the preferred amino acid at each position (REAGDGEE). Whereas the peptide corresponding to 3BP2 bound with an affinity of 4.9 ± 0.4 μM, the sequence-optimized peptide bound almost an order more tightly, with an affinity of 0.6 ± 0.04 μM (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). Deviations from the superconsensus at any position, individually or jointly, may allow the affinity of substrate-targeting peptides to be differentially tuned, as appears to be the case. Isoleucine at position 5 conferred weak binding (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 72.4 ± 31.6 μM) in the screen, but the TNKS-binding motif peptide of MCL1, which contains isoleucine at position 5, bound the ARC robustly (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 2.4 ± 0.2 μM). Similarly, valine at position 4 or proline at position 5 were disallowed/unfavorable in our screen, but AXIN1, another robust ARC binder (K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    = 6.1 ± 0.5 μM), contains exactly these residues at positions 4 and 5. Both of these TNKS-binding motifs contain the stabilizing glutamate residue at position 8, which can form a salt bridge interaction with K604
    <sup>
     TNKS2
    </sup>
    that likely offsets the negative impact of suboptimal amino acids at positions 4 and 5. The targeting peptides of both MCL1 and AXIN1 are indeed highly sensitive to the K604A mutation in ARC4 (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    C and
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, although introduction of the AXIN-like residues valine and proline at positions 4 and 5, respectively, into the TNKS-binding motif of 3BP2 abolished measurable binding, binding was partially restored when either glutamate or aspartate, but not glutamine or asparagine, was present at position 8 (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    An In Silico Prediction of Tankyrase Binders
   </title>
   <p>
    To identify candidate Tankyrase binders, we performed an in silico search of the human proteome, using a position-specific scoring matrix (PSSM) approach based on the affinity data obtained in the peptide library screen (
    <a>
     Yaffe et al., 2001
    </a>
    ; see
    <a>
     Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details). We calculated a Tankyrase-targeting score (TTS) of minimally −0.817 (no match) to maximally 1 (best match) for each peptide in the UniProt database (octapeptide scan with additional scoring of C-terminal hepta- and hexapeptides; see
    <a>
     http://research.lunenfeld.ca/sicheri/files/file/PSSM_raw_list.txt.zip
    </a>
    for a list of all peptides scored). The vast majority (10,420,456; 93.7%) of the 11,124,194 peptides scanned obtained a low TTS of &lt;0 (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). Eleven binders of the sixteen previously identified or predicted Tankyrase targets studied by FP (see
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A) were enriched in the region of high TTS (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). As points of reference, the prominent Tankyrase targets AXIN1 and AXIN2 displayed a low TTS of 0.385, due to suboptimal amino acids at positions 4 and 5 that are disallowed/unfavorable in the context of 3BP2 (see
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). All other previously identified and proposed Tankyrase binders that we observed to bind ARC4 in the FP assay scored above 0.68. An arbitrary cutoff at a TTS of 0.77, corresponding to a p value of ≤0.07, contained only known binders and no proven nonbinders (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <p>
    To reduce the number of unlikely targets in our scoring list, we additionally filtered the ranked score list for topology (to remove proteins annotated as extracellular, secreted, lumenal, or mitochondrial) and predicted disorder (to remove motifs that reside in structured regions) (
    <a>
     Table S4
    </a>
    ). The resulting list contains 11,698; 447; and 257 peptide motifs with TTS cutoffs of ≥0.385, ≥0.68, and ≥0.77, respectively. The apparent large number (257) and diversity of predicted Tankyrase binders at the highest stringency cutoff raise the possibility of a previously underappreciated pervasiveness of Tankyrase-dependent regulation of cellular processes.
   </p>
   <title>
    Validation of Tankyrase Binders
   </title>
   <p>
    We probed the validity of our Tankyrase substrate predictions by using FP to test whether peptides corresponding to a subset of predicted TNKS-binding motifs can bind ARC4. Out of 17 peptides tested, ranging in TTS from 0.483 to 0.967, 13 (from the 11 proteins DISC1, STRIATIN, FAT4, RAD54, BCR, MERIT40, CEP170, FASTK, TAOK2, MYO18B, and DIDO1) tested positive, whereas 4 (from the 4 proteins APC, TYK2, SMAD7, and LATS2) tested negative (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    A; TTS highlighted in
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Validation of Predicted Tankyrase Substrates, Related to Figure&amp;nbsp;6(A) FP assays ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-figs7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (778 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We next tested whether 8 of the 11 positive candidate substrate proteins (i.e., those for which we could generate or obtain epitope-tagged expression constructs) bound to Tankyrase as full-length proteins and whether the predicted TNKS-binding motifs were responsible for binding. We immunoprecipitated transiently expressed FLAG-tagged variants of Disc1, Striatin, Fat4 (lacking most of its extracellular portion), RAD54, BCR, MERIT40, FASTK, and Dido1. Coexpressed MYC-TNKS2 coimmunoprecipitated with all WT substrate candidates except for FASTK and Dido1, which expressed too weakly to allow for solid conclusions (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    and data not shown). Binding was abolished or reduced by mutation of the predicted TNKS-binding motifs (G at position 6 to R; equivalent to a cherubism mutation in 3BP2). In cases where two TNKS-binding motifs were predicted (Fat4 and MERIT40), both motifs contributed to Tankyrase binding. Using an anti-PAR antibody, we monitored the PARsylation status of these proteins to evaluate whether they were modified by TNKS2. Disc1, STRIATIN, Fat4, and BCR appeared strongly PARsylated by Tankyrase, whereas MERIT40 was weakly PARsylated and RAD54 was not detectably PARsylated (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    ). In all cases where PARsylation was observed, modification was sensitive to mutation of the TNKS-binding motifs (BCR to the least degree) and also dependent on the enzymatic integrity of the PARP domain of TNKS2.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Validation of Predicted Tankyrase Binders and SubstratesThe indicated proteins ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S009286741101350X-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (974 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To test whether binding of the Tankyrase targets was sensitive to mutation of the peptide-binding pocket in ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 and whether endogenous rather than overexpressed Tankyrase targets can bind the substrate recruitment module of Tankyrase, we performed GST pull-down experiments from a HEK293T cell lysate with a bacterially expressed TNKS2 N terminus encompassing all five ARCs (His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -GST-TNKS2(20–800), WT, or xx3xx and xxxxx mutants; see above). Although we were unable to detect endogenous expression of DISC1 and FAT4 in HEK293T cells with the antibodies at hand (data not shown), we detected endogenous expression of RAD54, MERIT40, BCR, STRIATIN, and TERF1 as a positive control (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    B). We observed ARC binding by each of the five proteins tested (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    B). Binding of RAD54 and TERF1 was abolished by ARC mutations, as predicted, whereas binding of MERIT40, BCR, and STRIATIN was not greatly affected. These results suggest that Tankyrase substrates may be differentially sensitive to the specific L-to-W ARC mutation employed in this analysis. Further analysis bore this conclusion out (
    <a>
     Figure S7
    </a>
    C) and highlighted a requirement for compound binding pocket mutations to each functional ARC to ensure universal abrogation of substrate recruitment to Tankyrases.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    In this study, we uncover the structural basis for substrate recognition by Tankyrase, mediated by its N-terminal ankyrin repeats. This provides a prototypic example for substrate recruitment by a PARP and also for the means by which an ankyrin repeat protein can recognize short, extended peptides rather than a globular protein domain, the more typical function described so far for ankyrin repeat proteins (reviewed in
    <a>
     Li et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). Given the sequence similarity of both human Tankyrases, our findings likely apply to substrate recognition by both TNKS and TNKS2.
   </p>
   <p>
    We demonstrate that the repeating unit of the Tankyrase N terminus, the ARC, consists of five stacked ankyrin repeats forming a modular unit and occurs five times within the Tankyrase N terminus. This clarifies previous uncertainties over the repetitive character of the Tankyrase N terminus.
   </p>
   <p>
    The crystal structure of ARC4 bound to the 3BP2 peptide fully explains how mutations in this sequence lead to a loss of 3BP2 binding that gives rise to cherubism (
    <a>
     Lietman et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Ueki et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). The ARC4-3BP2 binding mechanism appears universal to ARCs 1, 2, 4, and 5 and is employed for numerous other Tankyrase substrates, as demonstrated by our crystal structures of the TNKS-binding motif peptides of TERF1, MCL1, LNPEP, NUMA1, and FNBP1 bound to ARC4.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our peptide-binding studies reveal the sequence determinants for low-micromolar-affinity recognition of TNKS-binding motif peptides by Tankyrase: most importantly, positions 1 and 6 of a functional motif require arginine and glycine, respectively, whereas the amino acid at position 4 needs to be small and hydrophobic. The possibilities for position 5 are restricted: aspartate is strongly preferred, but glutamic acid, valine, glutamine, tyrosine, isoleucine, and cysteine are tolerated as well. Conversely, the side chains at positions 2 and 3 are solvent exposed and can thus adopt a wide range of identities. For such peptides to be recognized by Tankyrase, the amino acid at position 7 must not be proline. Glutamate or aspartate at position 8 positively contribute to Tankyrase binding. Interestingly, most predicted TNKS-binding motifs deviate from the optimal “superconsensus,” suggesting that their affinity may be detuned to avoid potentially deleterious effects from too high affinity. The presence of multiple TNKS-binding motifs in a single substrate, as demonstrated for MERIT40 and Fat4, provides a means for increasing affinity beyond levels afforded by a single motif.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our consensus-based in silico analysis predicts that a wide range, possibly hundreds, of proteins may be targeted by Tankyrase. Our analysis correctly predicts all known and proposed human Tankyrase binders in the UniProt database, including the recently identified Tankyrase substrates BLZF1 (UniProt ID GO45_HUMAN) and CASC3 (UniProt ID CASC3_HUMAN) (
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2011
    </a>
    ). We identified and validated six predicted Tankyrase binders, namely the neurogenesis regulator Disc1, the scaffold protein and PP2A phosphatase regulatory subunit Striatin, the atypical cadherin Fat4 involved in Hippo signaling and planar cell polarity, the DNA recombination protein RAD54, the GTPase-activating protein and Abl kinase fusion partner BCR, and the DNA repair protein MERIT40. Recruitment by Tankyrase did not strictly correlate with Tankyrase-mediated PARsylation, indicating that although Tankyrase binding via the TNKS-binding motif is required for modification, additional requirements for PARsylation are likely to exist.
   </p>
   <p>
    Out of five ARCs present in TNKS2, only ARC3, whose surfaces are relatively poorly conserved across species (see
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    B), fails to bind TNKS-binding motif peptides. This agrees with an earlier study in which isolated ARC3, but not other ARCs, of TNKS failed to bind full-length TERF1, TNKS1BP1, LNPEP, and an uncharacterized protein termed TNK1BP2 (
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). A function for ARC3 has yet to be determined. ARC3 may play a structural role in the context of the full-length enzyme or engage as-yet-unidentified binding partners in a way that is difficult to predict from sequence conservation.
   </p>
   <p>
    Future work is required to establish the contribution of individual ARCs to substrate PARsylation. In TNKS, ARC5 appears essential for TERF1 PARsylation, release of TERF1 from telomeres, and telomere elongation (
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), suggesting that at the level of PARP activity, ARCs may not be functionally interchangeable. ARC5, however, was not sufficient for TNKS to induce telomere elongation (
    <a>
     Seimiya et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), suggesting that the collaborative action of multiple ARCs is needed.
   </p>
   <p>
    Much attention is currently devoted to the development of PARP inhibitors, which are of interest as potential anticancer therapeutics (
    <a>
     Lord and Ashworth, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Rouleau et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Although TNKS and TNKS2, through their specific interactions with many substrates, are involved in a wide variety of biological processes, inhibition of Tankyrase may hold promise for treating BRCA1/2-deficient and Wnt-dependent cancers (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2009
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lord and Ashworth, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     McCabe et al., 2009
    </a>
    ) and a universal anticancer activity through the stabilization of TERF1 and a concomitant inhibition of telomerase function (
    <a>
     Ancelin et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Chong et al., 1995
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sbodio and Chi, 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     van Steensel and de Lange, 1997
    </a>
    ). All PARP inhibitors characterized to date compete with NAD
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    . The universality of NAD
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    as an enzymatic cofactor and the likely emergence of drug resistance are two major challenges in pharmaceutical PARP inhibition (
    <a>
     Edwards et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lord and Ashworth, 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rouleau et al., 2010
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Sakai et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Our advancing understanding of substrate recognition by Tankyrases opens avenues for the development of Tankyrase substrate antagonists, which would address questions of specificity and possibly resistance. Given our evidence for functional redundancy of different ARCs, such antagonists may need to recognize all active ARCs.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <p>
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    are available in the Supplemental Information online. Lists of plasmids and peptides used in this study are given in
    <a>
     Table S5. Plasmids Used in This Study, Related to Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Table S6. Peptides Used in This Study, Related to Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Protein Expression, Crystallization, and Structure Determination
   </title>
   <p>
    Purified human TNKS2 ARC constructs included residues 20–178 (ARC1), 173–487 (ARC2-3), 488–649 (ARC4) or 484–655 for apo-ARC4 structure, 641–800 (ARC5), and 20–800 (ARC1-5). Equivalent ARC mutations (denoted by “x”) were L92W (ARC1), L245W (ARC2), L401W (ARC3), L560W (ARC4), and L713W (ARC5). All crystals were grown at 20°C in hanging drops by mixing one volume of protein solution with one volume of precipitant solution. See
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details on expression plasmids, protein expression and purification, peptides, protein concentrations, precipitant solutions, cryoprotectants, and data collection and structure determination methodologies.
   </p>
   <title>
    FP Binding Assays
   </title>
   <p>
    Binding reactions were performed with 25 nM fluorophore-conjugated peptide and the indicated protein concentrations in 50 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.5), 100 mM NaCl, 2 mM TCEP, 80 μg/ml BSA. For
    <a>
     Figures 1
    </a>
    B,
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    A, and
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    , the FP buffer contained 300 mM NaCl and 10% glycerol. Nonlinear regression with FP values was performed in GraphPad Prism 5 using a one-site total binding model.
   </p>
   <title>
    GST Pull-Down Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    For
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    D, His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -GST-TNKS2(20–800) and mutants were immobilized on glutathione Sepharose and incubated with 48 μg purified murine His
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    -3BP2 each in 50 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.5), 300 mM NaCl, 2 mM DTT, 0.5 mM PMSF (total volume: 250 μl) for 90 min at 4°C. The resin was washed six times with binding buffer (without PMSF). Input and pull-down samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE, Coomassie staining (input), or western blotting with a FLAG-tagged anti-3BP2 F
    <sub>
     ab
    </sub>
    (1 ng/ml) and anti-FLAG M2-HRP.
   </p>
   <title>
    Coimmunoprecipitation
   </title>
   <p>
    For
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    E, HEK293T cells were transfected with expression plasmids for the indicated MYC-TNKS2 and FLAG-3BP2 derivatives or empty vector. After 24 hr, cells were lysed in 25 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 100 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 1 mM Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 5 mM EDTA, and protease inhibitors. Immunoprecipitation with soluble, precleared lysates was performed with anti-FLAG M2-agarose for 1 hr at 4°C. Immunoprecipitates were washed three times with lysis buffer.
   </p>
   <p>
    For
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    , HEK293T cells were transfected with expression plasmids for MYC-TNKS2 (wild-type or PARP-dead E1138A), FLAG-substrate candidates (wild-type or G6R), or empty vector. Cells were cotransfected with dominant-negative PARG to limit PAR hydrolysis. After 20–24 hr, cells were lysed in 50 mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% SDS, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 1% Triton X-100, 5 mM EDTA (pH 8.0), 2 μM ADP-HPD (PARG inhibitor), 5 mM DTT, and protease inhibitors. FLAG-substrate candidates were immunoprecipitated using anti-FLAG M2-agarose for 90 min at 4°C. Immuoprecipitates were washed five times with lysis buffer (without protease inhibitors and ADP-HPD). Lysates and immunoprecipitates were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and western blotting with anti-MYC 9E10, anti-FLAG M2, and polyclonal anti-PAR antibodies.
   </p>
   <title>
    In Silico Tankyrase Substrate Prediction
   </title>
   <p>
    An 8 × 20 PSSM (shown in
    <a>
     Table S7
    </a>
    ) was generated using the ARC4 affinities for the peptides in the positional scanning peptide library (
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    ). To score heptapeptides or hexapeptides at the extreme C terminus of proteins, the scoring matrix was truncated after positions 7 or 6. All possible octapeptides, one heptapeptide, and one hexapeptide were scored according to this matrix for each human protein in the UniProt database (release v1.37). A TTS was calculated using the formula
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    See
    <a>
     Extended Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for additional details and filtering procedures.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    Structure coordinates and structure factors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank under ID codes 3TWQ (apo-ARC4), 3TWR (ARC4:3BP2), 3TWS (ARC4:TERF1 chimera), 3TWT (ARC4:MCL1 chimera), 3TWU (ARC4:MCL1), 3TWV (ARC4:NUMA1 chimera), 3TWW (ARC4:LNPEP chimera), and 3TWX (ARC4:FNBP1 chimera).
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S1. Data Collection and Refinement Statistics, Related to Figures 2 and 4.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Parameters in parentheses refer to the highest resolution shell. Ramachandran data were obtained using PROCHECK (Laskowski et al., 1993) and B factors calculated using Baverage (Collaborative Computational Project Number 4, 1994).
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (38 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S2. Substrate Recognition Properties of the Different ARCs of TNKS2, Related to Figures 4 and S4.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Dissociation constants (K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       in μM with standard error of the fit) for the interaction of the indicated ARC constructs with TNKS-binding motif peptides from the indicated proteins (see Figure 4A and Table S6 for peptide sequences), as measured by an FP-based titration binding assay. Data are from one experiment done in technical duplicate, except the data for TERF1 (ARC5), LNPEP (ARC2
       <sub>
        mut
       </sub>
       -3), CACNA1S (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), EBNA1 (1) (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), EBNA1 (2) (ARC2-3), and GRB14 (ARCs 1, 2-3, 4, 5), which include an additional experiment done in technical duplicate with a maximum ARC concentration of 150 μM. Data were analyzed by nonlinear regression using a one-site total binding model. Provided quality criteria were passed (sigmoidal binding curve, standard error [K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       ] ≤ 60%); K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       are represented in Figure S4A; n.q., not quantifiable (no sigmoidal binding curve or no derivable K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       ); values shown in red were not reliable due to a high standard error of the fit and were therefore not represented in Figure S4A. See Figure S5 for all FP graphs.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (60 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S3. FP-Based Positional Scanning of the 3BP2 TNKS-Binding Motif Peptide to Define a Rule-Based Consensus for TNKS-Binding Motifs, Related to Figure 5.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Dissociation constants (K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       in μM with standard error of the fit) for the ARC4 interaction with peptides of the positional scanning library in an FP-based titration binding assay. Data are from one experiment performed in technical duplicate. Data were analyzed by nonlinear regression using a one-site total binding model. Provided quality criteria were passed (sigmoidal binding curve, standard error [K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       ] ≤ 60%); K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       are represented in Figure 5A; n.q., not quantifiable (no sigmoidal binding curve or no derivable K
       <sub>
        D
       </sub>
       ); values shown in red were not reliable due to a high standard error of the fit and were therefore not represented in Figure 5A. See Figure S6A for all FP graphs.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (54 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S4. Ranked and Filtered Scoring List for In Silico Prediction of Tankyrase Targets, Related to Figure 5.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Scoring list of peptides, filtered for topology as described in the Extended Experimental Procedures and ranked according to their TTS (descending order). Sheet 1: proteins with a TTS of at least 0.385. Although this small cutoff likely includes a large number of non-Tankyrase targets, this cutoff was chosen to include the TNKS-binding motifs of AXIN1 and AXIN2, which obtained low scores in our analysis. Sheet 2: list from sheet 1 with motifs that obtained an IUPred disorder score ≥0.45. Column 1, TTS rank; column 2, UniProt ID; column 3, position of first peptide residue in protein sequence; column 4, peptide sequence (amino acids at positions 1, 4, 5, and 6 shown in red for orientation); column 5, TTS with p value; column 6, IUPred disorder score (from 0, no disorder, to 1, maximum disorder); column 7, relative conservation score where available (from 1, no relative conservation, to 0, maximum relative conservation); column 8, number of motifs (with TTS ≥ 0.385 and IUPred disorder score ≥ 0.45) in the same protein; column 9, description of protein; column 10, subcellular localization (from UniProt FT); column 11, subcellular localization (from UniProt subcellular location); column 12, Gene Ontology (GO) annotation for cellular component. See the Extended Experimental Procedures for details.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with XLS files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file ( K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S5. Plasmids Used in This Study, Related to Experimental Procedures.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Details on point mutants derived from the listed plasmids are given in the text.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (67 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S6. Peptides Used in This Study, Related to Experimental Procedures.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Alternative names for Tankyrase targets are given where commonly used. 5(6)-CF, 5(6)-carboxyfluorescein.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (29 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Table S7. PSSM for Calculation of the TTS, Related to Figure 5.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       The individual PSSM scores for the 20 amino acids across all 8 positions of the TNKS-binding motif were calculated as described in the text.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (50 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Article plus Supplemental Information.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (4570 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Amé et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.C. Amé, C. Spenlehauer, G. de Murcia
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The PARP superfamily
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioessays, 26 (2004), pp. 882–893
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ancelin et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Ancelin, M. Brunori, S. Bauwens, C.E. Koering, C. Brun, M. Ricoul, J.P. Pommier, L. Sabatier, E. Gilson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeting assay to study the cis functions of human telomeric proteins: evidence for inhibition of telomerase by TRF1 and for activation of telomere degradation by TRF2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 22 (2002), pp. 3474–3487
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bae et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Bae, J.R. Donigian, A.J. Hsueh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase 1 interacts with Mcl-1 proteins and inhibits their regulation of apoptosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 5195–5204
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chang et al., 2005a
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Chang, M. Coughlin, T.J. Mitchison
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase-1 polymerization of poly(ADP-ribose) is required for spindle structure and function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 7 (2005), pp. 1133–1139
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chang et al., 2005b
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Chang, J.N. Dynek, S. Smith
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         NuMA is a major acceptor of poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation by tankyrase 1 in mitosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 391 (2005), pp. 177–184
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chang et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Chang, J.N. Dynek, S. Smith
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TRF1 is degraded by ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis after release from telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 17 (2003), pp. 1328–1333
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chi and Lodish, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.W. Chi, H.F. Lodish
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase is a golgi-associated mitogen-activated protein kinase substrate that interacts with IRAP in GLUT4 vesicles
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 275 (2000), pp. 38437–38444
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chong et al., 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Chong, B. van Steensel, D. Broccoli, H. Erdjument-Bromage, J. Hanish, P. Tempst, T. de Lange
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A human telomeric protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 270 (1995), pp. 1663–1667
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cook et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.D. Cook, J.N. Dynek, W. Chang, G. Shostak, S. Smith
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role for the related poly(ADP-Ribose) polymerases tankyrase 1 and 2 at human telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 22 (2002), pp. 332–342
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Deng et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Deng, L. Lezina, C.J. Chen, S. Shtivelband, W. So, P.M. Lieberman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Telomeric proteins regulate episomal maintenance of Epstein-Barr virus origin of plasmid replication
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 9 (2002), pp. 493–503
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Deng et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Deng, C. Atanasiu, K. Zhao, R. Marmorstein, J.I. Sbodio, N.W. Chi, P.M. Lieberman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inhibition of Epstein-Barr virus OriP function by tankyrase, a telomere-associated poly-ADP ribose polymerase that binds and modifies EBNA1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Virol., 79 (2005), pp. 4640–4650
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Edwards et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.L. Edwards, R. Brough, C.J. Lord, R. Natrajan, R. Vatcheva, D.A. Levine, J. Boyd, J.S. Reis-Filho, A. Ashworth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Resistance to therapy caused by intragenic deletion in BRCA2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 451 (2008), pp. 1111–1115
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Forrer et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Forrer, M.T. Stumpp, H.K. Binz, A. Plückthun
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel strategy to design binding molecules harnessing the modular nature of repeat proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 539 (2003), pp. 2–6
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fuchs et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        U. Fuchs, G.F. Rehkamp, R. Slany, M. Follo, A. Borkhardt
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The formin-binding protein 17, FBP17, binds via a TNKS binding motif to tankyrase, a protein involved in telomere maintenance
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 554 (2003), pp. 10–16
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hassa and Hottiger, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.O. Hassa, M.O. Hottiger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The diverse biological roles of mammalian PARPS, a small but powerful family of poly-ADP-ribose polymerases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Front. Biosci., 13 (2008), pp. 3046–3082
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hottiger et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.O. Hottiger, P.O. Hassa, B. Lüscher, H. Schüler, F. Koch-Nolte
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Toward a unified nomenclature for mammalian ADP-ribosyltransferases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biochem. Sci., 35 (2010), pp. 208–219
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hsiao and Smith, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.J. Hsiao, S. Smith
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase function at telomeres, spindle poles, and beyond
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochimie, 90 (2008), pp. 83–92
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huang et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.M. Huang, Y.M. Mishina, S. Liu, A. Cheung, F. Stegmeier, G.A. Michaud, O. Charlat, E. Wiellette, Y. Zhang, S. Wiessner,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase inhibition stabilizes axin and antagonizes Wnt signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 461 (2009), pp. 614–620
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kaminker et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.G. Kaminker, S.H. Kim, R.D. Taylor, Y. Zebarjadian, W.D. Funk, G.B. Morin, P. Yaswen, J. Campisi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TANK2, a new TRF1-associated poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase, causes rapid induction of cell death upon overexpression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 35891–35899
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kleine et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Kleine, E. Poreba, K. Lesniewicz, P.O. Hassa, M.O. Hottiger, D.W. Litchfield, B.H. Shilton, B. Lüscher
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Substrate-assisted catalysis by PARP10 limits its activity to mono-ADP-ribosylation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 32 (2008), pp. 57–69
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Levaot et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Levaot, O. Voytyuk, I. Dimitriou, F. Sircoulomb, A. Chandrakumar, M. Deckert, P.M. Krzyzanowski, A. Scotter, S. Gu, S. Janmohamed,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Loss of Tankyrase-mediated destruction of 3BP2 is the underlying pathogenic mechanism of cherubism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 147 (2011), pp. 1324–1339 this issue
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Li et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Li, A. Mahajan, M.D. Tsai
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ankyrin repeat: a unique motif mediating protein-protein interactions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 45 (2006), pp. 15168–15178
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lietman et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.A. Lietman, N. Kalinchinko, X. Deng, R. Kohanski, M.A. Levine
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of a novel mutation of SH3BP2 in cherubism and demonstration that SH3BP2 mutations lead to increased NFAT activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hum. Mutat., 27 (2006), pp. 717–718
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lord and Ashworth, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.J. Lord, A. Ashworth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeted therapy for cancer using PARP inhibitors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Pharmacol., 8 (2008), pp. 363–369
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lyons et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.J. Lyons, R. Deane, D.K. Lynch, Z.S. Ye, G.M. Sanderson, H.J. Eyre, G.R. Sutherland, R.J. Daly
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of a novel human tankyrase through its interaction with the adaptor protein Grb14
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 17172–17180
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McCabe et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. McCabe, M.A. Cerone, T. Ohishi, H. Seimiya, C.J. Lord, A. Ashworth
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeting Tankyrase 1 as a therapeutic strategy for BRCA-associated cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 28 (2009), pp. 1465–1470
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rouleau et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Rouleau, A. Patel, M.J. Hendzel, S.H. Kaufmann, G.G. Poirier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         PARP inhibition: PARP1 and beyond
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Cancer, 10 (2010), pp. 293–301
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sakai et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Sakai, E.M. Swisher, B.Y. Karlan, M.K. Agarwal, J. Higgins, C. Friedman, E. Villegas, C. Jacquemont, D.J. Farrugia, F.J. Couch,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Secondary mutations as a mechanism of cisplatin resistance in BRCA2-mutated cancers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 451 (2008), pp. 1116–1120
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sbodio and Chi, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.I. Sbodio, N.W. Chi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of a tankyrase-binding motif shared by IRAP, TAB182, and human TRF1 but not mouse TRF1. NuMA contains this RXXPDG motif and is a novel tankyrase partner
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 31887–31892
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sbodio et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.I. Sbodio, H.F. Lodish, N.W. Chi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase-2 oligomerizes with tankyrase-1 and binds to both TRF1 (telomere-repeat-binding factor 1) and IRAP (insulin-responsive aminopeptidase)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 361 (2002), pp. 451–459
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Seimiya and Smith, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Seimiya, S. Smith
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The telomeric poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase, tankyrase 1, contains multiple binding sites for telomeric repeat binding factor 1 (TRF1) and a novel acceptor, 182-kDa tankyrase-binding protein (TAB182)
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 14116–14126
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Seimiya et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Seimiya, Y. Muramatsu, S. Smith, T. Tsuruo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional subdomain in the ankyrin domain of tankyrase 1 required for poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation of TRF1 and telomere elongation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 24 (2004), pp. 1944–1955
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Smith et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Smith, I. Giriat, A. Schmitt, T. de Lange
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tankyrase, a poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase at human telomeres
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 282 (1998), pp. 1484–1487
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ueki et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Ueki, V. Tiziani, C. Santanna, N. Fukai, C. Maulik, J. Garfinkle, C. Ninomiya, C. doAmaral, H. Peters, M. Habal,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mutations in the gene encoding c-Abl-binding protein SH3BP2 cause cherubism
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Genet., 28 (2001), pp. 125–126
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         van Steensel and de Lange, 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. van Steensel, T. de Lange
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Control of telomere length by the human telomeric protein TRF1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 385 (1997), pp. 740–743
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yaffe et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.B. Yaffe, G.G. Leparc, J. Lai, T. Obata, S. Volinia, L.C. Cantley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A motif-based profile scanning approach for genome-wide prediction of signaling pathways
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Biotechnol., 19 (2001), pp. 348–353
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Zhang, S. Liu, C. Mickanin, Y. Feng, O. Charlat, G.A. Michaud, M. Schirle, X. Shi, M. Hild, A. Bauer,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         RNF146 is a poly(ADP-ribose)-directed E3 ligase that regulates axin degradation and Wnt signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 13 (2011), pp. 623–629
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <title>
      Supplemental References
     </title>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Adams et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Adams, P.D., Afonine, P.V., Bunkóczi, G., Chen, V.B., Davis, I.W., Echols, N., Headd, J.J., Hung, L.W., Kapral, G.J., Grosse-Kunstleve, R.W., et al. (2010). PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         66
        </em>
        , 213–221.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Arnold et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Arnold, K., Bordoli, L., Kopp, J., and Schwede, T. (2006). The SWISS-MODEL workspace: a web-based environment for protein structure homology modelling. Bioinformatics
        <em>
         22
        </em>
        , 195–201.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ashburner et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Ashburner, M., Ball, C.A., Blake, J.A., Botstein, D., Butler, H., Cherry, J.M., Davis, A.P., Dolinski, K., Dwight, S.S., Eppig, J.T., et al; The Gene Ontology Consortium. (2000). Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. Nat. Genet.
        <em>
         25
        </em>
        , 25–29.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Batchelor et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Batchelor, A.H., Piper, D.E., de la Brousse, F.C., McKnight, S.L., and Wolberger, C. (1998). The structure of GABPalpha/beta: an ETS domain- ankyrin repeat heterodimer bound to DNA. Science
        <em>
         279
        </em>
        , 1037–1041.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Binz et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Binz, H.K., Stumpp, M.T., Forrer, P., Amstutz, P., and Plückthun, A. (2003). Designing repeat proteins: well-expressed, soluble and stable proteins from combinatorial libraries of consensus ankyrin repeat proteins. J. Mol. Biol.
        <em>
         332
        </em>
        , 489–503.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Collaborative Computational Project Number 4, 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Collaborative Computational Project Number 4 (1994). The CCP4 suite: programs for protein crystallography. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         50
        </em>
        , 760–763.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Colwill et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Colwill, K., Wells, C.D., Elder, K., Goudreault, M., Hersi, K., Kulkarni, S., Hardy, W.R., Pawson, T., and Morin, G.B. (2006). Modification of the Creator recombination system for proteomics applications—improved expression by addition of splice sites. BMC Biotechnol.
        <em>
         6
        </em>
        , 13.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Davey et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Davey, N.E., Shields, D.C., and Edwards, R.J. (2009). Masking residues using context-specific evolutionary conservation significantly improves short linear motif discovery. Bioinformatics
        <em>
         25
        </em>
        , 443–450.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Dosztányi et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Dosztányi, Z., Csizmok, V., Tompa, P., and Simon, I. (2005). IUPred: web server for the prediction of intrinsically unstructured regions of proteins based on estimated energy content. Bioinformatics
        <em>
         21
        </em>
        , 3433–3434.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Emsley et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Emsley, P., Lohkamp, B., Scott, W.G., and Cowtan, K. (2010). Features and development of Coot. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         66
        </em>
        , 486–501.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goudreault et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Goudreault, M., D'Ambrosio, L.M., Kean, M.J., Mullin, M.J., Larsen, B.G., Sanchez, A., Chaudhry, S., Chen, G.I., Sicheri, F., Nesvizhskii, A.I., et al. (2009). A PP2A phosphatase high density interaction network identifies a novel striatin-interacting phosphatase and kinase complex linked to the cerebral cavernous malformation 3 (CCM3) protein. Mol. Cell. Proteomics
        <em>
         8
        </em>
        , 157–171.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Haince et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Haince, J.F., Ouellet, M.E., McDonald, D., Hendzel, M.J., and Poirier, G.G. (2006). Dynamic relocation of poly(ADP-ribose) glycohydrolase isoforms during radiation-induced DNA damage. Biochim. Biophys. Acta
        <em>
         1763
        </em>
        , 226–237.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kleywegt, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Kleywegt, G.J. (2007). Crystallographic refinement of ligand complexes. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         63
        </em>
        , 94–100.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Larkin et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Larkin, M.A., Blackshields, G., Brown, N.P., Chenna, R., McGettigan, P.A., McWilliam, H., Valentin, F., Wallace, I.M., Wilm, A., Lopez, R., et al. (2007). Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0. Bioinformatics
        <em>
         23
        </em>
        , 2947–2948.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Laskowski et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Laskowski, R.A., MacArthur, M.W., Moss, D.S., and Thornton, J.M. (1993). PROCHECK - a program to check the stereochemical quality of protein structures. J. Appl. Cryst.
        <em>
         26
        </em>
        , 283–291.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lavinder et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Lavinder, J.J., Hari, S.B., Sullivan, B.J., and Magliery, T.J. (2009). High-throughput thermal scanning: a general, rapid dye-binding thermal shift screen for protein engineering. J. Am. Chem. Soc.
        <em>
         131
        </em>
        , 3794–3795.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lovell et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Lovell, S.C., Davis, I.W., Arendall, W.B., 3rd, de Bakker, P.I., Word, J.M., Prisant, M.G., Richardson, J.S., and Richardson, D.C. (2003). Structure validation by Calpha geometry: phi,psi and Cbeta deviation. Proteins
        <em>
         50
        </em>
        , 437–450.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         McCoy et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        McCoy, A.J., Grosse-Kunstleve, R.W., Adams, P.D., Winn, M.D., Storoni, L.C., and Read, R.J. (2007). Phaser crystallographic software. J. Appl. Cryst.
        <em>
         40
        </em>
        , 658–674.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Murshudov et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Murshudov, G.N., Vagin, A.A., and Dodson, E.J. (1997). Refinement of macromolecular structures by the maximum-likelihood method. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         53
        </em>
        , 240–255.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Olhovsky et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Olhovsky, M., Williton, K., Dai, A.Y., Pasculescu, A., Lee, J.P., Goudreault, M., Wells, C.D., Park, J.G., Gingras, A.C., Linding, R., et al. (2011). OpenFreezer: a reagent information management software system. Nat. Methods
        <em>
         8
        </em>
        , 612–613.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Otwinowski and Minor, 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Otwinowski, Z., and Minor, W. (1997). Processing of X-ray Diffraction Data Collected in Oscillation Mode. Methods Enzymol.
        <em>
         276
        </em>
        , 307–326.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pantoliano et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Pantoliano, M.W., Petrella, E.C., Kwasnoski, J.D., Lobanov, V.S., Myslik, J., Graf, E., Carver, T., Asel, E., Springer, B.A., Lane, P., and Salemme, F.R. (2001). High-density miniaturized thermal shift assays as a general strategy for drug discovery. J. Biomol. Screen.
        <em>
         6
        </em>
        , 429–440.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Patel et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Patel, C.N., Koh, D.W., Jacobson, M.K., and Oliveira, M.A. (2005). Identification of three critical acidic residues of poly(ADP-ribose) glycohydrolase involved in catalysis: determining the PARG catalytic domain. Biochem. J.
        <em>
         388
        </em>
        , 493–500.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pettersen et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Pettersen, E.F., Goddard, T.D., Huang, C.C., Couch, G.S., Greenblatt, D.M., Meng, E.C., and Ferrin, T.E. (2004). UCSF Chimera—a visualization system for exploratory research and analysis. J. Comput. Chem.
        <em>
         25
        </em>
        , 1605–1612.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Potterton et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Potterton, E., Briggs, P., Turkenburg, M., and Dodson, E. (2003). A graphical user interface to the CCP4 program suite. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         59
        </em>
        , 1131–1137.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref62'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schüttelkopf and van Aalten, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Schüttelkopf, A.W., and van Aalten, D.M. (2004). PRODRG: a tool for high-throughput crystallography of protein-ligand complexes. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.
        <em>
         60
        </em>
        , 1355–1363.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref63'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Scotter et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Scotter, A.J., Kuntz, D.A., Saul, M., Graham, L.A., Davies, P.L., and Rose, D.R. (2006). Expression and purification of sea raven type II antifreeze protein from Drosophila melanogaster S2 cells. Protein Expr. Purif.
        <em>
         47
        </em>
        , 374–383.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref64'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shao et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Shao, G., Patterson-Fortin, J., Messick, T.E., Feng, D., Shanbhag, N., Wang, Y., and Greenberg, R.A. (2009). MERIT40 controls BRCA1-Rap80 complex integrity and recruitment to DNA double-strand breaks. Genes Dev.
        <em>
         23
        </em>
        , 740–754.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref65'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         UniProt Consortium, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        UniProt Consortium. (2010). The Universal Protein Resource (UniProt) in 2010. Nucleic Acids Res.
        <em>
         38
        </em>
        (
        <em>
         Database issue
        </em>
        ), D142–D148.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref66'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Thomä et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Thomä, N.H., Czyzewski, B.K., Alexeev, A.A., Mazin, A.V., Kowalczykowski, S.C., and Pavletich, N.P. (2005). Structure of the SWI2/SNF2 chromatin-remodeling domain of eukaryotic Rad54. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.
        <em>
         12
        </em>
        , 350–356.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref67'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Waterhouse et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Waterhouse, A.M., Procter, J.B., Martin, D.M., Clamp, M., and Barton, G.J. (2009). Jalview Version 2—a multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbench. Bioinformatics
        <em>
         25
        </em>
        , 1189–1191.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref68'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yaffe et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Yaffe, M.B., Leparc, G.G., Lai, J., Obata, T., Volinia, S., and Cantley, L.C. (2001). A motif-based profile scanning approach for genome-wide prediction of signaling pathways. Nat. Biotechnol.
        <em>
         19
        </em>
        , 348–353.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref69'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Zhao, X., Ghaffari, S., Lodish, H., Malashkevich, V.N., and Kim, P.S. (2002). Structure of the Bcr-Abl oncoprotein oligomerization domain. Nat. Struct. Biol.
        <em>
         9
        </em>
        , 117–120.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref70'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2011 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>