<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0960-9822(02)01184-3
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    14-3-3 Regulates Actin Dynamics by Stabilizing Phosphorylated Cofilin
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results and Discussion
   </title>
   <title>
    Purification of a Ser3 Phosphocofilin Binding Protein
   </title>
   <p>
    Bovine brain cytosol was fractionated by DEAE anion exchange chromatography, and column fractions were tested for cofilin binding proteins by using an overlay assay with in vitro Ser3-phosphorylated
    <em>
     Xenopus
    </em>
    cofilin (XAC-P).
    <em>
     Xenopus
    </em>
    and human cofilin are highly homologous, and their actin binding and -depolymerizing activities are equally inhibited by LIMK-mediated Ser3 phosphorylation
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [1]
    </xref>
    . We observed that a 31 kDa protein (p31) bound to Ser3-phosphorylated cofilin but not to unphosphorylated cofilin (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1A
    </xref>
    ). A protein of 49 kDa bound cofilin regardless of its phosphorylation state. In order to exclude the possibility that the p31/XAC-P interaction resulted from cofilin phosphorylation on other sites in addition to Ser3 (catalyzed by unidentified kinases during the in vitro phosphorylation reaction), overlay assays were performed with the LIMK phosphorylation site mutant XAC-S3A, which was subjected to a typical in vitro kinase reaction. As shown in the bottom panel of
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1A
    </xref>
    , p31 did not detectably associate with XAC-S3A. These results suggest that p31 represents a protein that specifically binds to Ser3-phosphorylated
    <em>
     Xenopus
    </em>
    cofilin.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Purification and Identification of a Ser3 Phosphocofilin Binding Protein(A&amp;ndash;C) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (516 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Identification of p31 as 14-3-3ζ by Mass Spectrometry
   </title>
   <p>
    Employing the XAC-P overlay assay to detect p31, the protein was purified to near homogeneity
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figures 1B–1D)
    </xref>
    and was sequenced by MS/MS tandem mass spectrometry. The peptide sequences obtained corresponded exclusively to members of the 14-3-3 family of proteins. Notably, 14-3-3ζ was by far the most abundant 14-3-3 protein present in the fraction, and the generated peptides encompassed about 70% of the sequence of 14-3-3ζ. The 14-3-3 proteins are a family of ubiquitously expressed and evolutionarily conserved molecules, including seven highly homologous mammalian isoforms (β, ϵ, γ, η, σ, τ, and ζ) that primarily exist as homo- or heterodimers. 14-3-3 proteins play key regulatory roles in signal transduction, cell cycle control, and cell survival by binding to a multitude of functionally diverse ligands and affecting their enzymatic activities, directing their subcellular localization, or altering their association with other cellular components
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     10
    </xref>
    . To our knowledge, a role for 14-3-3 proteins in cytoskeletal regulation has not been reported.
   </p>
   <title>
    14-3-3ζ and Ser3 Phosphocofilin Associate In Vitro and In Vivo
   </title>
   <p>
    The interaction between 14-3-3 and cofilin was confirmed in pulldown binding experiments with GST-14-3-3ζ. Cos-1 cells were either mock transfected or transfected with the constitutively active LIMK1 fragment Kd3
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    in order to specifically increase the endogenous pool of Ser3 phosphocofilin. In lysates of control cells, only a small amount of cofilin was able to bind GST-14-3-3ζ. In contrast, the cofilin/14-3-3ζ interaction was strongly increased by expression of Kd3
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figure 1E)
    </xref>
    . Similar results were obtained with GST-14-3-3τ (not shown). Immunoblotting of precipitated proteins with α-phosphocofilin antibodies clearly confirmed that 14-3-3ζ specifically pulled down the phosphorylated cofilin in both control and Kd3-expressing cells. Furthermore, pretreatment of cell lysates with the serine/threonine phosphatases PP1 and PP2A (which dephosphorylate cofilin in vitro;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [11]
    </xref>
    and data not shown) completely abolished the cofilin/14-3-3ζ interaction.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1F
    </xref>
    shows that endogenous cofilin coimmunoprecipitated with HA-14-3-3ζ, which is indicative of stable complex formation in cells. Cofilin also associated with HA-14-3-3ϵ, albeit to a lesser extent, suggesting that the interaction is not restricted to a single 14-3-3 isoform. Interestingly, 14-3-3 was able to immunoprecipitate cofilin even in the absence of increased LIMK signaling. Results discussed below show that the expression of 14-3-3ζ itself can lead to an elevation of the basal phosphocofilin pool, which typically constitutes up to 20%–50% of the total cofilin in nontransformed cells
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [12]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The affinity of purified [=P23528 protein] Ser3 phosphocofilin for [=P63104 protein] 14-3-3ζ was determined by a solid-phase binding assay (see Figure S1). Binding was best fit to a one binding site model, with a Kd of [=445553 kd] 0.6–1 × 10
    <sup>
     −7
    </sup>
    M, suggesting equivalent and independent function of the two ligand binding sites on the 14-3-3 dimer. In summary, the in vitro and in vivo association of phosphocofilin and 14-3-3ζ is consistent with the phosphorylation-dependent interaction observed in overlay assays.
   </p>
   <title>
    Mapping of the 14-3-3ζ Binding Site on Human Cofilin
   </title>
   <p>
    Numerous 14-3-3 binding proteins associate with 14-3-3 through a phosphorylated serine contained within a prototypical 14-3-3-recognition motif, RSxpSxP (where x represents any amino acid and pS stands for phosphorylated serine)
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [7]
    </xref>
    . Human cofilin contains one putative 14-3-3 recognition sequence (RKS
    <sup>
     23
    </sup>
    S
    <sup>
     24
    </sup>
    TP). Although Ser24 in this motif exists within a conserved CaM kinase II consensus sequence, it is not a phospho-acceptor site in vivo
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [13]
    </xref>
    . It seems reasonable to assume that the extreme amino terminus of cofilin also plays a role in 14-3-3 binding, since Ser3 phosphocofilin specifically associates with 14-3-3ζ
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figure 1)
    </xref>
    . However, the amino acid sequences surrounding Ser3 do not contain any of the described 14-3-3 interaction motifs. We note that some 14-3-3 binding partners interact with 14-3-3 in a phosphorylation-specific manner, but do not contain prototypical 14-3-3 recognition motifs
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [8]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    In order to map the 14-3-3 binding site(s) on cofilin, we expressed point mutants of human cofilin in Cos-1 cells and tested their binding to GST-14-3-3ζ. The employed mutants lack the regulatory phosphorylation site (cofilin
    <sup>
     S3A
    </sup>
    ) and/or contain a modification in the predicted 14-3-3 recognition motif (cofilin
    <sup>
     S3,23,24A
    </sup>
    or cofilin
    <sup>
     S23,24A
    </sup>
    ). As shown in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 2A
    </xref>
    , mutation of Ser3 to Ala clearly reduced 14-3-3 binding, confirming that Ser3 phosphorylation of cofilin is important for the association with 14-3-3. Cofilin
    <sup>
     S23,24A
    </sup>
    , which is Ser3 phosphorylated as efficiently as wild-type cofilin, also bound 14-3-3 comparable to wild-type cofilin. In contrast, the mutation of both the regulatory phosphorylation site and the predicted 14-3-3 binding motif (cofilin
    <sup>
     S3,23,24A
    </sup>
    ) abolished the cofilin/14-3-3 association. Similar results were obtained when GST-14-3-3τ was used (not shown). Thus, both the Ser3-phosphorylated amino terminus and the 14-3-3 consensus site of cofilin are functionally involved in 14-3-3 binding.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Mapping of the 14-3-3&amp;#950; Binding Site on Human Cofilin(A) The indicated mutants of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (179 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    It is tempting to speculate that, when cofilin is active, the unphosphorylated amino terminus of cofilin folds over the putative 14-3-3 recognition motif, thus impeding 14-3-3 binding. Phosphorylation of Ser3 would then lead to a conformational change of the molecule, rendering the 14-3-3 recognition motif more accessible to 14-3-3. In support of this hypothesis, we observed that a peptide comprising the eight amino-terminal amino acids of human cofilin, which might compete with this putative intramolecular association, significantly enhanced cofilin binding to 14-3-3
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figure 2B)
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    The Expression of 14-3-3ζ Increases Phosphocofilin Levels
   </title>
   <p>
    To investigate the functional relevance of the cofilin/14-3-3-interaction, 14-3-3ζ was transiently transfected into Cos-1 or BHK-21 cells, and effects on steady-state phosphocofilin levels were studied biochemically and by immunofluorescence analysis. Remarkably, 14-3-3ζ elevated the phosphocofilin pool to a similar extent as the constitutively active LIMK1 fragment Kd3 in Cos-1 cells (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3A
    </xref>
    ). The coexpression of 14-3-3ζ and Kd3 further increased the amount of phosphocofilin compared to the effect of each protein alone. Densitometric analysis of the phosphocofilin/cofilin ratios showed that 14-3-3ζ or Kd3 alone increased relative phosphocofilin levels 10- to 13-fold compared to the vector control, whereas coexpression of both led to a 57-fold increase in phosphocofilin. In BHK-21 cells, we frequently observed a downregulation of total cofilin protein coincident with 14-3-3ζ and/or Kd3 expression. However, densitometric comparison of the phosphocofilin immunosignals with the amounts of endogenous cofilin revealed a 14-3-3ζ- and/or Kd3-dependent increase in the phosphocofilin pool similar to the levels obtained in Cos-1 cells (14-3-3ζ: 3-fold, Kd3: 10-fold, 14-3-3ζ + Kd3: 58-fold). Immunofluorescence analysis in BHK-21 cells
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figure 3B)
    </xref>
    could be performed after shorter expression times, and staining for endogenous cofilin under these conditions did not show any detectable decrease in protein levels (data not shown). The expression of 14-3-3ζ led to a diffuse increase in cytoplasmic phosphocofilin staining, consistent with the largely cytoplasmic distribution of 14-3-3 proteins
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [14]
    </xref>
    . Wild-type LIMK1 promoted an accumulation of phosphocofilin predominantly in membrane ruffles, where it colocalized with actin and 14-3-3 (see
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    , and data not shown). The coexpression of both 14-3-3ζ and LIMK1 led to a further increase in largely cytoplasmic phosphocofilin staining. In addition, these cells showed a strikingly altered morphology reminiscent of the phenotypical changes encountered in cells expressing high amounts of the constitutively active LIMK1 fragment Kd3
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Expression of 14-3-3&amp;#950; Increases Phosphocofilin Levels(A) Cos-1 cells or ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (410 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Testicular protein kinase 1 (TESK1), an integrin-activated serine/threonine kinase with homology to LIMK1, also induces actin cytoskeletal reorganization through phosphorylation of cofilin on Ser3
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    . Interestingly, TESK1 was recently shown to bind 14-3-3β, resulting in an inhibition of TESK1 kinase activity
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [18]
    </xref>
    . In in vitro kinase assays with immunoprecipitated, myc-tagged TESK1 and TESK2, we were, however, unable to detect any effect of up to 6 μg purified GST-14-3-3ζ or -τ on TESK-dependent cofilin phosphorylation (data not shown). Additionally, the expression of endogenous TESK1 or TESK2 proteins in Cos-1 or BHK-21 cells appeared to be very low, since neither isoform was detected in lysates of up to 5 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    cells when the original antibodies described in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     18
    </xref>
    were used (data not shown). We further investigated whether LIMK1 might be an interaction partner of 14-3-3ζ. As shown in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 3C
    </xref>
    , LIMK1 indeed associated with GST-14-3-3ζ in pulldown experiments. However, 14-3-3ζ (and 14-3-3τ; data not shown) had no effect on the LIMK1-mediated cofilin-phosphorylation in in vitro kinase assays
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     (Figure 3D)
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    These results support the idea that the 14-3-3ζ-dependent increase in cellular phosphocofilin is a direct result of the phosphocofilin/14-3-3 interaction and implicate 14-3-3 proteins in the control of the actin cytoskeleton. However, we cannot formally exclude the possibility that binding of 14-3-3 to LIMK regulates the phosphorylation of an unidentified LIMK substrate that also controls cofilin activity.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    14-3-3ζ Potentiates the LIMK-Induced Actin Phenotype
   </title>
   <p>
    Expression analysis of wild-type and mutant LIMK in different cell types has revealed dose- and activity-dependent effects of LIMK on the actin cytoskeleton
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     5
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    . To obtain functional evidence that 14-3-3ζ is involved in cofilin-controlled actin dynamics, we expressed 14-3-3ζ and/or wild-type LIMK in BHK-21 cells. As shown in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4A
    </xref>
    , 14-3-3ζ induced the formation of membrane protrusions and triggered actin aggregation in a subset of cells. The character of these actin-rich protrusions is at present unclear. Consistent with published observations, cells overexpressing wild-type LIMK were generally characterized by exaggerated membrane protrusions, and only a small subset of LIMK expressors contained actin aggregates. However, cells coexpressing 14-3-3ζ and wild-type LIMK displayed dramatic F-actin accumulation and clumping, reminiscent of the effects induced by Kd3. These results were quantified in
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 4B
    </xref>
    and clearly demonstrate that 14-3-3ζ potentiates LIMK-mediated effects on the actin cytoskeleton through a mechanism synergistic with, but distinct from, effects on LIMK activity.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="14-3-3&amp;#950; Potentiates the LIMK-Induced Actin Phenotype(A) BHK-21 cells were ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (383 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    14-3-3ζ Protects Cofilin from Dephosphorylation
   </title>
   <p>
    To address the issue of how 14-3-3 is able to increase the pool of inactive cofilin independently of regulating LIMK activity, we conducted in vitro phosphatase assays with purified proteins.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 5
    </xref>
    shows that 14-3-3ζ inhibited the PP2A-mediated dephosphorylation of cofilin in a dose-dependent manner. The 14-3-3-mediated protection from dephosphorylation did not result from a general suppression of phosphatase activity, as 14-3-3 failed to antagonize the dephosphorylation of myelin basic protein (MBP) by PP2A. We have observed similar protection from dephosphorylation by a partially purified cofilin phosphatase from bovine brain (not shown). These results are biochemical evidence that 14-3-3ζ-bound phosphocofilin is specifically protected against phosphatase attack and are in good agreement with published observations. For example, it has been reported that 14-3-3ζ blocked Raf
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    and BAD
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    from PP1/PP2A-mediated dephosphorylation.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="14-3-3&amp;#950; Protects Cofilin from DephosphorylationXenopus cofilin and myelin basic ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0960982202011843-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (152 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Conclusions
   </title>
   <p>
    In summary, our results identify a previously uncharacterized role for 14-3-3 proteins in modulating the actin depolymerizing and/or severing functions of cofilin. Our data strongly indicate that LIMK and 14-3-3ζ act cooperatively to control actin cytoskeletal dynamics by increasing and stabilizing the levels of phosphocofilin. It will be of interest to evaluate whether the scaffolding function of 14-3-3 proteins plays any additional role in organizing and regulating the interplay between LIMK, cofilin, and various phosphocofilin regulatory phosphatases.
   </p>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <p>
    Supplementary material including Experimental Procedures, Table S1, and Figure S1 can be found at
    <a>
     http://images.cellpress.com/supmat/supmatin.htm
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary data
   </title>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Supplementary material.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (46 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         1
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.R. Bamburg
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proteins of the ADF/Cofilin family: essential regulators of actin dynamics
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol., 15 (1999), pp. 185–230
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         2
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Condeelis
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         How is actin polymerization nucleated
         <em>
          in vivo?
         </em>
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Cell Biol., 11 (2001), pp. 288–293
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         3
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.C. Edwards, L.C. Sanders, G.M. Bokoch, G.N. Gill
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Activation of LIM-kinase by Pak1 couples Rac/Cdc42 GTPase signalling to actin cytoskeletal dynamics
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 1 (1999), pp. 253–259
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         4
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Maekawa, T. Ishizaki, S. Boku, N. Watanabe, A. Fujita, A. Iwamatsu, T. Obinata, K. Ohashi, K. Mizuno, S. Narumiya
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Signaling from Rho to the actin cytoskeleton through protein kinases ROCK and LIM-kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 285 (1999), pp. 895–898
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         5
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Arber, F.A. Barbayannis, H. Hanser, C. Schneider, C.A. Stanyon, O. Bernard, P. Caroni
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of actin dynamics through phosphorylation of cofilin by LIM-kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 393 (1998), pp. 805–809
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         6
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Yang, O. Higuchi, K. Ohashi, K. Nagata, A. Wada, K. Kangawa, E. Nishida, K. Mizuno
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cofilin phosphorylation by LIM-kinase 1 and its role in Rac-mediated actin reorganization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 393 (1998), pp. 809–812
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         7
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Fu, R.R. Subramanian, S.C. Masters
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         14-3-3 proteins: structure, function, and regulation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol., 40 (2000), pp. 617–647
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         8
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Tzivion, J. Avruch
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         14-3-3 proteins: active cofactors in cellular regulation by serine/threonine phosphorylation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 3061–3064
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         9
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.B. Yaffe
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         How do 14-3-3 proteins work? Gatekeeper phosphorylation and the molecular anvil hypothesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 513 (2002), pp. 53–57
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         10
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Muslin, H. Xing
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         14-3-3 proteins: regulation of subcellular localization by molecular interference
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell. Signal., 12 (2000), pp. 703–709
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         11
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Ambach, J. Saunus, M. Konstandin, S. Wesselborg, S. Meuer, Y. Samstag
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The serine phosphatases PP1 and PP2A associate with and activate the actin-binding protein cofilin in human T-lymphocytes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Eur. J. Immunol., 30 (2000), pp. 3422–3431
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         12
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.J. Meberg, S. Ono, L. Minamide, M. Takahashi, J.R. Bamburg
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Actin depolymerizing factor and cofilin phosphorylation dynamics: response to signals that regulate neurite extension
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton, 39 (1998), pp. 172–190
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         13
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.J. Agnew, L. Minamide, J.R. Bamburg
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reactivation of phosphorylated actin depolymerizing factor and identification of the regulatory site
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 29 (1995), pp. 17582–17587
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         14
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Garcia-Guzman, F. Dolfi, M. Russello, K. Vuori
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell adhesion regulates the interaction between the docking protein p130
         <sup>
          Cas
         </sup>
         and the 14-3-3 proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 5762–5768
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         15
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.C. Edwards, G.N. Gill
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural features of LIM kinase that control effects on the actin cytoskeleton
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 11352–11361
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         16
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Toshima, J.Y. Toshima, T. Amano, N. Yang, S. Narumiya, K. Mizuno
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cofilin phosphorylation by protein kinase testicular protein kinase 1 and its role in integrin-mediated actin reorganization and focal adhesion formation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Biol. Cell, 12 (2001), pp. 1131–1145
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         17
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Toshima, J.Y. Toshima, K. Takeuchi, R. Mori, K. Mizuno
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cofilin phosphorylation and actin reorganization activities of testicular protein kinase 2 and its predominant expression in testicular sertoli cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 31449–31458
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         18
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Toshima, J.Y. Toshima, T. Watanabe, K. Mizuno
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Binding of 14-3-3β regulates the kinase activity and subcellular localization of testicular protein kinase 1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 43471–43478
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         19
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Dent, T. Jelinek, D.K. Morrison, M.J. Weber, T.W. Sturgill
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reversal of Raf-1 activation by purified and membrane-associated protein phosphatases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 268 (1995), pp. 1902–1906
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         20
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.A. Thorson, L.W. Yu, A.L. Hsu, N.-Y. Shih, P.R. Graves, J.W. Tanner, P.M. Allen, H. Piwnica-Worms, A.S. Shaw
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         14-3-3 proteins are required for maintenance of Raf-1 phosphorylation and kinase activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 18 (1998), pp. 5229–5238
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         21
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.-H. Chiang, G. Harris, C. Ellig, S.C. Masters, R. Subramanian, S. Shenolikar, B.E. Wadzinski, E. Yang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein phosphatase 2A activates the proapoptotic function of BAD in interleukin-3-dependent lymphoid cells by a mechanism requiring 14-3-3 dissociation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Blood, 97 (2001), pp. 1289–1297
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2002 Cell Press. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
