<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC1951821
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Protein Modulator of Multidrug Efflux Gene Expression in Pseudomonas aeruginosa▿
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     multidrug-resistant mutants of
     <em>
      Pseudomonas aeruginosa
     </em>
     show enhanced expression of the
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     multidrug efflux system as a direct result of the production of a ca. 6,100-Da protein, PA3719, in these mutants. Using a bacterial two-hybrid system, PA3719 was shown to interact in vivo with MexR, a repressor of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     expression. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) studies confirmed a high-affinity interaction (equilibrium dissociation constant [
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     ], 158.0 ± 18.1 nM) of PA3719 with MexR in vitro. PA3719 binding to and formation of a complex with MexR obviated repressor binding to its operator, which overlaps the efflux operon promoter, suggesting that
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     hyperexpression in
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     mutants results from PA3719 modulation of MexR repressor activity. Consistent with this, MexR repression of
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription in an in vitro transcription assay was alleviated by PA3719. Mutations in MexR compromising its interaction with PA3719 in vivo were isolated and shown to be located internally and distributed throughout the protein, suggesting that they impacted PA3719 binding by altering MexR structure or conformation rather than by having residues interacting specifically with PA3719. Four of six mutant MexR proteins studied retained repressor activity even in a
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     strain producing PA3719. Again, this is consistent with a PA3719 interaction with MexR being necessary to obviate MexR repressor activity. The gene encoding PA3719 has thus been renamed
     <em>
      armR
     </em>
     (
     <em>
      a
     </em>
     nti
     <em>
      r
     </em>
     epressor for
     <em>
      M
     </em>
     ex
     <em>
      R
     </em>
     ). A representative “noninteracting” mutant MexR protein, MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     , was purified, and ITC confirmed that it bound PA3719 with reduced affinity (5.4-fold reduced;
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     , 853.2 ± 151.1 nM). Consistent with this, MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     repressor activity, as assessed using the in vitro transcription assay, was only weakly compromised by PA3719. Finally, two mutations (L36P and W45A) in ArmR compromising its interaction with MexR have been isolated and mapped to a putative C-terminal α-helix of the protein that alone is sufficient for interaction with MexR.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    MATERIALS AND METHODS
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Bacterial strains and growth conditions.
    </title>
    <p>
     The bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        Table1.
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       1
      </span>
     </a>
     . Bacterial cells were cultivated in Luria broth (Miller's Luria broth base [Difco] and 2 g of NaCl per liter of H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O) and agar (Luria broth containing 1.5% [wt/vol] agar), supplemented with appropriate antibiotics when necessary, at 37°C. Plasmid pDSK519 and its derivatives were maintained with 50 μg/ml (in
     <em>
      Escherichia coli
     </em>
     ) or 100 μg/ml (in
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     ) kanamycin. Plasmid pMMB206 and its derivatives were maintained with 10 μg/ml (in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     ) or 150 μg/ml (in
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     ) chloramphenicol. Plasmid pBluescript II SK(+) and its derivatives were maintained in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     using 100 μg/ml ampicillin. Plasmids pDD1 (pET-Dest42::
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     ), pDD2 (pTYB12::PA3719), and pDD3 (pET-Dest42::
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     ) were maintained in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     with 50 μg/ml ampicillin. A
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     deletion was introduced into
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     strain K1454 using plasmid pRSP75 as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      63
     </xref>
     ) and was confirmed using colony PCR (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      59
     </xref>
     ) with primers MexRF and MexRR as described below.
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        TABLE 1.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Bacterial strains and plasmids
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     DNA protocols.
    </title>
    <p>
     Standard protocols were used for restriction endonuclease digestion, ligation, transformation, electroporation (
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     ), and agarose gel electrophoresis, as described by Sambrook and Russell (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      56
     </xref>
     ). Electroporation of plasmids into
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     was carried out as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ). Ligation mixtures were typically applied to Millipore type VM 0.05-μm filter disks over distilled H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O and incubated for 30 min at room temperature prior to electroporation. Genomic DNA of
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     was extracted by following the protocol of Barcak et al. (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      7
     </xref>
     ). Plasmids were isolated from
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     DH5α and
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202 using a QIAprep Spin MiniPrep kit (QIAGEN, Inc., Chatsworth, CA). DNA fragments used for cloning were excised from agarose gels using Prep-A-Gene (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA) in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. PCR products were purified using a QIAquick PCR purification kit (QIAGEN). Oligonucleotides were chemically synthesized by Cortec DNA Services Inc., Kingston, Ontario, Canada, and nucleotide sequencing was carried out by ACGT Corp., Toronto, Ontario, Canada, or by Agencourt, Beverly, MA.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Plasmids.
    </title>
    <p>
     The
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     gene was cloned into plasmid pDSK519 following amplification of the gene by PCR using primers MexRF (5′-GATC
     <span>
      GGATCC
     </span>
     CATTAGGTTTACTCGGCCAAACC-3′; BamHI site underlined) and MexRR (5′-GATC
     <span>
      <span>
       GAATTC
      </span>
     </span>
     CGCCAGTAAGCGGATACCTG-3′; EcoRI site underlined) in a reaction mixture (50 μl) containing 1 μg of PAO1 strain K767 chromosomal DNA as the template, 2.5 U of Vent DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Mississauga, Ontario, Canada), 0.2 mM of each deoxynucleoside triphosphate, 1× ThermoPol buffer (New England Biolabs), 30 pmol of each primer, 2 mM MgSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , and 10% (vol/vol) dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO). The reaction mixture was subjected to an initial 3-min denaturation step at 95°C, followed by 30 cycles of 45 s at 95°C, 30 s at 60°C, and 45 s at 72°C before a 5-min elongation at 72°C. PCR products were purified, digested with BamHI and EcoRI, and cloned into pDSK519 and pBluescript II SK(+), yielding pLC66 and pLC30, respectively. For use in isothermal calorimetry (ITC) studies MexR was expressed with a C-terminal His
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     tag from plasmids provided in Invitrogen Gateway cloning and expression kits (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Briefly, the
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     gene was amplified by PCR using Accuprime GC-rich DNA polymerase and primers MexRsrp-For (5′-GGGGACAAGTTTGTACAAAAAAGCAGGCTTCGAAGGCTTCGAAGGAGATAGAACCATGAACTACCCCGTGAATCCC-3′) and MexRsrp-Rev (5′-GGGGACCACTTTGTACAAGAAAGCTGGGTCAATATCCTCAAGCGGTTGCGC-3′) and inserted into pDONOR221 using the BP recombinase according to the manufacturer's instructions (Invitrogen). The
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     gene was then transferred from pDONOR221 to pET-Dest42 (yielding pDD1) using the LR recombinase, again according to the manufacturers’ instructions,. For ITC studies of MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     , plasmid pDD3 carrying
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     <sub>
      L104F
     </sub>
     was constructed by introduction of a point mutation into the
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     gene of pDD1 using the Stratagene QuickChange mutagenesis system and a protocol provided by the manufacturer (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA).
    </p>
    <p>
     The PA3719 gene was cloned into the two-hybrid vector pDP804 following amplification of the gene from plasmid pLC23 using PCR and primers PDP-PA3719F (5′-TCAG
     <span>
      <span>
       CTCGAGCTCGAG
      </span>
     </span>
     ATGTCCCTGAACACTCCG-3′; tandem XhoI sites underlined) and PDP-PA3719R (5′-TCAT
     <span>
      <span>
       AGATCTAGATCT
      </span>
     </span>
     TGCGCGGATTCTGATAGCT-3′; tandem BglII sites underlined). Reaction mixtures (50 μl) containing 100 ng of pLC23, 0.6 μM of each primer, 0.2 mM of each deoxynucleoside triphosphate, 2 mM MgSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , and 1 U of
     <em>
      Pfu
     </em>
     DNA polymerase (Fermentas Life Sciences, Burlington, Ontario, Canada) in 1×
     <em>
      Pfu
     </em>
     DNA polymerase buffer were heated at 98°C for 45 s and then subjected to 25 cycles of 98°C for 45 s, 62°C for 45 s, and 72°C for 1 min, followed by 10 min at 72°C. The PA3719-carrying PCR product was purified (see below), digested with XhoI and BglII, and cloned into pDP804, yielding pSF001. A New England Biolabs IMPACT intein fusion kit was used for cloning and expression of PA3719 (as an intein fusion) for use in ITC studies. PCR amplification of the gene was carried out using primers PA3719srp-For (5′-GGCGAA
     <span>
      <span>
       GCGGCCGC
      </span>
     </span>
     ATGTCCCTGAACACTCCGC-3′; NotI site underlined) and PA3719srp-Rev (5′-CGTGG
     <span>
      <span>
       CTCGAG
      </span>
     </span>
     TCAGTAGAAGTGCTCGCCG-3′; XhoI site underlined) and Accuprime GC-rich DNA polymerase, and the gene was cloned into the kit-provided plasmid pTYB12, yielding the PA3719-intein fusion-expressing vector pDD2.
    </p>
    <p>
     The 3′ end of PA3719 encoding residues S25 to Y53 was cloned into the two-hybrid vector pDP804 as a XhoI-BglII fragment following the annealing of two XhoI- and BglII-flanked 110-bp oligonucleotides corresponding to both strands of the S25- to Y53-encoding region of PA3719. Annealing was achieved by incubating 800 pmol of each oligonucleotide in T4 ligation buffer at 95°C for 3 min and allowing the reaction mixture to cool at room temperature for 5 h, after which the 3′ PA3719 DNA was purified using a gel and PCR cleanup kit (Promega).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Random mutagenesis.
    </title>
    <p>
     PCR-based random mutagenesis (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      53
     </xref>
     ) of
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     was carried out using primers RanMuMexRForward (5′-GAGC
     <span>
      <span>
       GGTGACC
      </span>
     </span>
     ATGAACTACCCCGTGAATCC-3′; BstEII site underlined) and RanMuMexRReverse (5′-GAGG
     <span>
      <span>
       CTCGAG
      </span>
     </span>
     TTAAATATCCTCAA-GCGGTTG-C-3′; XhoI site underlined). The reaction mixtures (50 μl) contained 100 ng of plasmid pLC30 as the template, 2.5 U of
     <em>
      Taq
     </em>
     DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Mississauga, Ontario, Canada), 1× ThermoPol buffer (New England Biolabs), 0.2 mM of each deoxynucleoside triphosphate (except dATP or dCTP [40 μM]), 30 pmol of each primer, 2 mM MgSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , and 10% (vol/vol) DMSO. The PCR mixtures were subjected to an initial 3-min denaturation step at 95°C, followed by 29 cycles of 45 s at 95°C, 30 s at 60°C, and 45 s at 72°C before a 5-min elongation at 72°C. The PCR products were then digested with BstEII and XhoI and cloned into pLK452 (pMS604::
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     ) purified so that it was free of the wild-type
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     -containing BstEII-XhoI fragment (i.e., the wild-type gene was replaced with mutagenized
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     ). PCR-based random mutagenesis of PA3719 was carried out with primers PDP-PA3719F and PDP-PA3719R (see above) as described above for
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     , omitting DMSO, using pLC23 as the template, and including MnCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     at a final concentration of 25 to 150 μM. The reaction conditions were the same as those described above for PCR of
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     . PCR products were purified, digested with XhoI and BglII, and cloned into pSF001 (pDP840::PA3719) purified so that it was free of the wild-type PA3719-containing XhoI-BglII fragment of this vector (i.e., the wild-type PA3719 gene of pSF001 was replaced with mutagenized PA3719).
    </p>
    <p>
     Mutant
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     genes (screened using the two-hybrid assay [see below]) were cloned into plasmid pDSK519 following their amplification, from plasmid pMS604 derivatives harboring them, with primers RanMexRForward (5′-GAGC
     <span>
      GGATCC
     </span>
     ATGAACTACCCCGTGAATCC-3′; BamHI site underlined) and RanMexR Reverse (5′-GAGG
     <span>
      <span>
       GAATTC
      </span>
     </span>
     TTAAATATCCTCAAG-CGGTTGC-3′; EcoRI site underlined). The reaction mixtures (50 μl) contained 1 μg of pMS604 derivative as the template, 2.5 U of
     <em>
      Pfu
     </em>
     DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Mississauga, Ontario, Canada), 1×
     <em>
      Pfu
     </em>
     buffer (New England Biolabs), 0.2 mM of each deoxynucleoside triphosphate, and 30 pmol of each primer. The PCR mixtures were subjected to an initial 3-min denaturation step at 98°C, followed by 29 cycles of 45 s at 98°C, 30 s at 65°C, and 45 s at 72°C before a 5-min elongation at 72°C. Following purification and digestion (with BamHI and EcoRI) the
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     -carrying fragments were cloned into appropriately digested pDSK519 and mobilized into
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     using a previously described triparental mating procedure (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      69
     </xref>
     ), with transconjugants selected on LB agar containing kanamycin (750 μg/ml) and imipenem (0.5 μg/ml) (to counterselect
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Wild-type and mutant (screened using the two-hybrid assay [see below]) PA3719 genes were cloned into plasmid pMMB206 following their amplification, from plasmid pDP804 derivatives harboring them, with primers PA3719SD-F (5′-GACT
     <span>
      <span>
       GAATTCGAATTC
      </span>
     </span>
     ACGGGGATGAACTGGTGACGCCGCCATGTCCCTGAACACTCCG-3′; tandem EcoRI sites underlined) and PA3719DS-R (5′-GACT
     <span>
      <span>
       AAGCTTAAGCTT
      </span>
     </span>
     TGCGCGGATTCTGATAGCT-3′; tandem HindIII sites underlined). The reaction mixtures were formulated as described above for PA3719 cloning into pDP804, except that Vent DNA polymerase (2 U; New England Biolabs, Ltd., Pickering, Ontario, Canada) and its buffer replaced
     <em>
      Pfu
     </em>
     and MgSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     was included at a concentration of 1 mM. The reaction mixtures were also heated as described above, with the exception that an annealing temperature of 65°C (not 62°C) was used. Following purification and digestion (with EcoRI and HindIII) the PA3719-carrying fragments were cloned into appropriately restricted pMMB206. The resultant plasmids were then introduced into
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     via electroporation.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Bacterial two-hybrid system.
    </title>
    <p>
     To assess an interaction between MexR and PA3719 in vivo and the impact of mutations (or truncations) on this interaction,
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     -carrying pMS604 (or its mutated derivatives) and PA3719-carrying pDP804 (or its mutated or truncated derivatives) were electroporated into
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     strain SU202 and plated onto 1% (wt/vol) lactose-MacConkey agar containing ampicillin (100 μg/ml) and tetracycline (10 μg/ml) as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      53
     </xref>
     ). Any interaction between MexR and PA3719 sequences encoded by the various
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     - and PA3719-containing pMS604 and pDP804 derivatives was observable as a lack of or reduction in β-galactosidase activity in SU202 (i.e., pale pink to white colonies on lactose-MacConkey agar), while the absence of an interaction yielded β-galactosidase activity (red colonies) in this reporter strain (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      53
     </xref>
     ). These results were confirmed using a more quantitative β-galactosidase assay, as described below. In screening randomly mutagenized
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     or PA3719 genes for mutations compromising the MexR-PA3719 interaction, the ligation mixtures producing the pLK452 and pSF001 derivatives that carry randomly PCR-mutagenized
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     and PA3719, respectively (see above), were electroporated directly into
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202, which was then plated onto 1% (wt/vol) lactose-MacConkey agar containing ampicillin and tetracycline and screened as described above. In all instances, whole-cell protein extracts were prepared and screened (using immunoblotting with anti-LexA antibodies [see below]) for the production of LexA-MexR and LexA-PA3719 fusions, to ensure production of wild-type and mutant versions of these proteins.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and immunoblotting.
    </title>
    <p>
     Whole-cell extracts were prepared as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      52
     </xref>
     ), electrophoresed on 20% (wt/vol) sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-polyacrylamide gels, and transferred to Immobilon-P polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Millipore) (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      61
     </xref>
     ). Membranes were probed with monoclonal anti-LexA antibodies (Invitrogen) as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      61
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     β-Galactosidase assay.
    </title>
    <p>
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202 derivatives containing pDP804 (or its derivatives) and pMS604 (or its derivatives) were grown in LB medium supplemented with ampicillin (100 μg/ml) and tetracycline (10 μg/ml) for approximately 18 h at 37°C. Cultures were then diluted 1:49 into fresh antibiotic-supplemented medium and incubated at 37°C until the optical density at 600 nm was 0.8 to 1.0 before they were assayed for β-galactosidase activity as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      35
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Susceptibility testing.
    </title>
    <p>
     The antibiotic susceptibility of
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     was assessed using a previously described broth dilution assay (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ), and the data are reported as the MIC for each agent tested.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Expression and purification of MexR and PA3719.
    </title>
    <p>
     Wild-type MexR used in mobility shift assays was expressed in and purified from
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     BL21(DE3) as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ). For use in ITC studies, MexR and MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     were expressed in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     BL21(DE3)* Star (Invitrogen) from plasmids pDD1 and pDD3, respectively. Briefly, Luria broth (4 liters) supplemented with ampicillin was inoculated 1:99 with an overnight culture of plasmid-carrying
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     BL21(DE3)* Star, and the culture was grown to an optical density at 600 nm of ∼0.5 and induced with IPTG (final concentration, 1 mM) for 4 h at 37°C. Cells were harvested by centrifugation at 7,500 ×
     <em>
      g
     </em>
     for 10 min at 4°C, resuspended in 10 ml of lysis buffer (20 mM sodium phosphate [pH 7.2], 500 mM NaCl, 10 mM imidazole, 1× Roche Complete EDTA-free protease inhibitor cocktail), and lysed by three consecutive passes through a French pressure cell at 20,000 lb/in
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     . Protein purification was performed on a HisTrap HP column according to the manufacturer's instructions (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ). Purified MexR proteins were quantitated using the Bradford assay and were verified by
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     <sub>
      280
     </sub>
     measurement after denaturation with 6 M guanidinium-HCl. PA3719 for use in ITC was expressed (as an intein fusion) from the pTYB12::PA3719 vector, pDD2, also in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     BL21 (DE3)* Star as described above except for the use of IPTG at a concentration of 0.5 mM and subsequent growth at 18°C for 18 h. Purification of the PA3719-intein fusion protein was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions (New England Biolabs). The intein-cleaved PA3719 protein retained an AGHMTSSRVDGGR N-terminal extension and was quantitated as described above for MexR. All proteins were &gt;98% pure as determined by SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     ITC.
    </title>
    <p>
     MexR, MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     , and PA3719 were purified as described above. The protein samples were buffer exchanged into ITC assay buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl [pH 8.0], 200 mM NaCl) using a combination of an Amicon 8200 stirred concentration cell with a YM1 ultrafiltration membrane to concentrate the samples to 10 ml, followed by dialysis for 8 h at room temperature. Proteins were quantitated using the Bradford assay and were verified by
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     <sub>
      280
     </sub>
     measurement after denaturation in 6 M guanidinium-HCl. ITC experiments were carried out using a VP-ITC Microcal calorimeter (Microcal Inc., Studio City, CA). Solutions were degassed for 15 min prior to experiments using a vacuum degasser. Calorimetric titrations were carried out with wild-type MexR protein at a concentration of 16.2 μM in the sample cell, ITC assay buffer in the reference cell, and PA3719 at a concentration of 107.9 μM in the automated syringe. The injection sequence consisted of a single 4-μl injection followed by a series of 28 injections of 10 μl, separated by 300 s of equilibration time. Calorimetric titrations with the site-directed variant MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     were performed as described above except that MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     was present at a concentration of 70 μM in the sample cell and PA3719 was present at a concentration of 350 μM in the syringe. The mixing speed was 307 rpm, the cell temperature was 25°C, and the reference power was 5 μcal/s, with an initial delay of 60 s. The saturation levels of the interaction at the concentrations tested were approximately 2.9-fold for wild-type MexR and 2.2-fold for MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     , giving PA3719/MexR molar ratios of approximately 1.45 and 1.1, respectively, by the end of the titrations.
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     values of the titrations were calculated using the following equation:
     <em>
      C = K
      <sub>
       A
      </sub>
     </em>
     ×
     <em>
      M
     </em>
     <sub>
      Tot
     </sub>
     ×
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     , where
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       A
      </sub>
     </em>
     is the association rate constant,
     <em>
      M
     </em>
     <sub>
      Tot
     </sub>
     is the concentration of the binding partner in the cell being titrated, and
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     is the stoichiometry of the interaction. The data were fitted by a single-site model using the ORIGIN ITC software provided by Microcal to obtain a least-squares estimate of
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       A
      </sub>
     </em>
     (in M
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     ). The equilibrium dissociation constant (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      D
     </sub>
     ) was calculated using the equation
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     = 1/
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       A
      </sub>
     </em>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Mobility shift assay.
    </title>
    <p>
     The mobility shift assay was carried out in 10 μl of 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5)-50 mM NaCl as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ), using purified MexR and PA3719 synthesized (with the N-terminal Met) by C S Bio Company, Inc. (Menlo Park, CA) (
     <a>
      www.csbio.com
     </a>
     ). The proteins (individually and together in various amounts) were mixed with target DNA (28-mer MexR operator [
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ]; 30 μM) at room temperature prior to gel loading.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     In vitro transcription assay.
    </title>
    <p>
     An 836-bp DNA fragment containing a phage T7 promoter at its 5′ end and
     <em>
      mex
     </em>
     DNA beginning 251 bp upstream of
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     (including the MexR-binding site) and extending 585 bp into
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     was amplified from
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     PAO1 genomic DNA by PCR using Accuprime GC-rich DNA polymerase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and primers A (5-GAAAT
     <span>
      TAATACGACTCACTATAGGG
     </span>
     TAAATGTGGTTGATCCAGTCAAC-3′; T7 promoter underlined) and B (5′-CGGGTCGAGCTGTTGCACGGTGGCCATCGCGTTGGC-3′). The PCR product was resolved using agarose (1%, wt/vol) gel electrophoresis, purified using a QIAGEN gel extraction kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, CA), and quantitated using a nanodrop spectrophotomoter (Nanodrop, Wilmington, DE). In vitro transcription from this template was conducted using a Megascript T7 RNA polymerase-based in vitro transcription kit (Ambion, Austin, TX) according to the manufacturers’ instructions, with the exception that the amount of template was reduced to 250 ng (final concentration, 22.7 nM) and one-half the suggested amounts of T7 polymerase enzyme mixture and nucleotides were used. Control experiments using the kit-provided pTRI-Xef-1 template were carried out according to the manufacturer's instructions. To assess the impact of the MexR or MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     repressors on transcription from these templates, the purified proteins were added at a final concentration of 1 μM in 20-μl reaction mixtures. To assess the impact of PA3719 on MexR/MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     repressor activity in this assay, PA3719 was added at various concentrations to reaction mixtures containing 1 μM of each repressor. Control reactions were also carried out with PA3719 alone. In all instances, reactions were allowed to proceed for 3 h at 37°C, after which the RNA product was purified using a QIAGEN RNeasy RNA purification kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, CA), incorporating on-column DNase digestion for 30 min. Purified RNA products were quantitated using a nanodrop spectrophotometer, mixed with 2× Novex Tris-borate-EDTA-urea sample buffer, heated to 70°C for 3 min, separated by electrophoresis in Novex 6% Tris-borate-EDTA-urea gels (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and visualized by ethidium bromide staining.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    RESULTS
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     MexR-PA3719 interaction.
    </title>
    <p>
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     multidrug-resistant mutants of
     <em>
      P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     show enhanced expression of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     that is dependent upon increased expression of PA3719, the second gene of the NalC repressor-regulated PA3720-PA3719 operon (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      8
     </xref>
     ). One way in which PA3719 might increase
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     expression is by interacting with and modulating the activity of MexR, the primary repressor of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     expression and a target for mutation in so-called
     <em>
      nalB
     </em>
     multidrug-resistant mutants (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      63
     </xref>
     ). To assess an interaction between MexR and PA3719, then, a bacterial two-hybrid approach was employed (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      12
     </xref>
     ), in which the PA3719 and
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     genes were cloned in frame to coding sequences for the DNA-binding domain of LexA on plasmids pDP804 and pMS604, respectively, and introduced into
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202 carrying a chromosomal
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     gene under the control of a LexA operator. LexA binding to its operator and subsequent repression of
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     in this strain require prior dimerization of the LexA-binding domains encoded by pDP804 and pMS604, necessitating interaction of the PA3719 and MexR sequences fused to the LexA DNA-binding domains of these vectors. As such, lack of β-galactosidase activity is a measure of the PA3719-MexR interaction. The two-hybrid vectors also contain sequences encoding Jun and Fos zipper motifs (which are known to interact) fused to
     <em>
      lexA
     </em>
     , such that
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202 carrying these vectors demonstrates substantial repression of
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table2).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). The unaltered vectors thus provide a positive control for the system, although the Jun and Fos zipper-encoding sequences will be disrupted upon cloning of PA3719 and/or
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     sequences, making
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     repression dependent upon the PA3719-MexR interaction. As shown in Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        Table2,
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     , individual cloning of
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     or PA3719 into pMS6054 or pDP804 provided substantial β-galactosidase activity in SU202 as a result of the absence of an appropriate interacting partner in these vectors to effect
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     repression. When
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     -carrying pMS604 and PA3719-carrying pDP804 were introduced into SU202, however, the β-galactosidase levels were reduced substantially (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table2),
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     ), consistent with
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     repression and thus a MexR-PA3719 interaction. A MexR-PA3719 interaction was subsequently confirmed in vitro using ITC analysis (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ). Integration of the raw data (peaks of heat released upon binding of PA3719 to wild-type MexR) gave an estimated stoichiometry of 0.54 ± 0.01 mol of PA3719 per mol of MexR, corresponding to one PA3719 binding site per MexR dimer in solution and a
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     of 158.0 ± 18.1 nM.
    </p>
    <fig id="f1" position="float">
     <label>
      FIG. 1.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Binding of PA3719 to MexR and MexR
       <sub>
        I104F
       </sub>
       measured by ITC. (A) ITC titration of wild-type MexR (16.2 μM) with 10-μl injections of 107.9 μM PA3719. The upper panel shows the raw data for heat released by the binding of PA3719 to MexR expressed in microcalories per second versus time in minutes, while the lower panel shows the peak integration for each injection expressed in kilocalories per mole of PA3719 versus the molar ratio of MexR to PA3719 in solution. The line shows the fit of the data to a single-site model. The least-squares estimate for N (stoichiometry) was 0.54 ± 0.01 PA3719 binding site per MexR molecule or one binding site per MexR dimer, the least-squares estimate for
       <em>
        K
        <sub>
         A
        </sub>
       </em>
       was 6.29 × 10
       <sup>
        6
       </sup>
       ± 0.72 × 10
       <sup>
        6
       </sup>
       M
       <sup>
        −1
       </sup>
       , and the least-squares estimate for
       <em>
        K
        <sub>
         D
        </sub>
       </em>
       was 158.0 ± 18.1 nM. (B) ITC titration of MexR
       <sub>
        I104F
       </sub>
       (70 μM) with 10-μl injections of 350 μM PA3719. The least-squares estimate for N was 0.63 ± 0.01, the least-squares estimate for
       <em>
        K
        <sub>
         A
        </sub>
       </em>
       was 1.17 × 10
       <sup>
        6
       </sup>
       ± 0.21 × 10
       <sup>
        6
       </sup>
       M
       <sup>
        −1
       </sup>
       , and the least-squares estimate for
       <em>
        K
        <sub>
         D
        </sub>
       </em>
       was 853.2 ± 151.1 nM.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        TABLE 2.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        β-Galactosidase activity of
        <em>
         E. coli
        </em>
        SU202 isolates expressing wild-type and mutant MexR and PA3719 proteins in the LexA-based two-hybrid system
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     PA3719 modulates MexR DNA binding and repressor activity.
    </title>
    <p>
     MexR regulates
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     expression by binding to an operator region that overlaps the major promoter of this efflux operon (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      13
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      39
     </xref>
     ). Gel shift assays involving a synthetic
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     operator sequence confirmed this MexR-DNA binding (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 3). Addition of PA3719 yielded, as expected, a MexR-PA3719 complex (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 6) and reduced MexR binding to operator DNA (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 6), and this became more pronounced (more complex, less DNA binding) as more PA3719 was added (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 7). The smear of DNA apparently comigrating with the MexR-PA3719 complex (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 7) is likely not indicative of DNA-bound MexR-PA3719, as one would not expect a DNA-free PA3719-MexR complex (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 5) to show the same mobility as a PA3719-MexR-DNA complex, just as DNA-free MexR and its DNA-bound form migrate very differently (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 2 and 3). While these data suggest that PA3719 modulates MexR operator binding and, ultimately, MexR-mediated repression of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     , in the absence of some explanation for the apparently anomalous migration of the MexR operator DNA in the presence of the PA3719-MexR complex we cannot unequivocally make this claim. To assess whether PA3719 does modulate MexR repression of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     , a system for in vitro transcription of
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     was established by first engineering a phage T7 promoter upstream of sequences encompassing the MexR-binding site and extending into
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     and then using T7 RNA polymerase to drive
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription from this template (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 1). While addition of MexR clearly reduced
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription in this assay (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 2), subsequent addition of PA3719 at a concentration equal to its
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 3) or threefold greater than its
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 4) interfered with MexR repressor activity (i.e.,
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription increased), ultimately restoring
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription to levels seen without the repressor (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lane 4 and with lane 1). As expected, PA3719 alone did not impact
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 2 and 3 with lane 1) and MexR did not impact transcription of a control template lacking a MexR-binding site (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 6 and 7 with lane 5).
    </p>
    <fig id="f2" position="float">
     <label>
      FIG. 2.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Electrophoretic mobility shift assay demonstrating disruption of the MexR-operator DNA complex in lieu of formation of a MexR-PA3719 complex as visualized by (A) ethidium bromide staining of the MexR operator DNA and (B) Coomassie brilliant blue staining of the protein. The protein components indicated, MexR (0.6 nmol) and PA3719 (0.6 nmol [+] or 1.2 nmol [++]), and MexR operator DNA (5′-ATTTTAGTTGACCTTATCAACCTTGTTT-3′; 0.3 nmol) (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        28
       </xref>
       ) were incubated in 10-μl (final volume) mixtures and subjected to nondenaturing polyacrylamide (12%, wt/vol) gel electrophoresis under reducing conditions at 77 V for 3 h at room temperature. Note that PA3719 has a high pI and migrates in the opposite direction when it is not in a complex with MexR. Thus, a control experiment run with PA3719 and operator DNA only shows no PA3719 and free, unshifted DNA (data not shown).
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3" position="float">
     <label>
      FIG. 3.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       PA3719 and MexR control of in vitro
       <em>
        mexA
       </em>
       transcription. (A) Impact of PA3719 on MexR repression of
       <em>
        mexA
       </em>
       transcription. Phage T7 RNA polymerase-based in vitro transcription reactions were initiated from a 836-bp PCR-generated template (250 ng) carrying a T7 promoter and
       <em>
        mexA
       </em>
       sequences extending from the MexR operator to 585 bp into the
       <em>
        mexA
       </em>
       gene (lanes 1 to 4). The results for control reactions with a T7 promoter-containing DNA template, pTRI-Xef, provided with the T7 in vitro transcription kit, are shown in lanes 5 to 7. Reactions were carried out at 37°C for 3 h, and RNA was purified and subjected to electrophoresis prior to visualization with ethidium bromide. MexR (1 μM) and PA3719 (150 nM [+
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       ] or 500 nM [+
       <sup>
        2]
       </sup>
       ) were included in the reaction mixtures as indicated. Equal volumes of RNA were loaded in each instance. The following amounts of RNA were produced: lane 1, 4.2 μg; lane 2, 1.1 μg; lane 3, 2.0 μg; lane 4, 4.2 μg; lane 5, 1.7 μg; lane 6, 1.6 μg; and lane 7, 1.6 μg. (B) Impact of PA3719 on
       <em>
        mexA
       </em>
       transcription. In vitro transcription of the
       <em>
        mex
       </em>
       (lanes 1 to 3) and pTRI-Xef (lanes 4 to 6) templates was carried out as described above with or without PA3719 (500 nM [+
       <sup>
        2
       </sup>
       ] or 2 μM [+
       <sup>
        3
       </sup>
       ]), as indicated. The following amounts of RNA were produced: lane 1, 4.4 μg; lane 2, 4.5 μg; lane 3, 4.6 μg; lane 4, 4.6 μg; lane 5, 4.6 μg; and lane 6, 4.4 μg. (C) Differential impact of PA3719 on the repressor activities of MexR and MexR
       <sub>
        I104F
       </sub>
       . In vitro transcription of the
       <em>
        mex
       </em>
       (lanes 1 to 5) and pTRI-Xef (lanes 6 to 8) templates was carried out as described above with or without PA3719 (500 nM) and MexR/MexR
       <sub>
        I104F
       </sub>
       (1 μM), as indicated. The following amounts of RNA were produced: lane 1, 4.2 μg; lane 2, 0.8 μg; lane 3, 3.8 μg; lane 4, 0.9 μg; lane 5, 1.9 μg; lane 6, 6.6 μg; lane 7, 6.5 μg; and lane 8, 6.4 μg. RNA was quantitated prior to loading, and the values reported reflect the amount loaded and not the total amount produced. Because reaction, recovery, and loading volumes were kept constant throughout, these values accurately reflect the relative transcript levels produced in each instance.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     MexR mutations compromising PA3719 interaction.
    </title>
    <p>
     To assess the details of the MexR-PA3719 interaction, including identification of residues or regions of MexR important for or involved in this interaction, mutations in
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     compromising this interaction were selected using the two-hybrid system mentioned above. Thus,
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     -carrying pMS604 was mutagenized and introduced into pDP804::PA3719-carrying SU202, and LacZ
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     colonies (i.e., red colonies) were selected on MacConkey agar; a defect in the MexR-PA3719 interaction was expected to obviate
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     repression in the SU202 reporter strain. Following confirmation that putative mutant MexR proteins (as fusions to LexA) defective in the PA3719 interaction were expressed (to eliminate further study of mutations compromising MexR production or stability, which would also compromise the interaction with PA3719 and obviate
     <em>
      lacZ
     </em>
     repression in SU202),
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     genes were sequenced and the genes carrying single point mutations were saved for further study. Six mutant
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     genes (from more than 40 noninteracting mutants originally selected and sequenced) producing a stable MexR (-LexA) product (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ) carried single mutations (L28P, L35P, L75P, I104F, M112T, L135F) and were shown in β-galactosidase assays to be defective in PA3719 interaction (i.e., the β-galactosidase activity increased relative to that of wild-type MexR) (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table2).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). These mutations, while distributed throughout MexR (L28P, helix 1; L35P, loop between helices 1 and 2; L75P, helix 4; and I104F, M112T, and L135P, helix 5), occurred at generally interior sites of the protein (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ) and are unlikely to define a PA3719-binding site or identify MexR residues involved directly in binding PA3719. More likely, these mutations impact MexR protein conformation and thereby PA3719 binding.
    </p>
    <fig id="f4" position="float">
     <label>
      FIG. 4.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Whole-cell anti-LexA immunoblot of
       <em>
        E. coli
       </em>
       SU202 expressing mutant versions of (A) MexR-LexA and (B) PA3719-LexA fusions defective in the MexR-PA3719 interaction. (A)
       <em>
        E. coli
       </em>
       SU202 carrying pSF001 (pDP804::PA3719
       <sub>
        WT
       </sub>
       ) and pMS604 derivatives expressing mutant MexR proteins (lane 1, L35P; lane 2, I104F; lane 3, M112T; lane 4, L135F; lane 5, L28P; lane 6, L75P). Note that the band below MexR is a cross-reactive product and not PA3719-LexA, which migrates lower in the gel, as indicated on the right. (B)
       <em>
        E. coli
       </em>
       SU202 carrying pLK452 (pMS604::mexR
       <sub>
        WT
       </sub>
       ) and pDP804 derivatives expressing wild-type (lane 4) or mutant (lane 5, W45A; lane 6, L36P) PA3719 proteins. Lane 1, pDP804 alone; lane 2, pMS604 alone; lane 3, pMS604::
       <em>
        mexR
       </em>
       and pDP804. The positions of the Jun-LexA (lanes 1 and 3) and Fos-LexA (lane 2) fusions encoded by the native pDP804 and pMS604 vectors, respectively, are indicated. PA3719
       <sub>
        L36P
       </sub>
       (PA3719*) migrates anomalously on gels (compare lanes 4 and 6). Equal loading of all wells was verified by running duplicate gels that were stained with Coomassie brilliant blue.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5" position="float">
     <label>
      FIG. 5.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Location in MexR of mutations compromising interaction with PA3719. Structural details of the MexR dimer (PDB accession no. 1LNW [
       <a>
        http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov
       </a>
       ]) are shown, with sticks highlighting the residues that, when mutated, compromised the interaction with PA3719. Residues are labeled on only one monomer.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Interestingly, four of these six mutations (L35P, I104F, M112T, L135F) did not impact MexR repressor activity, at least to any appreciable extent, as shown by the ability of plasmid pDSK519 derivatives carrying the corresponding cloned mutant
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     genes to reduce multidrug resistance in the Δ
     <em>
      mexR P. aeruginosa
     </em>
     strain K1491 to an extent comparable to that seen with the cloned wild-type
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     gene (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table3).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
     </a>
     ). These results were confirmed directly with a representative noninteracting MexR mutant protein, MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     , which was able to repress
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription in the in vitro transcription assay described above (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 1 and 4). The four above-mentioned mutant MexR proteins also showed substantial
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     repressor activity in the Δ
     <em>
      mexR nalC
     </em>
     strain K2519, as evidenced by their ability to reduce resistance to MexAB-OprM antimicrobial substrates in this strain when they were supplied in
     <em>
      trans
     </em>
     (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table3).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
     </a>
     ). This was in contrast to wild-type MexR, whose
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     repressor activity was largely ameliorated in a
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     background (the cloned gene yielded little or no change in resistance in K2519, similar to the vector control) (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table3).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Since
     <em>
      nalC
     </em>
     strains show increased expression of PA3719 that is essential for elevated
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     expression and associated multidrug resistance (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      8
     </xref>
     ), these data are consistent with a PA3719-MexR interaction ameliorating MexR-DNA binding (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ) and thus repression of
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table3).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
     </a>
     ). As such, mutant MexR proteins defective in the PA3719 interaction are unresponsive to PA3719 modulation and hence are able to bind and repress
     <em>
      mexAB-oprM
     </em>
     in the presence of PA3719, at least in vivo. To test this in vitro, a representative PA3719-binding-deficient MexR mutant protein (MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     ) was purified and examined for PA3719 interaction, again using ITC analysis. As expected, the mutant protein had a lower affinity for PA3719 than wild-type MexR, characterized by a 5.4-fold decrease in the
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     (
     <em>
      K
      <sub>
       D
      </sub>
     </em>
     , 853.2 ± 151.1 nM) (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ). Consistent with these results, while PA3719 effectively reversed wild-type MexR repression of
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription in vitro (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 2 and 3), it had only a modest impact on MexR
     <sub>
      I104F
     </sub>
     repression of
     <em>
      mexA
     </em>
     transcription, providing only a slight increase in transcription (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , compare lanes 4 and 5).
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        TABLE 3.
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Influence of
        <em>
         mexR
        </em>
        and PA3719 mutations on the antibiotic susceptibility of
        <em>
         P. aeruginosa
        </em>
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Mutations in PA3719 compromising interaction with MexR.
    </title>
    <p>
     To identify residues of PA3719 important for MexR interaction, the PA3719-carrying pDP804 plasmid was mutagenized as described above for
     <em>
      mexR
     </em>
     and introduced into pMS604-carrying
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     SU202, and again, LacZ
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     colonies were selected on MacConkey agar. Despite the fact that dozens of putative noninteracting PA3719 mutants were screened, only two bore single point mutations in PA3719 (yielding L36P and W45A changes in the protein) (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table2).
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). Immunoblotting confirmed production of pDP804-encoded PA3719
     <sub>
      L36P
     </sub>
     (fused to LexA), which migrated anomalously on SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis gels (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 6), although the W45A version was not detected (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     , lane 5). Still, control studies with pDP804-encoded wild-type PA3719 revealed that the protein (as a LexA fusion) was unstable and, as a result, undetectable in immunoblots in the absence of MexR (data not shown). One interpretation of these results is that an interaction with MexR stabilizes the PA3719 (-LexA) protein in this system and mutations in PA3719 that compromise this interaction (or the absence of its interacting partner) render the protein unstable. Interestingly, both L36 and W45 occur within the only predicted (using PSIPRED [
     <a>
      http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/
     </a>
     ]) secondary structure of note in the protein (an α-helix that extends from D31 to D46), which is likely involved in the MexR interaction. Indeed, an N-terminally truncated PA3719 derivative encompassing this region (S25 to Y53) was able to interact with MexR in the two-hybrid assay (Table
     <a>
      <span>
       ​
       <span>
        (Table2
       </span>
      </span>
      <span>
       2
      </span>
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    DISCUSSION
   </title>
   <p>
    In light of MexR's role as a repressor of
    <em>
     mexAB-oprM
    </em>
    expression, earlier observations of increased production of both MexAB-OprM and MexR in
    <em>
     nalC
    </em>
    strains of
    <em>
     P. aeruginosa
    </em>
    were initially hard to explain (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ). Clearly, MexR in such mutants was inactive as a repressor (hence, there was increased MexAB-OprM), and increased production of MexR reflected a loss of negative autoregulation. The current study confirms the loss of repressor activity of MexR in
    <em>
     nalC
    </em>
    strains and demonstrates that this results from an interaction between PA3719 (ArmR), whose expression increases in
    <em>
     nalC
    </em>
    mutants, and MexR. Thus, MexR is unique among MarR family regulators, which tend to bind or be modulated by chemical effectors (typically aromatic compounds) (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     15
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     51
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     67
    </xref>
    ) that also abrogate operator binding and thereby promote expression of MarR family-regulated genes (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     68
    </xref>
    ). Indeed, while MarR DNA binding and thus repressor activity are modulated by salicylate, an agent known to induce expression of the MarR-regulated
    <em>
     marRAB
    </em>
    locus in
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     3
    </xref>
    ), and the crystallized MarR repressor demonstrates two possible binding sites for this agent, salicylate does not modulate MexR DNA binding and at least one of the proposed salicylate-binding sites of MarR is absent in MexR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     4
    </xref>
    ). Clearly then, MexR differs from MarR (and other Mar family regulators) with regard to the mechanism by which its activity is modulated.
   </p>
   <p>
    Protein effectors of regulatory proteins, including repressors, are not uncommon in bacteria and may reflect a need to integrate multiple signals in controlling regulatory protein activity and/or perhaps a need to respond to a physical signal(s). In certain nitrogen-fixing organisms of the gamma subgroup of the
    <em>
     Proteobacteria
    </em>
    , for example, expression of the nitrogen fixation or
    <em>
     nif
    </em>
    genes is under the control of the NifA activator, whose activity is, however, modulated by NifL in response to both oxygen and fixed nitrogen (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     31
    </xref>
    ). Apparently, NifL negatively controls NifA activity via a stable protein-protein interaction (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     24
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    ) that is modulated by redox changes (which NifL can sense), ligand binding, and interactions with other proteins (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     31
    </xref>
    ). Similarly, redox and blue light control of expression of photosynthesis genes in
    <em>
     Rhodobacter sphaeroides
    </em>
    is mediated by a repressor, PpsR, whose activity is modulated by the AppA antirepressor that responds to redox and blue light and forms a complex with PpsR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     33
    </xref>
    ). As observed with PA3719 (ArmR) and MexR, AppA-PpsR complex formation abrogates PpsR binding to target DNA (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     33
    </xref>
    ). In addition, the ComA response regulator and transcription factor for competence development in
    <em>
     Bacillus subtilis
    </em>
    is also negatively regulated, by RapC, whose binding to ComA inhibits the latter's DNA-binding activity (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     11
    </xref>
    ). Still, in each of these examples, the effector proteins are large (NifL, 519 amino acids; AppA, 450 amino acids; RapC, 382 amino acids) and capable of ligand and/or cofactor binding (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     31
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     33
    </xref>
    ), something that PA3719 (ArmR), which consists of 52 amino acids, is unlikely to be capable of. Interestingly, a small protein effector/antirepressor reminiscent of ArmR has been described in
    <em>
     Myxococcus xanthus
    </em>
    , where it mediates light inducibility of carotenoid biosynthesis (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     30
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     66
    </xref>
    ). The 111-amino-acid protein, CarS, modulates the activity of a CarA repressor that controls expression of carotenoid biosynthetic genes (
    <em>
     crtEBDC
    </em>
    ) by binding to CarA and preventing the latter's binding to its operator sequence in the
    <em>
     crtEBDC
    </em>
    promoter (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     30
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     66
    </xref>
    ). In contrast to AppA, however, CarS does not respond directly to light; rather, its expression is light inducible and mediated by the ECF sigma factor CarQ, whose release by the anti-sigma factor CarR occurs in response to light (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     34
    </xref>
    ). Other small protein effectors that have been described include SinI, a 56-amino-acid residue antagonist of the SinR negative regulator of sporulation in
    <em>
     B. subtilis
    </em>
    (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ), and the 88-amino-acid Hpr and 85-amino-acid Crh effectors found in low-G+C-content gram-positive bacteria and
    <em>
     Bacillus
    </em>
    sp., respectively, which function as corepressors (with CcpA) in carbon catabolite regulation in these organisms (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     22
    </xref>
    ). While
    <em>
     sinI
    </em>
    expression itself (and SinI activity as an antirepressor) responds to unknown environmental stimuli that promote sporulation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ), the Hpr and Crh effectors are controlled by phosphorylation, with the phosphorylated forms of these proteins only able to bind CcpA and promote repressor binding to target promoters (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     16
    </xref>
    ). PA3719 (
    <em>
     armR
    </em>
    ) expression is under the control of the NalC repressor, and so modulation of NalC by some hitherto unknown signal(s) to effect PA3719 production may be sufficient for PA3719 to act on MexR, although we cannot rule out the possibility that some modification of the antirepressor might also be involved. In any case, the nature of the signal(s) to which NalC responds remains unknown, as do the reasons for MexAB-OprM recruitment under conditions where NalC repression of PA3719 (ArmR) is alleviated. As well, the functional significance of the PA3720 gene that forms an operon with the PA3719 gene is unclear; the deduced protein product of this gene shows no significant homology to any known protein, and no observable phenotype is associated with either overexpression or loss of this gene. One possibility, however, is that it modulates NalC repressor activity in response to the “signals” that require PA3719 and, ultimately,
    <em>
     mexAB-oprM
    </em>
    expression.
   </p>
   <p>
    How PA3719 (ArmR) negatively impacts MexR DNA binding and repression of target gene (
    <em>
     mexR
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     mexAB-oprM
    </em>
    ) expression is uncertain, although the identification of mutations in MexR that compromise its interaction with this effector provides some room for speculation. Three of the six mutations disrupting the PA3719 (ArmR) interaction (L35P, L75P, and I104F) occur in regions of MexR which, if substantially altered by PA3719 binding, would likely alter the structure and/or disposition of the DNA recognition helix α-4. Clearly, this would be expected to adversely impact MexR binding to its operator sequences in the
    <em>
     mexR
    </em>
    -
    <em>
     mexAB-oprM
    </em>
    intergenic region. Still, it is unclear whether PA3719 (ArmR) acts directly on the α-4 helix, thereby interfering with the MexR-DNA interaction, or indirectly by altering the relative positioning of the individual DNA-binding domains of the MexR homodimer. MexR operator binding probably requires that its recognition helices fit into successive major grooves in the DNA, and thus, the spacing between the two recognition helices in the MexR dimer must match the major groove spacing in the target DNA. Thus, one way in which MexR DNA binding might be modulated and its repressor activity controlled is by altering the spacing of the DNA-binding helices (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     28
    </xref>
    ), as has been seen for other repressor proteins (e.g., TetR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     41
    </xref>
    ] and FadR [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     65
    </xref>
    ]).
   </p>
   <p>
    Mutations in MexR distant from α-4 also negatively impact PA3719 (ArmR) binding, and it is impossible to predict with any certainty how these mutations might impact MexR structure and thus compromise PA3719 (ArmR) binding. Significantly, four of six mutations compromising PA3719 (ArmR) binding did not adversely affect MexR repressor activity, indicating that the lack of PA3719 (ArmR) binding is not explained by a gross alteration in the MexR structure but is explained by local perturbations specifically impacting PA3719 (ArmR) binding. This in itself suggests that the DNA-binding and PA3719 (ArmR)-binding domains may, in fact, be separate entities in MexR. This is reminiscent of another MarR family regulator, OhrR, which is involved in organic hydroperoxide resistance in several bacteria and whose effector- and DNA-binding regions are also distinct (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     19
    </xref>
    ), but it is in contrast to MarR (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     68
    </xref>
    ) (and CarA [
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     44
    </xref>
    ]), whose effector- and DNA-binding sites overlap. Ongoing efforts to determine the structure of the PA3719-MexR complex should identify the site of interaction and thus provide insights into the mechanism of action of this protein modulator of MexR activity.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    REFERENCES
   </title>
   <sec>
    <sec>
     1.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Adewoye, L., A. Sutherland, R. Srikumar, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2002. The MexR repressor of the
      <em>
       mexAB-oprM
      </em>
      multidrug efflux operon in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : characterization of mutations compromising activity.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       184
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      4308-4312.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     2.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Aires, J. R., and H. Nikaido.
      </strong>
      2005. Aminoglycosides are captured from both periplasm and cytoplasm by the AcrD multidrug efflux transporter of
      <em>
       Escherichia coli
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       187
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1923-1929.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     3.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Alekshun, M. N., and S. B. Levy.
      </strong>
      1999. Alteration of the repressor activity of MarR, the negative regulator of the
      <em>
       Escherichia coli marRAB
      </em>
      locus, by multiple chemicals in vitro.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       181
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      4669-4672.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     4.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Alekshun, M. N., S. B. Levy, T. R. Mealy, B. A. Seaton, and J. F. Head.
      </strong>
      2001. The crystal structure of MarR, a regulator of multiple antibiotic resistance, at 2.3 Å resolution.
      <span>
       Nat. Struct. Biol.
      </span>
      <span>
       8
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      710-714.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     5.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Ausubel, F. M., R. Brent, R. E. Kingston, D. D. Moore, J. G. Seidman, J. A. Smith, and K. Struhl.
      </strong>
      1992.
      <span>
       Short protocols in molecular biology
      </span>
      , 2nd ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., New York, NY.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     6.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Bai, U., I. Mandic-Mulec, and I. Smith.
      </strong>
      1993. SinI modulates the activity of SinR, a developmental switch protein of
      <em>
       Bacillus subtilis
      </em>
      , by protein-protein interaction.
      <span>
       Genes Dev.
      </span>
      <span>
       7
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      139-148.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     7.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Barcak, G. J., M. S. Chandler, R. J. Redfield, and J. F. Tomb.
      </strong>
      1991. Genetic systems in
      <em>
       Haemophilus influenzae
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Methods Enzymol.
      </span>
      <span>
       204
      </span>
      :321-342.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     8.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Cao, L., R. Srikumar, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2004. MexAB-OprM hyperexpression in NalC type multidrug resistant
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : identification and characterization of the
      <em>
       nalC
      </em>
      gene encoding a repressor of PA3720-PA3719.
      <span>
       Mol. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       53
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1423-1436.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     9.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Choi, K. H., A. Kumar, and H. P. Schweizer.
      </strong>
      2006. A 10-min method for preparation of highly electrocompetent
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      cells: application for DNA fragment transfer between chromosomes and plasmid transformation.
      <span>
       J. Microbiol. Methods
      </span>
      <span>
       64
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      391-397.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     10.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Chuanchuen, R., R. R. Karkhoff-Schweizer, and H. P. Schweizer.
      </strong>
      2003. High-level triclosan resistance in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      is solely a result of efflux.
      <span>
       Am. J. Infect. Control
      </span>
      <span>
       31
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      124-127.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     11.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Core, L., and M. Perego.
      </strong>
      2003. TPR-mediated interaction of RapC with ComA inhibits response regulator-DNA binding for competence development in
      <em>
       Bacillus subtilis
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Mol. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       49
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1509-1522.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     12.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Dmitrova, M., G. Younes-Cauet, P. Oertel-Buchheit, D. Porte, M. Schnarr, and M. Granger-Schnarr.
      </strong>
      1998. A new LexA-based genetic system for monitoring and analyzing protein heterodimerization in
      <em>
       Escherichia coli
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Mol. Gen. Genet.
      </span>
      <span>
       257
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      205-212.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     13.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Evans, K., L. Adewoye, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2001. MexR repressor of the
      <em>
       mexAB-oprM
      </em>
      multidrug efflux operon of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : identification of MexR binding sites in the
      <em>
       mexA-mexR
      </em>
      intergenic region.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       183
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      807-812.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     14.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Evans, K., L. Passador, R. Srikumar, E. Tsang, J. Nezezon, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1998. Influence of the MexAB-OprM multidrug efflux system on quorum-sensing in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       180
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      5443-5447.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     15.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Galan, B., A. Kolb, J. M. Sanz, J. L. Garcia, and M. A. Prieto.
      </strong>
      2003. Molecular determinants of the
      <em>
       hpa
      </em>
      regulatory system of
      <em>
       Escherichia coli
      </em>
      : the HpaR repressor.
      <span>
       Nucleic Acids Res.
      </span>
      <span>
       31
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      6598-6609.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     16.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Galinier, A., J. Deutscher, and I. Martin-Verstraete.
      </strong>
      1999. Phosphorylation of either Crh or HPr mediates binding of CcpA to the
      <em>
       Bacillus subtilis xyn cre
      </em>
      and catabolite repression of the
      <em>
       xyn
      </em>
      operon.
      <span>
       J. Mol. Biol.
      </span>
      <span>
       286
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      307-314.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     17.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Gorham, H. C., S. J. McGowan, P. R. Robson, and D. A. Hodgson.
      </strong>
      1996. Light-induced carotenogenesis in
      <em>
       Myxococcus xanthus
      </em>
      : light-dependent membrane sequestration of ECF sigma factor CarQ by anti-sigma factor CarR.
      <span>
       Mol. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       19
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      171-186.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     18.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Hirakata, Y., R. Srikumar, K. Poole, N. Gotoh, T. Suematsu, S. Kohno, S. Kamihira, R. E. Hancock, and D. P. Speert.
      </strong>
      2002. Multidrug efflux systems play an important role in the invasiveness of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Exp. Med.
      </span>
      <span>
       196
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      109-118.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     19.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Hong, M., M. Fuangthong, J. D. Helmann, and R. G. Brennan.
      </strong>
      2005. Structure of an OhrR-
      <em>
       ohrA
      </em>
      operator complex reveals the DNA binding mechanism of the MarR family.
      <span>
       Mol. Cell
      </span>
      <span>
       20
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      131-141.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     20.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Jalal, S., and B. Wretlind.
      </strong>
      1998. Mechanisms of quinolone resistance in clinical strains of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Microb. Drug Resist.
      </span>
      <span>
       4
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      257-261.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     21.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Jo, J. T., F. S. Brinkman, and R. E. Hancock.
      </strong>
      2003. Aminoglycoside efflux in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : involvement of novel outer membrane proteins.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       47
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1101-1111.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     22.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Jones, B. E., V. Dossonnet, E. Kuster, W. Hillen, J. Deutscher, and R. E. Klevit.
      </strong>
      1997. Binding of the catabolite repressor protein CcpA to its DNA target is regulated by phosphorylation of its corepressor HPr.
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem.
      </span>
      <span>
       272
      </span>
      :26530-26535.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     23.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Keen, N. T., S. Tamaki, D. Kobayashi, and D. Trollinger.
      </strong>
      1988. Improved broad-host-range plasmids for DNA cloning in Gram-negative bacteria.
      <span>
       Gene
      </span>
      <span>
       70
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      191-197.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     24.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Lei, S., L. Pulakat, and N. Gavini.
      </strong>
      1999. Genetic analysis of
      <em>
       nif
      </em>
      regulatory genes by utilizing the yeast two-hybrid system detected formation of a NifL-NifA complex that is implicated in regulated expression of
      <em>
       nif
      </em>
      genes.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       181
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      6535-6539.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     25.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Li, X. Z., K. Poole, and H. Nikaido.
      </strong>
      2003. Contributions of MexAB-OprM and an EmrE homologue to intrinsic resistance of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      to aminoglycosides and dyes.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       47
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      27-33.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     26.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Li, X. Z., L. Zhang, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1998. Role of the multidrug efflux systems of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      in organic solvent tolerance.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       180
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      2987-2991.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     27.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Li, X. Z., and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1999. Organic solvent-tolerant mutants of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      display multiple antibiotic resistance.
      <span>
       Can. J. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       45
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      18-22.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     28.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Lim, D., K. Poole, and N. C. Strynadka.
      </strong>
      2002. Crystal structure of the MexR repressor from the multidrug efflux operon in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem.
      </span>
      <span>
       277
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      29253-29259.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     29.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Llanes, C., D. Hocquet, C. Vogne, D. Benali-Baitich, C. Neuwirth, and P. Plesiat.
      </strong>
      2004. Clinical strains of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      overproducing MexAB-OprM and MexXY efflux pumps simultaneously.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       48
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1797-1802.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     30.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Lopez-Rubio, J. J., M. Elias-Arnanz, S. Padmanabhan, and F. J. Murillo.
      </strong>
      2002. A repressor-antirepressor pair links two loci controlling light-induced carotenogenesis in
      <em>
       Myxococcus xanthus
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem.
      </span>
      <span>
       277
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      7262-7270.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     31.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Martinez-Argudo, I., R. Little, N. Shearer, P. Johnson, and R. Dixon.
      </strong>
      2004. The NifL-NifA system: a multidomain transcriptional regulatory complex that integrates environmental signals.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       186
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      601-610.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     32.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Masuda, N., and S. Ohya.
      </strong>
      1992. Cross-resistance to meropenem, cephems, and quinolones in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       36
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1847-1851.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     33.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Masuda, S., and C. E. Bauer.
      </strong>
      2002. AppA is a blue light photoreceptor that antirepresses photosynthesis gene expression in
      <em>
       Rhodobacter sphaeroides
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Cell
      </span>
      <span>
       110
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      613-623.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     34.
     <span>
      <strong>
       McGowan, S. J., H. C. Gorham, and D. A. Hodgson.
      </strong>
      1993. Light-induced carotenogenesis in
      <em>
       Myxococcus xanthus
      </em>
      : DNA sequence analysis of the
      <em>
       carR
      </em>
      region.
      <span>
       Mol. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       10
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      713-735.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     35.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Miller, J. H.
      </strong>
      1992.
      <span>
       A short course in bacterial genetics. A laboratory manual and handbook for
       <em>
        Escherichia coli
       </em>
       and related bacteria
      </span>
      , p. 72-74. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Plainview, NY.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     36.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Mima, T., H. Sekiya, T. Mizushima, T. Kuroda, and T. Tsuchiya.
      </strong>
      2005. Gene cloning and properties of the RND-type multidrug efflux pumps MexPQ-OpmE and MexMN-OprM from
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Microbiol. Immunol.
      </span>
      <span>
       49
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      999-1002.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     37.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Money, T., T. Jones, R. Dixon, and S. Austin.
      </strong>
      1999. Isolation and properties of the complex between the enhancer binding protein NifA and the sensor NifL.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       181
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      4461-4468.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     38.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Morales, V. M., A. Backman, and M. Bagdasarian.
      </strong>
      1991. A series of wide-host-range low-copy-number vectors that allow direct screening for recombinants.
      <span>
       Gene
      </span>
      <span>
       97
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      39-47.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     39.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Morita, Y., L. Cao, G. Gould, M. B. Avison, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2006.
      <em>
       nalD
      </em>
      encodes a second repressor of the
      <em>
       mexAB-oprM
      </em>
      multidrug efflux operon of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       188
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      8649-8654.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     40.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Murakami, S., and A. Yamaguchi.
      </strong>
      2003. Multidrug-exporting secondary transporters.
      <span>
       Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.
      </span>
      <span>
       13
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      443-452.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     41.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Orth, P., D. Schnappinger, W. Hillen, W. Saenger, and W. Hinrichs.
      </strong>
      2000. Structural basis of gene regulation by the tetracycline inducible Tet repressor-operator system.
      <span>
       Nat. Struct. Biol.
      </span>
      <span>
       7
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      215-219.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     42.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Palmer, M.
      </strong>
      2003. Efflux of cytoplasmically acting antibiotics from gram-negative bacteria: periplasmic substrate capture by multicomponent efflux pumps inferred from their cooperative action with single-component transporters.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       185
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      5287-5289.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     43.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Pearson, J. P., C. Van Delden, and B. H. Iglewski.
      </strong>
      1999. Active efflux and diffusion are involved in transport of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      cell-to-cell signals.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       181
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1203-1210.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     44.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Perez-Marin, M. C., J. J. Lopez-Rubio, F. J. Murillo, M. Elias-Arnanz, and S. Padmanabhan.
      </strong>
      2004. The N terminus of
      <em>
       Myxococcus xanthus
      </em>
      CarA repressor is an autonomously folding domain that mediates physical and functional interactions with both operator DNA and antirepressor protein.
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem.
      </span>
      <span>
       279
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      33093-33103.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     45.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K.
      </strong>
      2001. Multidrug efflux pumps and antimicrobial resistance in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      and related organisms.
      <span>
       J. Mol. Microbiol. Biotechnol.
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      255-264.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     46.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K.
      </strong>
      2004. Efflux pumps, p. 635-674.
      <em>
       In
      </em>
      J.-L. Ramos (ed.),
      <em>
       Pseudomonas
      </em>
      ,
      <span>
       vol. I
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Genomics, life style and molecular architecture
      </span>
      . Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers, New York, NY.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     47.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K.
      </strong>
      2004. Efflux-mediated multiresistance in Gram-negative bacteria.
      <span>
       Clin. Microbiol. Infect.
      </span>
      <span>
       10
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      12-26.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     48.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K.
      </strong>
      2005. Efflux-mediated antimicrobial resistance 2007.
      <span>
       J. Antimicrob. Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       56
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      20-51.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     49.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K.
      </strong>
      p. 304-324.
      <span>
       Antimicrobial and stress resistance
      </span>
      .
      <em>
       In
      </em>
      M. Ehrmann (ed.), The periplasm. ASM Press, Washington, DC.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     50.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Poole, K., K. Tetro, Q. Zhao, S. Neshat, D. Heinrichs, and N. Bianco.
      </strong>
      1996. Expression of the multidrug resistance operon
      <em>
       mexA-mexB-oprM
      </em>
      in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      :
      <em>
       mexR
      </em>
      encodes a regulator of operon expression.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       40
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      2021-2028.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     51.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Providenti, M. A., and R. C. Wyndham.
      </strong>
      2001. Identification and functional characterization of CbaR, a MarR-like modulator of the
      <em>
       cbaABC
      </em>
      -encoded chlorobenzoate catabolism pathway.
      <span>
       Appl. Environ. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       67
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      3530-3541.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     52.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Redly, A., and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2003. Pyoverdine-mediated regulation of FpvA synthesis in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : involvement of a probable ECF sigma factor, FpvI.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       185
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1261-1265.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     53.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Redly, G. A., and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2005. FpvIR control of
      <em>
       fpvA
      </em>
      ferric pyoverdine receptor gene expression in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      : demonstration of an interaction between FpvI and FpvR and identification of mutations in each compromising this interaction.
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       187
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      5648-5657.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     54.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Saito, K., S. Eda, H. Maseda, and T. Nakae.
      </strong>
      2001. Molecular mechanism of MexR-mediated regulation of MexAB-OprM efflux pump expression in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       FEMS Microbiol. Lett.
      </span>
      <span>
       195
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      23-28.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     55.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Saito, K., H. Yoneyama, and T. Nakae.
      </strong>
      1999.
      <em>
       nalB
      </em>
      -type mutations causing the overexpression of the MexAB-OprM efflux pump are located in the
      <em>
       mexR
      </em>
      gene of the
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      chromosome.
      <span>
       FEMS Microbiol. Lett.
      </span>
      <span>
       179
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      67-72.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     56.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Sambrook, J., and D. W. Russell.
      </strong>
      2001.
      <span>
       Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual
      </span>
      , 3rd ed. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     57.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Sanchez, P., F. Rojo, and J. L. Martinez.
      </strong>
      2002. Transcriptional regulation of
      <em>
       mexR
      </em>
      , the repressor of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa mexAB-oprM
      </em>
      multidrug efflux pump.
      <span>
       FEMS Microbiol. Lett.
      </span>
      <span>
       207
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      63-68.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     58.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Schweizer, H. P.
      </strong>
      1998. Intrinsic resistance to inhibitors of fatty acid biosynthesis in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      is due to efflux: application of a novel technique for generation of unmarked chromosomal mutations for the study of efflux systems.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      394-398.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     59.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Sheu, D. S., Y. T. Wang, and C. Y. Lee.
      </strong>
      2000. Rapid detection of polyhydroxyalkanoate-accumulating bacteria isolated from the environment by colony PCR.
      <span>
       Microbiology
      </span>
      <span>
       146
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      2019-2025.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     60.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Sobel, M. L., D. Hocquet, L. Cao, P. Plesiat, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2005. Mutations in PA3574 (
      <em>
       nalD
      </em>
      ) lead to increased MexAB-OprM expression and multidrug resistance in lab and clinical isolates of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       49
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1782-1786.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     61.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Srikumar, R., T. Kon, N. Gotoh, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1998. Expression of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      multidrug efflux pumps MexA-MexB-OprM and MexC-MexD-OprJ in a multidrug-sensitive
      <em>
       Escherichia coli
      </em>
      strain.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      65-71.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     62.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Srikumar, R., X.-Z. Li, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1997. Inner membrane efflux components are responsible for the β-lactam specificity of multidrug efflux pumps in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       179
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      7875-7881.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     63.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Srikumar, R., C. J. Paul, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      2000. Influence of mutations in the
      <em>
       mexR
      </em>
      repressor gene on expression of the MexA-MexB-OprM multidrug efflux system of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Bacteriol.
      </span>
      <span>
       182
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1410-1414.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     64.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Srikumar, R., and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1999. Demonstration of ethidium bromide efflux by multiresistant pumps of
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       Clin. Microbiol. Infect.
      </span>
      <span>
       5
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      5S58-5S59.
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     65.
     <span>
      <strong>
       van Aalten, D. M., C. C. DiRusso, and J. Knudsen.
      </strong>
      2001. The structural basis of acyl coenzyme A-dependent regulation of the transcription factor FadR.
      <span>
       EMBO J.
      </span>
      <span>
       20
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      2041-2050.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     66.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Whitworth, D. E., and D. A. Hodgson.
      </strong>
      2001. Light-induced carotenogenesis in
      <em>
       Myxococcus xanthus
      </em>
      : evidence that CarS acts as an anti-repressor of CarA.
      <span>
       Mol. Microbiol.
      </span>
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      809-819.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     67.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Wilkinson, S. P., and A. Grove.
      </strong>
      2004. HucR, a novel uric acid-responsive member of the MarR family of transcriptional regulators from
      <em>
       Deinococcus radiodurans
      </em>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem.
      </span>
      <span>
       279
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      51442-51450.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     68.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Wilkinson, S. P., and A. Grove.
      </strong>
      2006. Ligand-responsive transcriptional regulation by members of the MarR family of winged helix proteins.
      <span>
       Curr. Issues Mol. Biol.
      </span>
      <span>
       8
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      51-62.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     69.
     <span>
      <strong>
       Zhao, Q., X.-Z. Li, R. Srikumar, and K. Poole.
      </strong>
      1998. Contribution of outer membrane efflux protein OprM to antibiotic resistance in
      <em>
       Pseudomonas aeruginosa
      </em>
      independent of MexAB.
      <span>
       Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
      </span>
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      <strong>
       :
      </strong>
      1682-1688.
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>