<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC33429
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Three-dimensional reconstruction of the recombinant type 3
 ryanodine receptor and localization of its amino terminus
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     Recombinant type 3 ryanodine receptor (RyR3) has been purified in
 quantities sufficient for structural characterization by cryoelectron
 microscopy and three-dimensional (3D) reconstruction. Two cDNAs were
 prepared and expressed in HEK293 cells, one encoding the wild-type RyR3
 and the other encoding RyR3 containing glutathione
     <em>
      S
     </em>
     -transferase (GST) fused to its amino terminus
 (GST-RyR3). RyR3 was purified from detergent-solubilized transfected
 cells by affinity chromatography using 12.6-kDa FK506-binding protein
 in the form of a GST fusion as the affinity ligand. Purification of
 GST-RyR3 was achieved by affinity chromatography by using
 glutathione-Sepharose. Purified recombinant RyR3 and GST-RyR3 proteins
 exhibited high-affinity [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine binding that was
 sensitive to activation by Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     and caffeine and to
 inhibition by Mg
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     . 3D reconstructions of both recombinant
 RyR3 and GST-RyR3 appeared very similar to that of the native RyR3
 purified from bovine diaphragm. Comparison of the 3D reconstructions of
 RyR3 and GST-RyR3 revealed that the GST domains and, hence, the amino
 termini of the RyR3 subunits are located in the “clamp”
 structures that form the corners of the square-shaped cytoplasmic
 region of homotetrameric RyR3. This study describes the 3D
 reconstruction of a recombinant ryanodine receptor and it demonstrates
 the potential of this technology for characterizing functional and
 structural perturbations introduced by site-directed mutagenesis.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     recombinant membrane protein, cryoelectron
 microscopy, single-particle image processing
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Materials and Methods
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Construction of RyR3 and GST-RyR3 cDNA.
    </title>
    <p>
     The cloning and construction of cDNAs encoding the rabbit smooth
 muscle RyR3 have been described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ). The cDNA encoding the
 GST was amplified from the pGEX-3X vector by PCR. A unique
     <em>
      Nhe
     </em>
     I site was introduced into the forward primer, and a
 unique
     <em>
      Asc
     </em>
     I site was added into the reverse primer. A unique
     <em>
      Asc
     </em>
     I site also was introduced into the RyR3 cDNA just before
 the start codon. The
     <em>
      Nhe
     </em>
     I-
     <em>
      Asc
     </em>
     I GST fragment was
 linked with the
     <em>
      Asc
     </em>
     I-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RV(555) RyR3 fragment.
 The resulting
     <em>
      Nhe
     </em>
     I-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RV GST-RyR3 fusion fragment
 then was used to replace the
     <em>
      Nhe
     </em>
     I-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RV fragment
 in the full-length RyR3 cDNA to form the GST-RyR3 expression vector.
 The GST-RyR3 construct also contained the c-myc tag, EQKLISEEDL,
 inserted after Glu-4318. The c-myc tag first was inserted into the
     <em>
      Spe
     </em>
     I(12795)-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI(13353) cDNA fragment in
 pBluescript by the overlap-extension method. The
     <em>
      Spe
     </em>
     I(12795)-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI(13353) (c-myc) was linked with
 the
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI(11833)-
     <em>
      Spe
     </em>
     I(12795) fragment to form
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI(11833)-
     <em>
      Eco
     </em>
     RI(13353) (c-myc), which
 subsequently was used to replace the corresponding fragment in
 GST-RyR3. The sequences of all PCR fragments were verified by DNA
 sequencing.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Expression and Purification of RyR3 and GST-RyR3.
    </title>
    <p>
     HEK293 cells were transfected with RyR3 or GST-RyR3 cDNA as described
 previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      25
     </xref>
     ). The transfected cells were lysed by the addition
 of a lysis buffer [20 mM Pipes (pH 7.2 with NaOH)/130 mM
 NaCl/5 mM Na
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     AMP/0.5 mM
 EGTA/0.7 mM CaCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     /2.5 mM
 DTT/1% CHAPS/0.5% egg lecithin/protease
 inhibitor mix (1 mM benzamidine/2 μg/ml leupeptin/2
 μg/ml pepstatin A/2 μg/ml aprotinin/0.5 mM PMSF)]
 and incubation on ice for 1 h. Insoluble materials were removed,
 and sucrose (300 mM, final) and NaCl (400 mM, final) were added to the
 supernatant (cell lysate). Glutathione-Sepharose beads (80 μl) bound
 with 225 μg of GST–12.6-kDa FKBP (FKBP12.6) were added to the cell
 lysate. For the purification of GST-RyR3, only glutathione-Sepharose
 beads were added. The mixture was incubated at 5°C with rotation for
 2 days. The beads were collected by centrifugation and washed four
 times with the lysis buffer containing 0.5% CHAPS and 0.25% egg
 lecithin. RyR3 or GST-RyR3 was eluted from the beads by incubating with
 an eluting buffer (20 mM Pipes, pH 7.2/400 mM NaCl/5 mM
 Na
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     AMP/300 mM sucrose/0.5 mM
 EGTA/0.7 mM CaCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     /2.5 mM
 DTT/0.4% CHAPS/0.16% egg lecithin/protease
 inhibitor mix/50 mM glutathione) for 10 min. For one preparation
 of RyR3, the elution buffer contained 60 μM FK506 instead of
 glutathione. Eluates were aliquoted, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and
 stored at −90°C.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]Ryanodine Binding.
    </title>
    <p>
     Equilibrium [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine binding to purified
 recombinant RyRs was carried out as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     ), with
 some modifications. [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]Ryanodine binding was
 carried out in a total volume of 300 μl of binding solution
 containing 24–153 ng of purified recombinant proteins, 500 mM KCl, 25
 mM Tris, 50 mM Hepes (pH 7.4), 0.8 mM CaCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , 2.5
 mM caffeine, 0.4–33 nM [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine, and the
 protease inhibitor mix at 37°C for 2 h. The binding mix was
 diluted with 5 ml of ice-cold washing buffer containing 25 mM
 Tris⋅HCl (pH 8.0) and 250 mM KCl and was filtered immediately
 through Whatman GF/B filters presoaked with 1%
 polyethylenimine. The filters were washed, and the radioactivity
 associated with the filters was determined by liquid scintillation
 counting. Nonspecific binding was determined by measuring
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine binding in the presence of 30
 μM unlabeled ryanodine. All binding assays were done in duplicate.
 For determining the effects of Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     , caffeine,
 and Mg
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     , [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine
 binding was carried out in a binding buffer containing 500 mM KCl, 25
 mM Tris, 50 mM Hepes (pH 7.4), 0.5 mM EGTA, 0.35 mM
 CaCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , 15 nM
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine, and the protease inhibitor mix,
 plus either 0.8 mM Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     , 2.5 mM caffeine, or 5 mM
 Mg
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     as indicated.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Cryo-EM and Image Processing.
    </title>
    <p>
     The purified RyR3 or GST-RyR3 was diluted 2- to 3-fold with EM diluting
 buffer (20 mM Pipes, pH 7.2/400 mM KCl/5 mM
 Na
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     AMP/0.7 mM
 CaCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     /0.5 mM EGTA/0.5%
 CHAPS/2 mM DTT/2 μg/ml leupeptin). A 5-μl aliquot was
 applied to a carbon-coated holey EM grid (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ). Specimen grids were
 transferred to a Gatan cryoholder and examined in a Philips EM 420
 transmission electron microscope (Eindhoven, the Netherlands). The
 operating voltage was 100 kV, the electron dose was estimated at 8–10
 electrons/Å
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     , and the temperature of the
 specimen grid was maintained at −178 ± 2°C. Electron
 micrographs were recorded at a magnification of ×38,600 and a defocus
 value of 1.5–2.0 μm. Selected micrographs were digitized by using a
 Eurocore Hi-Scan microdensitometer (Saint-Denis, France). Image
 processing was accomplished by using the
     <span>
      spider
     </span>
     /
     <span>
      web
     </span>
     software package (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      28
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     3D reconstructions were obtained by following the projection-matching
 procedure (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      29
     </xref>
     ). An initial set of 48 projection images that covered
 evenly the entire angular space was generated from a previous 3D
 reconstruction of native RyR1. For the recombinant RyR3
 (glutathione-eluted), RyR3 (FK506-eluted), and GST-RyR3, a total of
 7,690, 5,680, and 11,100 particle images were selected, respectively.
 After “matching” particles to the projection images by
 cross-correlation, 5,603, 5,272, and 7,101 high-quality particles were
 used to generate the first 3D reconstructions. For subsequent
 iterations, a set of 1,126 projection images was generated from the
 current 3D reconstruction to more finely sample the angular space, the
 particles were rematched to these projection images, and a new
 reconstruction was computed. The cycle was performed three to four
 times until the reconstruction stabilized. The final 3D reconstructions
 of RyR3 (glutathione-eluted), RyR3 (FK506-eluted), and GST-RyR3 were
 computed from 3,598, 4,722, and 5,893 particles, respectively. The
 final resolutions were estimated to be 34Å by Fourier shell
 correlation, using a cut-off of 0.5 for both RyR3s and GST-RyR3 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     -Release Measurements and Immunoblotting.
    </title>
    <p>
     Cytoplasmic Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     in transfected HEK293 cells was
 measured with the fluorescent Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     indicator dye
 fluo-3, and PAGE and immunoblotting were carried out as described
 previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Purification and Functional Properties of the Recombinant RyR3 and
 GST-RyR3.
    </title>
    <p>
     Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     shows SDS/PAGE
 of the affinity-purified RyRs. A high-molecular-weight band was
 detected clearly in both the RyR3 and GST-RyR3 samples (unless
 specified otherwise, RyR3 will refer to recombinant type 3 RyR that was
 eluted from glutathione-Sepharose beads by using glutathione rather
 than FK506; see
     <em>
      Materials and Methods
     </em>
     for details). These
 bands corresponded to RyR3 and GST-RyR3, as confirmed by immunoblotting
 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). GST-RyR3 exhibits a lower level of expression and
 slower migration in the gel compared with RyR3. The
 lower-molecular-weight bands present in the RyR3 sample are the intact
 and degraded GST-FKBP12.6. No degradation of either RyR3 or GST-RyR3
 was detected. These data indicate that the recombinant RyR3 and
 GST-RyR3 can be purified in one step by affinity chromatography.
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Purification and functional characterization of recombinant RyR3 and
 GST-RyR3. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Twenty-five microliters of purified
 recombinant RyR3 (glutathione-eluted) and GST-RyR3 were subjected to a
 12% SDS/PAGE gel and stained with Coomassie brilliant
 blue. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) A Western blot of 2 μl of purified RyR3 and
 GST-RyR3 by using the anti-RyR antibody 34C (Affinity BioRegents).
 (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) HEK293 cells were transfected with 10 μg of RyR3
 or GST-RyR3 cDNA. Fluorescence intensity of fluo 3-loaded cells was
 measured before and after additions of 2.5 mM caffeine
 (●) and 50 μM ryanodine (○).
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     To examine whether GST-RyR3 is functional, we determined the response
 to caffeine and ryanodine of Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     release in
 HEK293 cells transfected with the GST-RyR3 cDNA. As shown in Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     , addition of 2.5 mM caffeine to GST-RyR3-transfected
 cells induced a transient increase in the fluorescence signal. A
 further increase in fluorescence was observed on the subsequent
 addition of 50 μM ryanodine. These results are similar to those
 observed with RyR3 transfected cells (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). Neither
 caffeine- nor ryanodine-induced Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     release was
 detected in HEK293 cells transfected with control (pCDNA3) vector DNA
 or no DNA (data not shown). Thus, these results demonstrate that, like
 RyR3, GST-RyR3 forms a functional Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     release
 channel in HEK293 cells.
    </p>
    <p>
     To determine further whether the purified recombinant RyR3 and GST-RyR3
 retain functional activity and regulatory properties, we carried out
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine binding to the purified proteins.
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]Ryanodine binding has been widely used as a
 functional assay for RyR channel activities, because ryanodine binds to
 only the open state of the channel (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      27
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      31
     </xref>
     ). Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     shows that both purified
 RyR3 and GST-RyR3 proteins are capable of binding
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine. The
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     and
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     <sub>
      max
     </sub>
     values are 1.9 nM and 413
 pmol/mg protein for RyR3 and 1.6 nM and 447 pmol/mg
 protein for GST-RyR3, which are similar to those obtained with the
 purified native RyR3 proteins from diaphragm (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ). In addition,
 [
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]ryanodine binding to purified RyR3 and
 GST-RyR3 was activated by Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     and caffeine and
 was inhibited by Mg
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     and
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). These results suggest that the purified recombinant RyR3
 and GST-RyR3 are as functional and regulatable as native purified RyR3.
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Purified recombinant RyR3 and GST-RyR3 proteins exhibit regulated,
 high-affinity [
       <sup>
        3
       </sup>
       H]ryanodine binding. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       )
 Equilibrium [
       <sup>
        3
       </sup>
       H]ryanodine binding to purified RyR
 proteins was carried out as described in
       <em>
        Materials and
 Methods
       </em>
       . The purified GST-RyR3, which was from the same
 preparation that was used for cryo-EM and 3D reconstructions, exhibits
 a
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       of 1.6 nM and
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       <sub>
        max
       </sub>
       of 447 pmol/mg protein.
 Different preparations of purified RyR3 (glutathione-eluted) were used
 for [
       <sup>
        3
       </sup>
       H]ryanodine binding and for 3D reconstructions. The
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       and
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       <sub>
        max
       </sub>
       values for the RyR3 were 1.9 ± 0.17 nM and 413 ± 6.3
 pmol/mg protein (
       <em>
        n
       </em>
       = 2).
 [
       <sup>
        3
       </sup>
       H]Ryanodine binding to purified RyR3 (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       )
 and GST-RyR3 (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) was carried out in the presence of 150
 nM free Ca
       <sup>
        2+
       </sup>
       (control) or with 0.8 mM Ca
       <sup>
        2+
       </sup>
       , 2.5
 mM caffeine, or 5 mM Mg
       <sup>
        2+
       </sup>
       . Data shown are mean ±
 average error from three separate experiments. All binding
 determinations were done in duplicate.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     Cryo-EM of RyR3 and GST-RyR3.
    </title>
    <p>
     Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     shows electron micrographs of
 frozen-hydrated, purified, recombinant RyR3 and GST-RyR3. Both
 micrographs show individual receptors with apparently intact structure.
 For GST-RyR3, aggregated particles were found often (white arrows in
 Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). This could result from cross-linking among
 GST-RyR3 proteins through the N-terminal GST domain, which has the
 potential to dimerize (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      32
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      33
     </xref>
     ). In some of the aggregates, individual
 receptors were resolved (arrowheads in Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ), and in
 these instances the receptors frequently appeared to interact at or
 near their corners with adjoining receptors, indicating that the
 N-terminally fused GST moieties are localized at or near the corners of
 the RyR3's cytoplasmic region. Aggregated particles were seldom found
 for RyR3. All 3D reconstructions were computed by using images of
 isolated RyR3s that were not interacting with other receptors.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Cryo-EM of RyR3 and GST-RyR3. Parts of micrographs of
 glutathione-eluted RyR3 (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) and GST-RyR3
 (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) are shown embedded in a thin layer of vitreous ice.
 Some individual particles are marked with black arrows, and in
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       , the white arrows point to aggregated particles. The
 two arrowheads indicate a receptor in the 4-fold symmetric orientation
 that apparently is part of an oligomer. It appears to be connected to
 adjacent receptors by means of interactions near its corners. (Bar
 = 300Å.)
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Compared with micrographs of RyR1 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ), both expressed (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ) and
 native RyR3s (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ) showed lower contrast and multiple orientations. The
 lower contrast may have been caused by the sucrose and lipid in the
 final EM sample buffer. The recombinant RyR3s in the thin layer of
 vitreous ice showed a higher frequency of non-four-fold symmetric views
 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ) than we have observed for RyR1 in previous studies (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     ). This
 is an advantageous property for 3D reconstruction, but it was still
 necessary to collect some data with the specimen grid tilted by 30°
 to obtain an adequate sampling of orientations.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <p>
    </p>
    <title>
     3D Reconstruction of RyR3 and GST-RyR3: Localization of the Amino
 Terminus of RyR3.
    </title>
    <p>
     3D reconstructions of glutathione-eluted RyR3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ), FK506-eluted RyR3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ), and GST-RyR3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ) are very similar to
 those determined previously for the three RyR isoforms purified from
 native tissues (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     –
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ). The reconstructions consist of two major
 components: a larger cytoplasmic assembly (290 × 290 ×
 130Å) that is composed of at least 10 distinct domains (labeled by
 numerals) and a smaller transmembrane assembly (120 × 120 ×
 70Å, labeled “TA”).
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       3D surface representation of RyR3s and GST-RyR3. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       )
 Glutathione-eluted RyR3 is shown in blue. (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       )
 FK506-eluted RyR3 is shown in green. (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) GST-RyR3 is
 shown in yellow. The 3D reconstructions are shown in three different
 views. (
       <em>
        Left
       </em>
       ) “Top” views of the cytoplasmic
 surface, which interacts with the transverse-tubule in muscle.
 (
       <em>
        Center
       </em>
       ) “Bottom” views of the surface that would
 face the sarcoplasmic reticulum lumen. (
       <em>
        Right
       </em>
       )
 “Side” views. TA, transmembrane assembly. The numerals on the
 cytoplasmic assembly indicate the distinguishable domains as numbered
 previously (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        11
       </xref>
       ).
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Depending on the method of elution, RyR3 could be purified with or
 without GST-FKBP12.6. Because glutathione dissociates the
 GST-FKBP12.6/RyR3 complex from glutathione-Sepharose,
 glutathione-eluted RyR3 contains both RyR3 and GST-FKBP12.6. On the
 other hand, because FK506 dissociates RyR3 from GST-FKBP12.6 bound to
 glutathione-Sepharose, FK506-eluted RyR3 should be devoid of
 GST-FKBP12.6. One might expect then that the glutathione-eluted RyR3
 would have GST-FKBP12.6 bound to it, which would contribute additional
 density to its 3D map. This apparently is not the case. Comparison of
 the 3D reconstructions of glutathione-eluted RyR3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ) and of FK506-eluted RyR3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     )
 does not reveal any significant differences in either the known
 FKBP-binding site (between domains 3 and 9, as located on RyR1; ref.
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ) or anywhere else. This result is not entirely unexpected because
 there is evidence that RyR3 does not bind FKBP with high affinity (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      34
     </xref>
     ). Thus, the interaction of GST-FKBP12.6 with RyR3 apparently is not
 strong enough to be preserved after elution and cryo-EM under our
 experimental conditions.
    </p>
    <p>
     Comparison of the reconstructions of the recombinant RyR3 and GST-RyR3
 revealed some structural differences. In Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     , the two reconstructions
 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     and
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ) are aligned and superimposed.
 The 3D volume of RyR3 is shown in solid blue and that of GST-RyR3 is
 shown in transparent yellow. The main difference is located in each of
 the corners of the cytoplasmic assembly (the so-called “clamp”
 regions), in the middle of the region defined by domains 7–10
 (indicated with a red star). There are some other, smaller differences
 of less certain significance (e.g., in or near domains 1, 3, and 10).
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 5
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Comparison of RyR3 and GST-RyR3. (
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) 3D reconstructions
 (RyR3 in solid blue and GST-RyR3 in transparent yellow) that were
 mutually aligned and superimposed. A red star in one of the clamp
 regions indicates the major difference between the two reconstructions.
 (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Difference map. The differences (shown in red) were
 obtained by subtracting the 3D volume of the RyR3 from the GST-RyR3
 reconstruction.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Comparison of the two surface representations shown in Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     may give a misleading impression of the significance of
 differences between them because the magnitudes of the differences are
 not indicated. Therefore, we examined the differences in more detail by
 subtracting the 3D volume of RyR3 from that of GST-RyR3. The difference
 map shown in Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     (red regions) confirms that the excess
 density present in the clamps of GST-RyR3 is indeed the most
 significant difference from RyR3. The absolute values of the density
 differences in this region are substantially higher than the threshold
 density used to create the surface representations (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     ), and the
 volume of the region at this density threshold matches approximately
 that expected for GST [based on
     <em>
      M
     </em>
     <sub>
      r
     </sub>
     ≈ 26 (32) and assuming a density of 1.37
 g/cm
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      11
     </xref>
     )]. We attribute the density
 present in the clamp regions of the GST-RyR3 to the GST, and,
 therefore, the amino terminus of RyR3 must lie in the clamps.
    </p>
    <p>
     A minor difference, located in the vicinity of domain 3 (Fig.
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      None
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
 Left
     </em>
     ), appears to represent only about one-fourth of the volume
 corresponding to the main difference in the clamp regions. It seems
 unlikely that this region corresponds to the GST portion of GST-RyR3.
 Its small size indicates that it is near the limit of detection, and
 its significance therefore is uncertain. Furthermore, a region of
 negative difference was present nearby (not shown), indicating that if
 this difference is significant, it more likely represents a
 conformational change rather than the net addition of mass contributed
 by the GST (in this context, it is important to point out that only a
 positive difference was detected in the clamp region). If this is so,
 then the minor difference possibly was caused by the 10-residue c-myc
 insertion beginning at Glu-4318 and/or the N terminus-fused GST.
 It is highly unlikely that the main difference in the clamp region is
 due to the c-myc insertion. An insertion of this size is not expected
 to be detectable at the resolution achieved in this study. Furthermore,
 we recently have purified wild-type RyR2 and RyR2 containing the same
 c-myc insertion as present in GST-RyR3. The 3D reconstructions
 essentially were identical, and structural alterations resulting from
 the c-myc insertion were not detectable. More importantly, no
 differences were found in the clamp regions, which confirms our
 interpretation that the excess density present in the clamps of
 GST-RyR3 is due to the GST rather than to the c-myc insert
 (Z.L., J.Z., S.R.W.C., and T.W., unpublished
 results).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    This study describes the purification of functional recombinant
 RyRs that are suitable for structural characterization by cryo-EM. All
 previous 3D reconstructions have been carried out on RyRs that were
 purified from native tissues. It now should be feasible to genetically
 modify the amino acid sequence of the RyR and to determine the effects
 of such modifications on RyR structure by cryo-EM. As an example of
 this type of application, we have localized the amino termini of the
 RyR3 on the receptor's 3D structure by determining a reconstruction of
 a modified RyR3 in which a GST domain is fused to its N terminus.
   </p>
   <p>
    Previously, cryo-EM has been used to determine the binding locations of
 RyR modulators such as calmodulin and FKBP and to identify
 RyR domains that undergo movements associated with channel opening and
 closing (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     14
    </xref>
    –
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     18
    </xref>
    ). The amino acid residues involved in these processes,
 however, have yet to be identified. One way to obtain this information
 is to determine reconstructions of RyRs in complex with antibodies
 whose epitopes have been characterized (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     35
    </xref>
    ). However, RyR is an
 extremely large membrane protein containing ≈5,000 aa residues per
 protomer; to comprehensively map the sequence for surface-exposed
 regions using sequence-specific antibodies would be an arduous
 undertaking. Alternatively, as illustrated in this paper, it is
 possible to add sufficient protein mass at a defined location in the
 sequence to allow its detection in 3D reconstructions. This approach
 recently has been used successfully in the studies of some large,
 multisubunit complexes (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     36
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     37
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The GST-RyR3 construct used in this study was engineered to contain,
 after residue Glu-4318, a 10-residue insertion corresponding a well
 characterized epitope derived from the protein, c-myc. Little, if any,
 perturbation of the receptor's structure by the insertion was apparent
 in the 3D reconstruction at the resolution achieved (≈35Å), and the
 pharmacology and calcium-release activity were retained (Figs.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     C
    </em>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     C
    </em>
    ). We are encouraged by these results
 because they suggest a strategy for systematically mapping the
 locations of surface-exposed segments from RyR's sequence. It should
 be feasible to isolate a set of recombinant RyRs containing c-myc
 insertions at predicted surface-exposed sites and to then form
 immunocomplexes with anti-c-myc antibodies (or Fab fragments). These
 immunocomplexes then could be analyzed by cryo-EM to locate the
 antibodies and, thus, the location of the insertion. This approach is
 perhaps more suitable for localizing surface-exposed regions formed by
 sequences that are not at the amino or carboxyl termini, where
 insertion of a large domain such as GST may disrupt the native
 structure.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although RyR3 is capable of interacting with GST-FKBP12.6
 biochemically, we were unable to detect bound GST-FKBP12.6 in the 3D
 reconstruction of RyR3. The 3D reconstructions of RyR3 in the presence
 and absence of GST-FKBP12.6 are essentially identical (Fig.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     A
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     B
    </em>
    ). Apparently, under our experimental
 conditions, GST-FKBP12.6/RyR3 complexes did not remain
 associated after their elution with glutathione or when they are
 applied to a grid and frozen for cryo-EM. Dissociation of FKBPs from
 RyR1 and RyR3 also has been reported when the RyRs were purified by
 antibody affinity chromatography (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     21
    </xref>
    ). Thus, the differences observed
 in the 3D reconstructions between RyR3 and GST-RyR3 are most unlikely
 to result from the addition of GST-FKBP12.6 to the RyR3 structure.
 Furthermore, had this been the case, the addition of GST-FKBP12.6 to
 the RyR3 structure would have produced a negative volume change rather
 than a positive one in the difference map (Fig.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     B
    </em>
    ), which
 was formed by subtracting the volume of RyR3 from that of GST-RyR3
 (V
    <sub>
     GST-RyR3
    </sub>
    − V
    <sub>
     RyR3
    </sub>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The localization of the RyR3 N terminus reported here is of particular
 interest because a number of mutations that cause the skeletal muscle
 diseases, malignant hyperthermia, and central core disease have been
 found to involve amino acid residues spanning residues 38–614 of the
 RyR1 sequence (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     38
    </xref>
    ). It seems likely that these residues lie within the
 domains comprising the clamp regions, based on our finding that
 N-terminally fused GST lies approximately in the center of the cluster
 of domains that comprise the clamps. Intriguingly, the clamp structures
 have been shown previously to possess different conformations in the
 open and closed states of the channel (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     17
    </xref>
    ). Note that RyR1 and RyR3 are
 sufficiently similar to make such correlations among the isoforms.
 Thus, mutations in this region may affect conformational changes
 associated with channel gating. By the same token, insertion of the GST
 domain into this critical region would be likely to have some impact on
 channel gating, which may explain some observed differences in the
 extent of caffeine-induced Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    release (Fig.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     C
    </em>
    ) and in the degree of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    and
 caffeine activation and Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    inhibition between
 RyR3 and GST-RyR3 (Fig.
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     None
    </xref>
    <em>
     B
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     C
    </em>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In conclusion, RyR3, which is the most difficult RyR isoform to purify
 from natural sources, can be expressed and purified in sufficient
 quantities for biochemical and structural characterization. 3D
 reconstructions at (34 Å)
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    resolution of the
 recombinant RyR3s showed structures essentially identical to those of
 native RyR3. Comparison of the 3D reconstruction of GST-RyR3 with that
 of RyR3 reveals that the amino terminus of RyR3 lies in the clamp
 regions of the cytoplasmic assembly. The methodology developed in this
 study should be useful for mapping the receptor's linear sequence and
 functional domains onto the 3D structure of RyR, thereby providing
 insights into the structural basis of RyR function.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <sec>
    <sec>
     <table>
      <tbody>
       <tr>
        <td>
         RyR3
        </td>
        <td>
         type 3 ryanodine receptor
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         3D
        </td>
        <td>
         three-dimensional
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         GST
        </td>
        <td>
         glutathione
         <em>
          S
         </em>
         -transferase
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         EM
        </td>
        <td>
         electron microscopy
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         FKBP
        </td>
        <td>
         FK506-binding protein
        </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td>
         FKBP12.6
        </td>
        <td>
         12.6-kDa FKBP
        </td>
       </tr>
      </tbody>
     </table>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>