<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC3633811
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    p67phox terminates the phospholipase A2-derived signal for activation of NADPH oxidase (NOX2)
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <p>
     The phospholipase A
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     (PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     )activity of phosphorylated peroxiredoxin 6 (Prdx6) is required for activation of NADPH oxidase (NOX2). We investigated the interaction of Prdx6 with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and its effect on NOX2 activity. With the use of specific antibodies, coimmunoprecipitation of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and phosphorylated Prdx6 was demonstrated with lysates of mouse pulmonary microvascular endothelial cells (MPMVECs) that were stimulated with angiotensin II; the interaction of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with nonphosphorylated Prdx6 was relatively weak. Association of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and phosphoPrdx6 in intact MPMVECs after angiotensin II stimulation was demonstrated by proximity ligation assay and was abolished by U0126, a MAP kinase inhibitor. By isothermal titration calorimetry, p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     bound strongly to phosphoPrdx6 but bound poorly to Prdx6; phosphorylated p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     did not bind to either Prdx6 or phosphoPrdx6. PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of recombinant phosphoPrdx6 was decreased by &gt;98% in the presence of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     ; the calculated dissociation constant (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ) of the p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     : phosphoPrdx6 complex was 65 nM. PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity (MJ33 sensitive) in cell lysates following angiotensin II treatment of MPMVECs was increased by 85% following knockdown of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with siRNA. These data indicate that p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     binds to phosphoPrdx6 and inhibits its PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity, an interaction that could function to terminate the PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     -mediated NOX2 activation signal.—Krishnaiah, S. Y., Dodia, C., Feinstein, S. I., and Fisher, A. B. p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     terminates the phospholipase A
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     -derived signal for activation of NADPH oxidase (NOX2).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     peroxiredoxin 6, reactive oxygen species, protein-protein interactions, pulmonary microvascular endothelium
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    MATERIALS AND METHODS
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Materials
    </title>
    <p>
     1-Palmitoyl, 2-[9,10-
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H]-palmitoyl,
     <em>
      sn
     </em>
     -glycero-3-phosphocholine (
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H-DPPC) was obtained from American Radiolabeled Chemicals (St. Louis, MO, USA). Nonlabeled DPPC, egg phosphatidylcholine (PC), phosphatidylglycerol (PG), and cholesterol were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Birmingham, AL, USA). Cell lysis buffer and the phosphatase inhibitor cocktail (NaF, 2-glycerophosphate, Na
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     VO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     , and EDTA) were from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA, USA). Ang II was from Bachem Bioscience (Torrance, CA, USA). Erk2 MAP kinase was from Upstate (Temecula, CA, USA). The Li
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     salt of 1-hexadecyl-3-trifluoroethylglycero-sn-2-phosphomethanol (MJ33), Sephadex G-100, and protease inhibitor cocktail were from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). Tris-acetate (12%) NuPage-precast gels, buffers for SDS-PAGE, and Probond Ni chelating resin were from Invitrogen Life Technologies (Grand Island, NY, USA). Polyvinylidene difluoride membranes were from Millipore (Billerica, MA, USA). The
     <em>
      in situ
     </em>
     proximity ligation assay kit (Duolink) was from Olink Bioscience (Uppsala, Sweden). Predesigned p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     siRNAs (s70407, here siRNA 1, and s70409, here siRNA 2) with scrambled control siRNA were from Ambion Applied Biosystems (Austin, TX, USA).
    </p>
    <p>
     MPMVECs were obtained from the Insitute for Environmental Medicine Cell Culture Core and maintained in culture, as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      15
     </xref>
     ); these cells had been isolated from C57 BL/6 mice and were used at passage 4. We used the following antibodies: mouse monoclonal anti-p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (BD Biosciences San Jose, CA, USA), rabbit polyclonal anti-p47
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (Upstate); mouse monoclonal anti-IgG and monoclonal anti-GAPDH (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA); polyclonal donkey anti-mouse IR-680 and goat anti-rabbit IR-800Dye secondary antibodies (LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA); and mouse monoclonal anti-phosphothreonine and rabbit polyclonal anti-phosphoserine (Zymed, South San Francisco, CA, USA). Rabbit polyclonal antibodies to His-tagged human Prdx6, mouse Prdx6, and phosphorylated Prdx6 have been described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      16
     </xref>
     ). An antibody that reacted specifically to nonphosphorylated Prdx6 was generated by 21st Century Biochemicals (Marlboro, MA, USA); rabbits were immunized with a peptide, TKPVATPVDWKK, conjugated with an N-terminal cys-aminohexanoic acid moiety and a second construct with a C-terminal cys preceded by an aminohexanoic acid spacer. The immune serum, after repeated depletion by incubation with peptide one containing phosphothreonine replacing threonine at position 6, recognized Prdx6 but not phosphoPrdx6 on Western blot analysis (
     <strong>
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       Fig. 1
      </xref>
      <em>
       A
      </em>
     </strong>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Coimmunoprecipitation with antibodies to phosphoPrdx6 or p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       from MPMVEC lysates.
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) An antibody designed to react with nonphosphorylated Prdx6 was tested for specificity by Western blot. Gels were loaded with equal amounts of recombinant mouse His-tagged Prdx6 and pPrdx6. The Ab was used at 1:30,000 dilution. There is a faint band in the pPrdx6 lane consistent with the presence of ∼10% nonphosphorylated protein in the phosphorylated Prdx6 preparation. MPMVECs without (basal) or with Ang II stimulation (10 μM) were lysed, and the supernatant was incubated with anti-p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       mAb (
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) or anti-phosphoPrdx6 pAb (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) and protein A/G beads; anti-IgG mAb was the control. The immunoprecipitate was analyzed by Western blot using anti-p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       mAb or pAbs that react to Prdx6 (phospho plus nonphosphoPrdx6), only phosphoPrdx6, or only nonphosphoPrdx6. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Cloning, expression, purification, and phosphorylation of recombinant proteins
    </title>
    <p>
     Recombinant human and mouse Prdx6 in pET21b containing a C-terminal His tag were expressed in
     <em>
      Escherichia coli
     </em>
     ; purification on a Ni
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     column has been described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      12
     </xref>
     ). The purity of protein preparations after the Ni
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     column was &gt;90% as confirmed by SDS-PAGE. Purified recombinant His-Prdx6 was phosphorylated using a 6-h incubation with Erk2 MAP kinase in the presence of MgCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     and ATP, as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ). This method results in ∼90% phosphorylation of Prdx6 at T177 as determined by mass spectrometry (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      17
     </xref>
     ). Phosphorylation of Prdx6 was confirmed by Western blot using an antibody that is highly specific for phosphorylation of Prdx6 at T177 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Mouse p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     was cloned from spleen mRNA by reverse transcription and PCR using the forward primer 5′-ATCG
     <span>
      CATATG
     </span>
     TCCCTGGCTGAGGCC-3′ and the reverse primer 5′-
     <span>
      GCGGCCGC
     </span>
     GACTTCTCTGGGAATGCCTTC-3′. The restriction sites used for cloning are underscored. After cleavage with restriction enzymes,
     <em>
      Nde
     </em>
     I for the forward primer and
     <em>
      Not
     </em>
     I for the reverse primer, the mouse p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     coding region was ligated into the pET21b plasmid and expressed with a His tag in the BL21 host strain of
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     . His-tagged mouse p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     was purified on a nickel resin column, as described previously for Prdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      12
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Purified recombinant mouse His-tagged p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     was phosphorylated by incubation of protein (5 μg) at 30°C for 3 h with Erk2 MAP kinase in 50 mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 7.4) containing 10 mM MgCl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , 10 mM dithiothreitol, and 100 μM ATP in a total volume of 40 μl (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ). This reaction results in phosphorylation of T233 in p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      19
     </xref>
     ). Phosphorylation was confirmed by Western blot using antibodies that showed threonine phosphorylation but no serine phosphorylation consistent with published results (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      18
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      19
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Immunoprecipitation
    </title>
    <p>
     Coimmunoprecipitation of proteins from cells was performed as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      13
     </xref>
     ). Briefly, MPMVECs (∼1×10
     <sup>
      7
     </sup>
     ) before and after Ang II treatment were lysed in 1× cell lysis buffer supplemented with protease and phosphatase inhibitor cocktails. Lysates were incubated with slow rotation for 4–6 h with antibodies against p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     , Prdx6, phosphoPrdx6, or nonspecific IgG and then protein A/G-conjugated agarose beads were added to bind the immune complexes formed in the solution. After centrifugation, the pellet was extensively washed with cell lysis buffer to remove unbound proteins, and the components of the precipitated immune complexes were extracted with SDS-PAGE sample buffer; 25 μg of immune precipitate was analyzed by Western blot analysis.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Gel electrophoresis and Western blot analysis
    </title>
    <p>
     Proteins were boiled in reducing sample buffer containing dithiothreitol for 5 min at 95°C before loading onto the SDS-PAGE (10% gels) using an Xcell Surelock minicell system (Bio-Rad, Richmond, CA, USA). After electrophoresis, the protein bands were transferred to Immobilon-P membrane and blocked for 1 h in blocking buffer (LI-COR). The membranes were incubated overnight with primary antibodies; then secondary antibodies were added and blots were analyzed using the two-color Odyssey system (LI-COR).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC)
    </title>
    <p>
     ITC was performed using a VP-ITC titration microcalorimeter (Micro Cal Inc, Northampton, MA, USA) at pH 7. The samples were degassed for 5 min with gentle stirring under vacuum. The calorimeter cell was filled with recombinant His-tagged mouse p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     or phosphop67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (7 μM), and the injection syringe was filled with either His-tagged human Prdx6 or phosphoPrdx6 (57 μM). Titration, performed at 20°C in 50 mM PBS, consisted of 20 injections of 10 μl each at 5-min intervals with continuous stirring at 370 rpm. The heat of reaction per injection (microcalories per second) was determined by integration of the peak areas using Origin 5.0 software (OriginLab Corp., Northampton, MA, USA). The corresponding heat of dilution of Prdx6 or phosphoPrdx6 titrated into the buffer was subtracted as the background.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     assay
    </title>
    <p>
     PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of recombinant human His-tagged Prdx6 and of cell lysates was measured as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ), using mixed unilamellar liposomes as a substrate. For preparation of lysates, cells were suspended in lysis buffer and subjected to 4 or 5 freeze-thaw cycles using liquid nitrogen; lysates were extracted with CHCl
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     , MeOH, and NH
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     OH to remove contaminating lipids before assay (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      21
     </xref>
     ). Liposomes consisting of
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H-DPPC, egg PC, PG, and cholesterol (0.5:0.25:0.1:0.15, mol fraction) were generated by extrusion through a 100-nm-pore membrane under pressure and used as substrate for the reaction. The proteins used for assay were preincubated in Ca
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     -free buffer (50 mM Tris HCl and 1 mM EGTA) at pH 7.0 for 15 min, and then the liposomal substrate was added and incubation at 37°C was continued for an additional 1 h. To study inhibition of PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity, the assay was carried out in the absence and presence of 1 mol% MJ33 added to liposomes (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ). The radiolabeled free fatty acid product was extracted, resolved by thin-layer chromatography using hexane, ether, and acetic acid, and analyzed by scintillation counting. Results were expressed as nanomoles of substrate hydrolyzed on the basis of the specific activity of
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     H-DPPC and normalized for time of incubation and the amount of protein used for assay. Protein was measured by Bradford assay with Coomassie blue (Bio-Rad) and bovine γ-globulin as a standard. For assay of cell lysates, disintegrations per minute recovered after a 1-h incubation period with Ang II were corrected for the time 0 value.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Proximity ligation assay
    </title>
    <p>
     The Duolink assay (Olink Bioscience) was used according to the manufacturer's protocol to detect the interaction of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with Prdx6 in intact cells. Briefly, MPMVECs cultured on glass coverslips were rinsed with PBS and fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min at room temperature, followed by 10 min incubation with 0.2% Triton X-100 solution in PBS and an additional 40 min after the addition of 5% BSA for blocking. Cells were immunolabeled with primary antibodies (1:100 dilution) by overnight incubation at 4°C. The assay requires primary antibodies generated from 2 different species in order to obtain a Duolink reaction. The mouse monoclonal antibody to p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and rabbit polyclonal antibody to either Prdx6 (nonphosphorylated) or phosphoPrdx6 were used to detect protein-protein interaction as observed by confocal (Radiance 2000; Bio-Rad) or fluorescence (Nikon Eclipse TE 20000-U) microscopy. For fluorescence microscopy, signals were deconvoluted using the Metamorph program (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). The anti-mouse and anti-rabbit secondary antibodies with attached probes for the Duolink reaction and 4′, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) to identify nuclei are supplied with the Duolink kit. A fluorescence signal indicates that two proteins within cells are separated by &lt;40 nm (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      22
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     siRNA for knockdown of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     in endothelial cells
    </title>
    <p>
     For transfection experiments, endothelial cells were grown to 50–60% confluence, trypsinized from the dish, pelleted by centrifugation, and resuspended in Amaxa Nucleofector endothelial kit solution (Amaxa Biosystems, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     siRNA was used to knock down p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     in MPMVECs with scrambled siRNA as a control. Transfection with siRNA (1.5 μg) utilized the Amaxa Nucleofector system, as described previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      23
     </xref>
     ). After 72 h, cells were treated with 10 μM Ang II for 30 min, lysed, and assayed for PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Statistical analysis
    </title>
    <p>
     Values are shown as means ±
     <span>
      se
     </span>
     for
     <em>
      n
     </em>
     independent experiments. Statistical significance was assessed with SigmaStat software (Jandel Scientific, San Jose, CA, USA). Group differences were evaluated by 1-way ANOVA followed by Student's
     <em>
      t
     </em>
     test as appropriate. Differences between mean values were considered statistically significant at
     <em>
      P
     </em>
     &lt; 0.05.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    RESULTS
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Interaction of Prdx6 with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     in cells
    </title>
    <p>
     Coimmunoprecipitation of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and Prdx6 from MPMVECs was used to analyze the interaction of the two proteins. As described previously for PMNs (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      14
     </xref>
     ), anti-p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     antibody coimmunoprecipitated Prdx6 and p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , top 2 panels). The interaction was relatively weak for cells under basal conditions but increased considerably in cells after stimulation with Ang II to activate NOX2. This requirement for Ang II treatment suggests as one possibility that the interaction of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     in cells is predominantly with Prdx6 that has been phosphorylated and is consistent with our previous study indicating that Prdx6 phosphorylation is required for NOX2 activation (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ). The anti-Prdx6 Ab used for this Western blot (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , second panel) reacts to both native and phosphorylated Prdx6; the presence of a slightly higher band in the Ang II-stimulated lane is compatible with the phosphorylated form. Blotting of the coimmunoprecipitate using antibodies specific for either phosphorylated Prdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , third panel) or nonphosphorylated Prdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     , bottom panel) confirmed that the phosphorylated protein was the form that interacted with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     . Immunoprecipitation of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with the antiphosphoPrdx6-specific antibody provides confirmatory evidence for an interaction of phosphoPrdx6 with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     after Ang II treatment of the cells (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). The lack of an immunoprecipitation band from the cells under basal conditions indicates the absence of phosphoPrdx6 in unstimulated cells (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ,
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ). The control antibody (anti-mouse IgG) gave no reaction under basal or stimulated conditions (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 1
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ,
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     The interaction of the two proteins in intact MPMVECs was studied by the Duolink proximity ligation assay. This assay utilized the anti-p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     antibodies and that are specific either for phosphorylated Prdx6 or for nonphosphorylated Prdx6. No significant signal was observed under basal (nonstimulated) conditions, as evaluated by either the antibody to nonphosphorylated or phosphorylated Prdx6 (
     <strong>
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       Fig. 2
      </xref>
      <em>
       A–C
      </em>
     </strong>
     ). Ang II treatment had only a weak effect on the interaction of Prdx6 with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     when evaluated by the nonphosphoPrdx6 antibody (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      D
     </em>
     ) but resulted in a strong interaction as evaluated with the phosphoPrdx6 antibody, as indicated by the cytoplasmic fluorescence (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      E
     </em>
     ). The interaction of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with phosphoPrdx6 was diminished markedly when cells were treated with the MAP kinase inhibitor, U0126 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      F
     </em>
     ). We have shown previously that this inhibitor prevents Prdx6 phosphorylation following Ang II treatment (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ). Cell nuclei in this figure are indicated by DAPI staining; phase images of cells stimulated with Ang II are shown for the nonphosphoPrdx6 antibody (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      G
     </em>
     ) and the phosphoPrdx6 Ab (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      H
     </em>
     ). Anti-IgG antibody, used as an antibody control, gave no signal either in cells under basal conditions (not shown) or after stimulation with Ang II (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 2
     </xref>
     <em>
      I
     </em>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       Interaction of Prdx6 or phosphoPrdx6 with p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       in intact MPMVECs detected by the Duolink proximity ligation assay. The assay used mAb to p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       and pAbs specific for nonphosphoPrdx6 (
       <em>
        A, D
       </em>
       ) or phosphoPrdx6 (
       <em>
        B, E
       </em>
       ). The interaction of p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       with phosphoPrdx6 also was studied in the presence of U0126 (
       <em>
        C, F
       </em>
       ), an inhibitor of Prdx6 phosphorylation (
       <xref ref-type="bibr">
        13
       </xref>
       ). Cell nuclei were stained with DAPI. Cells were studied under basal conditions (unstimulated,
       <em>
        A–C
       </em>
       ) and in the presence of Ang II (10 μM,
       <em>
        D–F
       </em>
       ). Fluorescence (seen predominantly in
       <em>
        E
       </em>
       with minimal fluorescence in
       <em>
        D
       </em>
       ) indicates proximity (closer than 40 nm) of the two proteins. Phase images (
       <em>
        G
       </em>
       ,
       <em>
        H
       </em>
       ) are the same fields as in
       <em>
        D
       </em>
       ,
       <em>
        E
       </em>
       . For an antibody control, IgG from rabbit and mouse was substituted for the specific antibodies in Ang II-treated cells (
       <em>
        I
       </em>
       ). Results are representative of 3 experiments. Scale bar (
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) applies to all images.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Interaction of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     with Prdx6 measured by ITC
    </title>
    <p>
     To confirm that results obtained with intact cells, ITC was used to evaluate the interaction between Prdx6 and p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
     . There was only trivial binding between p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and Prdx6, as demonstrated by this method (
     <strong>
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       Fig. 3
      </xref>
      <em>
       A
      </em>
     </strong>
     ). However, significant binding was demonstrated between p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and phosphoPrdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). Binding was exothermic at 20°C, which allowed the calculation of the binding parameters using a single site binding model. Binding parameters between p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     and phosphoPrdx6 are ΔH (enthalpy), (−4.31±0.8)×10
     <sup>
      5
     </sup>
     kcal/mol; ΔS (entropy), −1445±40 kcal/mol/deg; and
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      a
     </sub>
     (association constant), (8.8±1.8)×10
     <sup>
      5
     </sup>
     M
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     . p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     was phosphorylated in order to study its interaction with phosphoPrdx6 by ITC. Phosphorylation of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     did not change its lack of binding to Prdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ), and neither did phosphorylated p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     bind to phosphoPrdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 3
     </xref>
     <em>
      D
     </em>
     ). Thus, these ITC studies clearly show that p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     primarily binds to phosphoPrdx6, and this interaction is abolished by p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     phosphorylation.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       ITC for quantitation of interactions using recombinant proteins. Experiments were performed with His-tagged p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       and His-tagged Prdx6, either phosphorylated or not, in 50 mM PBS at pH 7.0. Straight lines are the computer-drawn baselines. Results shown are representative of 3 independent experiments for each condition.
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       titrated with Prdx6.
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       titrated with phosphorylated Prdx6.
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Phosphorylated p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       titrated with Prdx6.
       <em>
        D
       </em>
       ) Phosphorylated p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       titrated with phosphorylated Prdx6. Panels show results for each injection in microcalories per second after baseline correction.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     inhibits the PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of Prdx6
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
    </title>
    <p>
     The effect of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     on the PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of recombinant Prdx6 was evaluated. PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity was measured at cytosolic pH, since this is the compartment of the presumed interaction between the 2 proteins. PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of Prdx6 was relatively low but increased markedly after phosphorylation of the protein (
     <strong>
      <a>
       <span>
        Table 1
       </span>
      </a>
     </strong>
     ), as reported previously (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      13
     </xref>
     ). The addition of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     inhibited the PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of both native and phosphoPrdx6, while phosphorylated p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     had no effect (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ) consistent with its lack of binding to Prdx6, as shown by ITC. IgG was used as a negative control. The inhibition of PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity by p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     was concentration dependent with essentially complete inhibition at 1:1 ratio of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (monomeric) to phosphoPrdx6 (dimeric) (
     <strong>
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       Fig. 4
      </xref>
      <em>
       A
      </em>
     </strong>
     ). We have assumed, on the basis of the crystal structure (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      24
     </xref>
     ), that Prdx6 exists normally as a homodimer.
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        Effect of recombinant p67
        <sup>
         phox
        </sup>
        on PLA
        <sub>
         2
        </sub>
        activity of recombinant Prdx6
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity of phosphorylated recombinant human Prdx6 in the presence of recombinant mouse p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       .
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Concentration dependence of the inhibition of PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity by p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       . PhosphoPrdx6 was present at 2 μg/ml and p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       was varied from 0 to 5.1 μg/ml to give p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       to phosphoPrdx6 (dimeric) molar ratios from 0 to 2. PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity was measured at pH 7 in the absence of Ca
       <sup>
        2+
       </sup>
       . Individual points are means ±
       <span>
        se
       </span>
       ;
       <em>
        n
       </em>
       = 3.
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) Double reciprocal plots show PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity
       <em>
        vs.
       </em>
       substrate (DPPC) concentration at varying p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       concentrations (indicated in micrograms per milliliter by the number above each line).
       <em>
        C
       </em>
       ) Plot of
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        m
       </sub>
       /
       <em>
        V
       </em>
       <sub>
        max
       </sub>
       <em>
        vs.
       </em>
       p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       concentration. Intercept of the plot with the horizontal axis indicates
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        i
       </sub>
       (
       <em>
        K
       </em>
       <sub>
        d
       </sub>
       ) for the interaction of p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       with phosphoPrdx6.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Kinetic parameters associated with p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     -mediated inhibition of PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity were investigated by varying the concentrations of the substrate (dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine, DPPC) and p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     . Double reciprocal plots were linear and indicate noncompetitive kinetics for the effect of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). The plot of
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      m
     </sub>
     /
     <em>
      V
     </em>
     <sub>
      max
     </sub>
     <em>
      vs.
     </em>
     p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     concentration also was linear (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 4
     </xref>
     <em>
      C
     </em>
     ) and gave a calculated dissociation constant (
     <em>
      K
     </em>
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ) of 65 nM, indicating a strong interaction between the two proteins.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Effect of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     on PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of endothelial cells
    </title>
    <p>
     To evaluate the physiological relevance of the interaction of the two proteins, PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity was measured in homogenates of MPMVECs that had been subjected to p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     siRNA treatment. Treatment with either of two different siRNAs resulted in knockdown of cellular p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     protein by ∼80% (
     <strong>
      <xref ref-type="fig">
       Fig. 5
      </xref>
      <em>
       A
      </em>
     </strong>
     ). There was no effect of siRNA on the cell content of p47
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     or Prdx6 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     <em>
      A
     </em>
     ). Cells treated with scrambled siRNA (control) showed an increase in PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity after Ang II (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ) similar to that described previously for control MPMVECs (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
     ). Cells with knockdown of p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     showed a significantly greater increase of PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity following Ang II, as compared to scrambled siRNA-treated cells (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ). The PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity under basal conditions or following Ang II treatment was markedly inhibited by the presence of MJ33 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Fig. 5
     </xref>
     <em>
      B
     </em>
     ), a known inhibitor of Prdx6 PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      13
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      20
     </xref>
     ). These results are compatible with a role for p67
     <sup>
      phox
     </sup>
     in regulating the PLA
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     activity of Prdx6 in MPMVECs following Ang II stimulation.
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 5.
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity of Prdx6 after knockdown of p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       with siRNA.
       <em>
        A
       </em>
       ) Immunoblot showing the expression of p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       , p47
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       , and Prdx6 after transfection of endothelial cells with scrambled siRNA or p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       siRNA 2 for 72 h. GAPDH was used as a loading control. Bar graphs show quantitation of immunoblots by densitometry normalized to GADPH to compare the effect of scrambled siRNA or p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       siRNA 2 on expression of p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       , p47
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       , and Prdx6. Values are expressed as means ±
       <span>
        se
       </span>
       ;
       <em>
        n
       </em>
       = 3.
       <em>
        B
       </em>
       ) MPMVECs pretreated with scrambled siRNA or p67
       <sup>
        phox
       </sup>
       siRNA were incubated in the absence or presence of 10 μM Ang II for 30 min. PLA
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       activity of cell lysates was measured at pH 7.0 in the absence or presence of MJ33 (1 mol%, inhibitor to substrate mol fraction). Results for siRNAs 1 and 2 were similar and are combined. Values are expressed as means ±
       <span>
        se
       </span>
       ;
       <em>
        n
       </em>
       = 6 for minus MJ33 and
       <em>
        n
       </em>
       = 3 for plus MJ33. *
       <em>
        P
       </em>
       &lt; 0.05
       <em>
        vs.
       </em>
       −MJ33;
       <sup>
        †
       </sup>
       <em>
        P
       </em>
       &lt; 0.05
       <em>
        vs
       </em>
       . scrambled siRNA.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    DISCUSSION
   </title>
   <p>
    The NOX2 enzyme complex is a major source of reactive oxygen species generation in PMNs, macrophages, vascular endothelial cells, and other cell types (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     1
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     7
    </xref>
    ). The complex generates O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     ·−
    </sup>
    (superoxide anion) on agonist-mediated induction of activity (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     6
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     8
    </xref>
    ). While considerable attention has focused on the cytoplasmic cofactors and their mobilization following agonist stimulation, the pathways that couple the agonist with activation of the cytoplasmic components are not as well understood. It has been shown by our previous studies that Prdx6 and its PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity represent an important step in the pathway leading to NOX2 activation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    ). Because continued PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity with the generation of bioactive products (lysoPC and free fatty acids) could be harmful to the cell, a mechanism for terminating this activity is necessary. One possibility in that regard would be the presence of a phosphatase to reverse the phosphorylation of Prdx6 and essentially terminate its PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity. That possibility has not yet been studied. Another possibility to terminate Prdx6 PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity would be the inhibition of enzymatic activity by a cytoplasmic component. On the basis of a previous report that indicated coimmunoprecipitation of Prdx6 and p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     14
    </xref>
    ), we postulated that the interaction of these two proteins could regulate Prdx6 PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity.
   </p>
   <p>
    The present results confirm the previous report showing interaction of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    with Prdx6 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     14
    </xref>
    ) with the additional information that the binding of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    is significantly greater to the phosphorylated Prdx6 protein. Coimmunoprecipitation of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    and phosphorylated Prdx6 was demonstrated with MPMVECs using either anti-p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    or anti-phosphoPrdx6 antibodies. The two proteins were coimmunoprecipitated from lysates of endothelial cells that had been treated with Ang II but not from control (untreated) cells. Likewise, the Duolink assay showed interaction between the proteins in intact cells, but again only after Ang II treatment and only for phosphorylated Prdx6. On the basis of our previous demonstration of Prdx6 phosphorylation in MPMVECs following Ang II treatment (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     9
    </xref>
    ), the immunoprecipitation and Duolink results are compatible with phosphoPrdx6 as the predominant binding partner for p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    . This result was confirmed using antibodies that are specific for either phosphoPrdx6 or the nonphosphorylated protein. Both the immunoprecipitation and Duolink assays show that the interaction of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    with nonphosphorylated Prdx6 is minimal in endothelial cells.
    <em>
     In vitro
    </em>
    confirmation of the binding partners was demonstrated by ITC. These results demonstrated clearly that p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    bound with much greater affinity to phosphorylated Prdx6, while phosphorylation of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    prevented an interaction.
   </p>
   <p>
    We next considered the physiological role of the interaction between p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    and phosphoPrdx6. The presence of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    markedly inhibited the PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity of recombinant Prdx6 assayed
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    . Relevance of this interaction to intact cells was demonstrated using siRNA to knock down p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    , thereby resulting in significant augmentation of the increase in PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity in response to Ang II. Inhibition by MJ33 provides evidence that the increased PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity with siRNA knockdown represents the PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity of Prdx6 (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     13
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     20
    </xref>
    ). We interpret this experiment as indicating that the increase in PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity following Ang II stimulation in control endothelial cells is restrained by the presence of p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    . We postulate that inhibition of PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity by p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    can terminate the signal for translocation of the cytoplasmic (NOX2) proteins and thereby limit the generation of potentially toxic metabolites of the PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    reaction. The p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    that translocates to the plasma membrane is the phosphorylated protein, while the PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    turn-off signal requires nonphosphorylated p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The present results suggest the following cycle related to Prdx6 and NOX2 activity. Stimulation of cells results in phosphorylation of Prdx6 that then binds to lipids in the cell membrane. The subsequent PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity results in liberation of products that signal for phosphorylation of cytosolic components (including p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    ) and activation of NOX2. Meanwhile, p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    (nonphosphorylated) binds to phosphoPrdx6, thereby terminating its PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity. A remaining question is how phosphoPrdx6 can be activated initially in the presence of cytosolic p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    . We postulate that binding of phosphoPrdx6 to its lipid substrate is more rapid than its binding to p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    , thus allowing PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity. This kinetic explanation has some support from measurements that showed a relatively high
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    for phosphoPrdx6 binding to p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    in aqueous solution by ITC and a considerably lower value when phosphoPrdx6 was bound to lipid substrate in the PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity assays. An alternate mechanism for a delayed interaction between phosphoPrdx6 and p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    may be differential location of the 2 proteins in the cell or other kinetic parameters that are not fully understood.
   </p>
   <p>
    In summary, our data indicate that p67
    <sup>
     phox
    </sup>
    binds to phosphorylated Prdx6, with consequent inhibition of its PLA
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    activity. This interaction may have physiological relevance for the modulation of the NOX2 pathway for generation of O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    <sup>
     ·−
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    REFERENCES
   </title>
   <sec>
    <sec>
     1.
     <span>
      Lambeth J. D. (2002)
      <span>
       Nox/Duox family of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (phosphate) oxidases
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Curr. Opin. Hematol
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       9
      </span>
      , 11–17
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     2.
     <span>
      Babior B. M. (1999)
      <span>
       NADPH oxidase: an update
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Blood
      </span>
      <span>
       93
      </span>
      , 1464–1476
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     3.
     <span>
      Segal A. W. (1989)
      <span>
       The electron transport chain of the microbicidal oxidase of phagocytic cells and its involvement in the molecular pathology of chronic granulomatous disease
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochem. Soc. Trans
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       17
      </span>
      , 427–434
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     4.
     <span>
      DeLeo F. R., Quinn M. T. (1996)
      <span>
       Assembly of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase: molecular interaction of oxidase proteins
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Leukoc. Biol
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       60
      </span>
      , 677–691
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     5.
     <span>
      Chanock S. J., el Benna J., Smith R. M., Babior B. M. (1994)
      <span>
       The respiratory burst oxidase
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       269
      </span>
      , 24519–24522
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     6.
     <span>
      Frey R. S., Ushio-Fukai M., Malik A. B. (2009)
      <span>
       NADPH oxidase-dependent signaling in endothelial cells: role in physiology and pathophysiology
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Antioxid. Redox Signal
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       11
      </span>
      , 791–810
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     7.
     <span>
      Lassegue B., Griendling K. K. (2010)
      <span>
       NADPH oxidases: functions and pathologies in the vasculature
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       30
      </span>
      , 653–661
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     8.
     <span>
      Pendyala S., Usatyuk P. V., Gorshkova I. A., Garcia J. G., Natarajan V. (2009)
      <span>
       Regulation of NADPH oxidase in vascular endothelium: the role of phospholipases, protein kinases, and cytoskeletal proteins
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Antioxid. Redox Signal
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       11
      </span>
      , 841–860
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     9.
     <span>
      Chatterjee S., Feinstein S. I., Dodia C., Sorokina E., Lien Y. C., Nguyen S., Debolt K., Speicher D., Fisher A. B. (2011)
      <span>
       Peroxiredoxin 6 phosphorylation and subsequent phospholipase A2 activity are required for agonist-mediated activation of NADPH oxidase in mouse pulmonary microvascular endothelium and alveolar macrophages
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       286
      </span>
      , 11696–11706
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     10.
     <span>
      Ambruso D. R., Ellison M. A., Thurman G. W., Leto T. L. (2011)
      <span>
       Peroxiredoxin 6 translocates to the plasma membrane during neutrophil activation and is required for optimal NADPH oxidase activity
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochim. Biophys. Acta
      </span>
      <span>
       1823
      </span>
      , 306–315
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     11.
     <span>
      Ellison M. A., Thurman G. W., Ambruso D. R. (2012)
      <span>
       Phox activity of differentiated PLB-985 cells is enhanced, in an agonist specific manner, by the PLA2 activity of Prdx6-PLA2
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Eur. J. Immunol
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      , 1609–1617
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     12.
     <span>
      Chen J. W., Dodia C., Feinstein S. I., Jain M. K., Fisher A. B. (2000)
      <span>
       1-Cys peroxiredoxin, a bifunctional enzyme with glutathione peroxidase and phospholipase A2 activities
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       275
      </span>
      , 28421–28427
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     13.
     <span>
      Wu Y., Feinstein S. I., Manevich Y., Chowdhury I., Pak J. H., Kazi A., Dodia C., Speicher D. W., Fisher A. B. (2009)
      <span>
       Mitogen-activated protein kinase-mediated phosphorylation of peroxiredoxin 6 regulates its phospholipase A(2) activity
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochem. J
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       419
      </span>
      , 669–679
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     14.
     <span>
      Leavey P. J., Gonzalez-Aller C., Thurman G., Kleinberg M., Rinckel L., Ambruso D. W., Freeman S., Kuypers F. A., Ambruso D. R. (2002)
      <span>
       A 29-kDa protein associated with p67phox expresses both peroxiredoxin and phospholipase A2 activity and enhances superoxide anion production by a cell-free system of NADPH oxidase activity
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       277
      </span>
      , 45181–45187
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     15.
     <span>
      Milovanova T., Chatterjee S., Hawkins B. J., Hong N., Sorokina E. M., Debolt K., Moore J. S., Madesh M., Fisher A. B. (2008)
      <span>
       Caveolae are an essential component of the pathway for endothelial cell signaling associated with abrupt reduction of shear stress
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochim. Biophys. Acta
      </span>
      <span>
       1783
      </span>
      , 1866–1875
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     16.
     <span>
      Wu Y. Z., Manevich Y., Baldwin J. L., Dodia C., Yu K., Feinstein S. I., Fisher A. B. (2006)
      <span>
       Interaction of surfactant protein A with peroxiredoxin 6 regulates phospholipase A2 activity
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Biol. Chem
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       281
      </span>
      , 7515–7525
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     17.
     <span>
      Rahaman H., Zhou S., Dodia C., Feinstein S. I., Huang S., Speicher D., Fisher A. B. (2012)
      <span>
       Increased phospholipase A2 activity with phosphorylation of peroxiredoxin 6 requires a conformational change in the protein
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochemistry
      </span>
      <span>
       51
      </span>
      , 5521–5530
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     18.
     <span>
      Dang P. M., Morel F., Gougerot-Pocidalo M. A., El Benna J. (2003)
      <span>
       Phosphorylation of the NADPH oxidase component p67(PHOX) by ERK2 and P38MAPK: selectivity of phosphorylated sites and existence of an intramolecular regulatory domain in the tetratricopeptide-rich region
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochemistry
      </span>
      <span>
       42
      </span>
      , 4520–4526
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     19.
     <span>
      Forbes L. V., Truong O., Wientjes F. B., Moss S. J., Segal A. W. (1999)
      <span>
       The major phosphorylation site of the NADPH oxidase component p67phox is Thr233
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Biochem. J
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       338
      </span>
      , 99–105
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     20.
     <span>
      Fisher A. B., Dodia C. (1996)
      <span>
       Role of phospholipase A2 enzymes in degradation of dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine by granular pneumocytes
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Lipid Res
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       37
      </span>
      , 1057–1064
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     21.
     <span>
      Fisher A. B., Dodia C., Feinstein S. I., Ho Y. S. (2005)
      <span>
       Altered lung phospholipid metabolism in mice with targeted deletion of lysosomal-type phospholipase A2
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       J. Lipid Res
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       46
      </span>
      , 1248–1256
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     22.
     <span>
      Soderberg O., Gullberg M., Jarvius M., Ridderstrale K., Leuchowius K. J., Jarvius J., Wester K., Hydbring P., Bahram F., Larsson L. G., Landegren U. (2006)
      <span>
       Direct observation of individual endogenous protein complexes in situ by proximity ligation
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Nat. Methods
      </span>
      <span>
       3
      </span>
      , 995–1000
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     23.
     <span>
      Lien Y. C., Feinstein S. I., Dodia C., Fisher A.B. (2012)
      <span>
       The roles of peroxidase and phospholipase A2 activities of peroxiredoxin 6 in protecting pulmonary microvascular endothelial cells against peroxidative stress
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Antioxid. Redox Signal
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       16
      </span>
      , 440–451
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PMC free article
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     24.
     <span>
      Choi H. J., Kang S. W., Yang C. H., Rhee S. G., Ryu S. E. (1998)
      <span>
       Crystal structure of a novel human peroxidase enzyme at 2.0 A resolution
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       Nat. Struct. Biol
      </span>
      .
      <span>
       5
      </span>
      , 400–406
      <span>
       [
       <a>
        PubMed
       </a>
       ]
      </span>
     </span>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>