<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC4163015
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Key steps in ERAD of luminal ER proteins reconstituted with purified
components
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Summary
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     Misfolded proteins of the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) are retro-translocated into
the cytosol, poly-ubiquitinated, and degraded by the proteasome, a process called
ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD). Here, we have used purified components from
     <em>
      Saccharomyces cerevisiae
     </em>
     to analyze the mechanism of
retro-translocation of luminal substrates (ERAD-L), recapitulating key steps in a basic
process where the ubiquitin ligase Hrd1p is the only required membrane protein. We show
that Hrd1p interacts with substrate through its membrane-spanning domain, discriminating
misfolded from folded polypeptides. Both Hrd1p and substrate are poly-ubiquitinated,
resulting in the binding of the Cdc48p ATPase complex. Subsequently, ATP hydrolysis by
Cdc48p releases substrate from Hrd1p. Finally, ubiquitin chains are trimmed by the
de-ubiquitinating enzyme Otu1p, which is recruited and activated by the Cdc48p complex.
Cdc48p-dependent membrane extraction of poly-ubiquitinated proteins can be reproduced with
reconstituted proteoliposomes. Our results suggest a model for retro-translocation in
which Hrd1p forms a membrane conduit for misfolded proteins.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Protein homeostasis in the ER is maintained by a quality control system. When a
protein misfolds, it is retained in the ER and ultimately retro-translocated into the
cytosol, poly-ubiquitinated, and degraded by the proteasome. This pathway is referred to as
ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD) (for review, see (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bagola et al., 2011
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Brodsky, 2012
    </xref>
    )). It
alleviates cytotoxic stress imposed by protein misfolding and is implicated in numerous
diseases (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Guerriero and Brodsky, 2012
    </xref>
    ). ERAD is found
in all eukaryotic cells, but is best understood in
    <em>
     S. cerevisiae
    </em>
    . Here,
substrates use three ERAD-pathways (ERAD-L, -M, or –C), depending on whether the
misfolded domain is localized in the ER lumen, inside the ER membrane, or at the cytosolic
side of the ER membrane (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Carvalho et al., 2006
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Huyer et al., 2004
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Vashist and Ng, 2004
    </xref>
    ). The pathways use distinct ubiquitin ligase complexes.
ERAD-L requires a hetero-tetrameric membrane protein complex, the Hrd1p complex, comprised
of the ubiquitin ligase Hrd1p and three additional membrane proteins (Hrd3p, Usa1p, and
Der1p). ERAD-M also requires Hrd1p, but only a subset of the other components, and ERAD-C
uses the ubiquitin ligase Doa10p. On the cytosolic side of the ER membrane, all pathways
require an ATPase complex, which includes the ATPase Cdc48p and the cofactors Ufd1p and
Npl4p.
   </p>
   <p>
    Among the ERAD-pathways, ERAD-L is arguably most complex, as polypeptides have to
be inserted into and moved across the ER membrane. ERAD-L begins with the recognition of a
misfolded protein in the ER lumen, which is best understood for misfolded glycoproteins (for
review, see (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Xie and Ng, 2010
    </xref>
    )). The N-linked glycan
of these proteins is trimmed to generate a terminal α-1,6-mannose residue, which is
recognized by the luminal protein Yos9p. Yos9p binds to the luminal domain of Hrd3p, which
also binds a misfolded segment around the glycan-attachment site of the substrate. Once a
segment of the substrate emerges on the cytoplasmic side of the ER membrane, it is
poly-ubiquitinated by the RING finger domain of Hrd1p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bays
et al., 2001a
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bordallo et al., 1998
    </xref>
    ). The
major ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme participating in this reaction is Ubc7p, which also
requires the activator Cue1p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bays et al., 2001a
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Biederer et al., 1997
    </xref>
    ). The recruitment of the
Cdc48p complex to the Hrd1p complex involves recognition of a poly-ubiquitin chain by the
cofactor Ufd1p/Npl4p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Meyer et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ). However,
it is unclear whether the recruitment requires the ubiquitin chain to be attached to the
substrate, to Hrd1p, or to an unknown component. The binding of Cdc48p to the membrane might
be facilitated by the adaptor protein Ubx2p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Neuber et al.,
2005
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Schuberth and Buchberger, 2005
    </xref>
    ).
Cdc48p is then thought to pull on the poly-ubiquitinated polypeptide substrate to move it
into the cytosol (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bays et al., 2001b
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jarosch et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Rabinovich et
al., 2002
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ye et al., 2001
    </xref>
    ). Recent
experiments have also implicated de-ubiquitinating enzymes (DUBs) in ERAD (for review, see
(
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Liu and Ye, 2012
    </xref>
    )). Several DUBs associate with
Cdc48p or its mammalian homolog p97, and the overexpression of dominant-negative forms
blocks ERAD in mammalian cells. However, it remains unclear how DUBs participate in
ERAD.
   </p>
   <p>
    The events of ERAD-L inside the ER membrane are less well understood. Hrd1p seems
to be a central component, as its overexpression bypasses the need for the other membrane
components, as well as for the luminal protein Yos9p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Carvalho et al., 2010
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Denic et al., 2006
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Garza et al., 2009
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Plemper et al., 1999
    </xref>
    ). Under these conditions, glycan trimming is not required,
and both glycosylated and non-glycosylated proteins are degraded. All downstream cytosolic
components, including the Cdc48p complex, are still required. Hrd1p overexpression makes
Hrd1p unstable and slows, but does not abolish, cell growth. These results suggest that
Hrd1p is the only membrane component required for a basic ERAD-L process. The minimal
components required for retro-translocation therefore comprise Hrd1p, Ubc7p, Cue1p, and the
Cdc48p complex. Because Hrd1p is a multi-spanning membrane protein, it is a good candidate
to be part of a retro-translocation channel. In fact, crosslinking experiments show that a
retro-translocating substrate interacts with Hrd1p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Carvalho
et al., 2010
    </xref>
    ). However, the exact function of Hrd1p during retro-translocation
remains unclear.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our knowledge on ERAD-L comes from genetics and biochemical experiments in intact
cells.
    <em>
     In vitro
    </em>
    reconstitution of ERAD-L using purified components is
critical to demonstrate that all ERAD components have been identified. Even more
importantly, reconstitution experiments are instrumental in addressing the molecular
mechanism of ERAD. Here, we have recapitulated crucial reactions of a basic ERAD-L process
with purified
    <em>
     S. cerevisiae
    </em>
    components in both detergent and reconstituted
proteoliposomes. Our results suggest a mechanistic model for how misfolded luminal ER
proteins associate with Hrd1p inside the ER membrane and how they are extracted by Cdc48p on
the cytoplasmic side of the membrane.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Direct interaction of ERAD-L substrates with Hrd1p
    </title>
    <p>
     <em>
      In vivo
     </em>
     experiments suggested that Hrd1p is the only membrane
protein required for a basic ERAD-L process (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Carvalho et
al., 2010
     </xref>
     ). We therefore tested whether purified Hrd1p directly interacts with
purified misfolded proteins. We used a well-characterized ERAD-L substrate, misfolded
pro-carboxypeptidase Y (CPY*), which differs from the native protein by a single
point mutation (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Finger et al., 1993
     </xref>
     ). His-tagged
CPY* was purified in urea after expression in
     <em>
      S. cerevisiae
     </em>
     , but
it remained soluble after removal of urea (
     <a>
      Figure S1A, available online
     </a>
     ). To facilitate
detection, CPY* was labeled with a fluorescent dye (
     <a>
      Figure S1B
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Hrd1p with a C-terminal streptavidin-binding peptide (SBP) tag (Hrd1p-SBP) was
purified from
     <em>
      S. cerevisiae
     </em>
     in the detergent decylmaltose neopentyl
glycol (DMNG). Although Hrd1p appeared pure by SDS-PAGE (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ), it was heterogeneous in size by
gel filtration (
     <a>
      Figure S1D
     </a>
     ),
consistent with it forming homo-oligomers
     <em>
      in vivo
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Carvalho et al., 2010
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     For binding experiments, we mixed labeled CPY* with increasing
concentrations of immobilized Hrd1p. Quantification of the bound and non-bound fractions
gave an apparent affinity of ∼30 nM (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 1A,
B
     </xref>
     ). Wild type pro-CPY (CPY) did not bind to Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1B
     </xref>
     ; see
     <a>
      Figures S1A and
S1B
     </a>
     for purified and labeled protein, respectively). Even when CPY was treated
like CPY*, i.e. denatured in urea followed by removal of urea, only a small
fraction was able to bind (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1B
     </xref>
     ). This suggests
that Hrd1p can discriminate misfolded from folded polypeptides.
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Substrate Interaction with Hrd1p
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Fluorescently labeled CPY* (10 nM) was incubated with increasing
concentrations of bead-immobilized SBP-tagged Hrd1p (Hrd1p). The bound and unbound
fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Quantification of four different experiments as in (A). Fitting of the data points
gives an apparent dissociation constant of 30 nM. Also shown are experiments with wild
type CPY, either purified as a native protein or after unfolding and refolding, as done
with CPY*.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) As in (A), but with sCPY* (100 nM).
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) Quantification of three different experiments as in (C). The apparent dissociation
constant is ∼300 nM.
      </p>
      <p>
       (E) Quantification of binding experiments of wild type Hrd1p with fluorescently labeled
sCPY*-DHFR (10 nM), sCPY*-GFP (100 nM), DHFR (100 nM), or GFP (100
nM).
      </p>
      <p>
       (F) As in (C), but sCPY* was incubated with either wild type Hrd1p, a fusion of
the TMs of Hrd1p with GFP (Hrd1p-TM-GFP), the cytoplasmic domain of Hrd1p (Hrd1p-c), or
GFP.
      </p>
      <p>
       (G) sCPY*-DHFR (200 nM) labeled with DyLight800 was incubated with a mixture of
unlabeled Hrd1p (20 μM) and Hrd1p (200 nM) labeled with DyLight680. The sample was
subjected to gel filtration in a buffer containing 120 μM DMNG and fractions were
analyzed in two fluorescence channels. A control was performed with labeled
sCPY*-DHFR alone. The arrows indicate the void volume, and the retention volume of
size standards.
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S1
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Hrd1p also bound other misfolded CPY variants, such as a C-terminal fragment of
CPY* (sCPY*), which is an ERAD-L substrate
     <em>
      in vivo
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Carvalho et al., 2010
     </xref>
     ). sCPY* was purified as a
mixture of glycosylated and non-glycosylated species (as shown by treatment with peptide
N-glycosidase F (
     <a>
      Figure S1A
     </a>
     )),
and was labeled with a fluorescent dye at a single C-terminal Cys-residue (
     <a>
      Figure S1B
     </a>
     ). sCPY* bound to Hrd1p with
significantly lower affinity than CPY* (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1C,
D
     </xref>
     ; ∼300 nM). Glycosylated and non-glycosylated sCPY* bound
equally well to Hrd1p, consistent with the fact that other ERAD components are required
for their discrimination and with both species being substrates in Hrd1p-overexpressing
cells (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Denic et al., 2006
     </xref>
     ). A fusion of
sCPY* with dihydrofolate reductase (DHFR) bound more tightly than sCPY*,
while a fusion with GFP (sCPY*-GFP) bound more weakly (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1E
     </xref>
     ; purity shown in
     <a>
      Figures S1A and S1B
     </a>
     ). These differences
correlate with the tendency of these proteins to aggregate; the concentration of urea
required to keep these proteins in solution was lowest for sCPY*-GFP, intermediate
for sCPY*, and highest for sCPY*-DHFR (data not shown). Purified GFP or
DHFR alone, or bovine serum albumin, did not bind (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
1E
     </xref>
     ; and data not shown; purified DHFR and GFP are shown in
     <a>
      Figures S1 and S1B
     </a>
     , respectively). Thus, Hrd1p
binds selectively to unfolded polypeptides.
    </p>
    <p>
     The membrane-embedded domain of Hrd1p is necessary and sufficient for substrate
interaction, as the C-terminal cytoplasmic domain (Hrd1p-c) did not bind sCPY*
(
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1F
     </xref>
     ), and a fusion of the membrane-embedded
domain of Hrd1p with GFP (Hrd1p-TM-GFP) bound substrate with the same affinity as wild
type Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1F
     </xref>
     ; purity of the proteins shown
in
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ). A folded state of
the TMs seems to be required for substrate interaction, as full-length Hrd1p was unstable
in detergents other than DMNG, and this correlated with the loss of substrate binding
(data not shown).
    </p>
    <p>
     We used the high-affinity substrate sCPY*-DHFR to test whether substrate
binds equally well to different oligomeric states of Hrd1p. Labeled sCPY*-DHFR
alone behaved in gel filtration as a homogeneous, low-molecular weight species (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1G
     </xref>
     ), as the low concentration and the presence of
detergent prevented its aggregation. When labeled sCPY*-DHFR was mixed with a
100-fold excess of Hrd1p, most substrate molecules migrated at very high molecular weight,
where few Hrd1p molecules were found, and
     <em>
      vice versa
     </em>
     , the smallest-sized
Hrd1p species did not contain bound substrate. Because sCPY*-DHFR is much smaller
than the Hrd1p oligomers (∼40 kDa versus &gt;250 kDa), the size shift of the
substrate indicates that it preferentially binds to high-molecular weight Hrd1p
oligomers.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Substrate poly-ubiquitination by Hrd1p
    </title>
    <p>
     Next we tested whether Hrd1p poly-ubiquitinates bound substrate. To this end, we
purified the ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme Ubc7p and its activator Cue1p (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ). Cue1p is a single-spanning
membrane protein (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Biederer et al., 1997
     </xref>
     ), but in our
experiments the full-length protein and a truncated version containing only the cytosolic
domain (Cue1p-c) behaved identically (data not shown). When Hrd1p was incubated with
fluorescently labeled CPY*, Ubc7p, Cue1p-c, purified Uba1p (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ), ubiquitin, and ATP,
poly-ubiquitinated CPY* was generated (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
2A
     </xref>
     ). The reaction rate depended mostly on the concentrations of Hrd1p and Ubc7p
and was complete within 60 min. No poly-ubiquitination was observed if ATP, Uba1p, Ubc7p,
or Hrd1p were omitted, or if an inactive Hrd1p mutant (Hrd1p C399S) was used (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Bordallo and Wolf, 1999
     </xref>
     ), and little modification was
seen in the absence of Cue1p-c (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2A
     </xref>
     ; for purity
of Hrd1p (C399S), see
     <a>
      Figure
S1C
     </a>
     ). Efficient poly-ubiquitination was also observed with sCPY* and
sCPY*-DHFR (shown for sCPY* in
     <a>
      Figure S2A
     </a>
     ). The experiments with sCPY*
showed that the glycosylated and non-glycosylated species were equally modified. Most of
the poly-ubiquitin chains on sCPY* and CPY* are linked through Lys48 in
ubiquitin, as indicated by the much shorter chains generated with a Lys48Arg ubiquitin
mutant (
     <a>
      Figure S2B
     </a>
     ). When
ubiquitin was replaced with methylated ubiquitin, which permits the attachment of a single
ubiquitin molecule but prevents the synthesis of ubiquitin chains, several modified bands
appeared, indicating that the substrates were modified at several different Lys-residues
(
     <a>
      Figure S2B
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Poly-ubiquitination by Hrd1p
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Time-course of ubiquitination of CPY* labeled with DyLight800. Some reactions
were analyzed after 60 min with the indicated components omitted. Where indicated, wild
type Hrd1p (100 nM) was replaced with 100 nM of an inactive Hrd1 p mutant (C399S) or 1
μM of the cytoplasmic domain of Hrd1 p (Hrd1p-c).
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Time-course of auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p labeled with DyLight680.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) The time-course of auto- and substrate-ubiquitination was determined in parallel. The
concentration of labeled Hrd1p was kept constant, while that of unlabeled Hrd1p was
varied.
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) The time-course of auto-ubiquitination was determined with 50 nM of labeled wild type
(WT) Hrd1p or C399S mutant in the absence or presence of a 10-fold excess of unlabeled WT
Hrd1p (solid and broken curves, respectively).
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S2
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     A purified cytoplasmic fragment of Hrd1p (Hrd1p-c) did not ubiquitinate
CPY* (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2A
     </xref>
     , lane 14) or sCPY*
(
     <a>
      Figure S2A
     </a>
     , lane 12), even
when added at 10-fold higher concentrations, although it could generate poly-ubiquitin
chains (
     <a>
      Figure S2C
     </a>
     ). Thus,
substrate needs to bind to the membrane-embedded domain of Hrd1p to become
poly-ubiquitinated.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p
    </title>
    <p>
     Hrd1p itself was also poly-ubiquitinated. To study Hrd1p auto-ubiquitination in
more detail, we attached by sortase labeling a fluorescent dye to the C-terminus of Hrd1p,
allowing the simultaneous detection of Hrd1p and substrate. Hrd1p poly-ubiquitination was
very efficient (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2B
     </xref>
     ). Experiments with
methylated ubiquitin showed that modification of Hrd1p occurs at several different
Lys-residues and that Hrd1p molecules often contain two ubiquitin chains (
     <a>
      Figure S2C
     </a>
     , last lane). Mass spectrometry
confirmed the modification of several Lys residues (positions 126, 143, 282, 325, 387,
407, 511, 518, 539, 540, 546), but replacement of single Lys residues with Arg did not
drastically reduce auto-ubiquitination (data not shown). Because a Hrd1p mutant in which
all 27 Lys residues were changed to Arg did not express, we generated mutants, in which
Lys residues were replaced in the trans-membrane domain (residues 1-301), the RING finger
domain (302-407), or the C-terminal tail (408-551) (RKK, KRK, and KKR mutants,
respectively). The RKK had significantly reduced levels of both auto- and
substrate-ubiquitination, whereas the KKR mutant was specifically affected in
auto-ubiquitination (
     <a>
      Figure S2D
     </a>
     ).
The KRK mutant showed an intermediate phenotype. In none of the mutants,
auto-ubiquitination was completely abolished. The cytoplasmic fragment of Hrd1p (Hrd1p-c)
showed little or no auto-ubiquitination; much of Hrd1p-c remained unmodified, and no
modified protein was seen with methylated ubiquitin (
     <a>
      Figure S2C
     </a>
     ). Thus, the trans-membrane domain is
required for efficient auto-ubiquitination.
    </p>
    <p>
     Hrd1p seems to modify itself by an intra-molecular reaction, since the rate of
Hrd1p poly-ubiquitination was independent of the Hrd1p concentration, in contrast to
substrate poly-ubiquitination (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2C
     </xref>
     ).
Furthermore, when wild type Hrd1p was mixed with an inactive Hrd1p mutant (Hrd1p C399S),
only the wild type, and not the mutant, was modified (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
2D
     </xref>
     ), even though the two proteins bind each other (
     <a>
      Figure S2E
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     We found no conditions where only substrate ubiquitination was observed. For
example, reducing the concentrations of Ubc7p or Cue1p-c, did not favor substrate- over
auto-modification (
     <a>
      Figure S2F
     </a>
     ).
Auto-ubiquitination was observed even under conditions where Hrd1p was saturated with
substrate, although the rate was somewhat reduced (
     <a>
      Figure S2G
     </a>
     ). Thus, auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p
appears to be an integral part of the poly-ubiquitination reaction.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p recruits the Cdc48p ATPase complex
    </title>
    <p>
     Next we tested whether Hrd1p poly-ubiquitination leads to recruitment of the
Cdc48p ATPase complex. We first separately purified hexameric Cdc48p and a complex of the
heterodimeric cofactor Ufd1p/Npl4p from
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ). The individual components
assembled into the Cdc48p complex, as shown by gel filtration (
     <a>
      Figure S3A
     </a>
     ). Next, we treated beads containing
poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p with Cdc48p in the presence or absence of Ufd1p/Npl4p. Binding of
Cdc48p was observed in the presence of the cofactor at low or physiological salt
concentrations (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     , lane 4 versus 1, and lane
9 versus 6), but not at high salt concentrations (lane 14). Ufd1p/Npl4p alone also bound
to ubiquitinated Hrd1p (lanes 2 and 7), indicating that the cofactor is responsible for
the recruitment of the Cdc48p complex. When Hrd1p was not pre-incubated with the
ubiquitination machinery, Cdc48p binding was drastically reduced (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3C
     </xref>
     ); the residual binding is likely due to purified Hrd1p
carrying some ubiquitin chains (shown by mass spectroscopy).
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Recruitment of Cdc48p to Ubiquitinated Hrd1p
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Bead-immobilized Hrd1p (1 μM) was ubiquitinated and incubated at different
salt conditions with 2 μM of the indicated components (UN, Ufd1p/Npl4p) in the
presence of 250 μM ATPγS. The bound material was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and
staining with IRDye Blue.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) As in (A), but bead-immobilized Hrd1p was modified with methylated ubiquitin.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) As in (A), but with non-ubiquitinated Hrd1p.
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S3
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We also tested the role of Ubx2p, a protein that interacts with Cdc48p and
ubiquitin and is involved in ERAD (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Neuber et al.,
2005
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Schuberth and Buchberger, 2005
     </xref>
     ).
Full-length Ubx2p with an N-terminal His-tag was purified in the detergent DMNG by Ni-NTA
chromatography, followed by gel filtration (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ). Ubx2p bound to ubiquitinated Hrd1p
(
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     , lanes 3, 8, 13), but not unmodified
Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3C
     </xref>
     ). Ubx2p increased the binding
affinity of the Cdc48p complex for poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p, as indicated by the
resistance of the interaction to high salt concentrations (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     , lane 15). In contrast to Cdc48p complex alone, a complex with Ubx2p
also bound to mono-ubiquitinated Hrd1p generated with methylated ubiquitin (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3B
     </xref>
     , lanes 5 and 10). Even in the presence of Ubx2p, the
Ufd1p/Npl4p complex was essential for the recruitment of Cdc48p (not shown), suggesting
that Ubx2p interacts only weakly with Cdc48p itself. Indeed, gel filtration showed an
increased association of Ubx2p's UBX domain (Ubx2p-c) with Cdc48p in the presence
of Ufd1p/Npl4p (
     <a>
      Figure S3A and B
     </a>
     ;
see
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     for purity of the
protein). A similar hierarchy has been observed with another UBX domain containing protein
(
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Hanzelmann et al., 2011
     </xref>
     ). Taken together, our
results show that poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p recruits the Cdc48p complex. Ubx2p stimulates
or stabilizes the association, but is not essential, consistent with
     <em>
      in
vivo
     </em>
     data (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Neuber et al., 2005
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Schuberth and Buchberger, 2005
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Cdc48p-dependent substrate release from Hrd1p
    </title>
    <p>
     Next we tested whether Cdc48p can release substrate bound to Hrd1p. We first
formed a complex between bead-immobilized SBP-tagged Hrd1p and fluorescently labeled
CPY*, and then incubated the beads with the ubiquitination machinery. After
removal of the ubiquitination machinery, the beads were incubated with Cdc48p in the
presence Ufd1p/Npl4p and ATP. About 50% of poly-ubiquitinated CPY* was
released from the beads (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     , lane 6;
quantification in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4B
     </xref>
     ). No release above
background was seen if ATP was depleted with hexokinase/glucose (Hk/G) (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     , lane 7), or if Cdc48p or Ufd1/Npl4p were omitted (lanes
4 and 5). Similar results were obtained with sCPY* (
     <a>
      Figures S4A,B
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Substrate Release from Hrd1p by Cdc48p ATPase
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) A bead-immobilized complex of 500 nM SBP-tagged Hrd1p and 100 nM fluorescently
labeled CPY* was incubated with the ubiquitination machinery. The beads were
washed and incubated with 100 nM Cdc48p and ATP in the absence or presence of 100 nM
Ufd1/Npl4p (UN) complex, or with UN alone. Where indicated, ATP was depleted with
hexokinase/glucose (Hk/G). The released material was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence
scanning. The total releasable amount of CPY* was determined by incubating the
beads with biotin.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Quantification (means and standard deviations) of released poly-ubiquitinated
CPY* determined from four experiments as shown in (A). The released fraction is
expressed relative to the total releasable material.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) Bead-immobilized SBP-tagged Hrd1p was ubiquitinated (Ub-Hrd1p) for 1 h. The beads
were washed, incubated with fluorescently labeled CPY*, and treated as in (A). The
lower panel shows the same experiment with non-ubiquitinated Hrd1p (non-Ub-Hrd1p).
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) Quantification (means and standard deviations) of released non-ubiquitinated
CPY* determined from four experiments as shown in (C) (released from Ub-Hrd1p,
black columns; released from non-Ub-Hrd1p, grey columns).
      </p>
      <p>
       (E) Immobilized Hrd1p mutants with Lys to Arg mutations in three different regions were
ubiquitinated for 30 min, and Cdc48p-dependent release of unmodified CPY* was
tested as in (C). Shown are means and standard deviation of three experiments.
      </p>
      <p>
       (F) Bead-immobilized Hrd1p was incubated with untagged, fluorescently labeled Hrd1p.
After ubiquitination and washing, the beads were incubated with the indicated components.
The material released from the beads was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence
scanning.
      </p>
      <p>
       (G) Quantification of three experiments performed as in (E) (means and standard
deviations).
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S4
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We noticed that non-ubiquitinated CPY* and sCPY* were also
released from Hrd1p by Cdc48p activity (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4A
     </xref>
     and
     <a>
      S4A
     </a>
     ). This was confirmed in
experiments in which CPY* was added after the ubiquitination reaction, so that
only Hrd1p was modified (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4C
     </xref>
     ; quantification in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4D
     </xref>
     ). Some CPY* was released from the
beads without Cdc48p action, likely because ubiquitinated Hrd1p is partially dissociating
from the beads. No release was seen for substrate bound to non-ubiquitinated Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4C,D
     </xref>
     ). Similar results were obtained with
sCPY* and sCPY*-DHFR (
     <a>
      Figures S4C,D
     </a>
     ), although more spontaneous release was seen with sCPY*,
consistent with its reduced binding affinity for Hrd1p. Together, these data indicate that
the Cdc48p ATPase complex is first recruited to poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p and then uses ATP
hydrolysis to release both poly-ubiquitinated and non-ubiquitinated substrate from
Hrd1p.
    </p>
    <p>
     To test whether auto-ubiquitination at a specific site is required for the
release of non-ubiquitinated substrate, we employed Lys-mutants of Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4E
     </xref>
     ). The release was significantly reduced with the RKK and
KRK mutants, but was even stimulated with the KKR mutant. Thus, ubiquitin chains attached
to either one of the N-terminal regions, but not the C-terminal tail, are required for
efficient release of non-modified substrate from Hrd1p.
    </p>
    <p>
     We next tested whether substrate release from Hrd1p is mediated by the
dissociation of Hrd1p oligomers. Streptavidin beads were incubated with a mixture of
Hrd1p-SBP and fluorescently labeled Hrd1p, so that labeled Hrd1p was bound to the beads
through Hrd1p-SBP. After poly-ubiquitination, the addition of Cdc48p, Ufd1p/Npl4p, and ATP
led to the dissociation of ∼80% of labeled poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4F
     </xref>
     , lane 4;
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
4G
     </xref>
     ). Significantly less Hrd1p was released when ATP was depleted with Hk/G, or in
the absence of Ufd1/Npl4p (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4F
     </xref>
     , lanes 7 and 3;
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4G
     </xref>
     ). These results indicate that the Cdc48p
ATPase causes the dissociation of poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p oligomers. As monomers bind
substrate more weakly (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1G
     </xref>
     ), this may explain
the release of substrate from Hrd1p, particularly the release of non-ubiquitinated
substrate, which itself cannot interact with the Cdc48p complex. Cdc48p complex added
directly to the ubiquitination reaction reduced substrate modification (
     <a>
      Figure S4E
     </a>
     ), consistent with increased
substrate release. Auto-ubiquitination was not affected (
     <a>
      Figure S4E
     </a>
     ), as expected from an
intra-molecular reaction (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2D
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Involvement of the DUB enzyme Otu1p in ERAD
    </title>
    <p>
     Since the DUB enzyme Yod1p had been implicated in ERAD-L (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Ernst et al., 2009
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Rumpf and
Jentsch, 2006
     </xref>
     ), we next investigated the role of its yeast homolog Otu1p.
Expression of an inactive Otu1p mutant (Otu1p C120S), but not wild type Otu1p, strongly
inhibited the degradation of the ERAD-L substrate sCPY*-DHFR in
     <em>
      S.
cerevisiae
     </em>
     cells (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 5A,B
     </xref>
     ). The Hrd1p
levels were not greatly affected (
     <a>
      Figure
S5A
     </a>
     ). The degradation of the ERAD-C substrate Erg1p was also inhibited (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 5C,D
     </xref>
     ). Although Otu1p C120S expression inhibited
cell growth (
     <a>
      Figure S5B
     </a>
     ), the
effect on ERAD occurred in viable cells, as demonstrated by the degradation of the
cytosolic proteasome substrate Deg1-LacZ (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures
5C,D
     </xref>
     ; and data not shown). As Deg1-LacZ degradation does not depend on Cdc48p
(
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Ravid et al., 2006
     </xref>
     ), the Otu1p mutant seems to
affect only Cdc48p-dependent substrates. Indeed, deletion of the Cdc48p-interacting Ubx
domain from Otu1p C120S greatly reduced the inhibition (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 5A,B
     </xref>
     ). Otu1p does not seem to be the only DUB involved in ERAD, as a
yeast strain lacking Otu1p did not show ERAD-L defects (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 5E,F
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 5
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Cdc48p-dependent function of Otu1p
       <em>
        in vivo
       </em>
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) The degradation of a fusion of sCPY* with DHFR and a hemagglutinin (HA) tag
(sCPY*-DHFR-HA) was tested in
       <em>
        S. cerevisiae
       </em>
       . The cells were
transformed with an empty vector or plasmids expressing FLAG-tagged wild type or mutant
Otu1p (Otu1p (C120S)) from a Gal1 promoter. Where indicated, Otu1p variants lacking their
Ubx domains were expressed instead. The samples were analyzed at different time points
after addition of cycloheximide (chx) by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with anti-HA and
anti-FLAG antibodies. Loading controls were performed with Kar2p antibodies.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Quantification of two experiments as in (A) (means and standard deviations).
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) As in (A), but following simultaneously the degradation of Erg1p and Deg1-LacZ with
antibodies to the endogenous protein and to LacZ, respectively.
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) Quantification of three experiments as in (C) (means and standard deviations).
      </p>
      <p>
       (E) The degradation of sCPY*-DHFR-HA was analyzed in cells lacking Otu1p and wild
type (wt) cells. Cells lacking Hrd1p were analyzed in parallel.
      </p>
      <p>
       (F) Quantification of the experiment in (E).
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S5
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     To analyze Otu1p
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
     , we expressed a His-tagged version
and purified it by Ni-affinity chromatography and gel filtration (
     <a>
      Figure S1C
     </a>
     ). Otu1p de-ubiquitinated modified
fluorescently labeled Hrd1p or CPY* efficiently only when Cdc48p and Ufd1/Npl4p
were present (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6A-C
     </xref>
     ). Much less
de-ubiquitination was observed with Otu1p and Cdc48p alone, even though they interact with
one another, consistent with the slow reaction previously observed (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Rumpf and Jentsch, 2006
     </xref>
     ). Addition of Ufd1p/Npl4p alone
significantly accelerated Otu1p action (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures
6A,B
     </xref>
     ), in contrast to another ubiquitin-binding protein (Rad23p) (data not shown).
As expected, the Otu1p C120S mutant was inactive (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
6B
     </xref>
     ). ATP hydrolysis by Cdc48p stimulated de-ubiquitination by Otu1p, as shown
with an ATPase-deficient Cdc48p mutant (E588Q mutation) and by ATP-depletion with Hk/G
(
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6B
     </xref>
     ). Otu1p needs to bind to the Cdc48p
complex, as deletion of the Ubx domain drastically reduced DUB activity (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6B
     </xref>
     ). Similar results were obtained with poly-ubiquitinated
Hrd1p containing fluorescently labeled ubiquitin, instead of labeled Hrd1p (
     <a>
      Figures S6A,B
     </a>
     ). Otu1p removes short
ubiquitin chains, rather than individual ubiquitin molecules, and it does not completely
de-ubiquitinate Hrd1p.
    </p>
    <fig id="F6" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 6
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Cdc48p-dependent
       <em>
        in vitro
       </em>
       de-ubiquitination by Otu1p
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Bead-immobilized fluorescently labeled Hrd1p-SBP was incubated with the
ubiquitination machinery. After washing, Hrd1p was eluted from the beads with biotin and
incubated with the indicated components (Ufd1/Npl4p; UN) for different time periods in the
presence of ATP. Hrd1p was in a 30-fold excess over Otu1p, whereas all other components
were about equimolar to Hrd1p. The samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and
fluorescence-scanning.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Quantification of experiments performed as in (A). The disappearance of the longest
ubiquitin chains was quantified under different conditions (means and standard deviation
of three experiments). ATP was depleted with hexokinase/glucose (Hk/G). Where indicated,
an ATPase-defective Cdc48p mutant (Cdc48p E588Q) or an Otu1p mutant lacking the Ubx domain
were used.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) Bead-immobilized complexes of Hrd1p-SBP and CPY*, labeled with different
fluorescent dyes, were treated as in (A). The de-ubiquitination of modified Hrd1p and
CPY* was followed in parallel (solid and broken lines, respectively). Shown are
the means and standard deviations of three experiments.
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) Bead-immobilized ubiquitinated Hrd1-SBP was incubated with Cdc48p complex in the
presence of ATPγS. After washing, the beads were incubated for 1 h with the
indicated components. Supernatants and beads were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie
staining.
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S6
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     We found that Otu1p inhibited Cdc48p-dependent substrate-release by only
∼50%, even at high concentrations (data not shown). Thus, Cdc48p often
functions before Otu1p had a chance to make the ubiquitin chains too short. On the other
hand, experiments with bead-immobilized poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p showed that extended
incubation with Otu1p causes most of the Cdc48p complex to eventually dissociate, both in
the absence or presence of ATP hydrolysis (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6D
     </xref>
     ;
see supernatants in lanes 7 and 3 versus 6 and 1). The inactive Otu1p C120S mutant had no
effect. These data suggest that Cdc48p function generally precedes Otu1p-mediated trimming
of the ubiquitin chains. Interestingly, Ubx2p inhibited Cdc48p-dependent de-ubiquitination
(
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6C
     </xref>
     ), suggesting that
     <em>
      in
vivo
     </em>
     it could help to prevent the premature function of Otu1p at the
membrane.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Cdc48p-dependent protein extraction from reconstituted proteoliposomes
    </title>
    <p>
     Finally, we tested whether the ERAD-L reactions would also occur with Hrd1p
reconstituted into proteoliposomes. Proteoliposomes were generated by detergent removal
from a mixture of purified Hrd1p and synthetic phospholipids, both in DMNG. We also added
a fluorescently labeled lipid (Texas-Red phosphatidyl ethanolamine; TR-PE) prior to
detergent removal. The reconstituted vesicles, including labeled Hrd1p and lipid, floated
in a Nycodenz-step gradient (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7A
     </xref>
     ). The majority
of Hrd1p was found in the second fraction from the top, while much of the lipid floated
all the way to the top, indicating that some vesicles contain no protein and others Hrd1p
oligomers. Most Hrd1p molecules have their cytoplasmic domain exposed to the outside of
the vesicles, as demonstrated by the accessibility of a C-terminal TEV cleavage site to
the TEV protease (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7B
     </xref>
     ). When labeled
Hrd1p-containing proteoliposomes or protein-free liposomes were mixed with fluorescently
labeled CPY*, only ∼10% of substrate floated with the
proteoliposomes (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7C
     </xref>
     ; blue and black columns).
Thus, substrate binds only weakly to the cytoplasmic side of membrane-incorporated Hrd1p.
Next we co-reconstituted labeled CPY* and Hrd1p into vesicles. Flotation
experiments showed that essentially all substrate co-migrated with the reconstituted
vesicles (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7C
     </xref>
     ; red columns). The efficiency of
co-flotation correlated with the binding affinity of substrate for Hrd1p in detergent;
∼40% were found for sCPY* (not shown), whereas wild type CPY did
not float at all (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7C
     </xref>
     ). Addition of trypsin to
the proteoliposomes showed that labeled CPY* was not protected by the lipid
bilayer (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7D
     </xref>
     ), indicating that the substrate is
bound to the transmembrane domain of Hrd1p with segment(s) exposed to the outside of the
vesicles.
    </p>
    <fig id="F7" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 7
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Membrane Extraction of Poly-ubiquitinated Proteins by Cdc48p
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Proteoliposomes containing fluorescently labeled Hrd1p-SBP and Texas-red labeled
phosphatidyl ethanolamine (TR-PE) were subjected to flotation in a Nycodenz gradient.
Fractions were collected from the top, and analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning
of the gel. The lipid content of the fractions was determined by absorbance at 590 nm.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Proteoliposomes containing Hrd1p-SBP with a TEV-cleavage site at the C-terminus were
treated with TEV protease in the absence or presence of DMNG. The samples were analyzed by
SDS-PAGE and staining with Coomassie blue.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) Fluorescently labeled CPY* was incubated with either protein-free liposomes
or proteoliposomes containing Hrd1p, or it was co-reconstituted with Hrd1p into vesicles
(black, light blue and red bars, respectively). The samples were subjected to flotation in
a Nycodenz gradient and fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning.
Wild type CPY was used as a control.
      </p>
      <p>
       (D) Proteoliposomes containing Hrd1p and labeled CPY* were incubated with trypsin
in the absence or presence of DMNG. The samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence
scanning.
      </p>
      <p>
       (E) Proteoliposomes were generated by co-reconstitution of Hrd1p with either CPY*
or wild type CPY. Hrd1p and substrate were labeled with different fluorophores. The
vesicles were incubated with the ubiquitination machinery for different time periods, and
samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning. For Hrd1p, the gel was
cropped to only show the disappearance of unmodified protein.
      </p>
      <p>
       (F) The disappearance of unmodified protein in (D) was quantitated. Solid and broken
lines show the modification of substrate and Hrd1p, respectively.
      </p>
      <p>
       (G) Fluorescently labeled Hrd1p and CPY* were co-reconstituted into
proteoliposomes. The vesicles were incubated with the ubiquitination machinery, followed
by incubation in the absence or presence of the Cdc48p complex (Cdc48p/UN). The vesicles
were floated in a Nycodenz gradient and fractions analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence
scanning.
      </p>
      <p>
       (H) Experiments as in (G) were quantified by determining the total fluorescence in the
bottom two fractions (material released from the vesicles) as a fraction of the total
fluorescence in the gradient (mean and standard deviation of at least three experiments).
Where indicated, ATP was depleted with hexokinase/glucose (Hk/G) or an ATPase-deficient
Cdc48p mutant (Cdc48p E588Q) was used.
      </p>
      <p>
       (I) As in (G), but with Hrd1p mutants carrying Lys to Arg mutations in three different
regions. Quantification of three experiments was done as in (H).
      </p>
      <p>
       See also
       <a>
        Figure S7
       </a>
       .
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Next we incubated proteoliposomes containing labeled Hrd1p and substrate with
the ubiquitination machinery. About 80% of both Hrd1p and CPY* were
poly-ubiquitinated (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7E,F
     </xref>
     ). Wild type CPY
remained largely unmodifed. About 90% of poly-ubquitinated Hrd1p and CPY*
floated with the vesicles in a Nycodenz gradient (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
7G
     </xref>
     ; lanes 1-6), indicating that poly-ubiquitination alone does not extract
proteins from the membrane. Ubiquitination increased the density of the vesicles.
Unmodified Hrd1p and CPY* also shifted their position in the gradient, consistent
with the observation that the vesicles contain multiple Hrd1p molecules, some of which
become poly-ubiquitinated.
    </p>
    <p>
     Finally, we tested whether poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p- and CPY*-molecules
are extracted from the membrane by the Cdc48p complex. Proteoliposomes containing
fluorescently labeled Hrd1p and CPY* were incubated with the ubiquitination
machinery, followed by the addition of Cdc48p and Ufd1p/Npl4p. The sample was then
subjected to flotation in a Nycodenz gradient. Approximately 20-25% of
CPY* and up to 35% of Hrd1p were found in the bottom fractions (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 7G
     </xref>
     , lanes 7-12; quantification in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7H
     </xref>
     ), indicating that they were no longer associated with
the liposomes. Longer incubation times or higher Cdc48p complex concentrations did not
increase the efficiency of membrane extraction (
     <a>
      Figure S7A,B
     </a>
     ). No membrane extraction was
observed in the absence of ubiquitination, when Cdc48p or Ufd1p/Npl4p were omitted, when
an ATPase-defective Cdc48p mutant was used, or when ATP was depleted with Hk/G (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7H
     </xref>
     ). The extracted Hrd1p and CPY* proteins
carried relatively short ubiquitin chains (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
7G
     </xref>
     ); most of the longer chains remained in the floated fractions, suggesting that
they are poor substrates for the Cdc48p complex.
    </p>
    <p>
     Otu1p addition inhibited the membrane extraction of poly-ubiquitinated proteins
to a maximum of ∼50% (
     <a>
      Figures S7C,D
     </a>
     ), similar to the effect of Otu1p on substrate release from Hrd1p
in detergent (data not shown). The inactive Otu1p C120S mutant had no effect on membrane
extraction, even when added in a 10-fold excess over Cdc48p (
     <a>
      Figure S7D
     </a>
     ), suggesting that its effect
     <em>
      in vivo
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 5A,B
     </xref>
     ) is caused
at a step following substrate release into the cytosol.
    </p>
    <p>
     All three Hrd1p mutants with Lys mutations showed reduced extraction of
poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p from the membrane (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure
7I
     </xref>
     ), consistent with their lowered level of modification (
     <a>
      Figure S2D
     </a>
     ). The site of modification does not
seem to be important, in contrast to the release of unmodified substrate from
poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1 in detergent (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4E
     </xref>
     ).
Although less pronounced, the site of modification also affected the extraction of
poly-ubiquitinated substrate from Hrd1p-containing proteoliposomes, as the RKK mutant had
a significantly stronger effect on substrate- than Hrd1p- extraction (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7I
     </xref>
     ). The KKR mutant was not affected in membrane extraction
of the substrate (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7I
     </xref>
     ), indicating that
modification of the C-terminal tail is not required for substrate release from Hrd1p, and
suggesting that substrate is not obligatorily extracted as a complex with Hrd1p.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    We have reproduced key steps of ERAD-L with purified protein components, both in
detergent and in reconstituted proteoliposomes. Our minimal
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    system
mimics essential aspects of ERAD-L
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    when Hrd1p is overexpressed
(basic ERAD-L). In both systems, glycosylated and non-glycosylated misfolded proteins serve
as substrates for Hrd1p, and Hrd1p itself is poly-ubiquitinated and extracted from the
membrane. Since Hrd1p appears to be the only membrane component required for a basic ERAD-L
reaction
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    , and because Hrd1p is sufficient for the binding and
membrane extraction of misfolded proteins
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    , it is likely to form a
channel for the transport of misfolded proteins through the ER membrane.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    system allowed us to break down the basic ERAD-L
process into individual steps. First, Hrd1p binds unfolded polypeptides through its
membrane-spanning domain. Next, both Hrd1p and substrate are poly-ubiquitinated, resulting
in the recruitment of the Cdc48p ATPase complex, a process mediated by the cofactor
Ufd1p/Npl4p and facilitated by the adaptor protein Ubx2p. Then, the poly-ubiquitinated
proteins are extracted from the membrane by the Cdc48p complex in an ATP
hydrolysis-dependent reaction. Finally, Otu1p trims the poly-ubiquitin chains in a Cdc48p
complex-dependent manner, resulting in the dissociation of the Cdc48p complex from
substrate.
   </p>
   <p>
    In basic ERAD-L, substrates are exclusively selected by Hrd1p. We show that Hrd1p
in detergent discriminates folded from unfolded polypeptides. Hrd1p uses its hydrophobic TM
segments to bind unfolded polypeptide segments. Oligomeric Hrd1p may provide more TMs for
substrate interaction than monomeric Hrd1p, explaining why it has a higher affinity. Hrd1p
does not interact with all hydrophobic polypeptide segments, since it does not bind Ubx2p
(
    <a>
     Figure S3C
    </a>
    ) or a fragment of
Usa1p lacking the N-terminal cytoplasmic interaction domain (data not shown). Perhaps, a
loosely folded polypeptide structure is also required for substrate recognition. It seems
likely that several TMs in Hrd1p interact with an unfolded polypeptide chain because
mutations scattered throughout the membrane-embedded domain of Hrd1p affect different
substrates to varying degrees (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Sato et al., 2009
    </xref>
    ).
Although some substrate interaction may be caused simply by the hydrophobicity of the TMs,
the membrane-embedded domain of Hrd1p must have unique properties, as it needs to be folded,
and only little substrate interaction is seen with purified Usa1p containing two TM segments
(data not shown).
   </p>
   <p>
    Insertion of a polypeptide loop into the Hrd1p channel could be the first step in
the actual retro-translocation process. Such a model would be analogous to loop insertion of
a signal sequence-containing polypeptide into the Sec61/SecY channel during forward
translocation (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Park and Rapoport, 2012
    </xref>
    ). In both
cases, a substrate segment would reach the other side of the membrane and the binding of a
hydrophobic region to the channel would provide the driving force for polypeptide chain
insertion. Our experiments show that a misfolded substrate co-reconstituted with Hrd1p
indeed exposes a segment to the outside of vesicles. As expected, substrate does not bind to
Hrd1p from the cytoplasmic side when added after reconstitution. However, it remains to be
shown that reconstituted Hrd1p can bind substrate on the luminal side of the membrane, as
suggested by experiments in intact yeast cells overexpressing Hrd1p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Carvalho et al., 2010
    </xref>
    ). A system in which the starting
proteoliposomes contain only Hrd1p or substrate and are subsequently fused will also address
whether actual retro-translocation can be reproduced with the purified components.
   </p>
   <p>
    Similarly to forward translocation, a polypeptide chain may be able to slide back
and forth in a Hrd1p channel, but there has to be energy input to achieve net movement into
the cytosol. One possibility is that the attachment of poly-ubiquitin chains to the
substrate would bias polypeptide sliding, providing a ratcheting mechanism for
translocation. However, poly-ubiquitination alone is insufficient to completely move a
polypeptide chain from the ER membrane into the cytosol, as shown both
    <em>
     in
vivo
    </em>
    (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Flierman et al., 2003
    </xref>
    ) and by our
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    experiments; this requires the function of the Cdc48p complex as
well. In fact, our data indicate that the Cdc48p complex is sufficient to move
poly-ubiquitinated proteins into the cytosol, although other cytosolic factors could be
stimulatory. Current models assume that the Cdc48p-binding poly-ubiquitin chains need to be
attached to the substrate, but our data raise the possibility that the crucial modification
is on Hrd1p itself. We show that Cdc48p releases unmodified substrate from
poly-ubiquitinated Hrd1p in detergent, probably by disassembling Hrd1p oligomers into
smaller assemblies that have a lower affinity for substrate. Indeed, for Cdc48p's
segregase activity, it is not necessary that the ubiquitin chains are attached to the
protein extracted from the membrane, as shown for the generation of the transcription
factors Mga2p and Spt23p. Here, Cdc48p action releases an unmodified polypeptide (the p90
fragment) into the cytosol by acting on poly-ubiquitin chains attached to an associated
membrane-anchored protein (the p120 precursor) (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Shcherbik
and Haines, 2007
    </xref>
    ). Auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p followed by Cdc48p function could
provide the driving force for retro-translocation by allowing substrate segments to move
through the membrane by multiple rounds of binding to and release from Hrd1p. Such a model
does not exclude a role for substrate ubiquitination, which could determine directionality
of polypeptide movement by a ratcheting mechanism or by interaction with the Cdc48p
complex.
   </p>
   <p>
    A model in which auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p is a crucial modification event
would be consistent with studies that showed that substrates, in which all Lys residues are
removed, continue to be degraded; in these cases, the ubiquitination machinery was still
required, suggesting that a protein other than the substrate is ubiquitinated (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Hassink et al., 2006
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Wang et al., 2013
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Yu and Kopito, 1999
    </xref>
    ).
There are also ERAD-L substrates, such as prepro-a-factor and cholera toxin, which are never
ubiquitinated and whose retro-translocation can be blocked with a dominant-negative DUB
(
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Bernardi et al., 2013
    </xref>
    ), again indicating
ubiquitination of another component. Protease-protection studies showed that ubiquitination
is required to expose a substrate segment to the cytosol (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Jarosch et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ), and photo-crosslinking demonstrated that the ubiquitination
activity of Hrd1p and Cdc48p action are needed for an early Hrd1p-substrate interaction on
the luminal side of the membrane (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Carvalho et al.,
2010
    </xref>
    ). These results suggest that ubiquitination by Hrd1 p of a component other
than substrate is crucial for ERAD-L.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although a role for auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p is attractive, it is difficult to
exclude that at least some Hrd1 p modification is the result of a non-specific side reaction
that has been observed with other ligases. Indeed, we found that ubiquitination of the
C-terminal tail of Hrd1p has no effect on substrate modification and release. There is also
little evidence that Hrd1p is poly-ubiquitinated in wild type yeast cells. It is therefore
possible that Hrd1p modification and Cdc48p-dependent extraction serve to regulate Hrd1p
levels in the membrane. However, because auto-ubiquitination occurs in an intramolecular
reaction, our results argue that Hrd1p molecules do not recognize each other as unfolded
ERAD-M substrates. Regardless of whether auto-ubiquitination is required for ERAD or as a
regulatory mechanism, it is minimized in wild type cells.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    results faithfully recapitulate what is observed
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    in Hrd1p-overexpressing yeast cells. However, they do not
recapitulate substrate selection as seen in wild type cells, where the additional ERAD
components Yos9p, Hrd3p, and Der1p ensure that only genuine substrates are degraded (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Denic et al., 2006
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Gauss
et al., 2006
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Mehnert et al., 2013
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Xie and Ng, 2010
    </xref>
    ). Our results indicate that recognition
of an unfolded polypeptide by Hrd1p is the last checkpoint before substrate is committed to
retro-translocation and degradation. This may explain why bypassing all upstream steps in
Hrd1p-overexpressing cells slows, but does not prevent, cell growth. In addition, Hrd1p may
provide the main checkpoint for non-glycosylated ERAD substrates. The additional ERAD
components may also minimize excessive auto-ubiquitination and membrane extraction of Hrd1p.
Hrd3p has a particularly important role, as in its absence, Hrd1p is poly-ubiquitinated and
degraded (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Gardner et al., 2000
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Plemper et al., 1999
    </xref>
    ). Perhaps, Hrd3p is regulating
auto-ubiquitination of Hrd1p in response to substrate binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our results support the idea that DUBs, specifically Otu1p, play a role in ERAD.
We show that Otu1p is only activated after recruitment by the Cdc48p complex. This ensures
that poly-ubiquitination, Cdc48p recruitment, and de-ubiquitination occur in a sequential
manner. Our data suggest that Cdc48p-mediated membrane extraction precedes Otu1p function,
so that most substrate de-ubiquitination occurs in the cytosol. Ubx2p could help to prevent
premature de-ubiquitination at the membrane by competing with Otu1p for Cdc48p binding. The
kinetic delay would guarantee that Otu1p does not interfere with Cdc48p's function
as a segregase. The sequential action of Cdc48p and Otu1p would be further enhanced by the
ubiquitin ligase Hrd1p counteracting de-ubiquitination at the membrane, but not in the
cytosol. A function of Otu1p downstream of Cdc48p's segregase activity explains why
overexpression of wild type Otu1p does not affect ERAD
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    . The
inactive Otu1p mutant would inhibit by interacting with poly-ubiquitin chains bound to the
Cdc48p complex, preventing the dissociation of Ufd1p/Npl4p, and blocking the access of other
DUBs. Indeed, expression of the equivalent Yod1p mutant in mammalian cells leads to the
accumulation of ubiquitinated substrate bound to the ATPase complex (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Ernst et al., 2009
    </xref>
    ). The inactive Otu1p mutant does not inhibit
membrane extraction
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    , because there is probably no need for
recycling of the Cdc48p complex. Otu1p/Yod1p probably function not only in ERAD, but also in
other processes involving the Cdc48p/Ufd1p/Npl4p complex.
   </p>
   <p>
    Finally, our results suggest that ERAD-L proceeds through an intermediate in which
the substrate is bound to the membrane-embedded domain of Hrd1p, a situation that resembles
the recognition of an ERAD-M substrate. Thus, ERAD-M substrates may enter the same process
at a later stage, explaining why the same ubiquitin ligase (Hrd1p) is involved, and why
ERAD-M requires only a subset of the ERAD-L components. Many other ubiquitin ligases, such
as Doa10p involved in ERAD-C, are also multi-spanning membrane proteins. As proposed
previously for Doa10p (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Swanson et al., 2001
    </xref>
    ), the
membrane-spanning domains may serve as conduits for polypeptides through the membrane.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <p>
    Details of protein purifications and experimental procedures are described in
Extended Experimental Procedures.
   </p>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Protein Expression and Purification
    </title>
    <p>
     All proteins are from
     <em>
      S. cerevisiae
     </em>
     . Uba1p, Ubx2p, and the
substrates CPY*, sCPY*, sCPY*-DHFR, and CPY, as well as Hrd1p and
its variants were expressed in
     <em>
      S. cerevisiae
     </em>
     under the Gal1 promoter. All
other proteins were expressed in
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     strain BL21 DE3 RIPL. The
membrane proteins Ubx2p and Hrd1p and its variants were solubilized in DMNG. ERAD
substrates were extracted from a crude membrane fraction with urea. Hrd1p and its variants
were first purified by streptavidin affinity chromatography utilizing a C-terminal
streptavidin-binding peptide (SBP) tag, followed by gel filtration. All other proteins
were purified as His-tagged variants by Ni-affinity chromatography, followed by ion
exchange chromatography and/or gel filtration. Unless noted otherwise, the tags were
proteolytically removed.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Labeling with Fluorescent Dyes
    </title>
    <p>
     The substrates sCPY*, sCPY*-DHFR, sCPY*-GFP, DHFR, and
GFP were labeled at a C-terminally attached Cys residue with DyLight 800 maleimide.
CPY* and CPY were labeled with a N-hydroxy-succinimidyl ester of DyLight 800.
Hrd1p was labeled using the sortase technique.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Ubiquitination Assays
    </title>
    <p>
     All ubiquitination assays were performed at 30°C. Unless indicated
otherwise, the concentrations of the components of the ubiquitination machinery were: 100
nM Uba1p, 1 μM Ubc7p, 1μM Cue1p-c, 100 nM Hrd1p, 100 nM substrate, 100
μM ubiquitin, 2.5 mM ATP.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Binding and Release Experiments
    </title>
    <p>
     All binding experiments were performed at room temperature with Hrd1p
immobilized on magnetic streptavidin beads via its C-terminal SBP-tag. Unbound and bound
fluorescent material was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning of the gel in an
Odyssey scanner (Li-COR). Binding of substrates or Cdc48p to ubiquitinated Hrd1p was
tested by first immobilizing Hrd1p-SBP on beads at room temperature for 1h and then adding
the ubiquitination machinery.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Reconstitution into Proteoliposomes and Density Gradients
    </title>
    <p>
     For reconstitution of Hrd1p, protein-free liposomes (final lipid concentration
10 mM, containing 0.5 mol% Texas Red labeled phosphatidyl ethanolamine) were mixed
with DMNG (15 mM), Hrd1p (2 μM) and, optionally, with substrate (0.5 μM),
and incubated for 1h at room temperature. This mixture was applied to detergent-removal
spin columns (Pierce).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     <em>
      In vivo
     </em>
     ERAD-Substrate Degradation Experiments
    </title>
    <p>
     Cycloheximide shutoff experiments were performed essentially as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Carvalho et al., 2010
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     1
    </title>
    <p>
     Figure S1. Characterization of the Purified ERAD Components and Substrates
(Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1
     </xref>
     )
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S2. Ubiquitination of Substrate and Hrd1p (Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2
     </xref>
     )
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S3. Recruitment of Cdc48p to Ubiquitinated Hrd1p (Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3
     </xref>
     )
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S4. Release of Substrate from Hrd1p by Cdc48p (Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4
     </xref>
     )
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S5. Otu1p function in vivo (Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 5
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S6. Cdc48p-dependent in vitro de-ubiquitination by Otu1p (Related to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 6
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Figure S7. Membrane Extraction of Poly-ubiquitinated Proteins by Cdc48p (Related
to
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 7
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (176K, docx)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     2
    </title>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (74K, docx)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>