<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC3551298
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Long Pentraxin 3/TSG-6 Interaction: a Biological Rheostat for Fibroblast Growth Factor 2-Mediated Angiogenesis
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
  <abstract>
   <sec>
    <sec>
     <title>
      Objective
     </title>
     <p>
      Angiogenesis is regulated by the balance between pro- and anti-angiogenic factors and by extracellular matrix protein interactions. Fibroblast growth factor-2 (FGF2) is a major pro-angiogenic inducer inhibited by the interaction with the soluble pattern recognition receptor long pentraxin 3 (PTX3). PTX3 is locally co-expressed with its ligand TSG-6, a secreted glycoprotein that co-operates with PTX3 in extracellular matrix assembly. Here, we characterized the effect of TSG-6 on PTX3/FGF2 interaction and FGF2-mediated angiogenesis.
     </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     <title>
      Methods and Results
     </title>
     <p>
      Solid phase binding and surface plasmon resonance assays show that TSG-6 and FGF2 bind the PTX3 N-terminal domain with similar affinity. Accordingly, TSG-6 prevents FGF2/PTX3 interaction and suppresses the inhibition exerted by PTX3 on heparan sulfate proteoglycan/FGF2/FGF receptor complex formation and on FGF2-dependent angiogenesis
      <em>
       in vitro
      </em>
      and
      <em>
       in vivo
      </em>
      . Also, endogenous PTX3 exerts an inhibitory effect on vascularization induced by FGF2 in a murine s.c. Matrigel plug assay, the inhibition being abolished in
      <em>
       Ptx3
      </em>
      -null mice or by TSG-6 treatment in wild-type animals.
     </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
     <title>
      Conclusions
     </title>
     <p>
      TSG-6 reverts the inhibitory effects exerted by PTX3 on FGF2-mediated angiogenesis through competition of FGF2/PTX3 interaction. This may provide a novel mechanism to control angiogenesis in those pathological settings characterized by the co-expression of TSG-6 and PTX3, in which the relative levels of these proteins may fine-tune the angiogenic activity of FGF2.
     </p>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <strong>
     Keywords:
    </strong>
    <span>
     angiogenesis, endothelium, FGF2, pentraxin, TSG-6
    </span>
   </sec>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Methods
   </title>
   <p>
    The detailed descriptions of the methods that were used in this study are provided in the
    <a>
     supplemental materials
    </a>
    (available online at
    <a>
     http://atvb.ahajournals.org
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Solid phase binding assays
    </title>
    <p>
     96 well microtiter plates were coated with PTX3, N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 or C
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3, TSG-6, Link_TSG6 or CUB_C_TSG6 and incubated with the proteins under test for 1 hour at 37 °C. Bound proteins were detected using the corresponding primary antibody. In competition experiments, bound biotinylated PTX3 (bPTX3) was revealed by incubation with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated streptavidin and absorbance was read at 405 nm.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Surface plasmon resonance
    </title>
    <p>
     A BIAcore X system (BIAcore Inc., Piscataway, NJ) was used to analyze the binding of FGF2, wild-type and TSG-6 mutants, Link_TSG6 and CUB_C_TSG6 to PTX3 immobilized on CM4 sensor chips
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       20
      </xref>
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Cross-linking assay
    </title>
    <p>
     FGF2 (11 pmoles) was incubated for 1 hour at room temperature with PTX3 (55 pmoles) in a 30 μL volume of PBS containing 1.25 mmol/L bis[sulfosuccinimidyl]suberate in the absence or presence of TSG-6 (110 pmoles). Reaction products were separated by SDS-PAGE and revealed by Western blotting with either anti-FGF2 or anti-PTX3 antibodies.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     FGF2-mediated cell-cell adhesion assay
    </title>
    <p>
     FGFR1-overexpressing, HSPG-deficient chinese hamster ovary cells (A745 CHO flg-1A; 50,000 cells/cm
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     ) were incubated on glutaraldehyde-fixed wild type CHO-K1 cell monolayers with or without 1.66 nmol/L of FGF2 in the absence or presence of PTX3 or N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 (220 nmol/L) and increasing doses of TSG-6. After 2 hours at 37 °C, A745 CHO flg-1A cells bound to the CHO-K1 cell monolayers were counted
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       39
      </xref>
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     EC proliferation assay
    </title>
    <p>
     Subconfluent cultures of ECs were incubated in medium containing 0.4% (v/v) FCS
     <em>
      plus
     </em>
     FGF2 (0.55 nmol/L) in the absence or presence of PTX3 (220 nmol/L) and increasing doses of wildtype or TSG-6 mutants or Link_TSG6. Following 24 hours incubation, cells were trypsinized and counted
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       20
      </xref>
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Chicken embryo chorioallantoic membrane (CAM) assay
    </title>
    <p>
     Alginate beads containing vehicle or FGF2 (8 pmoles) with or without PTX3 (33 pmoles) and TSG-6 (83 pmoles) were placed on top of the CAM at day 11 of incubation. After 72 hours, blood vessels converging toward the implant were counted under a stereomicroscope by two observers in a double-blind fashion
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       40
      </xref>
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Matrigel plug angiogenesis assay
    </title>
    <p>
     Six week old female C57BL/6 wild type and
     <em>
      Ptx3
     </em>
     <sup>
      -/-
     </sup>
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       41
      </xref>
     </sup>
     mice were injected s.c. with 400 μL of Matrigel containing PBS or 4.0 pmoles of FGF2 and/or 33 pmoles of TSG-6. After 7 days, pellets were processed for total RNA extraction and the levels of expression of PTX3, FGF2, TSG-6 and VEGF-A were assayed by semi-quantitative RT-PCR in representative samples. The vascular response was quantified by evaluation of the levels of expression of the endothelial marker CD31 by quantitative RT-PCR.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Immunohistochemistry
    </title>
    <p>
     Sections of human atherosclerotic carotid artery specimens, human gastric carcinoma and human pleomorphic parotid adenoma biopsies were immunostained with anti-human PTX3, anti-human TSG-6, and anti-human FGF2 polyclonal antibodies.
    </p>
    <p>
     Throughout the whole paper, PTX3 concentrations are expressed as concentrations of PTX3 protomer.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     TSG-6 binds the N-terminal domain of PTX3 via the Link module
    </title>
    <p>
     Previous observations suggest that TSG-6 interacts with PTX3 through its Link module at a distinct site from the HA-binding surface
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       37
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1A
     </xref>
     , PTX3 bound to microtiter plates coated with full-length human TSG-6 or with its Link module domain (Link_TSG6) whereas little or no interaction was observed when a recombinant preparation of the CUB_C domain (CUB_C_TSG6) was applied. Accordingly, real time surface plasmon resonance analysis shows that both full length TSG-6 and Link_TSG6, but not CUB_C_TSG6, bind PTX3 immobilized to the sensorchip (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1B
     </xref>
     ). Kinetic fitting of sensorgrams gave equilibrium dissociation constants (
     <em>
      k
      <sub>
       d
      </sub>
     </em>
     ) of 314 nmol/L and 648 nmol/L for the binding of full length TSG-6 and Link_TSG6 to PTX3, respectively (
     <a>
      Supplemental Figure I
     </a>
     ). Similar results were obtained when Scatchard plot regression was performed on binding data acquired under state steady conditions (data not shown).
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       The Link module of TSG-6 binds PTX3.
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Microtiter plates were coated with 25 pmoles/well of TSG-6 (■),Link_TSG6 (△) or CUB_C_TSG6 (▲) and incubated with PTX3. Bound protein was detected using the anti-human PTX3 polyclonal antibody αPTX3pb. Data are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 12).
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) TSG-6, Link_TSG6 and CUB_C_TSG6 were injected onto a PTX3-coated sensorchip and protein binding was monitored by surface plasmon resonance (BIAcore). Sensorgrams are representative of the binding response at analyte concentration of 300 nmol/L.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Consistent with the observation that PTX3 and HA recognize distinct surfaces on TSG-6
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       37
      </xref>
     </sup>
     , the TSG-6
     <sub>
      Y94F
     </sub>
     mutant, which has greatly reduced (~100-fold) HA-binding activity (
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       42
      </xref>
     </sup>
     and A.J Day, unpublished data, 2010), has a similar affinity as wildtype TSG-6 for PTX3 (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure I
     </a>
     ). Conversely, the TSG-6
     <sub>
      Y47F
     </sub>
     mutant, that also has greatly impaired HA-binding activity (A.J Day, unpublished data, 2010), binds PTX3 with somewhat lower affinity than wildtype TSG-6 (~6-fold) suggesting that this amino acid may participate to some extent in PTX3 binding. Mutation of Glu-183, located within the CUB module, to Ser (TSG-6E183S) (A.J Day, unpublished data, 2010), had no affect on PTX3 binding, consistent with the finding that the CUB_C domain does not play a part in the interaction (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure I
     </a>
     ). Taken together, these results demonstrate that the Link module, rather than the CUB_C domain, mediates the binding of TSG-6 to PTX3 and that this interaction occurs with an affinity similar to that reported for FGF2/PTX3 interaction (
     <em>
      k
      <sub>
       d
      </sub>
     </em>
     = 300 nmol/L
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       20
      </xref>
     </sup>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     To identify which region of the PTX3 molecule is involved in the interaction with TSG-6, microtiter plates coated with recombinant forms of the N-terminal and C-terminal domains of PTX3 (N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 and C
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3, respectively) were incubated with TSG-6. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2A
     </xref>
     , TSG-6 bound to immobilized N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 in a concentration-dependent manner, similar to that seen with the full length PTX3 protein, whereas no interaction of TSG-6 with C
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 was observed. Accordingly, Link_TSG6 bound immobilized full-length PTX3 and N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 but not C
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3, whereas CUB_C_TSG6 did not interact with any of the PTX3 domains (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2B
     </xref>
     ). Therefore, it can be concluded that PTX3 interacts with the Link module of TSG-6
     <em>
      via
     </em>
     its N-terminal domain, which is also the site where FGF2 binds
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       13
      </xref>
      ,
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       20
      </xref>
      ,
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       43
      </xref>
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       TSG-6 binds the N-terminal domain of PTX3.
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Full length PTX3 (■) or recombinant domains N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 (△) and C
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 (▲) were immobilized on microtiter plates (15 pmoles/well) and incubated with TSG-6. Bound TSG-6 was detected using the anti-human TSG-6 polyclonal antibody RAH1.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Microtiter plates were coated with 15 pmoles/well of full length PTX3 (black bars), N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 (open bars) or C
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 (dashed bars). Following incubation with full length TSG-6, Link_TSG6 or CUB_C_TSG6 (all at 1 μmol/L), bound proteins were detected with RAH1 (for TSG-6 and CUB_C_TSG6) or Q75 (for Link_TSG6) antibodies. Data are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 12).
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     TSG-6 inhibits the PTX3/FGF2 interaction
    </title>
    <p>
     As described above TSG-6 and FGF2 both bind PTX3 with similar affinities where these interactions are mediated via the N-terminal region of PTX3. This suggests that TSG-6 might be able to modulate the interaction of PTX3 with FGF2. Indeed, TSG-6 competed for the binding of biotinylated PTX3 (bPTX3) to microtiter plates coated with FGF2 with a potency (IC
     <sub>
      50
     </sub>
     ~ 100 nmol/L) similar to that of non-biotinylated PTX3, here used as a positive control (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     ). Also, TSG-6 inhibits the binding of N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 fragment to immobilized FGF2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3B
     </xref>
     ), whereas the short pentraxin serum amyloid P component (SAP), which is homologous to the C-terminal domain of PTX3 but does not bind FGF2 and TSG-6
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       17
      </xref>
     </sup>
     , had no affect on bPTX3/FGF2 interaction. Furthermore, TSG-6 inhibited the chemical cross-linking of the FGF2/PTX3 complex in solution (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure II
     </a>
     ). Thus, TSG-6 acts as an inhibitor of the FGF2 interaction with PTX3.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       TSG-6 inhibits PTX3/FGF2 interaction.
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Microtiter plates were coated with FGF2 (25 pmoles/well) and incubated with 12 nmol/L biotinylated PTX3 (bPTX3) and various concentrations of TSG-6 (■). Bound bPTX3 was detected by incubation with ExtrAvidin™ and absorbance was read at 405 nm. Non-biotinylated PTX3 (△) and SAP (▲) were used as positive and negative controls, respectively.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) FGF2-coated microtiter plates were incubated with 50 nmol/L recombinant N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 and the indicated amounts of TSG-6 (■). Bound N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 was detected with the αPTX3pb antibody. SAP was used as a negative control (▲). In both panels, data are the mean ± SD of three independent experiments in quadruplicate and are expressed as percent of ligand binding in the absence of competitors.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     TSG-6 restores HSPG/FGF2/FGFR ternary complex formation inhibited by PTX3
    </title>
    <p>
     FGF2 exerts its biological activity by leading to the formation of a pro-angiogenic HSPG/FGF2/FGFR ternary complex in ECs
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       8
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . In keeping with its FGF2-antagonist activity, PTX3 inhibits the formation of this ternary complex in a cell-cell adhesion assay
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       39
      </xref>
      ,
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       44
      </xref>
     </sup>
     in which FGF2 mediates the interaction of HSPG-deficient CHO cells stably transfected with FGFR1 to a monolayer of CHO cells expressing HSPGs but not FGFRs (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     ). To investigate the effect of TSG-6 on the inhibitory activity exerted by PTX3 on HSPG/FGF2/FGFR ternary complex formation, cells were incubated with varying concentrations of TSG-6 in the presence of constant amounts of FGF2 and PTX3. As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     , TSG-6 restored FGF2-mediated cell-cell adhesion (i.e. the formation of the intercellular HSPG/FGF2/FGFR complex) in a dose-dependent fashion. It must be pointed out that TSG-6 alone (i.e. in the absence of FGF2 and PTX3) did not induce cell-cell interaction nor did it affect the FGF2-mediated formation of the HSPG/FGF2/FGFR complex when PTX3 was omitted. Similarly, TSG-6 also reversed the inhibitory effect of the N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 fragment on HSPG/FGF2/FGFR complex formation (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure III
     </a>
     ). These data indicate that TSG-6 can rescue the PTX3-mediated inhibition of FGF2 engagement with its receptors, presumably via its competition for the PTX-FGF2 interaction.
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       TSG-6 suppresses the inhibitory effect exerted by PTX3 on FGF2 activity
       <strong>
        . A
       </strong>
       ) FGFR1-overexpressing, HSPG-deficient CHO cells were incubated on a monolayer of CHO-K1 cells with FGF2 (1.66 nmol/L) and the indicated amounts of TSG-6 in absence (○) or presence (●) of PTX3 (220 nmol/L). After 2 hours, bound cells were counted under an inverted microscope. Data are expressed as percentage of the cell-cell adhesion induced by FGF2 alone. Binding of TSG-6-treated cells in the absence of FGF2 and PTX3 is shown as control (□).
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) GM7373 cells were incubated with 0.4% FCS containing 0.56 nmol/L FGF2 and the reported concentrations of TSG-6 in the absence (○) or presence (●) of PTX3 (220 nmol/L). After 24 hours cells were trypsinized and counted. Data are expressed as percentage of GM7373 cells stimulated with FGF2 only. The proliferation of GM7373 cells treated with TSG-6 only (i.e. in the absence of FGF2 and PTX3) is shown as a control (□).
       <strong>
        C, D
       </strong>
       ) Retrovirus-infected PTX3 cells overexpressing PTX3 (PTX3_MAECs, in
       <strong>
        C
       </strong>
       ) or N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3 (N
       <sub>
        term
       </sub>
       PTX3_MAECs, in
       <strong>
        D
       </strong>
       ) were incubated with 0.4% FCS
       <em>
        plus
       </em>
       0.56 nmol/L FGF2 and the indicated amounts of TSG-6 (●). Following 24 hours incubation, cells were trypsinized and counted. Data are expressed as percentage of the proliferation measured in mock-infected cells stimulated with FGF2 only. The proliferation of cells treated with TSG-6 alone is shown as a control (○). In all graphs, intermediate markings on the
       <em>
        x
       </em>
       axis represent the actual concentrations of TSG-6 used in the different assays. Data are the mean ± SD of three experiments performed in triplicate.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     TSG-6 suppresses the inhibitory effect of PTX3 on FGF2-dependent angiogenesis
    </title>
    <p>
     PTX3 inhibits the mitogenic activity exerted by FGF2 on ECs, without affecting the activity of unrelated mitogens
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       19
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . On this basis, TSG-6 was assessed for its capacity to reverse the inhibition caused by PTX3 on FGF2-dependent EC proliferation. To this aim, fetal bovine aortic GM7373 ECs were incubated with FGF2 (0.56 nmol/L), PTX3 (220 nmol/L) and a range of TSG-6 concentrations. Consistent with its ability to restore HSPG/FGF2/FGFR ternary complex formation inhibited by PTX3, increasing doses of TSG-6 progressively restored FGF2-induced EC proliferation in the presence of PTX3 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4B
     </xref>
     ). A similar effect was also seen with the TSG-6 mutants TSG-6
     <sub>
      Y47F
     </sub>
     , TSG-6
     <sub>
      Y94F
     </sub>
     , and TSG-6E183S (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure IV
     </a>
     ) that all retain binding to PTX3 (see
     <a>
      supplemental Figure I
     </a>
     ). It should be noted that TSG-6 alone did not affect EC proliferation when tested in the absence or in the presence of FGF2 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4B
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     To further confirm the capacity of TSG-6 to restore EC proliferation by preventing FGF2/PTX3 interaction, we took advantage of an experimental model in which human PTX3 or the N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3 fragment are endogenously expressed by retrovirus-infected murine aortic ECs (PTX3_MAECs and N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3_MAECs, respectively) and inhibit EC proliferation in response to exogenous FGF2
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       20
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . As shown in
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4C,D
     </xref>
     , increasing doses of TSG-6 progressively restored the capacity of PTX3_MAEC and N
     <sub>
      term
     </sub>
     PTX3_MAEC transfectants to proliferate in response to FGF2. Again, similar activities were seen with the TSG-6 mutant proteins (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure IV
     </a>
     ). These and the data above demonstrate that neither the HA-binding function of TSG-6
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       24
      </xref>
     </sup>
     nor its ability to form covalent complexes with the HCs of IαI
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       36
      </xref>
     </sup>
     (i.e. properties impaired in these mutants) are necessary for TSG-6 to show activity in these angiogenesis assay systems.
    </p>
    <p>
     The capacity of TSG-6 and PTX3 to affect FGF2-induced neovascularization
     <em>
      in vivo
     </em>
     was then investigated in a chicken embryo CAM angiogenesis assay
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       45
      </xref>
     </sup>
     and in a murine s.c. Matrigel plug assay
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       46
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . In the CAM assay, alginate beads adsorbed with FGF2 (8.0 pmoles/embryo) exert a potent angiogenic response when applied on the top of the CAM as compared to beads adsorbed with vehicle. Consistent with the
     <em>
      in vitro
     </em>
     observations, the angiogenic response elicited by FGF2 was significantly reduced by the addition of 33 pmoles of PTX3 to the FGF2 implants (p &lt; 0.001) and this inhibition was fully abolished by co-administration of 83 pmoles of TSG-6. No effect on CAM vascularization was instead exerted by TSG-6 alone (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 5A
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 5
     </label>     <caption>
      <p>
       TSG-6/PTX3 cross-talk modulates FGF2-mediated angiogenesis
       <em>
        in vivo
       </em>
       .
       <strong>
        A
       </strong>
       ) Chicken embryo CAMs were implanted at day 11 with alginate beads containing FGF2 (8 pmoles), PTX3 (33 pmoles) and TSG-6 (83 pmoles) or combinations of these proteins. At day 14, newly-formed thin blood microvessels converging toward the implant in a spoke-wheel pattern (readily distinguishable from preexisting, larger vessels with no directionality)
       <sup>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         45
        </xref>
       </sup>
       were counted. CAM implants that contained vehicle (PBS) or TSG-6 only were used as controls. Data are the mean ± SD (n = 7-11). *, p&lt;0.01, Student’s
       <em>
        t
       </em>
       test.
       <strong>
        B
       </strong>
       ) Wild-type (open bars) and
       <em>
        Ptx3
       </em>
       -null mice (black bars) where injected s.c. with Matrigel plugs containing PBS or 4 pmoles of FGF2 and/or 33 pmoles of TSG-6. After 7 days, pellets were processed for total RNA extraction and the vascular response was quantified by RT-PCR analysis of the expression of the endothelial marker CD31. Data are the mean ± SEM (n = 8-10). *, p&lt;0.05 or better, n.s., not statistically significant, Student’s
       <em>
        t
       </em>
       test.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     Next, the effect of TSG-6 on FGF2-induced angiogenesis was assessed in wild-type and
     <em>
      Ptx3
     </em>
     -null mice using a s.c. Matrigel plug assay (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 5B
     </xref>
     ). It must be pointed out that the s.c. injection of Matrigel induces
     <em>
      per sè
     </em>
     a mild pro-inflammatory reaction
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       47
      </xref>
     </sup>
     , leading to the co-expression within the plug of PTX3, FGF2, TSG-6, and VEGF-A transcripts (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure V
     </a>
     ). Also, no significant difference in the levels of FGF2, TSG-6, and VEGF-A expression occurred in PBS-treated Matrigel plugs injected in
     <em>
      Ptx3
     </em>
     -null mice when compared to plugs implanted in wild-type animals (
     <a>
      supplemental Figure V
     </a>
     ). Consistent with the FGF2-antagonist activity of PTX3, we observed a significant increase of vascularization in both PBS-treated and FGF2-treated plugs implanted in
     <em>
      Ptx3
     </em>
     -deficient mice when compared to wild-type animals, as assessed by quantitative RT-PCR analysis of the levels of expression of the endothelial marker CD31 in the Matrigel plugs
     <sup>
      <xref ref-type="bibr">
       48
      </xref>
     </sup>
     . A similar increase was observed when TSG-6 was added to PBS-treated and FGF2-treated Matrigel plugs implanted in wild-type animals, no further significant increase in vascularization being exerted by TSG-6 in
     <em>
      Ptx3
     </em>
     -null mice (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 5B
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Taken together, the above results indicate that TSG-6 suppresses the inhibition exerted by PTX3 on FGF2-dependent angiogenesis both
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    . Thus, this provides the first direct evidence of a role for TSG-6 as a modulator of neovascularization. Our observations clearly indicate that TSG-6 exerts its ‘pro-angiogenic’ functions
    <em>
     via
    </em>
    inhibition of the PTX3/FGF2 interaction, where this may be mediated by the binding of TSG-6 to PTX3. Preliminary solid phase binding and surface plasmon resonance assays suggest that TSG-6 may also interact directly with FGF2 (A. Inforzato and A. J. Day, unpublished data, 2009). Thus, TSG-6 might prevent FGF2/PTX3 interaction through a combination of mechanisms that together lead to suppression of the inhibition exerted by PTX3 on the angiogenic activity of FGF2. Further work is required to fully dissect the molecular interplay between PTX3, FGF2 and TSG-6 so as to understand the mechanism of TSG-6 action.
   </p>
   <p>
    As described above, PTX3 may contribute to the modulation of FGF2-driven angiogenesis in different pathological settings characterized by the co-expression of the two proteins, including inflammation, wound healing, atherosclerosis, and neoplasia [see
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      44
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      49
     </xref>
    </sup>
    for a further discussion]. The coordinated expression of TSG-6 and PTX3 has been described in inflamed tissues
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      26
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      50
     </xref>
    </sup>
    and in the cumulus oophorus
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      37
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      50
     </xref>
    </sup>
    . Accordingly, FGF2, TSG-6 and PTX3 are co-expressed following s.c. injection of a Matrigel plug in mice (see
    <a>
     supplemental Figure V
    </a>
    ), a mild pro-inflammatory experimental condition
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      47
     </xref>
    </sup>
    . Moreover, immunohistochemical analysis performed on a limited series of human specimens shows that FGF2, TSG-6 and PTX3 are co-expressed in human atherosclerotic carotid artery and in biopsies of human benign tumors (pleomorphic parotid adenoma) and cancer (gastric carcinoma)
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      51
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      52
     </xref>
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     supplemental Figure VI
    </a>
    ). Further studies on larger cohorts of patients will be required to assess the relationship between the expression of these modulators of the angiogenic process and tissue vascularization in different inflammatory/cancerous conditions.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our study indicates that the relative levels of TSG-6 and PTX3 likely dictate the biological activity of FGF2; a low TSG-6:PTX3 ratio exerting an inhibitory effect on FGF2-mediated angiogenesis whereas an high TSG-6:PTX3 ratio represents a permissive condition for the angiogenic activity of the growth factor. Thus, the interaction of TSG-6 and PTX3 might act as a biological rheostat for FGF2-dependent neovascularization, contributing to the complex extracellular protein interactome
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      9
     </xref>
    </sup>
    that mediates the angiogenic process. These conclusions are supported by the observation that endogenous PTX3 exerts a significant inhibitory effect on vascularization induced by endogenous FGF2 or by the exogenously added growth factor in a murine Matrigel plug assay, this effect being abolished in
    <em>
     Ptx3
    </em>
    -null mice or by TSG-6 treatment in wild-type animals. As anticipated, no effect is exerted by TSG-6 in the absence of endogenous PTX3, i.e. in
    <em>
     Ptx3
    </em>
    -null mice.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our studies indicate that TSG-6 can act as a novel indirect ‘pro-angiogenic’ cofactor by releasing FGF2 from the PTX3 constraints, no direct angiogenic activity being exerted by this protein when administered alone in the different assays. On the other hand, recent data have shown that intra-ocular TSG-6 treatment in a rat model of corneal wound healing can inhibit neovascularization
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      53
     </xref>
    </sup>
    , possibly as a consequence of its anti-inflammatory activity (e.g. inhibition of neutrophil infiltration)
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
    </sup>
    . Notably, the anti-angiogenic and anti-inflammatory effects were observed only when TSG-6 was administered within 4 hours after injury, no effect being observed when the inflammatory cell infiltrate was already established
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      30
     </xref>
    </sup>
    . Previous observations had shown that some anti-inflammatory cytokines, including erythropoietin
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      54
     </xref>
    </sup>
    and interleukin-10
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      55
     </xref>
    </sup>
    may promote angiogenesis, whereas tumor necrosis factor-α may exert pro- or anti-angiogenic effects depending upon the dose of the cytokine
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      56
     </xref>
    </sup>
    . Taken together, these data suggest that TSG-6 may have both pro-angiogenic and anti-angiogenic properties, such that the balance between promotion and inhibition of neovascularization may depend on context (e.g. the microenvironment). Further research is needed to investigate the precise role of TSG-6 as a modulator of angiogenesis and how this is regulated, for example, by components of the ECM.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     1
    </title>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (776K, pdf)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Acknowledgements
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     We thank Patrizia Dell’Era, Ragnar Lindstedt and Giovanni Salvatori for reagents, Michela Corsini for having performed the CAM assays and Manuela Nebuloni and Fabio Pasqualini for assistance with immunohistochemistry.
    </p>
    <p>
     <strong>
      Sources of Funding
     </strong>
     Supported by Arthritis Research UK (grant nos. 16539 and 18472), the Medical Research Council (grant no. G0701180) and Sigma-Tau to A.J.D. and by Ministero dell’Istruzione, Università e Ricerca (Centro di Eccellenza per l’Innovazione Diagnostica e Terapeutica, Cofin projects), Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro, Fondazione Berlucchi, and Fondazione Cariplo (grant 2008-2264 and NOBEL Project) to M.P. The contribution of the European Commission (“TOLERAGE” 2008-202156) and European Research Council (project HIIS) to A.I., M.S., B.B. and C.G. is gratefully acknowledged. A.I. was the recipient of fellowships from Fondazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro, Fondazione “Humanitas” per la Ricerca, and Scuola Europea di Medicina Molecolare (SEMM).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>