<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ccr.2014.01.010
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    A Peptide Mimicking VGLL4 Function Acts as a YAP Antagonist Therapy against Gastric Cancer
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Significance
   </title>
   <p>
    <strong>
     As an emerging significant player in tumorigenesis, the Hippo pathway has attracted increasing attention for the development of new anticancer drugs. In contrast to targeting upstream regulators such as MST1/2 and LATS, inhibition of YAP, the ultimate downstream effector of Hippo signaling, may provide a more effective and direct way to redress the Hippo pathway. Our findings that VGLL4 is a natural antagonist of YAP, and its TDU region is sufficient for YAP inhibition, allowed for the development of a peptide-based YAP inhibitor. This peptide potently suppresses gastric tumor growth, providing an opportunity for treating gastric cancer that currently lacks effective treatment options. The therapeutic strategy may also be extended to other cancer types driven by hyperactive YAP.
    </strong>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Hippo pathway controls organ size in diverse species from
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    to human. This pathway features a central kinase cascade formed by Hippo (Hpo; MST1/2 in mammals) and Warts (Wts; LATS1/2 in mammals) (
    <a>
     Huang et al., 2005
    </a>
    ), whose activations lead to phosphorylation of the downstream transcriptional coactivator Yorkie (Yki; YAP/TAZ in mammals), thus preventing its interaction with and therefore transactivation of the DNA-binding transcriptional factor Scalloped (Sd; TEADs/TEF in mammals) (
    <a>
     Goulev et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wu et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Inactivation of the Hippo signaling leads to proproliferation and anti-apoptosis associated with increased cancer risk (
    <a>
     Halder and Johnson, 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Harvey and Tapon, 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pan, 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zeng and Hong, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2010
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    As a downstream effector, YAP plays a key role in Hippo pathway to control cell proliferation. Despite a possible suppressor function in some circumstances (
    <a>
     Barry et al., 2013
    </a>
    ), YAP was mostly reported as an oncoprotein and its elevated expression and nuclear localization have been frequently observed in human cancers (i.e., lung cancers, liver cancers, colon cancers, pancreatic cancer, and breast cancers) (
    <a>
     Avruch et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Cui et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hergovich, 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pan, 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Steinhardt et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zender et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). The role of YAP as a promising and important therapeutic target has been increasingly recognized. However, research regarding specific YAP inhibitors and their potential therapeutic use in treating cancers remains very limited with only a few reports so far confined to small-molecule inhibitors (
    <a>
     Liu-Chittenden et al., 2012
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    As a transcriptional coactivator, YAP does not contain any DNA-binding domain but functions through interaction with TEADs, whereby inducing expression of target genes promoting cell proliferation as well as inhibiting apoptosis. Similar to YAP, the mammalian Vestigial-like proteins VGLL1-4 do not contain DNA-binding domain and they also exert their transcriptional regulatory functions through pairing with TEADs via their Tondu (TDU) domain(s). Specifically, VGLL1-3 proteins share one conserved TDU domain at their N-terminal regions, while VGLL4 has two partially conserved TDU domains at its C terminus (
    <a>
     Chen et al., 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Maeda et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pobbati et al., 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Vaudin et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). Most studies to date have identified VGLL1-3 as TEADs-related transcriptional coactivators (
    <a>
     Faucheux et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Günther et al., 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Halperin et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Maeda et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). The function of VGLL4 has not been clearly defined, however, although it has been suggested as a candidate tumor suppressor in pancreatic adenocarcinoma (
    <a>
     Mann et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). Recently, we and others have identified VGLL4 in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    and human as a transcriptional repressor that inhibits YAP-induced overgrowth and tumorigenesis (
    <a>
     Guo et al., 2013
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Koontz et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2014
    </a>
    ). However, the possible role of VGLL4 in human gastric cancer (GC) has not been defined, and the potential therapeutic application of VGLL4 remains unknown.
   </p>
   <p>
    Human GC is characteristic of poor prognosis and high death rate, making it the second most common cause of cancer-related death worldwide. Therefore, there is a great need to identify new prognostic markers as well as develop novel therapeutic strategies in GC treatment. In this work, we set out to investigate the clinical relevance of VGLL4 and its regulatory function and mechanism in Hippo pathway, aiming to discover and design a peptide drug candidate against gastric cancer.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    VGLL4 Is a Potential Tumor Suppressor in Human Gastric Cancer
   </title>
   <p>
    To explore a potential role of VGLL4 in gastric tumorigenesis, we first examined its mRNA levels in 84 human gastric tumor clinical specimens. Univariate analysis indicated that the mRNA levels of
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    were downregulated in 51 out of 84 (61%) GC samples (p &lt; 0.0087) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). We collected and preprocessed patients’ data by extracting nine available clinical factors in three categories, i.e., the clinical background (age, gender), immunohistochemistry data (Lauren’s classification, tumor differentiation, lymphatic invasion), and the cancer’s stage information (tumor size, lymph node metastasis, distant metastasis, tumor stage) (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). Considering the important role of
    <em>
     Helicobacter pylori
    </em>
    infection in gastric tumorigenesis, we also included
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infectious status for patient analysis. These data indicated that aberrant levels of
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    mRNA were inversely correlated not only with tumor size and tumor stage, but also with lymphatic invasion and lymph node metastasis. Downregulation of
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    was found in 5 of 14 grade I (35.7%), 10 of 19 grade II (52.6%), 16 of 26 grade III (61.5%), and 20 of 25 grade IV (80%) (p
    <em>
     =
    </em>
    0.044) GC samples. Consistent with our observations at mRNA level, VGLL4 expression at protein level also showed an inverse correlation with GC progression (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    A available online). Semiquantitative immunoblot analysis undertaken for 24 pairs of gastric tumor samples showed that protein levels of VGLL4 in grades I and II were much higher than those in grades III and IV (p = 0.026). To further determine the potential association of VGLL4 expression with clinical outcomes, we performed immunohistochemical (IHC) staining of VGLL4 on tissue microarrays containing 91 GC specimens that have a long-term clinical follow-up record (four lost to follow-up). VGLL4 staining was significantly associated with tumor size, lymph node metastasis, and TNM stage (p &lt; 0.05), but not significantly correlated to age, gender, and tumor metabasis (
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). The positive rates of VGLL4 in both dysplasia (abnormal growth of gastric mucosa) and GC samples were significantly lower than that in normal tissues (p &lt; 0.05) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). Subsequent Kaplan-Meier survival analysis showed that expression levels of VGLL4 were inversely correlated with 5 year survival rate of GC patients (p = 0.0416) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D). Together, these results suggested that VGLL4 is a potential tumor suppressor as well as an independent prognostic marker for overall survival of GC patients (relative risk: 0.2110, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.1932–0.6315, p = 0.0215) (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Downregulation of VGLL4 Was Associated with Upregulation of YAP Target Genes and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1135 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Downregulation of VGLL4 Correlates with Gastric Cancer Progression
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Groups
          </th>
          <th>
           VGLL4 mRNA
           <hr/>
          </th>
          <th>
           n
          </th>
          <th>
           Decreased (%)
          </th>
          <th>
           p Value (Fisher’s Test)
          </th>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Nondecreased
          </th>
          <th>
           Decreased
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Age (years)
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           &lt;60
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
          <td>
           22
          </td>
          <td>
           37
          </td>
          <td>
           59.4
          </td>
          <td>
           1.0000
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           ≥60
          </td>
          <td>
           18
          </td>
          <td>
           29
          </td>
          <td>
           47
          </td>
          <td>
           61.7
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Gender
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Male
          </td>
          <td>
           18
          </td>
          <td>
           32
          </td>
          <td>
           50
          </td>
          <td>
           68.0
          </td>
          <td>
           0.5002
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Female
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
          <td>
           34
          </td>
          <td>
           55.0
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            <em>
             Helicobacter pylori
            </em>
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Positive
          </td>
          <td>
           14
          </td>
          <td>
           31
          </td>
          <td>
           45
          </td>
          <td>
           62.1
          </td>
          <td>
           0.1201
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Negative
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
          <td>
           20
          </td>
          <td>
           39
          </td>
          <td>
           51.2
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Lauren
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Intestinal
          </td>
          <td>
           25
          </td>
          <td>
           41
          </td>
          <td>
           66
          </td>
          <td>
           66.1
          </td>
          <td>
           0.7860
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Nonintestinal
          </td>
          <td>
           8
          </td>
          <td>
           10
          </td>
          <td>
           18
          </td>
          <td>
           55.6
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Differentiation
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Low
          </td>
          <td>
           21
          </td>
          <td>
           29
          </td>
          <td>
           50
          </td>
          <td>
           58.0
          </td>
          <td>
           0.6502
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Moderate or high
          </td>
          <td>
           12
          </td>
          <td>
           22
          </td>
          <td>
           34
          </td>
          <td>
           64.7
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Lymphatic invasion
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Ly0-1
          </td>
          <td>
           14
          </td>
          <td>
           10
          </td>
          <td>
           24
          </td>
          <td>
           45.4
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0287
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Ly2-3
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
          <td>
           41
          </td>
          <td>
           60
          </td>
          <td>
           66.3
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Tumor size
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           pT1 + pT2(≤5 cm)
          </td>
          <td>
           11
          </td>
          <td>
           6
          </td>
          <td>
           17
          </td>
          <td>
           35.3
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0251
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           pT3 (&gt;5 cm) + pT4
          </td>
          <td>
           22
          </td>
          <td>
           45
          </td>
          <td>
           67
          </td>
          <td>
           67.2
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Lymph node metastasis
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           N0 + N1
          </td>
          <td>
           19
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
          <td>
           34
          </td>
          <td>
           44.1
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0130
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           N2 + N3
          </td>
          <td>
           14
          </td>
          <td>
           36
          </td>
          <td>
           50
          </td>
          <td>
           72.0
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Distant metastasis
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           M0
          </td>
          <td>
           29
          </td>
          <td>
           45
          </td>
          <td>
           74
          </td>
          <td>
           60.1
          </td>
          <td>
           1.0000
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           M1
          </td>
          <td>
           4
          </td>
          <td>
           6
          </td>
          <td>
           10
          </td>
          <td>
           60.0
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Tumor stage
           </strong>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Stage I + stage II
          </td>
          <td>
           18
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
          <td>
           33
          </td>
          <td>
           45.4
          </td>
          <td>
           0.0247
           <a>
            <sup>
             a
            </sup>
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Stage III + stage IV
          </td>
          <td>
           15
          </td>
          <td>
           36
          </td>
          <td>
           51
          </td>
          <td>
           70.6
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <strong>
            Total
           </strong>
          </td>
          <td>
           <strong>
            33
           </strong>
          </td>
          <td>
           <strong>
            51
           </strong>
          </td>
          <td>
           <strong>
            84
           </strong>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
          <td>
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Fisher’s exact test was used to test the association between two categorical variables.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         a
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          Represents statistically significant, p &lt; 0.05.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Previously, it has been reported that increased
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    mRNA levels in GC samples are correlated with lymphatic metastasis and tumor TNM stage (
    <a>
     Zhou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). In our study, we found that
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    mRNA levels were not only associated with tumor size, differentiation, and stage, but also with
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infectious status (p &lt; 0.05) (
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    ).
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    -positive rates in GC and dysplasia were much higher than that in normal tissues (p &lt; 0.01) (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    B). Consistently, the protein levels of YAP also tend to increase in higher tumor grade (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    A). Notably, we found that the average ratio of
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    to
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    at mRNA levels in higher grade tumor samples is significantly higher than in lower grade tumor samples (p &lt; 0.05) (
    <a>
     Table S4
    </a>
    ). Moreover, the
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    ratio at mRNA level is strongly correlated with GC clinical factors including lymphatic invasion, tumor size, TNM stage, and
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infectious status (
    <a>
     Table S5
    </a>
    ). Consistently, the average ratio of YAP to VGLL4 at protein levels increases from 2.7 ± 0.4 in tumor tissues of stage I to 9.1 ± 1.6 in GC samples of stage IV (
    <a>
     Table S3
    </a>
    ). IHC analysis showed that among YAP-positive GC patients, those with VGLL4-positive expression have a better clinical outcome (survival time: 39 months) when compared with VGLL4 negative expression (survival time: 16 months) (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D). Taken together, these results indicate that YAP/VGLL4 ratio could be considered as an important clinical factor for GC classification and diagnosis.
   </p>
   <p>
    Overexpression of YAP target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    have been suggested to correlate with GC progression (
    <a>
     Da et al., 2009
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Jacobson and Cunningham, 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Jiang et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kang et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lin et al., 2005
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Maeta et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2011
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhou et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). Consistent with these reports, we observed an elevated expression of
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    C) and its target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    in GC tissues than those in paired control tissues (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E). In our experiment, upregulation of
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    was not statistically significant, despite of their increasing tendency (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E). Importantly, we found that downregulation of
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    mRNA was correlated with upregulation of YAP target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F). Moreover, hierarchical cluster analysis showed that during the early stage of GC (stage I and II), mRNA levels of YAP target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    in high
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    expression group was obviously lower than those in normal and low
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    expression group (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    D). Further tumor stage analysis found that
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    expression in high tumor stage was lower than that in low tumor stage, while the expressions of
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    were significantly upregulated along tumor progression (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    E). Patients with higher
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    ratio also have higher expressions of YAP target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    F). Together, these results indicated that VGLL4 may affect YAP-TEADs transcriptional activity in GC.
   </p>
   <title>
    VGLL4 Suppresses GC Growth in Vitro by Targeting YAP-TEADs
   </title>
   <p>
    To confirm a biological role of VGLL4 in GC, we first checked the effect of VGLL4 on the growth of several GC cell lines with different differentiation states including BGC-823, HGC-27, MGC-803, and MKN-45. First, we analyzed the expression profiles of YAP and VGLL4, as well as YAP/VGLL4 protein ratio in these cells (
    <a>
     Figure S2
    </a>
    A). Except MKN-45, all other three GC cell lines appear to have increased YAP levels and decreased VGLL4 levels. As a result, the YAP/VGLL4 ratios are much higher in BGC-823, HGC-27, and MGC-803 cells than those in MKN-45 and HEK293 cells. Next, we found that overexpression of VGLL4 in MGC-803 cells (YAP/VGLL4 ratio: 3.6) not only induced apoptosis, but also inhibited cell viability on plate and anchorage-independent cell growth in soft agar (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    A–2C). To examine whether VGLL4’s function is related to a potential inhibition against YAP-TEADs transcriptional activity, we performed TEAD4 reporter assay and analyzed downstream target genes’ expression. As shown in
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    D and 2E, both TEAD4 reporter activity and expressions of YAP-TEADs target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    were reduced upon transfection of VGLL4 in MGC-803 cells. Similar results were observed for BGC-823 (YAP/VGLL4 ratio: 2.2) and HGC-27 (YAP/VGLL4 ratio: 4.0) cells (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    B–S2F). By contrast, overexpression of VGLL4 in MKN-45 cells (YAP/VGLL4 ratio: 0.1) did not significantly promote apoptosis or inhibit cell growth and colony formation (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    B–S2D). Meanwhile, TEAD4 reporter activity and the target genes’ expression were not significantly altered either in MKN-45 cells (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    E and S2F).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="VGLL4 Inhibits Gastric Tumor Cell Growth through Inhibiting YAP-Induced TEAD4 ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (872 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Next, we depleted endogenous VGLL4 by special short hairpin RNA (shRNA) targeting its 5′-UTR. Our results showed that knockdown of VGLL4 in BGC-823, MGC-803, and HGC-27 promoted cell growth and enhanced both TEAD4 reporter activity and target genes’ expression (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    F–2H and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    G–S2I). Such effects could be rescued by transfection of VGLL4 back into these cells (
    <a>
     Figures 2
    </a>
    G and
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    H). By contrast, the viability, TEAD4
    <em>
     trans
    </em>
    -activity, and downstream target genes’ expression were not significantly altered by knockdown of VGLL4 in MKN-45 cells (
    <a>
     Figures S2
    </a>
    G–S2I). Taken together, these results indicated that VGLL4 inhibits GC growth in vitro in a way related to cellular YAP/VGLL4 ratio, and importantly, VGLL4 functions through targeting YAP-TEADs transcriptional activity.
   </p>
   <p>
    To assess the functional importance of the potential TEADs-binding domain of VGLL4, namely the tandem TDU domains, we generated several deletion mutants of VGLL4 (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    I). Our results showed that deletion of the tandem TDU domains of VGLL4 totally abrogated its inhibitory effect on cell growth (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    J). Moreover, deletion of the first TDU domain (TDU1) only moderately impaired VGLL4’s inhibition of cell growth, while deletion of the second TDU domain (TDU2) almost completely abolished such function. Consistently, clonogenic assays showed that introduction of wild-type VGLL4, but not the TDU-deletion mutants inhibited clonogenicity of MGC-803 cells in a dose-dependent manner at both basal and YAP-induced levels (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    K). Meanwhile, deletion of VGLL4 TDU1, TDU2 or the whole tandem TDU region impaired or abolished its inhibitory activity toward YAP-induced TEAD4 reporter activity (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    L). Moreover, VGLL4 TDU deletion mutants failed to inhibit YAP-induced
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    expression (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    M). Taken together, these results indicated that the tandem TDU region, especially TDU2, is functionally essential for VGLL4.
   </p>
   <title>
    Structural Study Identified Key Residues for VGLL4-TEAD4 Complex Formation
   </title>
   <p>
    Given the importance of the tandem TDU domains for VGLL4 function, we performed a structural study of the VGLL4-TEAD4 complex. As shown by gel filtration and dynamic light scattering assays, the tandem TDU region of VGLL4 directly interacts with the YAP-binding domain (YBD) of TEAD4 and form a stable complex with a molar ratio of 1:2 (
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    A and S3B). We then determined the crystal structure of mouse VGLL4 tandem TDU region in complex with the YBD domain of mouse TEAD4 (
    <a>
     Table S6
    </a>
    ). Consistent with our solution studies, each TDU domain of VGLL4 binds one molecule of TEAD4 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    A,
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    C, and S3D). TDU1 is composed of only one α helix (helix α1), while TDU2 consists of a β strand followed by two short α helices (helices α2 and α3) packed against each other (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    A–3C). Due to its highly extended conformation of the tandem TDUs, the two bound TEAD4 molecules (assigned as A and B) do not contact with each other. Thus, TDU1 and TDU2 appear to function as individual binding units for separate TEADs molecules.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Crystal Structure of VGLL4-TEAD4 Complex(A) Overall structure of the mouse ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (899 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Next, we investigated the details of the VGLL4-TEAD4 complex interface, which is dominated by hydrophobic interactions. Residues V206, H209, F210, R212, and L214 of TDU1 form a hydrophobic core with F330, Y362, F366, K369, L370, L373, M378, and V382 of the TEAD4 molecule A (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). A total surface area of 588 Å
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    is buried upon TDU1 binding with TEAD4. On the other hand, residues V235, H237, F238, K240, and L242 of TDU2 form a hydrophobic core with TEAD4 molecule B (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C). In addition, residues W246 and I249 from the extra helix (α3) of TDU2 form additional hydrophobic interactions with TEAD4. Besides the two short helices, the β strand of the TDU2 forms an intermolecular β sheet with TEAD4 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    A,
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    D, and S3E). The total interface area between TDU2 and TEAD4 is up to 1,048 Å
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    , suggesting that TDU2 has much stronger interaction with TEAD4 when compared with TDU1.
   </p>
   <p>
    According to the structural analysis, we designed a series of mutations based on human VGLL4 and TEAD4 to probe and disturb the complex interface (
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    F). In vitro biolayer interferometry (BLI) and pull-down assays were subsequently performed to assess the importance of individual amino acids on the interface (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    D and 3E). In agreement with the structural analysis, we found that the overall contribution of TDU2 is much larger than that of TDU1 during complex formation with TEAD4. Specifically, mutations of V209A, H212A, F213A, R215A, L217A, and H212A/F213A targeting TDU1 did not significantly affect VGLL4-TEAD4 interactions. However, mutations of H240A and H240A/F241A targeting TDU2, or H212A/F213A/H240A/F241A (HF4A) targeting both TDUs dramatically decreased VGLL4-TEAD4 complex formation. Moreover, substitution of the β strand of TDU2 with poly-Glycine only slightly decreased VGLL4’s binding to TEAD4 (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    D and 3E), suggesting that this β strand is not essential but may help for VGLL4-TEAD4 interaction. We then used H212A/F213A, H240A/F241A, and HF4A as representative mutants for further studies (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    F) and confirmed their effects by coimmunoprecipitation (coIP) analysis (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    VGLL4 Functions through Competing with YAP for TEAD4 Binding
   </title>
   <p>
    Structural comparison of VGLL4-TEAD4 with YAP-TEAD4 and VGLL1-TEAD4 suggested that VGLL4 and YAP have partially overlapped binding sites on TEADs, thus probably acting as an inhibitor of each other in terms of binding TEADs (see
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figures S3
    </a>
    F–S3H). To further validate that VGLL4 functions through a direct competition with YAP for TEAD4 binding, we examined whether the mutations disrupting VGLL4-TEAD4 interaction will affect VGLL4 function. As shown in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A, mutation H212A/F213A in TDU1 slightly blocked the inhibitory effect of VGLL4 on YAP-induced TEAD4 reporter activity, while, strikingly, mutation H240A/F241A in TDU2 almost completely abolished this repression effect, suggesting that TDU2 with a tighter binding to TEAD4 also possesses higher inhibitory activity toward YAP. Similarly, cells transfected with VGLL4 mutant HF4A displayed high TEAD4 reporter activity as did the empty vector. Consistent with the luciferase assay, VGLL4 mutant H212A/F213A only partially impaired its inhibitory function on YAP-induced
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    expression, while mutants H240A/F241A and HF4A completely blocked VGLL4’s inhibition on YAP-induced target gene expression (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    B). Moreover, VGLL4 mutant H212A/F213A showed partially reduced inhibitory effect on YAP-induced cell proliferation and colony formation in soft agar, while VGLL4 mutants H240A/F241A and HF4A almost completely lost the inhibitory activity (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    C and 4D), again indicating that VGLL4’s binding to TEAD4 is required for its repressor function.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Tandem TDU Domains of VGLL4 Are Sufficient to Inhibit YAP Activity(A&amp;ndash;D) The ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (863 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Next, we dissected the interplay between VGLL4, YAP, and TEAD4 using purified recombinant proteins. As shown by pull-down assay in
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    E, YAP readily competes with VGLL4 tandem TDUs for TEAD4 binding in a dose-dependent manner. On the other hand, VGLL4 tandem TDUs also competes with YAP for TEAD4 binding, although higher concentration of VGLL4 is required (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    E). However, VGLL4 mutants defective in TEAD4 binding could not compete with YAP (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    F). We then quantified the binding affinities between TEAD4 and YAP/VGLL4 using BLI assay (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    G). Consistently, the binding affinity between TEAD4 and YAP (K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    = 2.1 nM) is higher than that between TEAD4 and VGLL4 (K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    = 6.8 nM), suggesting that higher concentration of VGLL4 would be required to compete with YAP for TEADs binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    Taken together, these results clearly demonstrated that VGLL4 and YAP compete with each other for TEADs binding, and thus a ratio between their local concentrations may dictate the function of TEADs as either transcriptional activator or repressor.
   </p>
   <title>
    TDU Domains Alone Are Sufficient for VGLL4 Function of Inhibiting YAP
   </title>
   <p>
    We then investigated whether the tandem TDU region alone could be fully competent toward YAP inhibition as is the full-length VGLL4. As shown in
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    H and 4I, all the fragments including TDU1, TDU2, and tandem TDU, exerted inhibitory effects on YAP-induced TEAD4 reporter activity, although to different extents. Moreover, TDU2 exhibited a stronger inhibitory activity than TDU1 when used alone, whereas TDU1 and TDU2 mutants with disabled TEAD4-binding showed impaired inhibitory effects on YAP-induced TEAD4 reporter activity. Notably, when compared with the full-length VGLL4, the tandem TDU region alone was fully functional in terms of inhibiting YAP-induced TEAD4 reporter activity. These observations were further confirmed on the levels of YAP-induced
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    expression (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    J), as well as proliferation and colony formation of MGC-803 cells (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    K and 4L). These results demonstrated that the tandem TDU domains of VGLL4, especially TDU2, are not only essential but also sufficient for VGLL4 in inhibiting YAP function, corroborating the conclusion that VGLL4 functions as a competitive inhibitor of YAP.
   </p>
   <title>
    A Rationally Designed Peptide “Super-TDU” Potently Inhibits GC Growth
   </title>
   <p>
    Based on our findings that (1) the TDU region of VGLL4 is sufficient for inhibiting YAP activity, and (2) the most important binding sites for VGLL4 and YAP do not overlap on TEAD4, we designed an inhibitor peptide termed “Super-TDU” targeting YAP-TEADs interaction for therapeutic purpose (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). As shown by coIP experiment, the Super-TDU reduced endogenous interaction between YAP and TEADs (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). As predicted, the Super-TDU inhibited cell viability and colony formation of GC cell lines MGC-803, BGC-823, and HGC27, but not MKN-45 (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    C, 5D, and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    A). Moreover, the Super-TDU downregulated expression of YAP-TEADs target genes
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    E and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    B). Further chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays also showed that the Super-TDU dose-dependently reduced the amount of
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    promoter cDNA ChIPed by YAP antibody (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    F). To verify the specificity of the Super-TDU, we created two Super-TDU mutants harboring mutations that disable TEADs binding. As expected, the mutant Super-TDUs failed to interact with TEADs and inhibit cell proliferation (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    C and S4D).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Super-TDU Potently Inhibits Gastric Tumor Growth(A) A structural model of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (936 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Next, we carried out a preclinical study in which several types of GC cell lines mentioned above were injected into the armpits of BALB/cA nu/nu mice and allowed to form tumors (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    G). Once palpable tumors were detected, pairs of mice were randomized to receive a tail vein injection of either 50 μg/kg (n = 5) or 500 μg/kg (n = 5) per day of the Super-TDU peptide or an irrelevant control peptide (n = 10). In parallel, mice were treated with 50 mg/kg 5-fluorouracil (5-FU), a conventional drug used in GC treatment, intravenously as a positive control (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    H). Consistent with our in vitro observations, not only the sizes and weights of tumors, but also YAP target genes were markedly decreased for the Super-TDU-treated animals in a dose-dependent manner (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    H, 5I, and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    E–S4G).
   </p>
   <title>
    Pharmacological Evaluation of the Super-TDU
   </title>
   <p>
    We first determined the acute toxicity of the Super-TDU in ICR mice. Our results in BALB/cA nu/nu mice showed that a dosage of 50 μg/kg Super-TDU was equally effective as 50 mg/kg of 5-FU in terms of reducing tumor mass, tumor volume, and human β2 microglobulin concentration (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    H,
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    E, S4G, S4H). However, the Super-TDU exerted no obvious adverse toxic effects in ICR mice at a dosage of 1 mg/kg, while there was a significant decrease of white cell and platelet number in the 5-FU-treated control group (50 mg/kg). The maximum tolerance dose (MTD) of the Super-TDU was &gt;1 mg/kg body weight intravenously in mice (
    <a>
     Table S7
    </a>
    ). We then performed pharmacokinetic analysis of the Super-TDU in ICR and C57BL/6 mice. Representative curves of the Super-TDU concentration versus time were shown in
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    J and pharmacokinetic parameters were listed in
    <a>
     Table S8
    </a>
    (see
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    ). Moreover, consistent with the downregulation of YAP-TEADs target genes in the Super-TDU-treated mice (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    I and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    F), we found that a biotin-labeled Super-TDU peptide could efficiently pull down the endogenous TEADs, again indicating that the Super-TDU exerts its antitumor activity via directly targeting TEADs (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    K).
   </p>
   <p>
    Next, we introduced multiple tumor cell lines and evaluated the efficacy of the Super-TDU in these different cellular contexts (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    I;
    <a>
     Table S9
    </a>
    ). The Super-TDU significantly inhibited growth of HeLa, MGC-803, HCT116, A549, and MCF-7 cells, but only marginally inhibited growth of Jurkat and Raji cells, indicating a selectivity of the Super-TDU in inhibiting tumor cell growth. Consistent with our clinical analysis, we found that
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    ratio correlates well with susceptibility of tumor cells toward the Super-TDU (
    <a>
     Figures S4
    </a>
    J and S4K). For example, MGC-803 cells (high
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     VGLL4
    </em>
    ratio) were more susceptible to the Super-TDU than HEK293 cells (low
    <em>
     YAP
    </em>
    /VGLL4 ratio). Thus the Super-TDU may specifically target tumor cells with an elevated YAP/VGLL4 ratio.
   </p>
   <p>
    Taken together, these results suggested that the Super-TDU is relatively safe and specific as a drug candidate, which may have a broader antitumor activity toward YAP-driven human cancers.
   </p>
   <title>
    The Super-TDU Inhibits Tumor Growth of Human Primary GC
   </title>
   <p>
    To further validate the clinical relevance of our findings, we assessed the efficacy of the Super-TDU on primary gastric tumor cells (T1 and T2), which were derived from two individual patients. Paired normal tissue cells (N1 and N2), as well as MGC-803 cells, were used as controls. We found that the cells with a higher ratio of YAP to VGLL4 (sample T1) exhibited an obvious impairment in cell growth and colony formation upon treatment with the Super-TDU, while only a marginal influence was observed for the cells with lower ratio of YAP to VGLL4 (sample T2) (
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    A, 6B,
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    A, and S5B). By contrast, 5-FU inhibited almost equally the growth and colony formation of all the cells tested (
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    B,
    <a>
     S5
    </a>
    C, and S5D). These observations were further confirmed by tumor formation assay and expression of YAP-TEADs target genes in nude mice (
    <a>
     Figures 6
    </a>
    C–6E). Taken together, these results indicated a promising therapeutic potential of the Super-TDU in treating GC by directly targeting YAP-TEADs, and importantly, unlike the conventional drug compound 5-FU, its antitumor activity tends to be specific toward tumors with an elevated ratio of YAP to VGLL4.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Super-TDU Inhibits Human Primary GC Growth and GC Tumorigenesis in the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S153561081400035X-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1097 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    The Super-TDU Inhibits GC Tumor Growth in the
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    -Infected Mouse Model
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infection is worldwide and once acquired it becomes chronic and probably persists for life if untreated. Multiple lines of evidence demonstrate that
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    together with cocarcinogens, such as N-methyl-N′-nitro-N-nitrosoguanidine (MNNG), induce gastric carcinogenesis in animals (
    <a>
     Danon and Eaton, 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Han et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Furthermore, previous studies have shown that YAP mRNA levels were increased in mouse mucosa after
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infection (
    <a>
     Takaishi and Wang, 2007
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    To corroborate our observations of the Super-TDU in treating nude mice, we assessed its therapeutic effect in
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    -infected GC mouse model. Here, we attempted to develop GC mouse models through the administration of
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    intragastrically with alkylating agent MNNG in drinking water (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    F). C57BL/6 mice were orally gavaged 50 μl of bacterial suspension (∼1 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    CFU) every day. MNNG (100 mg/ml) was added to the drinking water for a period up to 2 months. After treatment with MNNG, mice were randomized to receive 500 μg/kg per day of the super-TDU (control peptide as negative control, 5-FU as positive control), which persisted for at least 4 months before sacrifice. Consistent with a previous report (
    <a>
     Takaishi and Wang, 2007
    </a>
    ), we found that YAP expression was significantly elevated in
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    -infected mice (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    G). Tumor numbers in the Super-TDU-treated group displayed a significant decrease, compared with those in the control group, indicating an obvious therapeutic effect of the Super-TDU on gastric carcinogenesis (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    H). These observations were further confirmed by Ki67 IHC staining (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    I). Consistently, we found that expressions of YAP-TEADs target genes (
    <em>
     CTGF
    </em>
    ,
    <em>
     CYR61
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     CDX2
    </em>
    ) were downregulated in mice treated with the Super-TDU (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    J). Taken together, these results confirmed our evaluation of the Super-TDU in nude mice, further demonstrating therapeutic potentials of the Super-TDU in treating human cancer with YAP-activation.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    The Hippo pathway controls multiple cellular processes related to cell proliferation and apoptosis and its dysregulation has been linked to various cancers (
    <a>
     Chan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Harvey and Tapon, 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Pan, 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Steinhardt et al., 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). As a tumor suppressor pathway, therapeutic targeting of the Hippo signaling has recently surfaced (
    <a>
     Stanger, 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Sudol et al., 2012
    </a>
    ). Our current work identified the clinical relevance of VGLL4 as a YAP antagonist and found its TDU region is sufficient for inhibiting YAP activity. These findings led to the generation of a peptide-based YAP inhibitor, which exhibits potent antitumor activity against gastric cancer in vitro and in mice.
   </p>
   <p>
    From a clinical point of view, both YAP and VGLL4 levels should be well confined within a suitable range and thus maintain a concentration balance or ratio to properly control Hippo signaling intensity required for normal development and homeostasis, which, however, may be disrupted under certain disease conditions such as cancers. Consistent with this notion, we found that YAP/VGLL4 ratios in clinical samples were sharply skewed and well correlated with tumor progression in GC. Moreover, we observed an inhibitory effect on a range of different cancer cell lines treated with the Super-TDU, but found that tumor cells with a relatively high YAP/VGLL4 ratio were more susceptible to such treatment. These observations were further confirmed by our clinical study of VGLL4 and therapeutic evaluation of the Super-TDU in colorectal carcinoma (data not shown). Thus the Super-TDU appears to have a broad but specific antitumor activity toward YAP-driven human cancers in which YAP/VGLL4 ratio should be considered as an important prognostic marker for personalized treatment.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    The observations that YAP levels, especially in the nucleus, increase specifically under pathological conditions makes it an ideal drug target. Although it has been increasingly revealed that selective inhibition of YAP-induced TEADs transactivation is “a promising and pharmacologically viable strategy” with minimal side effects in treating cancers related to YAP overexpression (
    <a>
     Cai et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Koontz et al., 2013
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Liu-Chittenden et al., 2012
    </a>
    ), studies regardingYAP inhibitors for therapeutic purposes are still very limited. VGLL4 functions as a physical antagonist of YAP and blocks YAP oncogenic activity at transcriptional level, hence providing a more effective and direct way to correct the consequences caused by excessive YAP.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our results clearly demonstrated that both VGLL4 and YAP levels were altered in GC samples. Currently, however, the molecular mechanism by which the expressions of YAP and VGLL4 are regulated in cancer remains unknown. There could be multiple pathological reasons accounting for the disruption of YAP-VGLL4 balance. Compared with other pathways correlated with tumorigenesis, DNA mutations are rare in Hippo pathway, while epigenetic silencing of some tumor suppressor candidates such as MST1/2 and LATS1/2, have been reported in cancer (
    <a>
     Chan et al., 2011
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Chen et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Zeng and Hong, 2008
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhou et al., 2009
    </a>
    ). It is also possible that VGLL4 loss in cancer could be related to epigenetic changes. Recently, it was reported that aberrant Wnt signaling causes YAP upregulation in liver cancer (
    <a>
     Wang et al., 2013
    </a>
    ). In addition, several other tumorigenesis-related pathways have been reported to crosstalk with Hippo pathway (
    <a>
     Azzolin et al., 2012
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Barry et al., 2013
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Fernandez et al., 2009
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Konsavage et al., 2012
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Varelas et al., 2010
    </a>
    ). Hence, it is also possible that aberration of these pathways may lead to dysregulation of VGLL4 and YAP in cancer. On the other hand, both negative (
    <a>
     Genevet et al., 2010
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Hamaratoglu et al., 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Neto-Silva et al., 2010
    </a>
    ) and positive (
    <a>
     Jukam et al., 2013
    </a>
    ) feedback regulation of YAP has been documented, indicating tissue-dependent plasticity and intrinsic complexity of the YAP-related signaling network. Notably, dysregulation of signaling pathways induced by
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    infection is attributed to ∼80% of GC cases (
    <a>
     Houghton and Wang, 2005
    </a>
    ). How such infection may cause malfunction of Hippo pathway in GC remains to be determined. In the future, mechanistic elucidation of VGLL4 and YAP dysregulations in cancer will not only further our understanding of tumorigenesis, but may also help to find new biomarkers and facilitate patient selection.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Collection of Human Gastric Cancer Specimens
   </title>
   <p>
    All samples used in this research were collected with written informed consent from patients. The use of human tissues was approved by the Institutional Ethics Board of the Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences (SIBS) and conforms to the Helsinki Declaration and to local legislation. All patients receiving treatment on this study were treated as part of a clinical protocol. See the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details.
   </p>
   <title>
    Tissue Microarray and Immunohistochemical Staining
   </title>
   <p>
    Gastric cancer and normal tissue microarray sections were prepared by Shanghai Outdo Biotech. This tissue array contains tissues from 31 cases of dysplasia, 91 cases of gastric tumors, and paired normal tissue. The follow-up time of GC patients ranged from 2 to 66 months. This array was used for IHC staining analysis. For details, see the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Cell Viability Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Cells were transfected with the indicated plasmids of pcDNA3.1 or Flag-VGLL4 wild-type or mutant and/or HA-tagged YAP. ATP cell viability assay was used for detecting cell proliferation. ATP content was measured in accordance with the protocol of the CellTiter-Glo luminescent cell viability assay kit (Promega). Briefly, 100 μl of assay reagent was added to the wells and mixed for 2 min at room temperature. After 10 min, intracellular ATP content was measured using a luminescence multilabel counter (Envision, Perkin Elmer). Cell viability was calculated using the following equation:
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <title>
    Protein Purification and Structure Determination
   </title>
   <p>
    Proteins used in this study were expressed in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    using pET28a-derived vectors and purified by affinity chromatography and size-exclusive chromatography. Diffraction data were collected at beamline BL17U, Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility (SSRF) of China. See the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details.
   </p>
   <title>
    Design and Production of the Super-TDU
   </title>
   <p>
    The basic rationale for the Super-TDU design lies in that the tandem TDU region of VGLL4 is fully competent in terms of competing with YAP for TEAD binding and therefore inhibiting YAP-mediated TEAD transactivation, and VGLL4 and YAP have overlapped but distinct primary binding sites on TEAD. The amino acid sequence of the Super-TDU contains “SVDD
    <em>
     <span>
      HF
     </span>
    </em>
    AK
    <strong>
     S
    </strong>
    LGDTWLQIGGSGNPKTANVPQTVP
    <em>
     <span>
      M
     </span>
    </em>
    RLRKLPDS
    <em>
     <span>
      F
     </span>
    </em>
    FKPPE.” The Super-TDU was expressed and purified in
    <em>
     E. coli.
    </em>
    For details, see the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    . In addition, two Super-TDU mutants were constructed by substitution of underlined residues MF or HFMF with alanines (termed as mutations MF2A and HFMF4A, respectively).
   </p>
   <title>
    Animal Experiments
   </title>
   <p>
    Male nude mice (BALB/cA-nu/nu) and C57/BL6 were obtained from Shanghai Experimental Animal Center and maintained in pathogen-free conditions. For animal research, all procedures for animal experimentation were performed in accordance with the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee guidelines of the Animal Core Facility of the Institutes of Biochemistry and Cell Biology (SIBCB). The approval ID for using the animals was 081 by the Animal Core Facility of SIBCB.
   </p>
   <p>
    During the tumor formation assay of BALB/c-nu/nu, cancer cell lines were injected at the flank of the mice (1 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    to 2 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    ). Tumor volumes were then measured. Once tumors were detected, mice were injected once daily with Super-TDU in saline at the 0.1 ml injection volume via the tail vein. Mice were randomized to receive either 50 μg/kg or 500 μg/kg per day of super-TDU peptide or control peptide. In addition, mice were treated with 50 mg/kg 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) intravenously as a positive control.
   </p>
   <p>
    For the
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    -infected mice model, SPF C57BL/6-slac mice were housed in an air-conditioned biohazard room designed for infectious animals, with a 12 hr light/dark cycle. The mice were inoculated with
    <em>
     H. pylori
    </em>
    SS1 grown on solid medium and harvested by swabbing, a single intragastric dose of a 1 × 10
    <sup>
     7
    </sup>
    CFU/ml. Normal mice (n = 20) were given same amount of normal saline and were housed in isolators in order to prevent risk of infection.
   </p>
   <p>
    See the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    for details.
   </p>
   <title>
    Statistical Analysis
   </title>
   <p>
    Statistical analysis was performed using the SAS statistical software package (9.1.3). Data are presented as means ± SD. ANOVA and Student’s t test were used for continuous variables. Fisher’s exact test was used for categorical variables. Survival analysis was performed using log-rank test. The Cox proportional hazards model was used for multivariate analysis, and calculation of the hazard ratios and confidence intervals was performed with the ascending step-by-step maximum likelihood method. A p value &lt; 0.05 was considered significantly different.
   </p>
   <p>
    Other methods are described in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The Protein Data Bank accession number for the crystal structure of VGLL4-TEAD4 complex reported in this paper is
    <a>
     4LN0
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Supplemental Experimental Procedures, Figures S1–S5, and Tables S1–S9.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (2432 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Avruch et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Avruch, D. Zhou, N. Bardeesy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         YAP oncogene overexpression supercharges colon cancer proliferation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Cycle, 11 (2012), pp. 1090–1096
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Azzolin et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Azzolin, F. Zanconato, S. Bresolin, M. Forcato, G. Basso, S. Bicciato, M. Cordenonsi, S. Piccolo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role of TAZ as mediator of Wnt signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 151 (2012), pp. 1443–1456
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Barry et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.R. Barry, T. Morikawa, B.L. Butler, K. Shrestha, R. de la Rosa, K.S. Yan, C.S. Fuchs, S.T. Magness, R. Smits, S. Ogino,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Restriction of intestinal stem cell expansion and the regenerative response by YAP
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 493 (2013), pp. 106–110
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cai et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Cai, N. Zhang, Y. Zheng, R.F. de Wilde, A. Maitra, D. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo signaling pathway restricts the oncogenic potential of an intestinal regeneration program
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 24 (2010), pp. 2383–2388
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chan et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.W. Chan, C.J. Lim, L. Chen, Y.F. Chong, C. Huang, H. Song, W. Hong
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo pathway in biological control and cancer development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell. Physiol., 226 (2011), pp. 928–939
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chen et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.H. Chen, S.J. Mullett, A.F. Stewart
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Vgl-4, a novel member of the vestigial-like family of transcription cofactors, regulates alpha1-adrenergic activation of gene expression in cardiac myocytes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 30800–30806
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chen et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Chen, F. Qin, X. Deng, J. Avruch, D. Zhou
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hippo pathway in intestinal homeostasis and tumorigenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein Cell, 3 (2012), pp. 305–310
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Cui et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z.L. Cui, F.F. Han, X.H. Peng, X. Chen, C.Y. Luan, R.C. Han, W.G. Xu, X.J. Guo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         YES-associated protein 1 promotes adenocarcinoma growth and metastasis through activation of the receptor tyrosine kinase Axl
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Int. J. Immunopathol. Pharmacol., 25 (2012), pp. 989–1001
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Da et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.L. Da, Y. Xin, J. Zhao, X.D. Luo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Significance and relationship between Yes-associated protein and survivin expression in gastric carcinoma and precancerous lesions
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         World J. Gastroenterol., 15 (2009), pp. 4055–4061
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Danon and Eaton, 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.J. Danon, K.A. Eaton
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The role of gastric Helicobacter and N-methyl-N’-nitro- N-nitrosoguanidine in carcinogenesis of mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Helicobacter, 3 (1998), pp. 260–268
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Faucheux et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Faucheux, F. Naye, K. Tréguer, S. Fédou, P. Thiébaud, N. Théze
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Vestigial like gene family expression in Xenopus: common and divergent features with other vertebrates
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Int. J. Dev. Biol., 54 (2010), pp. 1375–1382
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fernandez et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.A. Fernandez, P.A. Northcott, J. Dalton, C. Fraga, D. Ellison, S. Angers, M.D. Taylor, A.M. Kenney
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         YAP1 is amplified and up-regulated in hedgehog-associated medulloblastomas and mediates Sonic hedgehog-driven neural precursor proliferation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 23 (2009), pp. 2729–2741
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Genevet et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Genevet, M.C. Wehr, R. Brain, B.J. Thompson, N. Tapon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Kibra is a regulator of the Salvador/Warts/Hippo signaling network
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 18 (2010), pp. 300–308
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Goulev et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Goulev, J.D. Fauny, B. Gonzalez-Marti, D. Flagiello, J. Silber, A. Zider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SCALLOPED interacts with YORKIE, the nuclear effector of the hippo tumor-suppressor pathway in Drosophila
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 18 (2008), pp. 435–441
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Günther et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Günther, M. Mielcarek, M. Krüger, T. Braun
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         VITO-1 is an essential cofactor of TEF1-dependent muscle-specific gene regulation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 32 (2004), pp. 791–802
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Guo et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Guo, Y. Lu, P. Li, M.X. Yin, D. Lv, W. Zhang, H. Wang, Z. Zhou, H. Ji, Y. Zhao, L. Zhang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel partner of Scalloped regulates Hippo signaling via antagonizing Scalloped-Yorkie activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Res., 23 (2013), pp. 1201–1214
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Halder and Johnson, 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Halder, R.L. Johnson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hippo signaling: growth control and beyond
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 138 (2011), pp. 9–22
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Halperin et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.S. Halperin, C. Pan, A.J. Lusis, P. Tontonoz
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Vestigial-like 3 is an inhibitor of adipocyte differentiation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Lipid Res., 54 (2013), pp. 473–481
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hamaratoglu et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Hamaratoglu, M. Willecke, M. Kango-Singh, R. Nolo, E. Hyun, C. Tao, H. Jafar-Nejad, G. Halder
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The tumour-suppressor genes NF2/Merlin and Expanded act through Hippo signalling to regulate cell proliferation and apoptosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 8 (2006), pp. 27–36
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Han et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.U. Han, Y.B. Kim, H.J. Joo, K.B. Hahm, W.H. Lee, Y.K. Cho, D.Y. Kim, M.W. Kim
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Helicobacter pylori infection promotes gastric carcinogenesis in a mice model
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Gastroenterol. Hepatol., 17 (2002), pp. 253–261
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Harvey and Tapon, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Harvey, N. Tapon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Salvador-Warts-Hippo pathway - an emerging tumour-suppressor network
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Cancer, 7 (2007), pp. 182–191
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hergovich, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Hergovich
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         YAP-Hippo signalling downstream of leukemia inhibitory factor receptor: implications for breast cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Breast Cancer Res., 14 (2012), p. 326
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Houghton and Wang, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Houghton, T.C. Wang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Helicobacter pylori and gastric cancer: a new paradigm for inflammation-associated epithelial cancers
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gastroenterology, 128 (2005), pp. 1567–1578
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Huang et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Huang, S. Wu, J. Barrera, K. Matthews, D. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo signaling pathway coordinately regulates cell proliferation and apoptosis by inactivating Yorkie, the Drosophila Homolog of YAP
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 122 (2005), pp. 421–434
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Jacobson and Cunningham, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Jacobson, J.L. Cunningham
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Connective tissue growth factor in tumor pathogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Fibrogenesis Tissue Repair, 5 (Suppl 1) (2012), p. S8
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Jiang et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.G. Jiang, L. Lv, F.R. Liu, Z.N. Wang, F.N. Liu, Y.S. Li, C.Y. Wang, H.Y. Zhang, Z. Sun, H.M. Xu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Downregulation of connective tissue growth factor inhibits the growth and invasion of gastric cancer cells and attenuates peritoneal dissemination
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cancer, 10 (2011), p. 122
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Jukam et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Jukam, B. Xie, J. Rister, D. Terrell, M. Charlton-Perkins, D. Pistillo, B. Gebelein, C. Desplan, T. Cook
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Opposite feedbacks in the Hippo pathway for growth control and neural fate
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 342 (2013), p. 1238016
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kang et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.M. Kang, B.H. Lee, N. Kim, H.S. Lee, H.E. Lee, J.H. Park, J.S. Kim, H.C. Jung, I.S. Song
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         CDX1 and CDX2 expression in intestinal metaplasia, dysplasia and gastric cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Korean Med. Sci., 26 (2011), pp. 647–653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Konsavage et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.M. Konsavage Jr., S.L. Kyler, S.A. Rennoll, G. Jin, G.S. Yochum
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Wnt/β-catenin signaling regulates Yes-associated protein (YAP) gene expression in colorectal carcinoma cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 287 (2012), pp. 11730–11739
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Koontz et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.M. Koontz, Y. Liu-Chittenden, F. Yin, Y. Zheng, J. Yu, B. Huang, Q. Chen, S. Wu, D. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo effector Yorkie controls normal tissue growth by antagonizing scalloped-mediated default repression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 25 (2013), pp. 388–401
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lin et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.T. Lin, C.Y. Zuon, C.C. Chang, S.T. Chen, C.P. Chen, B.R. Lin, M.Y. Wang, Y.M. Jeng, K.J. Chang, P.H. Lee,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cyr61 induces gastric cancer cell motility/invasion via activation of the integrin/nuclear factor-kappaB/cyclooxygenase-2 signaling pathway
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Clin. Cancer Res, 11 (2005), pp. 5809–5820
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu-Chittenden et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Liu-Chittenden, B. Huang, J.S. Shim, Q. Chen, S.J. Lee, R.A. Anders, J.O. Liu, D.J. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genetic and pharmacological disruption of the TEAD-YAP complex suppresses the oncogenic activity of YAP
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 26 (2012), pp. 1300–1305
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Maeda et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Maeda, D.L. Chapman, A.F. Stewart
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mammalian vestigial-like 2, a cofactor of TEF-1 and MEF2 transcription factors that promotes skeletal muscle differentiation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 48889–48898
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Maeta et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Maeta, M. Osaki, K. Shomori, A. Inaba, K. Kidani, M. Ikeguchi, H. Ito
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         CYR61 downregulation correlates with tumor progression by promoting MMP-7 expression in human gastric carcinoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncology, 73 (2007), pp. 118–126
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mann et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.M. Mann, J.M. Ward, C.C. Yew, A. Kovochich, D.W. Dawson, M.A. Black, B.T. Brett, T.E. Sheetz, A.J. Dupuy, D.K. Chang, Australian Pancreatic Cancer Genome Initiative,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Sleeping Beauty mutagenesis reveals cooperating mutations and pathways in pancreatic adenocarcinoma
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 109 (2012), pp. 5934–5941
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Neto-Silva et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.M. Neto-Silva, S. de Beco, L.A. Johnston
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Evidence for a growth-stabilizing regulatory feedback mechanism between Myc and Yorkie, the Drosophila homolog of Yap
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 19 (2010), pp. 507–520
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pan, 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The hippo signaling pathway in development and cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 19 (2010), pp. 491–505
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pobbati et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.V. Pobbati, S.W. Chan, I. Lee, H. Song, W. Hong
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural and functional similarity between the Vgll1-TEAD and the YAP-TEAD complexes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structure, 20 (2012), pp. 1135–1140
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Stanger, 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.Z. Stanger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Quit your YAPing: a new target for cancer therapy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 26 (2012), pp. 1263–1267
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Steinhardt et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.A. Steinhardt, M.F. Gayyed, A.P. Klein, J. Dong, A. Maitra, D. Pan, E.A. Montgomery, R.A. Anders
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Expression of Yes-associated protein in common solid tumors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hum. Pathol., 39 (2008), pp. 1582–1589
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sudol et al., 2012
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Sudol, D.C. Shields, A. Farooq
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structures of YAP protein domains reveal promising targets for development of new cancer drugs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Semin. Cell Dev. Biol., 23 (2012), pp. 827–833
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Takaishi and Wang, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Takaishi, T.C. Wang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gene expression profiling in a mouse model of Helicobacter-induced gastric cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Sci., 98 (2007), pp. 284–293
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Varelas et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        X. Varelas, B.W. Miller, R. Sopko, S. Song, A. Gregorieff, F.A. Fellouse, R. Sakuma, T. Pawson, W. Hunziker, H. McNeill,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo pathway regulates Wnt/beta-catenin signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 18 (2010), pp. 579–591
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vaudin et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Vaudin, R. Delanoue, I. Davidson, J. Silber, A. Zider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TONDU (TDU), a novel human protein related to the product of vestigial (vg) gene of Drosophila melanogaster interacts with vertebrate TEF factors and substitutes for Vg function in wing formation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 126 (1999), pp. 4807–4816
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Wang, J.S. Park, Y. Wei, M. Rajurkar, J.L. Cotton, Q. Fan, B.C. Lewis, H. Ji, J. Mao
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TRIB2 acts downstream of Wnt/TCF in liver cancer cells to regulate YAP and C/EBPα function
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 51 (2013), pp. 211–225
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wu et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Wu, Y. Liu, Y. Zheng, J. Dong, D. Pan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The TEAD/TEF family protein Scalloped mediates transcriptional output of the Hippo growth-regulatory pathway
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 14 (2008), pp. 388–398
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zender et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Zender, M.S. Spector, W. Xue, P. Flemming, C. Cordon-Cardo, J. Silke, S.T. Fan, J.M. Luk, M. Wigler, G.J. Hannon,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification and validation of oncogenes in liver cancer using an integrative oncogenomic approach
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 125 (2006), pp. 1253–1267
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zeng and Hong, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Q. Zeng, W. Hong
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The emerging role of the hippo pathway in cell contact inhibition, organ size control, and cancer development in mammals
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 13 (2008), pp. 188–192
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Zhang, F. Ren, Q. Zhang, Y. Chen, B. Wang, J. Jiang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The TEAD/TEF family of transcription factor Scalloped mediates Hippo signaling in organ size control
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 14 (2008), pp. 377–387
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        X. Zhang, J. George, S. Deb, J.L. Degoutin, E.A. Takano, S.B. Fox, D.D. Bowtell, K.F. Harvey, AOCS Study Group
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo pathway transcriptional co-activator, YAP, is an ovarian cancer oncogene
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 30 (2011), pp. 2810–2822
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2014
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Zhang, Y. Gao, P. Li, Z. Shi, T. Guo, F. Li, X. Han, Y. Feng, C. Zheng, Z. Wang,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         VGLL4 functions as a new tumor suppressor in lung cancer by negatively regulating the YAP-TEAD transcriptional complex
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Res. (2014)
         <a>
          http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cr.2014.10
         </a>
         Published online January 24, 2014
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Zhao, X. Wei, W. Li, R.S. Udan, Q. Yang, J. Kim, J. Xie, T. Ikenoue, J. Yu, L. Li,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inactivation of YAP oncoprotein by the Hippo pathway is involved in cell contact inhibition and tissue growth control
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 21 (2007), pp. 2747–2761
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Zhao, X. Ye, J. Yu, L. Li, W. Li, S. Li, J. Yu, J.D. Lin, C.Y. Wang, A.M. Chinnaiyan,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         TEAD mediates YAP-dependent gene induction and growth control
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 22 (2008), pp. 1962–1971
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 2010
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Zhao, L. Li, Q. Lei, K.L. Guan
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Hippo-YAP pathway in organ size control and tumorigenesis: an updated version
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 24 (2010), pp. 862–874
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 2011
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z.S. Zhao, L. Li, H.J. Wang, Y.Y. Wang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Expression and prognostic significance of CEACAM6, ITGB1, and CYR61 in peripheral blood of patients with gastric cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Surg. Oncol., 104 (2011), pp. 525–529
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhou et al., 2009
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Zhou, C. Conrad, F. Xia, J.S. Park, B. Payer, Y. Yin, G.Y. Lauwers, W. Thasler, J.T. Lee, J. Avruch, N. Bardeesy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mst1 and Mst2 maintain hepatocyte quiescence and suppress hepatocellular carcinoma development through inactivation of the Yap1 oncogene
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 16 (2009), pp. 425–438
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhou et al., 2013
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.X. Zhou, X.Y. Li, Q. Zhang, K. Zhao, C.P. Zhang, C.H. Xue, K. Yang, Z.B. Tian
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Effects of the hippo signaling pathway in human gastric cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev., 14 (2013), pp. 5199–5205
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>