<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0014-5793(02)02358-X
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    The acidic regions of WASp and N-WASP can synergize with CDC42Hs and Rac1 to induce filopodia and lamellipodia
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      Actin cytoskeleton
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      WASp family protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Arp2/3 complex
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Filopodium
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Lamellipodium
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Arp2/3 complex has been implicated in the formation of f-actin structures like lamellipodia
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [1]
    </xref>
    , podosomes
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    , comet tails of
    <em>
     Listeria
    </em>
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [3]
    </xref>
    (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [4]
    </xref>
    ) and
    <em>
     Shigella
    </em>
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [5]
    </xref>
    (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [4]
    </xref>
    ), and phagocytic uptake structures
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [6]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [7]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [8]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The human WASp family comprises WASp, N-WASp and three WAVE/Scar isoforms and is thought to link RhoGTPase-mediated signal transduction to actin nucleation via Arp2/3 complex (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [9]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [10]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [11]
    </xref>
    ). For example, CDC42 has been shown to trigger formation of filopodia
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [12]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [13]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [14]
    </xref>
    (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [11]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [15]
    </xref>
    ), while Rac mediates formation of lamellipodia/ruffles via WASp family proteins
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [16]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [17]
    </xref>
    (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [11]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [15]
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The isolated C-terminal VCA domain of WASp family proteins, containing
    <img/>
    erprolin-like,
    <img/>
    entral and
    <img/>
    cidic regions (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1A
    </xref>
    ), binds both actin and Arp2/3 complex and activates Arp2/3 complex in vitro and in vivo
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [18]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [19]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [20]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    . Binding of monomeric actin is mostly achieved through the V region, while both the C and A regions mediate binding to Arp2/3 complex
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Domain organization of WASp, GST fusion constructs of WASp C-terminus and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Domain organization of WASp, GST fusion constructs of WASp C-terminus and comparison of acidic regions of WASp family proteins. A: Domain organization of WASp: WASp homology domain 1 (WH1), basic domain (B), GTPase binding domain (GBD), polyproline domain, C-terminal domain (containing verprolin-like (V), central C-terminal (C) and acidic (A) regions). Numbers indicate first and last amino acids of proteins. B: Comparison of acidic regions of WASp, N-WASP and WAVE1. C: Truncated or mutated forms of the WASp A region used in this study.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Binding to members of the Wiskott–Aldrich syndrome protein (WASp) family transforms the basally inactive Arp2/3 complex into a highly efficient nucleator of actin filaments that grow from their barbed ends (reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [9]
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [10]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [11]
    </xref>
    ). In this context, the C-terminal acidic (A) region of WASp family proteins is thought to represent a high-affinity binding site for Arp2/3 complex without activating properties (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [18]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [19]
    </xref>
    , reviewed in
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [9]
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Recently, WASp-VC was shown to be the minimal necessary region for Arp2/3 complex activation in vitro and in cells
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    . Furthermore, GST fusions of the CA or C regions lead to actin aggregation in cells upon microinjection
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    . This leaves the Arp2/3 complex binding A region of WASp as a potential tool to probe Arp2/3 complex involvement in cellular processes. This study was therefore set up to explore in greater detail the Arp2/3 binding abilities of acidic regions of WASp family proteins (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1B
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and methods
   </title>
   <title>
    2.1. Cell isolation and culture
   </title>
   <p>
    Human peripheral blood leukocytes were isolated by centrifugation of heparinized blood in Ficoll (Biochrom, Berlin, Germany). Monocytic cells were isolated with magnetic anti-CD14 antibody beads and an MS+ separation column (Miltenyi Biotec, Auburn, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions and seeded onto Cellocate coverslips (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) at a density of 5×10
    <sup>
     4
    </sup>
    per coverslip. Cells were cultured in RPMI containing 20% autologous serum at 37°C, 5% CO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and 90% humidity. Medium was changed every 3–4 days.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.2. Generation of constructs and protein expression
   </title>
   <p>
    WASp constructs were created by cloning PCR-generated inserts (in the case of WASp-CA and WASp-A constructs) or commercially synthesized oligonucleotides (MWG Biotech, Germany) in the case of WASp-A13, WASp-A11, WASp-A9, WASp-A7 and WASpA/W500S into the
    <em>
     Bam
    </em>
    HI and
    <em>
     Eco
    </em>
    RI sites of vector pGEX-2T (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, Uppsala, Sweden), as in part described earlier
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [23]
    </xref>
    . Vectors for expression of V12CDC42Hs and V12Rac1 were kind gifts of Dr. A. Hall (London, UK). Proteins were expressed as glutathione
    <em>
     S
    </em>
    -transferase (GST) fusion proteins in
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    as described
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [23]
    </xref>
    . When indicated, GST was removed by thrombin cleavage, according to the manufacturer’s instructions. For microinjection, proteins were dialyzed against microinjection buffer (50 mM Tris–HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ), concentrated in Centricon filters (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA), shock-frozen and stored at −80°C. Purity was tested by SDS–PAGE and Coomassie staining. For anisotropy experiments, GST fusions of the WASp acidic region were purified by FPLC, as described
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2.3. GST pull down assay and immunoblotting
   </title>
   <p>
    GST pull downs were prepared as described previously
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    . Briefly, a total of 3×10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    cells cultured for 5–14 days in six well plates (Nunc) at a density of 1×10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    cells/well were washed in ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and lysed by the addition of 200 μl/well RIPA buffer (20 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 75 mM NaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) containing protease inhibitors. After centrifugation (15 000 rpm, 15 min, 4°C), aliquots of the supernatant were added to glutathione Sepharose beads, previously incubated for 1 h with 50 μg of GST fusion proteins. Beads were incubated with lysate for 30 min at 4°C, washed extensively in RIPA buffer and pelleted. 100 μl of SDS sample buffer was added, and an aliquot was run on a 12.5% SDS gel. Western blots were prepared as described previously
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [23]
    </xref>
    . Arp2/3 complex was detected by using polyclonal anti-ARPC1 and -ARPC2 antibodies
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    . Secondary antibody was horseradish peroxidase-conjugated (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech). No binding of the screened proteins was detected when GST alone was bound to beads.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.4. Fluorescence anisotropy measurements
   </title>
   <p>
    Experiments were conducted as described elsewhere
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    . Briefly, 0.1 μM of rhodamine-labeled WASp VCA (without GST), 0.1 μM Arp2/3 complex and varying concentrations of binding partners were incubated in 20 nM imidazole, pH 7.0, 50 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , 1 mM EGTA, 0.025% Thesit (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, Basel, Switzerland) for 2 min at room temperature. Fluorescence anisotropy was measured in an Alpha-scan spectrofluorimeter (Photon Technologies International) at 552 nm excitation at 574 nm emission and plotted in arbitrary units. Dissociation equilibrium constants (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    ) were calculated as described earlier
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    . GST controls showed no effect in the anisotropy measurements. Arp2/3 complex was prepared from bovine thymus as described
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [24]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.5. Microinjection of proteins
   </title>
   <p>
    Cells for microinjection experiments were cultured for 5–8 days. Microinjection was performed using transjector 5246 (Eppendorf) and a Compic Inject micromanipulator (Cell Biology Trading, Hamburg, Germany). GST fusions of WASp C-terminal regions, GST-V12CDC42 and GST-free V12Rac were injected at the indicated concentrations. Cells were incubated for 1 h post injection. Control injections were performed with GST alone. Injected cells were identified by detection of coinjected rat IgG (5 mg/ml) with FITC-labeled goat anti-rat IgG antibody (both Dianova, Hamburg, Germany).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.6. Immunofluorescence microscopy
   </title>
   <p>
    For actin and Arp2/3 complex staining, cells were grown on coverslips for 5–8 days and microinjected when indicated. Samples were then fixed for 10 min in PBS solution containing 3.7% formaldehyde and permeabilized for 5 min in ice-cold acetone. Background fluorescence was reduced by incubating coverslips with 5% human serum and 5% normal goat serum (both Dianova) in PBS. Actin was detected with Alexa 568-labeled phalloidin (Molecular Probes, Leiden, The Netherlands) or with monoclonal antibody MAB1501 (Chemicon, Temecula, CA, USA), Arp2/3 complex was detected by staining with anti-ARPC2 antibody
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    . Secondary antibody was Alexa 488-labeled goat anti-rabbit (Molecular Probes). Coverslips were mounted in Mowiol (Calbiochem, Schwalbach, Germany), containing
    <em>
     p
    </em>
    -phenylenediamine (Sigma, Deisenhofen, Germany) as anti-fading reagent, and sealed with nail polish. Images were obtained either by confocal laser scanning microscopy (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany) or with a spot digital camera (Leica).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    3. Results and discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    To map residues of the 15 aa WASp A region necessary for interaction with Arp2/3 complex, a series of N-terminally truncated constructs fused to the C-terminus of GST were created and named accordingly WASp-A13, WASp-A11, WASp-A9 and WASp-A7 (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1C
    </xref>
    ). We first assessed the ability of these constructs to pull down Arp2/3 complex from macrophage lysates (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2A
    </xref>
    ). WASp-A was able to pull down Arp2/3 complex, as described
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    , while shorter constructs bound with decreasing efficiency. WASp-A11 displayed only minimal ability to pull down Arp2/3 complex, while WASp-A7 showed no interaction in this assay (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2A
    </xref>
    ). Decreasing ability to pull down Arp2/3 complex was reflected by decreasing affinity for Arp2/3 complex in anisotropy assays. For example, [=P42768 protein] WASp-A15 bound [=O15143 protein] Arp2/3 complex with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of [=8292892 kd] 1.0 μM (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2C
    </xref>
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    ), while WASp-A9 bound with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of 4.0 μM (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2D
    </xref>
    ). As positive and negative controls respectively, we used construct WASp-CA (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1A
    </xref>
    ), comprising all known binding sites for Arp2/3 complex in the VCA domain
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    , and construct WASp-A/W500S (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1C
    </xref>
    ) carrying a point mutation previously shown to drastically reduce the affinity of WASp VCA for Arp2/3 complex
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    . WASp-CA bound Arp2/3 complex efficiently, as shown earlier
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2A
    </xref>
    ), while WASp-A/W500S displayed no detectable interaction with Arp2/3 complex in this assay (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2A
    </xref>
    ). We conclude from these experiments that, apart from the previously identified W500 amino acid residue, also the presence of the four N-terminal amino acid residues of the WASp A region (aa 488–491) is critical for interaction with Arp2/3 complex in vitro.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Arp2/3 complex binding of GST fusions containing C-terminal acidic peptides of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         Arp2/3 complex binding of GST fusions containing C-terminal acidic peptides of WASp family proteins. Western blots of GST pull down experiments using (A) a series of N-terminally truncated or mutated constructs of WASp C-terminus or (B) constructs of acidic regions of WASp family proteins, probed with ARPC1-specific antibody. Denominations of polypeptides are given above each lane. Anisotropy measurement of binding to Arp2/3 complex by WASp-A (C) and WASp-A9 (D) constructs. Increasing amounts of the respective construct were allowed to compete with rhodamine-labeled (GST-free) WASp VCA. Decrease in anisotropy indicates successful competition by the respective construct.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The A regions of WASp and N-WASP are highly homologous (11 identical amino acids;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1B
    </xref>
    ), while those of WAVE proteins are clearly more divergent (7 homologous amino acids in WAVE1-A compared to WASp-A;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1B
    </xref>
    ). A GST fusion of the N-WASP acidic region, N-WASP-A (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1B
    </xref>
    ), showed comparable ability to WASp-A to pull down Arp2/3 complex from macrophage lysates (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2B
    </xref>
    ), while the respective WAVE1 construct, WAVE1-A (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1C
    </xref>
    ), was barely able to do so (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 2B
    </xref>
    ). The high identity of WASp and N-WASp acidic regions is therefore also mirrored by a functional similarity in Arp2/3 complex binding. In contrast, the acidic region of WAVE1 seems to be necessary
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [18]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [25]
    </xref>
    , but is clearly not sufficient for Arp2/3 complex binding.
   </p>
   <p>
    We went on to investigate whether formation of specific actin structures in cells is dependent on Arp2/3 complex. Microinjection of primary human macrophages with the constitutively active GTPase mutants V12CDC42Hs (0.2 μg/μl) or V12Rac1 (0.2 μg/μl) leads to formation of filopodia or lamellipodia/ruffles, respectively (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [23]
    </xref>
    and Linder, unpublished). The latter effect is mostly associated with cell spreading. When microinjected at values below the effective concentrations, neither the GTPase mutants (V12CDC42: 0.1 μg/μl; V12Rac: 0.1 μg/μl;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3A,B
    </xref>
    ) nor WASp-A (4 μg/μl;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3C
    </xref>
    ) or N-WASP-A (4 μg/μl;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3F
    </xref>
    ) had a discernible effect on the actin cytoskeleton (cells showing filopodia: V12CDC42, 10±9%; WASp-A, 12±2%; N-WASp-A, 12±4%; cells showing ruffles: V12Rac, 3±3%; WASp-A, 0±0%; N-WASp-A, 0±0%;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ). However, coinjection of WASp-A or N-WASp-A with either one of the constitutively active GTPase mutants, all proteins at sub-threshold concentrations, dramatically enhanced formation of filopodia or ruffles (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3D,E,G,H
    </xref>
    ). The respective phenotype was dependent on the GTPase mutant: coinjection with V12CDC42Hs resulted in filopodia formation (cells showing filopodia: V12CDC42+WASp-A, 97±6%; V12CDC42+N-WASp-A, 96±4%;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ), while coinjection with V12Rac triggered formation of ruffles and cell spreading (cells showing ruffles: V12Rac+WASp-A, 91±2%; V12Rac+N-WASp-A, 94±5%;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 3
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ). In this respect, the A regions of WASp and N-WASp were interchangeable.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Coinjection of WASp-A or N-WASp-A with constitutively active GTPase mutants has ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         Coinjection of WASp-A or N-WASp-A with constitutively active GTPase mutants has a synergistic effect on filopodia and lamellipodia formation. A–H: Confocal laser scanning micrographs of primary human macrophages stained for f-actin 1 h post injection. Insets show staining of rat IgG used as an injection marker. V12CDC42 (A) and V12Rac (B) were injected at 0.1 μg/μl. WASp-A (C) and N-WASP-A (F) were injected at 4 μg/μl. No effect on the actin cytoskeleton was observed at these concentrations. Coinjection of V12CDC42 with WASp-A (D) or N-WASp-A (G) at these concentrations led to prominent formation of filopodia, while coinjection of V12Rac with WASp-A (E) or N-WASP-A (H) led to formation of ruffles and cell spreading. White bar indicates 12 μm for E and H and 10 μm for all others.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Evaluation of actin structure formation in primary human macrophages ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         Evaluation of actin structure formation in primary human macrophages microinjected with WASp family acidic constructs and/or constitutively active GTPase mutants. White columns: injection of WASp family acidic construct without GTPase mutant; black columns: injection of V12CDC42 (0.1 μg/μl); gray columns: injection of V12Rac (0.1 μg/μl), ‘+’ indicates coinjection with respective WASp family acidic region construct (4 μg/μl). Denominations of microinjected polypeptides are given above each column. Values for cells showing actin structure formation are given as mean percentage±S.D. Filopodia formation: WASp-A, 12±2%; N-WASp-A, 12±4%; WAVE1-A, 12±7%; V12CDC42, 10±9%; V12CDC42+WASp-A, 97±6%; V12CDC42+N-WASp-A, 96±4%; V12CDC42+WAVE1-A, 8±2%; V12CDC42+WASp-A/W500S, 12±8%; V12CDC42+WASp-A13, 41±10%; V12CDC42+WASp-A11, 3±6%. Ruffle formation: WASp-A, 0±0%; N-WASp-A, 0±0%; WAVE1-A, 8±4%; V12Rac, 3±3%; V12Rac+WASp-A, 91±2%; V12Rac+N-WASp-A, 94±5%; V12Rac+WAVE1-A, 6±7%; V12Rac+WASp-A/W500S, 19±5%; V12Rac+WASp-A13, 53±7%; V12Rac+WASp-A11, 8±5%. For each value, three times 30 cells microinjected with the respective construct were evaluated.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In contrast, coinjection of the GTPase mutants with WAVE1-A failed to elicit any discernible effect on the actin cytoskeleton (cells showing filopodia: V12CDC42+WAVE1-A, 8±2%; cells showing ruffles: V12Rac+WAVE1-A, 6±7%;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ). In addition, WASp-A13 was able to stimulate formation of filopodia or ruffles in coinjection experiments (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ), although to a lesser degree compared to WASp-A, while all shorter constructs of the WASp acidic region failed to do so (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    and not shown). Coinjection of GTPase constructs with the WASp-A/W500S mutant resulted in a marked decrease in both filopodia and ruffle formation compared to coinjections with WASp-A (cells showing filopodia: V12CDC42+WASp-A/W500S, 12±8%; cells showing ruffles: V12Rac+WASp-A/W500S, 19±5%;
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 4
    </xref>
    ). Additionally, coinjection of WASp-CA (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 1A
    </xref>
    ) stimulated filopodia or ruffle formation even at concentrations of 0.5 μg/μl (not shown). This requirement for lower effective concentrations fits well with WASp-CA showing a 10-fold higher affinity for Arp2/3 complex (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    : 0.1 μM
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    ) than WASp-A (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    : 1 μM).
   </p>
   <p>
    Formation of filopodia or ruffles in microinjected cells was often accompanied by disruption of podosomes, actin-rich adhesion structures controlled by WASp
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    and
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [23]
    </xref>
    . Therefore, regulation of podosomes apparently differs from that of filopodia and lamellipodia. It seems that Arp2/3 complex bound to WASp family A region constructs is not incorporated into podosomes
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [2]
    </xref>
    , but can be used effectively by GTPase-triggered pathways to induce filopodia and ruffles. These signals may involve e.g. the CDC42-IRSp53-Mena pathway recently shown to be important for filopodia formation in Swiss 3T3 cells
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [26]
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    In sum, we assessed the Arp2/3 complex binding abilities of WASp family acidic constructs in vitro and in vivo. The acidic regions of WASp and N-WASp, but not of WAVE1, were found to interact efficiently with Arp2/3 complex in vitro. The four N-terminal amino acid residues of WASp-A are crucial for this effect. Significantly, we observed a synergistic effect in the formation of filopodia and ruffles when GST fusions of the acidic regions of WASp or N-WASP were coinjected into macrophages with constitutively active mutants of CDC42Hs or Rac1. Coinjection with WASp-A13 also showed a synergistic effect on filopodia or ruffle formation, although to a less marked degree compared to the full-length WASp-A. Coinjections of GTPases with all shorter constructs of the WASp acidic region as well as the WASp-A/W500S construct or the WAVE-1A construct led to no significant increase in actin structure formation. The ability of WASp family A region constructs to induce actin structure formation thus closely correlated with their ability to bind actin nucleating Arp2/3 complex in vitro. Therefore, Arp2/3 complex binding is most probably a prerequisite for the observed effects, which is also indicated by the recruitment of Arp2/3 complex to the induced structures (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Fig. 5
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Arp2/3 complex localizes to actin structures induced by coinjection of WASp ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S001457930202358X-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         Arp2/3 complex localizes to actin structures induced by coinjection of WASp acidic regions and constitutively active GTPase mutants. Confocal laser scanning micrographs of 7 day old macrophages microinjected with V12Rac+WASp-A (A–C), or V12CDC42Hs+WASp-A (D–I). Pictures were gained by superimposition of each time three (A–C) or two (D–I) confocal sections with a scanning difference of 1–2 μm. Red color, Arp2/3 complex stained with anti-ARPC2 antibody (A,D,G), blue color, actin stained with anti-actin antibody (B,E,H), overlay of a and b (C), of d and e (F) and of g and h (I), pink color indicates colocalization. Insets in A,D show staining of coinjected rat IgG used as injection marker. G–I show details of D–F, with white box in D indicating the magnified part of the respective panels. White arrows indicate the basis of a filopodium with accumulations of Arp2/3 complex and f-actin, white arrowheads indicate tip of filopodium with accumulations of f-actin but not of Arp2/3 complex. White bars indicate 10 μm for all panels of the same sizes.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To elucidate the mechanism by which the observed structures are induced, we studied the distribution of WASp, N-WASP and WAVE in uninjected cells and in cells coinjected with WASp-A with CDC42
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    /Rac
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    (not shown). We find that, although the podosomal localization of WASp is destroyed upon microinjection of WASp-A with CDC42
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    /Rac
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    , there is no significant colocalization of endogenous WASp with either filopodia or ruffles. In a previous study, we also found no indication for an interaction of WASp-A with endogenous WASp in vitro
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [22]
    </xref>
    . On the other hand, N-WASp and WAVE localize to newly formed filopodia or ruffles, respectively. Ultimately, we cannot rule out that WASp-A or endogenous WASp plays a role in the generation of these structures. However, according to our data it is likely that filopodia and lamellipodia are induced and localized by the pathways CDC42-N-WASP-Arp2/3 complex and Rac-WAVE-Arp2/3 complex, respectively. In this scenario, WASp-A would only induce ‘priming’ of Arp2/3 complex, which would explain the high efficiency in structure formation, while the generation of specific structures as well as their localization would not be based on WASp-A activity.
   </p>
   <p>
    In a recent paper, Zalevsky et al.
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [27]
    </xref>
    show that in a chimera of the WAVE1 C-terminal domain, replacement of the acidic region of WAVE1 with the acidic region of N-WASp results in a 20-fold increase in actin nucleating ability. This fits well with our data that, in contrast to WASp-A and N-WASP-A, WAVE1-A is not able to bind Arp2/3 complex efficiently in vitro or to induce actin structures upon coinjection of WASpA with CDC42
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    /Rac
    <sup>
     V12
    </sup>
    . It is not yet clear where the ‘priming’ step proposed in the present paper would fit in the actin nucleation model presented by Zalevsky et al.
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [27]
    </xref>
    . It may occur directly upon binding of WASp/N-WASp to Arp2/3 complex but also at a later step.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our results imply that (i) Arp2/3 complex is critically involved in the generation of both filopodia and ruffles in primary human macrophages and (ii) the acidic regions of WASp and N-WASP are not simply high-affinity binding sites for Arp2/3 complex. It may be that these regions induce a ‘priming’ step which does not lead to full activation but to heightened susceptibility of Arp2/3 complex for GTPase-triggered signals to induce actin polymerization. The existence of additional activation steps in actin nucleating pathways has already been speculated upon
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     [21]
    </xref>
    . Our results give the first indication at the cellular level that at least one such additional step may in fact exist. The acidic region constructs used in this study may also be helpful tools in further addressing this issue and also whether actin-dependent processes in cells are Arp2/3 complex-dependent.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [1]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.M. Svitkina, G.G. Borisy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 5 (1999), pp. 1009–1026
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [2]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Linder, H.N. Higgs, K. Hüfner, K. Schwarz, U. Pannicke, M. Aepfelbacher
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Immunol., 165 (2000), pp. 221–225
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [3]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. May, M.E. Hall, H.N. Higgs, T.D. Pollard, T. Chakraborty, J. Wehland, L.M. Machesky, A.S. Sechi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 9 (1999), pp. 759–762
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [4]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Cossart
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Microbiol., 2 (2000), pp. 195–205
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [5]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Egile, T.P. Loisel, V. Laurent, R. Li, D. Pantaloni, P.J. Sansonetti, M.F. Carlier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 146 (1999), pp. 1319–1332
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [6]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.C. May, E. Caron, A. Hall, L.M. Machesky
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature Cell Biol., 2 (2000), pp. 246–248
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [7]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Wiedemann, S. Linder, G. Grassl, M. Albert, I. Autenrieth, M. Aepfelbacher
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell Microbiol., 3 (2001), pp. 693–702
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [8]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Linder, C. Heimerl, V. Fingerle, M. Aepfelbacher, B. Wilske
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Infect. Immun., 69 (2001), pp. 1739–1746
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [9]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.N. Higgs, T.D. Pollard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 32531–32534
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [10]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.D. Mullins
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Cell Biol., 12 (2000), pp. 97–103
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [11]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Takenawa, H. Miki
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Sci., 114 (2001), pp. 1801–1807
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [12]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.D. Nobes, A. Hall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 81 (1995), pp. 53–62
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [13]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Miki, T. Sasaki, Y. Takai, T. Takenawa
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 391 (1998), pp. 93–96
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [14]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Castellano, P. Montcourrier, J-C. Guillemot, E. Gouin, L.M. Machesky, P. Cossart, P. Chavrier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 9 (1999), pp. 351–360
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [15]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.M. Svitkina, G.G. Borisy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Biol. Sci., 24 (1999), pp. 432–436
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [16]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.J. Ridley, H.F. Paterson, C.L. Johnston, C.L. Diekmann, A. Hall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 70 (1992), pp. 401–410
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [17]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.M. Machesky, R.H. Insall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 8 (1998), pp. 1347–1356
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [18]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.M. Machesky, D.M. Mullins, H.N. Higgs, D.A. Kaiser, L. Blanchoin, R.C. May, M.E. Hall, T.D. Pollard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 96 (1999), pp. 3739–3744
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [19]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Rohatgi, L. Ma, H. Miki, M. Lopez, T. Kirchhausen, T. Takenawa, M.W. Kirschner
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 97 (1999), pp. 221–231
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [20]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Blanchoin, K.J. Amann, H.N. Higgs, J.B. Marchand, D.A. Kaiser, T.D. Pollard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 404 (2000), pp. 1007–1011
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [21]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.B. Marchand, D.A. Kaiser, T.D. Pollard, H.N. Higgs
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature Cell Biol., 3 (2001), pp. 76–82
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [22]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Hüfner, H.N. Higgs, T.D. Pollard, C. Jacobi, M. Aepfelbacher, S. Linder
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 35761–35767
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [23]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Linder, D. Nelson, M. Weiss, M. Aepfelbacher
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 96 (1999), pp. 9648–9653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [24]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.N. Higgs, L. Blanchoin, T.D. Pollard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 38 (1999), pp. 15212–15222
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [25]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Sasaki, H. Miki, T. Takenawa
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 272 (2000), pp. 386–390
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [26]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Krugmann, I. Jordens, K. Gevaert, M. Driessens, J. Vandekerckhove, A. Hall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 11 (2001), pp. 1645–1655
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <xref ref-type="bibr">
         [27]
        </xref>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Zalevsky, L. Lempert, H. Kranitz, R.D. Mullins
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Biol., 11 (2001), pp. 1903–1913
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2002 Federation of European Biochemical Societies. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
