<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2009.06.004
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    TOE1 interacts with p53 to modulate its transactivation potential
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keyword
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      Protein interaction
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    In our ongoing efforts to identify target genes for the Egr1 transcription factor that may participate in its tumor suppressor function, we applied an approach based upon the cloning of in vivo binding sites for DNA-binding proteins by chromatin immunoprecipitation. We have adapted this method to a PCR based protocol allowing the cloning of cDNAs from a library and previously cloned a gene we have named
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    for Target of Egr1
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . Sequence homology analysis of the
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    gene revealed a unique nucleotide and amino acid structure with the gene mapping to human chromosome 1 within a region encompassing 1p34.1-3. Interestingly, deletions in this same region are frequently associated with various tumor genotypes with 1p deletion providing an accurate prognostic indicator of therapeutic efficacy
    <a>
     [2]
    </a>
    . The
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    gene lies within a small region of the chromosome that has been shown to harbor one or more potential tumor suppressor genes
    <a>
     [3]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [4]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [5]
    </a>
    . It remains to be determined whether
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    displays regulated expression between normal versus tumor cells. Its localization to the nucleus was, however, predicted based upon a stretch of basic amino acid residues located toward the C terminus of the protein. We have confirmed that these residues are important for the nuclear targeting of TOE1 since deletion of this region resulted in the cytoplasmic localization of TOE1. Although the precise biological function of TOE1 has not been determined, a deadenylating enzymatic activity has recently been attributed to TOE1
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    We have shown that expression of
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    is associated with an accumulation of cells in the G2/M cell cycle phase, as well as increased expression of the cyclin dependent kinase inhibitor p21
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . The TOE1-mediated inhibition of cellular growth is consistent with the effects of Egr1 expression
    <a>
     [7]
    </a>
    , as well as with our previous findings for Egr1 insofar as we observed a non-G1 cell cycle accumulation of cells as well as increased p21 expression
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    . By this criterion, TOE1 appears to act as an important mediator of the growth effects of Egr1. Since it is well established that induction of p21 expression is frequently associated with activation of p53, and since p53 has been reported as a target gene for Egr1
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    , we sought to determine whether the effects of TOE1 involved p53. Our earlier studies showed that
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    expression did not result in any apparent increase in the overall synthesis of p53, nor any increase in the phosphorylation of p53 on serine 15, a common indicator of its activation
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . Since both p53 and TOE1 occupy a similar cellular distribution within the nucleus and nucleolus, we hypothesized that the two proteins might physically interact to affect p21 gene expression and impact cellular growth. In this study, we present our data identifying an interaction between TOE1 and p53 and describe the effect of this interaction on p21 activation.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and methods
   </title>
   <title>
    2.1. Cell lines and culture conditions
   </title>
   <p>
    293 and HeLa cells were cultured in DMEM medium containing 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum and supplemented with 2 mM
    <span>
     l
    </span>
    -glutamine and grown in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    . For transfection, cells were seeded the previous day and then transfected with the appropriate plasmids using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), according to the manufacturers instructions.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.2. Co-immunoprecipitation
   </title>
   <p>
    For co-immunoprecipitation assays, 293 cells were transfected with the indicated plasmids. Cells were collected and washed with cold PBS and then lysed in ice cold lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES, pH 7.6/250 mM NaCl/1 mM EDTA/1% (v/v) NP40). Lysates were sonicated for 2 s to break open nuclei, and incubated on ice for 15 min. Cell lysates were clarified by centrifugation at 16 000×
    <em>
     g
    </em>
    for 10 min at 4 °C and pre-cleared with protein A sepharose beads for 1 h at 4 °C with rotation. For immunoprecipitation, 1 μg of rabbit anti-p53 antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnologies, Santa Cruz, CA), was added and incubated overnight at 4 °C with rotation. The next day protein A sepharose beads were added and incubation continued for an additional 1 h. The beads were then washed four times with lysis buffer, and suspended in SDS sample loading buffer. Western blotting was then performed using a mouse anti-TOE1 monoclonal antibody (Abnova, Taipei, Taiwan).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.3. GST pulldown assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Bacterial expression constructs expressing full length, wild type p53 or fragments consisting of amino acids 1–160, 160–320, 320–393 as GST fusion proteins were kindly provided by Dr. James Borowiec (NYU). Fusion proteins were expressed in bacteria following IPTG induction and purified using glutathione sepharose beads. Quantitation of captured fusion protein was performed by elution of an aliquot of the beads with reduced glutathione, followed by protein concentration determination by the Bradford assay. The purity of the recombinant proteins was assessed by SDS–PAGE. About 293 cells were transfected with an expression plasmid containing the cDNA for TOE1. Twenty-four hours after transfection, the cells were lysed in the same buffer described for co-immunoprecipitation. Cell lysates were mixed with beads containing an equimolar concentration of each affinity purified GST fusion protein and mixed overnight at 4 °C. The next day the beads were washed four times with lysis buffer and suspended in SDS sample buffer, and Western blotting was performed using a rabbit affinity purified anti-TOE1 antibody.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.4. Nanoporous optical interferometry
   </title>
   <p>
    For label free protein/protein interaction detection and kinetic constant measurement, the SKi Pro (Silicon Kinetics, San Diego), instrument was used with a flow cell configuration equipped with an autosampler for sample delivery. SKi Pro uses derivatized nanoporous silicon chips to allow crosslinking with biomolecules and when incorporates a self-referenced channel when used in the flow cell configuration to permit background, non-specific binding subtraction. Nanoporous carboxy chips were activated using sulfo-NHS/EDAC chemistry in a buffer consisting of 0.1 M MES pH 6, 0.15 M NaCl following the manufacturers guidelines (see
    <a>
     www.siliconkinetics.com
    </a>
    ). The chips were subsequently immobilized with recombinant TOE1 expressed as a GST fusion protein at a concentration of 5 μM in 20 mM sodium acetate, pH 4.5 and then blocked with 1 M ethanolamine, pH 8.0. The indicated purified, recombinant protein was provided for the binding reaction in phosphate buffered saline, pH 7.2, and the optical interference pattern was recorded as a change in optical path difference in units of nm. For kinetic constant calculation, the analysis software package included with the SKi Pro system was used.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2.5. Chromatin Immunoprecipitation
   </title>
   <p>
    HeLa cells were cultured in a 10 cm plate as described above and fixed by adding to the culture medium 1/10 volume of a solution containing 11% HCHO, 50 mM Tris pH 8, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA for 20 min at room temperature with gentle agitation. Cells were lysed in RIPA buffer modified to reach a final concentration of 0.5 M NaCl, and 1% SDS and supplemented with Complete protease inhibitors (Roche, Laval, Quebec). The lysate was sonicated for 5 cycles of 20″ at 10% power. Lysates were cleared by centrifugation for 10′ at 16 000×
    <em>
     g
    </em>
    and the supernatant was diluted with RIPA minus SDS to obtain a final concentration of 0.1% SDS. The samples were incubated with 30 μl of protein A sepharose beads for 1 h at 4 °C for preclearing. 10 μl of affinity purified polyclonal anti-TOE1 antibody or pre-immune serum were added to the cleared supernatant that were incubated o/n at 4 °C. The day after 30 μl of protein A sepharose beads for were added for an additional 1 h at 4 °C. The beads were then washed four times with RIPA buffer, followed by two washes in LiCl buffer (10 mM Tris pH 8, 0.25 M LiCl, 0.5% NP40, 0.5% deoxycholate, 1 mM EDTA), and two washes in TE. The crosslinking was reversed by incubation at 68 °C o/n. DNA was recovered by phenol/chloroform extraction followed by EtOH precipitation in the presence of 20 μg of glycogen (Roche). After precipitation the DNA was dissolved in H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O and 1/50 of the immunoprecipitate or 200 ng of input chromatin were subjected to PCR with the following primers: GAGGGACTGGGGGAGGAGGGAAG and CGGCAGCTGCTCACACCTCAGC for the p21 promoter, and TGGTGTTGCAAGCAGGATCCAA and TCGGCTGGAGTTGCAGATGGA for the TLR2 promoter for 30 cycles.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.6. Luciferase reporter assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Freshly thawed HeLa cells were seeded in 24 well culture plates and transfected in triplicate with 100 ng of reporter vector plasmid together with 150 ng of each of the indicated expression vector as described above. Twenty-four hours later, the cells were lysed in 100 mM KPO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , pH 7.8/0.2% (v/v) Triton X-100/1 mM DTT, and the luciferase activity was measured using a EG&amp;G Berthold Microplate luminometer.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    3. Results
   </title>
   <p>
    To test the hypothesis that TOE1 may form a complex with p53 through protein/protein interactions, our first experiments were to perform a co-immunoprecipitation assay from cells transfected with TOE1 in the presence or absence of transfected, wild type p53. For these experiments we have chosen 293 cells for their ease of transfection. While these cells have been transformed with Adenovirus 5 DNA, we overexpressed wild type p53 by transfection to detect protein/protein interaction. As shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    , we were able detect an interaction between p53 and TOE1 by co-immunoprecipitation. These results suggest that p53 and TOE1 are capable of interacting. To test whether the protein/protein interaction occurred non-specifically following cell lysis, we performed a co-immunoprecipitation experiment using a mutant version of TOE1 that does not enter the nucleus. We observed no interaction between p53 and the non-nuclear mutant of TOE1 (data not shown).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Co-immunoprecipitation of TOE1 with p53. About 293 cells were transfected with ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Co-immunoprecipitation of TOE1 with p53. About 293 cells were transfected with empty vector (pcDNA3), or vectors expressing p53 alone or together with FLAG-tagged TOE1. Following transfection cells were incubated for 24 h at 37 °C. Cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with rabbit anti-p53 antibodies, and Western blots probed for either p53 or FLAG-TOE1 using mouse antibodies.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (39 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    p53 is known to interact with a large number of protein partners and has been shown to bind non-specifically to many more
    <a>
     [10]
    </a>
    . To test the specificity of interaction between TOE1 and p53 we performed in vitro GST pulldown assays using purified recombinant proteins. TOE1 was expressed as a full length GST fusion protein while GST-p53 fusion proteins were expressed as either full length or as truncated proteins. The GST-p53 fusion constructs used, representing the N terminal activation, central DNA-binding and C terminal tetramerization domains and as shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    A.
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    B shows a Coomassie blue stained gel of the recombinant purified proteins used for the pulldown experiments. To detect a potential interaction between TOE1 and p53, equimolar amounts of each GST-p53 construct, captured on glutathione beads, were mixed with TOE1 to allow binding to occur. Following washes, the beads were eluted with SDS sample buffer and analysed by SDS–PAGE and Western blotting using TOE1 anti-serum. The results of the pulldown experiments are shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    C and show that purified, recombinant TOE1 was capable of interacting with both full length p53 as well as displaying a strong interaction with the C terminal tetramerization domain of p53. The small amount of interaction seen with the N terminal portion of p53 we consider to be non-specific as the same signal can be seen using the control GST protein alone. These results confirm that TOE1 can interact with p53 and furthermore support that this interaction occurs via the C terminal tetramerization domain in p53.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="GST pulldown of TOE1 with the C terminal domain of p53. (A) Schematic diagram of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         GST pulldown of TOE1 with the C terminal domain of p53. (A) Schematic diagram of the p53 GST fusion proteins used in the pulldown assay with the corresponding amino acids indicated. Not drawn to scale. (B) SDS–PAGE of the expressed and purified GST fusion proteins used in the pulldown assays. Molecular weight markers are shown at the left. (C) Western blot detection of TOE1 following GST pulldown assay. The indicated GST fusion protein was incubated with 293 cell extracts expressing TOE1, and TOE1 detected using affinity purified rabbit anti-TOE1 antibodies.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (163 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    In order to further characterize the interaction between TOE1 and p53 we determined the binding affinity kinetic constants using nanoporous optical interferometry
    <a>
     [11]
    </a>
    . This technology uses nanoporous silicon chips derivatized with carboxylated polyethylene glycol to permit protein immobilization via amine coupling using NHS/EDAC ester crosslinking. Once the nanoporous silicon chip has been immobilized with receptor protein a target protein is provided to the chip using microfluidics. Upon binding, the optical interference pattern is measured and recorded as a sensorgram allowing the quantitation of binding kinetic constants. Using the SKi Pro bisensor interaction instrument we were able to detect an interaction between immobilized TOE1 with the C terminal domain, but not with the N terminal or central DNA-binding domain of p53 (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    A). Further, we did not observe any interaction with the GST moiety alone. To determine the affinity between TOE1 and the p53 C terminal domain, we again used SKi Pro nanoporous optical interferometry. As previously, TOE1 was immobilized to the nanoporous silicon chip and the C terminal domain of p53 was provided at varying concentrations.
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    B shows the sensorgrams of the binding reactions. Following data collection, the kinetic parameters and affinity constants were calculated using the SKi Pro kinetic analysis package and results for the kinetic constants are presented in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Nanoporous optical interferometry measurement of binding kinetics. (A) Purified ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         Nanoporous optical interferometry measurement of binding kinetics. (A) Purified recombinant TOE1 was immobilized to a carboxy chip at a concentration of 5 μM. Following chip blocking, the chip was provided with target protein in the flow cell at a concentration of 2000 nM in PBS binding buffer. (B) TOE1 immobilized to a carboxy chip was provided with the C terminal GST-p53 domain at concentrations varying from 400 to 1000 nM in PBS binding buffer.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (147 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Table of kinetic binding constants. Table shows calculated kinetic binding constants for the interaction between immobilized TOE1 and GST-p53 representing residues 320–393.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Interaction
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            k
           </em>
           <sub>
            a
           </sub>
           (M
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           s
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            k
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (s
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (M)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           TOE1 + p53 C terminus
          </td>
          <td>
           1.27 × 10
           <sup>
            3
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           1.7 × 10
           <sup>
            −4
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           7.2 × 10
           <sup>
            −8
           </sup>
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Using a variety of methodologies, the combined experiments described above provide consistent evidence that TOE1 is capable of specific interaction with the C terminal tetramerization domain of p53. In addition, we have shown previously that expression of TOE1 increases p21 levels
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . Since p53 is a known transactivator of p21, we sought to determine whether the interaction between TOE1 and p53 could be detected in vivo on the p21 promoter.
   </p>
   <p>
    As shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    A, anti-TOE1, but not pre-immune, immunoprecipitates contained sequences corresponding to the p21 promoter. As a negative control, primers for the TLR2 promoter showed no amplification from the same immunoprecipitates. These results indicate that TOE1 can be found in vivo in a complex containing the p21 promoter.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Binding and activation of p53-responsive promoter by p53 and TOE1. (A) ChIP of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         Binding and activation of p53-responsive promoter by p53 and TOE1. (A) ChIP of TOE1 bound to p21 promoter. PCR amplification of the p21 promoter but not a negative control (TLR2) from chromatin immunoprecipitated with anti TOE1 antibody. (B and C) HeLa cells were transfected with a luciferase reporter vector containing the p21 or PTEN promoter together with the indicated expression vectors. Control samples were transfected with empty expression vector. Twenty-four hours after transfection, cells were collected and assayed for luciferase activity by luminometry. Results are presented as the average of tripicate samples with the standard deviations indicated with error bars.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (157 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To determine whether a TOE1/p53 interaction may have functional consequences to the biological function of p53, we examined the transcriptional activation of two eukaryotic promoters known to be induced by p53, in the presence or absence of TOE1. We chose to look at the effects on the PTEN promoter since it is known to be p53 and Egr1 activated and is a recognized tumor suppressor gene
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    . Additionally, we examined the transcriptional effects on the p21 promoter because of its known targeting by p53 as well as the documented upregulation of p21 following TOE1 expression
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [14]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [15]
    </a>
    . As shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    B and C, while both reporter genes were activated by p53 as expected
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    , TOE1 alone had no or a marginal effect on reporter gene activation. However when both proteins were co-expressed we observed a TOE1 dependent enhancement of p53 transactivation. This suggested that the interaction between TOE1 and p53 may have functional significance with respect to augmenting the transactivation potential of p53.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    4. Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    It has been well established that the Egr1 and p53 growth inhibitory effects display considerable overlap
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [16]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [17]
    </a>
    . Both proteins are capable of producing growth inhibition, likely through activation of key common target genes exemplified by p21 and PTEN. Establishing the key biological activities of TOE1 will allow us to proceed to address our hypothesis that Egr1 and p53 mediated growth inhibition may include the activity of TOE1. It is estimated that p53 mutations occur in roughly 50% of human cancers
    <a>
     [18]
    </a>
    , and the identification of a modulator of p53 function would be a significant advance in understanding both the regulation of p53 activity as well as possibly contributing to furthering the understanding of tumor biology.
   </p>
   <p>
    In our studies we have demonstrated that TOE1 makes physical contact with p53 using multiple independent methods. Additionally, we have characterized the kinetic association constants between these two proteins using nanoporous optical interferometry. Our affinity constant determinations suggest that TOE1 binding to p53 demonstrates a high affinity binding capability with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of 72 nM. This affinity is within the same range as the previously published affinity constant between p53 and Bcl2
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . Our results indicate that the binding surface for TOE1 lies within the C terminal portion of p53 responsible for protein tetramerization. It is possible that TOE1 may exert its effects on p53 by stabilizing the active tetrameric form of the protein, to promote DNA-binding. Other possibilities include, but are not limited to, facilitating other protein/protein interactions, altering p53 degradation, affecting nuclear export and influencing p53 post-translational modification.
   </p>
   <p>
    Since there are a large number of p53 binding partners, the identification of an additional p53 binding protein requires a demonstration that the interaction serves a biologically significant role. We show here that the binding of TOE1 to p53 enhances the transactivation function of p53 on two independent p53 responsive promoters; p21 and PTEN. In addition, we show proof of an in vivo association of TOE1 with the p21 promoter, likely through the interaction with p53. Thus, we propose that the effects of TOE1 on growth inhibition might function through a signal-directed interaction with p53 resulting in a change in the activity of p53. A model for this hypothesis is shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    . We propose that the overlapping effects demonstrated between Egr1 and p53 may be mediated by TOE1. In this model, activation of Egr1 leads to increased expression of
    <em>
     TOE1
    </em>
    , which subsequently binds to p53. This interaction promotes the p53-dependent activation of its target genes including p21 and PTEN to favor cell cycle arrest and growth inhibition. In this manner, we propose that TOE1 is capable of integrating the effects of Egr1 and p53 and thereby serves as a biologically important target of Egr1 with respect to its tumor suppressor activity as well as a co-regulator of the p53 tumor suppressor function. We are initiating genetic knock out studies to allow us to address these and other aspects of TOE1 function in greater detail.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Model for TOE1 as a co-activator of gene expression leading to growth ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579309004451-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         Model for TOE1 as a co-activator of gene expression leading to growth suppression. Proposed model for the cooperation between Egr1 and p53 in activating target genes leading to growth/cell cycle arrest. Egr1 and p53 both activate PTEN, TGFβ1and p21 genes. TOE1 is shown as an Egr1 target gene that binds to and augments the activity of p53. In this way, Egr1 enhances the cooperative effect with p53 by inducing its activator.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (65 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    5. Statement of competing interest
   </title>
   <p>
    M.L. and I. de B. declare receiving financial assistance from Silicon Kinetics for performing some of the experiments described herein.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [1]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I. de Belle, J.-X. Wu, S. Sperandio, D. Mercola, E.D. Adamson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         In vivo cloning and characterization of a new growth suppressor protein TOE1 as a direct target gene of Egr1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 14306–14312
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [2]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R. Spitz, B. Hero, F. Westermann, K. Ernestus, M. Schwab, F. Berthold
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Fluorescence in situ hybridization analyses of chromosome band 1p36 in neuroblastoma detect two classes of alterations
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Chromosomes Cancer, 34 (2002), pp. 299–305
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [3]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Hashimoto, M. Murakami, Y. Takahashi, M. Fujimoto, J. Inazawa, K. Mineura
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Correlation between genetic alteration and long-term clinical outcome of patients with oligodendroglial tumors, with identification of a consistent region of deletion on chromosome arm 1p
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer, 97 (2003), pp. 2254–2261
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [4]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E.P. Sulman, P.S. White, G.M. Brodeur
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genomic annotation of the meningioma tumor suppressor locus on chromosome 1p34
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 23 (2004), pp. 1014–1020
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [5]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Iuchi, H. Namba, Y. Iwadate, T. Shishikura, H. Kageyama, Y. Nakamura, M. Ohira, A. Yamura, K. Osato, S. Sakiyama, A. Nakagawara
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of the small interstitial deletion at chromosome band 1p34–p35 and its association with poor outcome in oligodendroglial tumors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes, Chromosomes and Cancer, 35 (2002), pp. 170–175
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [6]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Wagner, S.L. Clement, J. Lykke-Andersen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         An unconventional human Ccr4-Caf1 deadenylase complex in nuclear cajal bodies
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell Biol., 27 (2007), pp. 1686–1695
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [7]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.-P. Huang, C.-T. Liu, Y. Fan, D.A. Mercola, E.D. Adamson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Egr-1 negatively regulates human tumor cell growth via the DNA-binding domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 55 (1995), pp. 5054–5062
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [8]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I. de Belle, R.-P. Huang, Y. Fan, C. Liu, D. Mercola, E.D. Adamson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         P53 and Egr-1 additively suppress transformed growth in HT1080 cells but Egr-1 counteracts p53-dependent apoptosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 18 (1999), pp. 3633–3642
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [9]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Nair, S. Muthukkumar, S.F. Sells, S.S. Han, V.P. Sukhatme, V.M. Rangnekar
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Early growth response-1-dependent apoptosis is mediated by p53
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 20131–20138
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [10]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.J. Ko, C. Prives
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         P53: Puzzle and paradigm
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 10 (1996), pp. 1054–1072
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [11]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Latterich, M. and Corbeil, J. (2008) Label-free detection of biomolecular interactions in real time with a nano-porous silicon-based detection method. Proteome Sci. 6 (E pub ahead of print).
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [12]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V. Stambolic, D. MacPherson, D. Sas, Y. Lin, B. Snow, Y. Jang, S. Benchimol, T.W. Mak
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of PTEN transcription by p53
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 2 (2001), pp. 317–325
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [13]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Virolle, E.D. Adamson, V. Baron, D. Birle, D. Mercola, T. Mustelin, I. de Belle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Egr-1 transcription factor directly activates PTEN during irradiation-induced signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 3 (2001), pp. 1124–1128
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [14]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.S. El-Deiry, T. Tokino, V.E. Velculescu, D.B. Levy, R. Parsons, J.M. Trent, D. Lin, W.E. Mercer, K.W. Kinzler, B. Vogelstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         WAF1, a potential mediator of p53 tumor suppression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 75 (1993), pp. 817–825
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [15]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W.S. El-Deiry, J.W. Harper, P.M. O’Connor, V.E. Velculescu, C. Canman, J. Jackman, J.A. Pietenpol, M. Burrell, D.E. Hill, Y. Wang, K.G. Wiman, W.E. Mercer, M.B. Kastan, K.W. Kohn, S.J. Elledge, K.W. Kinzler, B. Vogelstein
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         WAF1/CIP1 is induced in p53-mediated G1 arrest and apoptosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 54 (1994), pp. 1169–1174
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [16]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Krones-Herzig, E.D. Adamson, D. Mercola
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Early growth response 1 protein, an upstream gatekeeper of the p53 tumor suppressor, controls replicative senescence
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 100 (2003), pp. 3233–3238
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [17]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Krones-Herzig, S. Mittal, K. Yule, H. Liang, C. English, R. Urcis, T. Soni, E.D. Adamson, D. Mercola
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Early growth response 1 acts as a tumor suppressor in vivo and in vitro via regulation of p53
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 65 (2005), pp. 5133–5143
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [18]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Vogelstein, D. Lane, A.J. Levine
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Surfing the p53 network
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 408 (2000), pp. 307–310
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [19]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Tomita, N. Marchenko, S. Erster, A. Nemajerova, A. Dehner, C. LKlein, H. Pan, H. Kessler, P. Pancoska, U.M. Moll
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         WT p53 but not tumor-derived mutants bind to Bcl2 via the DNA binding domain and induce mitochondrial permeabilization
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 281 (2006), pp. 8600–8606
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2009 Federation of European Biochemical Societies. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>