<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0076-6879(06)06018-6
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Purification and Enzyme Activity of ACK1
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The activated Cdc42‐associated kinases (ACKs), ACK1 and ACK2, are a family of nonreceptor tyrosine kinases that associate specifically with Cdc42 (not Rac or Rho) and act as Cdc42 effectors in several signaling pathways (
    <a>
     Manser 1993
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yang 1997
    </a>
    ). ACK1 and ACK2 contain similar functional domains but differ at the amino‐ and carboxy termini. The domain structure of ACK kinases is unique among nonreceptor tyrosine kinases: it consists of an N‐terminal tyrosine kinase catalytic domain followed by an SH3 domain, a Cdc42/Rac interactive binding (CRIB) domain, and a proline‐rich region (
    <a>
     Manser
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 1993
    </a>
    ). The position of the SH3 domain C‐terminal to the catalytic domain contrasts with the N‐terminal SH3 domain observed in the Src, Csk, Abl, Frk, and Tec families. The C‐terminal proline‐rich domain of ACK1 interacts with the adaptor proteins Nck (
    <a>
     Teo
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 2001
    </a>
    ), Grb2 (
    <a>
     Satoh
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 1996
    </a>
    ), sorting nexin protein 9 (SH3PX1) (
    <a>
     Lin 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Worby 2002
    </a>
    ) and Hck (
    <a>
     Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    In this chapter, we describe procedures for the expression and purification of active ACK1. We have used purified ACK1 to study how enzyme activity is regulated. We have also developed a convenient synthetic peptide substrate to be used in ACK1 activity assays.
   </p>
   <title>
    Peptide Synthesis and Characterization
   </title>
   <p>
    The following synthetic peptides were used in this study: Abl substrate (EAIYAAPFAKKKG), Src substrate (AEEEIYGEFEAKKKKG), EGFR substrate (AEEEEYFELVAKKKG), IR substrate (KKEEEEYMMMMG), IRS‐1 Y987 peptide (KKSRGDY‐Nle‐TMQIG), SH3‐binding substrate (KKAEEEIYGEFGGGGGGRPLPSPPKFG), WASP peptide (KVIYDFIEKKKG), and a proline‐rich SH3 binding peptide (DFPLGPPPPLPPRATPSR). The synthetic peptides were purified by preparative reversed‐phase high‐performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) and characterized by matrix‐assisted laser description/ionization time of flight mass spectrometry.
   </p>
   <title>
    Baculovirus Expression Vector for the Kinase‐SH3‐CRIB Construct of ACK1
   </title>
   <p>
    We expressed and purified active ACK1 using the baculovirus/Sf9 cell system. This ACK1 construct contains (from N‐ to C‐terminus) the kinase catalytic domain, SH3 domain, and Cdc42‐binding CRIB domain (residues 110–476). The ACK1 construct possesses CBD‐ and His‐tags at the C‐terminus.
   </p>
   <p>
    In our initial attempts to produce active ACK1, we expressed a number of other ACK1 constructs in Sf9 cells. These included full‐length ACK1, kinase domain alone (residues 110–383), N‐terminus plus kinase domain (residues 1–383), and N‐terminus plus kinase, SH3, and CRIB domains (residues 1–476). These constructs were expressed with a variety of different affinity tags at the N‐ and C‐termini. Although the various constructs were expressed to reasonable levels and were active in Sf9 cells, we found that only the kinase–SH3‐CRIB construct was stable and active throughout the multiple chromatographic steps necessary for purification.
   </p>
   <p>
    The kinase–SH3‐CRIB construct was generated by the polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The 5′ PCR primer had the sequence GGGATCCGGGGGAGGGGCCCCTGCA G, and the 3′ primer was GGAATTCAAGTCCCGCAGGGCCACAAAC. These primers had 27 nucleotides (5′‐primer) and 28 nucleotides (3′‐primer) of complementarily with the template and encoded unique restriction sites (
    <em>
     Bam
    </em>
    HI at the 5′‐end and
    <em>
     Eco
    </em>
    R1 at the 3′‐end). The PCR product was ligated into plasmid pCR‐BluntII‐TOPO (Invitrogen). The resulting plasmid was digested with
    <em>
     Bam
    </em>
    H1/
    <em>
     Eco
    </em>
    R1, and the ACK1 insert was purified on an agarose gel. The ACK1 fragment was subcloned into plasmid pBACgus‐9 (N‐terminal T7 tag and C‐terminal CBD‐tag and poly‐Histidine‐tag, Novagen), and expressed in Sf9 cells using the BacVector‐3000 DNA transfection kit (Novagen). The virus was amplified twice to generate high‐titer virus, and the final titer was determined by plaque assay. Sf9 cells were grown in a 1‐l spinner flask in Ex‐cell‐401 media with
    <span>
     l
    </span>
    ‐glutamine (JRH Biosciences) and 2.5% fetal calf serum. For protein production, 0.6 l of Sf9 cells (1.8 × 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    cells/ ml) were infected with recombinant ACK1 baculovirus at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 7.5. After 4 days of infection, cells were harvested and washed with phosphate‐buffered saline two times.
   </p>
   <title>
    Purification of ACK1 Kinase–SH3‐CRIB Construct
   </title>
   <p>
    We purified the kinase–SH3‐CRIB construct to homogeneity by chromatography on Source‐Q, Ni‐NTA, and Mono‐Q columns. All chromatography steps were carried out at 4°. Gel filtration was also effective as the third step in the purification and could be used in place of Mono‐Q anion exchange. For experiments not requiring homogeneous protein, ACK1 can be used after the Ni‐NTA step, at which point it is substantially pure.
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Step 1. Preparation of cell lysates.
    </em>
    Sf9 Cells were lysed in a French pressure cell two times in 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl buffer (pH 8.0) containing 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    2‐mercaptoethanol, 10 μg/ml leupeptin, 10 μg/ml aprotinin, and 1 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF). Homogenates were centrifuged at 40,000
    <em>
     g
    </em>
    for 30 min. The supernatant was filtered (0.8 μm).
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Step 2. Source Q FPLC column chromatography.
    </em>
    A 1.6 × 10 cm Source‐Q FPLC column (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ) was pre‐equilibrated with loading buffer (same as lysis buffer, but without leupeptin, aprotinin, and PMSF). The ACK1 filtrate was applied to the column at 2 ml/min. After washing extensively with loading buffer, ACK1 kinase was eluted with a linear gradient of NaCl (0–0.6
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    ). Fractions of 1.3 ml were collected and 10‐μl aliquots were assayed for ACK1 kinase activity using the phosphocellulose paper–binding assay (
    <a>
     Casnellie, 1991
    </a>
    ). The peptide EAIYAAPFAKKKG was used as a substrate in the assays at a concentration of 0.5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    . ACK1 activity eluted at 0.2–0.4
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl. The peaks that showed high ACK1 activity were pooled, and 0.3
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl was added.
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Step. 3. Ni
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     ‐affinity column chromatography.
    </em>
    Pooled fractions were applied to a 3 ml Ni‐NTA column (QIAGEN), which was pre‐equilibrated with 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH 8.0), 0.5
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl, 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 10% glycerol, 5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    2‐mercaptoethanol. The column was washed with 125 ml of buffer containing 15 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    imidazole, 0.3
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl, 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 10% glycerol, 5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    2‐mercaptoethanol, 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH. 8.0), and further washed with 25 ml of buffer containing 1
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl, 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    2‐mercaptoethanol, 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH. 8.0). ACK1 was eluted with buffer containing 150 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    imidazole, 0.15
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl, 5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    2‐mercaptoethanol, 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 10% glycerol, and 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH. 8.0). Fractions were tested for ACK1 activity using the phosphocellulose paper–binding assay described previously.
   </p>
   <p>
    <em>
     Step. 4. Mono Q FPLC chromatography.
    </em>
    Peaks of activity were pooled, concentrated in an Amicon Ultra 30,000 molecular weight cutoff device (Millipore), and applied to a Mono Q HR 5/5 FPLC column (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ) at a rate of 1 ml/min. The column was washed with 5–10 column volumes of buffer containing 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris (pH 8.0) and 0.05
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl, and proteins were eluted with a linear gradient of 0.05–0.6
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl in the same buffer. ACK1 eluted at 0.2–0.25
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    NaCl. The protein was identified by SDS‐PAGE, Western blotting, and by activity assay. The purified ACK1 was stored in buffer containing 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    DTT, 10% glycerol, 2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , and 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH 8.0) at –20°. The CBD‐ and His‐tags at the C‐terminus of ACK1 could be removed by thrombin treatment. ACK1 (300 μg) was treated with 0.4 units of thrombin at 4° overnight. After digestion, the tags were separated from ACK1 by gel filtration or Mono‐Q chromatography.
   </p>
   <p>
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    shows an SDS‐PAGE analysis of the purification steps. Purified ACK1 migrates with the expected molecular weight (≈60.4 kDa). ACK1 reacted with a rabbit polyclonal antibody raised against a peptide sequence in the ACK1 catalytic domain (KPDVLSQPEAMDDFI). ACK1 also reacted with anti‐phosphotyrosine antibody, suggesting that purified ACK1 is autophosphorylated or phosphorylated by an endogenous Sf9 cell kinase (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Purification of ACK1 kinase&amp;#8208;SH3&amp;#8208;CRIB construct. (Left) Proteins from each step ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Purification of ACK1 kinase‐SH3‐CRIB construct. (Left) Proteins from each step of the purification were separated by SDS‐PAGE and visualized with Coomassie brilliant blue. Lane 1, crude Sf9 cell lysate. Lane 2, Pooled fractions after Source‐Q chromatography. Lane 3, Pooled fractions after Ni‐NTA chromatography. Lane 4, Pooled fractions after Mono‐Q chromatography. (Right) Purified ACK1 was analyzed by Western blotting using anti‐phosphotyrosine and anti‐ACK antibodies. (From
         <a>
          Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
         </a>
         ).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Substrate Specificity of ACK1 Kinase Using Synthetic Peptide Substrates
   </title>
   <p>
    Because relatively few protein substrates have been identified for ACK1, we used synthetic peptides as an initial screen of substrate specificity. We used substrates that were derived from peptide library screens of four prototypical tyrosine kinases: Src, Abl, EGF receptor, and insulin receptor (
    <a>
     Songyang, 1995
    </a>
    ). We included a substrate that is derived from the sequence of IRS‐1 that has been shown to be an excellent substrate for insulin receptor kinase (
    <a>
     Shoelson
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 1992
    </a>
    ), as well as for Jak2 (
    <a>
     Yokoyama
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 2003
    </a>
    ). Finally, we included a substrate that possesses an SH3 domain–binding polyproline sequence. For Src‐family kinases, addition of an SH3 domain ligand to a substrate increases its phosphorylation by activating down‐regulated kinase and by decreasing substrate K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Scott and Miller, 2000
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    ACK1 kinase activity was determined using the p81 phosphocellulose paper assay (
    <a>
     Casnellie, 1991
    </a>
    ). Reaction mixtures (20 μl) contained 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH 7.4), 10 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , 0.1 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , 0.5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    DTT, 0.25 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    ATP, 5 mg/ml BSA, varying concentrations of peptide substrate, and [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP (200–400 cpm/pmol). Reactions were initiated by addition of [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP. Reactions were terminated by addition of 50% acetic acid, and samples were spotted on P81 phosphocellulose paper (Whatman). Incorporation of
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P into peptide was determined by Cerenkov counting. The values of K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    for peptide were determined using a range of peptide concentrations (0.05–2.0 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    ) and 0.25 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP. Kinetic parameters were calculated by fitting data to the Michaelis–Menten equation. Initial studies on several peptides (Src, EGFR, IRS‐1, SH3, and IR peptides) established that their Michaelis constants were in the millimolar range (≫2 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    ). Thus, it was not possible to determine accurate Michaelis constants by using initial rate kinetics. The complete time course for the phosphorylation of each these peptides was measured by using peptide concentrations less than the Michaelis constant. For these peptides, we analyzed the data graphically as described (
    <a>
     Thomas
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 1987
    </a>
    ) to determine k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    /K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    <a>
     Table I
    </a>
    shows a summary of the ACK1 kinetic parameters using different peptide substrates. Most of the peptides from this original group were poor substrates for ACK1, with the exception of the Abl peptide. We carried out kinetic measurements with saturating concentrations of ATP and varying concentrations of Abl peptide. These experiments yielded a Km for the Abl peptide of 507 μ
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    and a k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    of 0.249 min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    (k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    /K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    = 4.8 × 10
    <sup>
     −4
    </sup>
    min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    μ
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    ) (
    <a>
     Table I
    </a>
    ). By comparison, the Src‐specific peptide was phosphorylated with a k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    /K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    of 2.2 × 10
    <sup>
     −5
    </sup>
    min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    μ
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    , approximately 20 times lower than the Abl substrate (
    <a>
     Table I
    </a>
    ). Phosphorylation of the EGFR‐ and insulin receptor–specific peptides was barely detectable above background. The SH3‐binding substrate was not phosphorylated appreciably by ACK1. SH3‐binding peptides containing either a longer spacer length between the substrate sequence and the SH3 ligand, or with these sequences reversed, were also poorly phosphorylated (data not shown). This is in contrast to results from Src‐family kinases and suggests that the SH3 domain of ACK1 may not play a direct role in substrate targeting. The substrate specificity of ACK1 seems to be narrower than other tyrosine kinases. These results are consistent with a recent report in which only four of 160 diverse peptides containing known tyrosine kinase phosphorylation sites showed a low level of phosphorylation (
    <a>
     Lougheed
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table I.
        </span>
        <p>
         Kinetic Parameters for ACK1
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Peptide
          </th>
          <th>
           Sequence
          </th>
          <th>
           k
           <sub>
            cat
           </sub>
           /K
           <sub>
            m
           </sub>
           (min
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           μ
           <em>
            M
           </em>
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           k
           <sub>
            cat
           </sub>
           (min
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
           )
          </th>
          <th>
           K
           <sub>
            m
           </sub>
           (μ
           <em>
            M
           </em>
           )
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Abl substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           EAIYAAPFAKKKG
          </td>
          <td>
           4.8 × 10
           <sup>
            −4
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           0.24
          </td>
          <td>
           507
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Src substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           AEEEIYGEFEAKKKKG
          </td>
          <td>
           2.2 × 10
           <sup>
            −5
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           EGFR substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           AEEEEYFELVAKKKG
          </td>
          <td>
           &lt; 3 × 10
           <sup>
            −6
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           IR substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           KKEEEEYMMMMG
          </td>
          <td>
           &lt; 3 × 10
           <sup>
            −6
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           sequence from IRS‐1 Y987
          </td>
          <td>
           KKSRGDY‐Nle‐TMQIG
          </td>
          <td>
           1.2 × 10
           <sup>
            −5
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           SH3‐binding substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           KKAEEEIYGEFGGGGGGRPLPSPPKFG
          </td>
          <td>
           5.8 × 10
           <sup>
            −6
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
          <td>
           <a>
            *
           </a>
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           WASP substrate
          </td>
          <td>
           KVIYDFIEKKKKG
          </td>
          <td>
           1.36 ×10
           <sup>
            −1
           </sup>
          </td>
          <td>
           107.6
          </td>
          <td>
           789
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        Kinetic parameters were determined by the phosphocellulose binding assay, as described in experimental procedures.
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <dl>
        <dt>
         *
        </dt>
        <dd>
         <p>
          It was not possible to determine accurate Michaelis constants for these peptides using initial rate kinetics. We analyzed the data graphically (
          <a>
           Thomas
           <em>
            et al.
           </em>
           , 1987
          </a>
          ) to determine k
          <sub>
           cat
          </sub>
          /K
          <sub>
           m
          </sub>
          , using ATP and peptide concentrations of 1 m
          <em>
           M
          </em>
          and 0.5 m
          <em>
           M
          </em>
          , respectively.
         </p>
        </dd>
       </dl>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We recently identified WASP as a protein substrate for ACK1 (N. Y. and W. T. M., unpublished observations). We mapped the site of phosphorylation as Tyr291 of WASP, in the sequence VIYDFIE. To determine whether this sequence would be phosphorylated in the context of a synthetic peptide, we prepared a peptide with the sequence KVIYDFIEKKKG. As shown in
    <a>
     Table I
    </a>
    , this peptide is by far the best substrate yet reported for ACK1. This WASP peptide had a k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    /K
    <sub>
     m
    </sub>
    of 0.136 min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    μ
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    , approximately 450 times higher the Abl peptide. The kcat value of 107.6 min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    is comparable to turnover numbers for other tyrosine kinases in their maximum‐activity states (e.g., Hck with k
    <sub>
     cat
    </sub>
    = 60 min
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    ;
    <a>
     LaFevre‐Bernt
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 1998
    </a>
    ). Thus, the WASP peptide is a convenient substrate for
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    assays of ACK1 kinase activity, and it should be useful in future studies of ACK1 function.
   </p>
   <p>
    We have carried out initial experiments aimed at understanding how ACK1 activity is regulated. Addition of activated Cdc42 to purified ACK1
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    did not stimulate ACK1 activity, although the CRIB domain of this construct is able to bind Cdc42 (
    <a>
     Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
    </a>
    ). In contrast, both ACK1 and ACK2 have been shown to be activated by Cdc42 in intact mammalian cells (
    <a>
     Yang 1999
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yokoyama 2003
    </a>
    ). We were also unable to activate ACK1
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    by addition of a polyproline‐containing peptide (DFPLGPPPPLPPRATPSR). Thus, it is not clear whether the SH3 domains of ACK kinases play a role in regulating enzyme activity. For Src‐ and Abl‐family nonreceptor tyrosine kinases, the SH3 domains are involved in autoinhibition; they bind to polyproline type II helices in the linker region between the SH2 domain and the catalytic domain. Protein or peptide ligands for the SH3 domains of Src‐ or Abl‐family kinases disrupt these intramolecular interactions and increase enzymatic activity (
    <a>
     Alexandropoulos 1996
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Briggs 1997
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Moarefi 1997
    </a>
    ). The SH3 domains of ACK kinases, which are on the C‐terminal side of the catalytic domain, may not play an analogous role.
   </p>
   <title>
    Autophosphorylation of ACK1
   </title>
   <p>
    We carried out experiments to measure the ability of purified ACK1 to undergo autophosphorylation. Purified ACK1 was incubated with 0.25 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP (400–700 cpm/pmol) in kinase buffer containing 20 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Tris‐HCl (pH 7.5), 10 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , 0.5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    DTT and 0.1 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    VO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    at 30°. Reactions were stopped by the addition of SDS‐sample buffer and analyzed by SDS‐PAGE and autoradiography. ACK1 was autophosphorylated in a time‐dependent manner (
    <a>
     Fig. 2A
    </a>
    ). Preincubation of ACK1 with 0.25 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    unlabeled ATP in kinase buffer for 40 min, followed by incubation with [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP for 40 min at 30°, led to a decrease in the level of
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P incorporation (
    <a>
     Fig 2A
    </a>
    ). To measure changes in ACK1 activity after autophosphorylation, ACK1 was incubated with 0.5 m
    <em>
     M
    </em>
    unlabeled ATP in kinase reaction buffer for 40 min at 30°. Activity was then measured using the phosphocellulose paper assay. Autophosphorylation activated ACK1 kinase threefold compared with unphosphorylated ACK1 (
    <a>
     Fig. 2B
    </a>
    ). This increase in ACK1 activity is low compared with other kinases that are autoinhibited by their unphosphorylated activation loop (
    <a>
     Nolen
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 2004
    </a>
    ). Interestingly, the recently reported structure of ACK1 shows that the activation loop of unphosphorylated ACK1 has a partially “active” conformation that is generally observed only in phosphorylated protein kinases (
    <a>
     Lougheed
     <em>
      et al.
     </em>
     , 2004
    </a>
    ). Thus, it is not surprising that autophosphorylation triggers only a modest increase in ACK1 activity.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ACK1 autophosphorylation. (A) Top, the ACK1 kinase&amp;#8208;SH3&amp;#8208;CRIB construct was ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0076687906060186-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         ACK1 autophosphorylation. (A) Top, the ACK1 kinase‐SH3‐CRIB construct was incubated with 0.25 m
         <em>
          M
         </em>
         [γ‐
         <sup>
          32
         </sup>
         P]‐ATP in kinase assay buffer for 0, 20, 40, or 60 min. Reactions were terminated by addition of SDS‐sample buffer and analyzed by SDS‐PAGE and autoradiography. Bottom, ACK1 was preincubated with 0.25 m
         <em>
          M
         </em>
         ATP for 40 min, followed by an incubation with [γ‐
         <sup>
          32
         </sup>
         P]‐ATP for 40 min as described above. Reactions were followed by SDS‐PAGE and autoradiography. (B) The ACK1 kinase‐SH3‐CRIB construct was preincubated in the presence or absence of 0.5 m
         <em>
          M
         </em>
         ATP (“autophos.” and “unphos.”, respectively) in kinase reaction buffer for 1 h at 37°. ACK1 activity was then determined using the phosphocellulose binding assay. Kinase assays contained 0.1 m
         <em>
          M
         </em>
         [γ‐
         <sup>
          32
         </sup>
         P]‐ATP and 0.25 m
         <em>
          M
         </em>
         Abl peptide, and proceeded for 30 min. (From
         <a>
          Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
         </a>
         ).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We have identified Tyr 284 as the major autophosphorylation site of ACK1 by mass spectrometry (
    <a>
     Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
    </a>
    ). After autophosphorylation and trypsin digestion, one tryptic fragment of ACK1 was shifted by the mass of a phosphate (+80 daltons) relative to the unphosphorylated sample. This tryptic fragment had the sequence
    <sup>
     276
    </sup>
    ALPQNDDHYVMQEHR
    <sup>
     290
    </sup>
    and contains a single tyrosine residue, Tyr284. We confirmed the identity of this autophosphorylated peptide by sequence analysis by LC/MS/MS. On the basis of a sequence alignment of the ACK kinase catalytic domain with the Src catalytic domain, Tyr284 of ACK1 is predicted to be in the kinase activation loop. The sequence surrounding Tyr284 of ACK1 is similar to the sequence surrounding Tyr416 of Src, the major autophosphorylation site. Expression of a full‐length Y284F mutant form of ACK1 in COS‐7 cells showed a dramatically reduced level of tyrosine phosphorylation relative to wild‐type ACK1 (
    <a>
     Yokoyama and Miller, 2003
    </a>
    ). We purified a Y284F mutant version of ACK1 using the Sf9/baculovirus system. The Y284F mutant is capable of additional autophosphorylation after incubation with [γ‐
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]‐ATP, suggesting that there are additional, unidentified autophosphorylation sites on ACK1.
   </p>
   <title>
    Concluding Remarks
   </title>
   <p>
    We report here the first purification of active ACK1 from eucaryotic cells, using the Sf9/baculovirus expression system. Of four peptides tested that are specific for different families of tyrosine kinases, we show that the specific activity of ACK1 most closely resembles that of Abl. However, the peptide derived from the phosphorylation site of WASP is a superior peptide substrate, and it is the most potent
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    substrate yet identified for this enzyme. We also identified Tyr284 as the major autophosphorylation site of ACK1; autophosphorylation enhances ACK1 activity. Neither an SH3 ligand nor Cdc42 activates ACK kinase
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    , although both ligands bind ACK1. At present, the roles of the SH3 domain and polyproline region of ACK1 in enzyme regulation have not been explained. A full understanding of the intramolecular interactions of ACK1 will require additional structure–function studies on full‐length ACK1.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Alexandropoulos 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Alexandropoulos, D. Baltimore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Coordinate activation of c‐Src by SH3‐ and SH2‐binding sites on a novel p130Cas‐related protein, Sin
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 10 (1996), pp. 1341–1355
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Briggs 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.D. Briggs, M. Sharkey, M. Stevenson, T.E. Smithgall
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3‐mediated Hck tyrosine kinase activation and fibroblast transformation by the Nef protein of HIV‐1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 17899–17902
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Casnellie 1991
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.E. Casnellie
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Assay of protein kinases using peptides with basic residues for phosphocellulose binding
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Methods Enzymol., 200 (1991), pp. 115–120
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         LaFevre‐Bernt 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. LaFevre‐Bernt, F. Sicheri, A. Pico, M. Porter, J. Kuriyan, W.T. Miller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Intramolecular regulatory interactions in the Src family kinase Hck probed by mutagenesis of a conserved tryptophan residue
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 32129–32134
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lin 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Q. Lin, C.G. Lo, R.A. Cerione, W. Yang
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Cdc42 target ACK2 interacts with sorting nexin 9 (SH3PX1) to regulate epidermal growth factor receptor degradation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 10134–10138
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lougheed 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.C. Lougheed, R.H. Chen, P. Mak, T.J. Stout
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Crystal structures of the phosphorylated and unphosphorylated kinase domains of the Cdc42‐associated tyrosine kinase ACK1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 44039–44045
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Manser 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Manser, T. Leung, H. Salihuddin, L. Tan, L. Lim
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A non‐receptor tyrosine kinase that inhibits the GTPase activity of p21cdc42
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 363 (1993), pp. 364–367
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Moarefi 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I. Moarefi, M. LaFevre‐Bernt, F. Sicheri, M. Huse, C.H. Lee, J. Kuriyan, W.T. Miller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Activation of the Src‐family tyrosine kinase Hck by SH3 domain displacement
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 385 (1997), pp. 650–653
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nolen 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Nolen, S. Taylor, G. Ghosh
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulation of protein kinases; controlling activity through activation segment conformation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 15 (2004), pp. 661–675
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Satoh 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Satoh, J. Kato, K. Nishida, Y. Kaziro
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tyrosine phosphorylation of ACK in response to temperature shift‐down, hyperosmotic shock, and epidermal growth factor stimulation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 386 (1996), pp. 230–234
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Scott 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.P. Scott, W.T. Miller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A peptide model system for processive phosphorylation by Src family kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 39 (2000), pp. 14531–14537
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shoelson 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.E. Shoelson, S. Chatterjee, M. Chaudhuri, M.F. White
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         YMXM motifs of IRS‐1 define substrate specificity of the insulin receptor kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 89 (1992), pp. 2027–2031
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Songyang 1995
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Z. Songyang, K.L. Carraway III, M.J. Eck, S.C. Harrison, R.A. Feldman, M. Mohammadi, J. Schlessinger, S.R. Hubbard, D.P. Smith, C. Eng, M.J. Lorenzo, B.A.J. Poner, B.J. Mayer, L.C. Cantley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Catalytic specificity of protein‐tyrosine kinases is critical for selective signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 373 (1995), pp. 536–539
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Teo 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Teo, L. Tan, L. Lim, E. Manser
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The tyrosine kinase ACK1 associates with clathrin‐coated vesicles through a binding motif shared by arrestin and other adaptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 18392–18398
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Thomas 1987
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.E. Thomas, H.N. Bramson, W.T. Miller, E.T. Kaiser
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role of enzyme‐peptide substrate backbone hydrogen bonding in determining protein kinase substrate specificities
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 26 (1987), pp. 4461–4466
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Worby 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C.A. Worby, N. Simonson‐Leff, J.C. Clemens, D. Huddler Jr., M. Muda, J.E. Dixon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         <em>
          Drosophila
         </em>
         Ack targets its substrate, the sorting nexin DSH3PX1, to a protein complex involved in axonal guidance
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 9422–9428
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yang 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Yang, R.A. Cerione
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cloning and characterization of a novel Cdc42‐associated tyrosine kinase, ACK‐2, from bovine brain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 24819–24824
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yang 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Yang, Q. Lin, J.L. Guan, R.A. Cerione
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Activation of the Cdc42‐associated tyrosine kinase‐2 (ACK‐2) by cell adhesion via integrin beta1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 8524–8530
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yokoyama 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Yokoyama, W.T. Miller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemical properties of the Cdc42‐associated tyrosine kinase ACK1. Substrate specificity, autophosphorylation, and interaction with Hck
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 47713–47723
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yokoyama 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Yokoyama, N.C. Reich, W.T. Miller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Determinants for the interaction between Janus kinase 2 and protein phosphatase 2A
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Arch. Biochem. Biophys., 417 (2003), pp. 87–95
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2006 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>