<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    PMC4381837
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Direct Binding of the PDZ Domain of Dishevelled to a Conserved Internal Sequence in the C-Terminal Region of Frizzled
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Summary
   </title>
   <sec>
    <p>
     The cytoplasmic protein Dishevelled (Dvl) and the associated membrane-bound receptor Frizzled (Fz) are essential in canonical and noncanonical Wnt signaling pathways. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying this signaling are not well understood. By using NMR spectroscopy, we determined that an internal sequence of Fz binds to the conventional peptide binding site in the PDZ domain of Dvl; this type of site typically binds to C-terminal binding motifs. The C-terminal region of the Dvl inhibitor Dapper (Dpr) and Frodo bound to the same site. In
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     , Dvl binding peptides of Fz and Dpr/Frodo inhibited canonical Wnt signaling and blocked Wnt-induced secondary axis formation in a dose-dependent manner, but did not block noncanonical Wnt signaling mediated by the DEP domain. Together, our results identify a missing molecular connection within the Wnt pathway. Differences in the binding affinity of the Dvl PDZ domain and its binding partners may be important in regulating signal transduction by Dvl.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Wnt signaling pathways are essential for development (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Cadigan and Nusse, 1997
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Moon et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ) and have been implicated in tumorigenesis (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Taipale and Beachy, 2001
    </xref>
    ). Of the distinct Wnt pathways, the canonical Wnt signaling pathway, which involves the inhibition of GSK3β activity and stabilization of β-catenin in the cytoplasm, is essential for the specification of cell fate in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     Xenopus
    </em>
    . The noncanonical Wnt pathway, which involves the Rho family of GTPases and JNK, affects planar polarity in the same species (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Moon and Shah, 2002
    </xref>
    ). The Wnt/Calcium pathway stimulates intracellular calcium release in a G protein-dependent manner (Kühl et al., 2000). In all these pathways, the 7 transmembrane domain Fz proteins are bound by the secreted molecule Wnt and transduce the signal to the cytoplasmic protein Dvl (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Siegfried et al., 1994
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Noordermeer et al., 1994
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Krasnow et al., 1995
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Shulman et al., 1998
    </xref>
    ), the component at which these signaling pathways diverge (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Axelrod et al., 1998
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Boutros et al., 1998
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Li et al., 1999
    </xref>
    ). Dvl also functions in a feedback loop of Fz (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Tree et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ). However, a direct interaction between Fz and Dvl has not been shown, and the mechanism by which Dvl distinguishes between different Wnt pathways has not been defined (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Wharton, 2003
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Dvl proteins are composed of an N-terminal DIX domain, a central PDZ domain, and a C-terminal DEP domain (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Wong et al., 2000
    </xref>
    ). Of these three, the PDZ domain appears to play an important role in both the canonical and noncanonical Wnt pathways (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Moon and Shah, 2002
    </xref>
    ). In addition, several molecules can interact with the PDZ domain (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Yan et al., 2001
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Rousset et al., 2001
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Gloy et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Park and Moon, 2002
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Cheyette et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ). Indeed, it has been suggested that the PDZ domain of Dvl is involved in distinguishing between the two pathways (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Boutros and Mlodzik, 1999
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Weston and Davis, 2001
    </xref>
    ). To test such an hypothesis, we investigated the interactions between the PDZ domain (residues 247-341) of mouse Dvl1 (mDvl1) and its binding partners by using nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy. We discovered that the same peptide-interacting site of the mDvl1 PDZ domain interacts with different molecules whose sequences have no obvious homology. One peptide that binds to the mDvl1 PDZ domain is the conserved motif (KTXXXW) of Fz, which is located two amino acids after the seventh transmembrane domain (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Umbhauer et al., 2000
    </xref>
    ), although it is not a typical PDZ binding motif (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Hung and Sheng, 2002
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Cowburn, 1997
    </xref>
    ). This finding revealed a previously unknown connection between the membrane-bound receptor and downstream components of the Wnt signaling pathways. On the basis of these studies, we have conducted further analyses of the function(s) of Dvl to distinguish different signals in a complex cellular network of signal transduction.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results and Discussion
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Solution Structure of the PDZ Domain of mDvl1
    </title>
    <p>
     To examine the interactions between the PDZ domain of mDvl and its binding partners, we first determined the solution structure of the PDZ domain. The structure was elucidated on the basis of 1124 NMR-derived constraints. Twenty structures that best fit the experimental constraints in the structural calculation were analyzed. The structure resembles that of the typical PDZ-domain fold. Unlike class I PDZ domains (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Bezprozvanny and Maximov, 2001
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Hung and Sheng, 2002
     </xref>
     ), the mDvl1 PDZ domain lacks the conserved His at a G-H (glycine and histidine) position in the peptide binding pocket (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1
     </xref>
     ). Moreover, the mDvl1 PDZ domain differs from class II PDZ domains in that it has no hydrophobic residues at its G-H positions (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Daniels et al., 1998
     </xref>
     ) (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 1
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 1
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Structure-Based Alignment of the Amino Acid Sequences of the PDZ Domains of Dvl Homologs and Other Proteins
      </strong>
      <p>
       Secondary structural elements are indicated above the sequences. Residues at the GH positions are in boldface type. The asterisk denotes the binding pocket for the ligand's C terminus. Sequence differences among the PDZ domains are indicated by underlining.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     High Specificity of the Molecular Recognition of the Dvl PDZ Domain
    </title>
    <p>
     We next analyzed the interactions between the PDZ domain and several binding partners by conducting chemical-shift perturbation NMR spectroscopy as described by
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Wuthrich (2000)
     </xref>
     . The method can be used to precisely map binding sites and is well suited to detect weak but specific biologically relevant interactions (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Zheng et al., 1996
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Wong et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ). We first analyzed the interaction between the C-terminal residues of Dpr or Frodo (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheyette et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Gloy et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ) and residues 247 through 341 of the mDvl1 PDZ domain; similar analyses of the
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     homolog have been done by using X-ray crystallography (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheyette et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ). We used a peptide comprising the C-terminal 10 residues of Dpr/Frodo (SGSLKLMTTV, designated Dpr/Frodo peptide) to titrate the
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled PDZ domain of mDvl1 and found that the Dpr/Frodo peptide bound to the peptide binding groove, a result similar that observed in
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     homolog studies (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheyette et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ). We then examined the interaction between Van Gogh (an inhibitor of canonical Wnt signaling) and the PDZdomainofmDvl1. Despite a high degree of similarity to the C-terminal region of Dpr/Frodo, the peptide corresponding to the 11 C-terminal residues of Van Gogh (FVMRLQSETSV), when added to the solution of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled PDZ domain, caused no chemical-shift perturbation. This result is consistent with the observation that the interaction between Van Gogh and Dvl requires both the Dvl PDZ domain and the basic region that is N-terminal to the PDZ domain and was not present in our construct (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Park and Moon, 2002
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Direct Interaction between the Conserved Motif KTXXXW of Fz and the PDZ Domain of Dvl
    </title>
    <p>
     We investigated the possible interaction between Fz and Dvl. Previous studies have demonstrated that the C-terminal region of Fz transduces the canonical Wnt signal (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). Moreover, a conserved motif (KTXXXW) located two amino acids C-terminal to the seventh transmembrane domain is required for activation of the canonical Wnt pathway and for membrane relocalization and phosphorylation of Dvl (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). When a synthetic peptide that consisted of Fz7 residues 525 through 536 (G
     <strong>
      KT
     </strong>
     LQS
     <strong>
      W
     </strong>
     RRFYH, designated the Fz7 peptide) was added to the solution of the
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled PDZ domain, we observed a chemical-shift perturbation similar to that seen when the Dpr/Frodo peptide was added to the same type of solution.
    </p>
    <p>
     Examination of a series of
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
     H-
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N correlation spectra for the
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-labeled mDvl1 PDZ domain (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 2A
     </xref>
     ) revealed that the Fz7 peptide, although an internal sequence, bound to the conventional C-terminal peptide-binding groove (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cowburn, 1997
     </xref>
     ) located between αB and βB (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 2B and 2C
     </xref>
     ). Binding was essentially abolished when three conserved amino acids in the Fz7 peptide were mutated (replacements in boldface type: G
     <strong>
      MV
     </strong>
     LQS
     <strong>
      G
     </strong>
     RRFYH, designated mutFz7). Furthermore, two single-mutation peptides, G
     <strong>
      M
     </strong>
     TLQSWRRFYH, designated Fz7K/M, and GKTLQS
     <strong>
      G
     </strong>
     RRFYH, designated Fz7W/G, bound to the PDZ domain with an affinity that was much weaker than that of the Fz7 peptide. These results demonstrated that the three residues in Fz are essential to binding to Dvl and that the C terminus of the Fz7 peptide does not bind to the PDZ domain. Although internal peptides rarely bind to PDZ domains, an internal sequence within a context of β-hairpin conformation has been shown to compete with a conventional C-terminal motif that binds to PDZ domains (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Hillier et al., 1999
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Tochio et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). Nevertheless, the Fz-Dvl interaction that we identified is an example of an internal sequence of an otherwise unstructured receptor cytoplasmic tail that can interact with a PDZ domain. Moreover, it is unusual that both the internal sequence and C-terminal peptides can bind to the same binding site on the PDZ domain.
    </p>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 2
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Interaction between the mDvl1 PDZ Domain and Fz7
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A)
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N-HSQC spectra of free Fz7 peptide and Fz7 peptide bound to the PDZ domain of mDvl1. The red contour lines represent spectra of the free form of the PDZ domain when no Fz7 peptide (GKTLQSWRRFYH) was present, the green lines (upper inset) represent spectra of partially bound forms of the PDZ domain when 0.86 mM Fz7 peptide was present, and the blue lines represent spectra of the fully bound forms of the PDZ domain when 10 mM Fz7 peptide was present. The concentration of the PDZ domain was 1.1 mM. The two insets show the enlarged regions where the chemical-shift perturbations were small (lower inset) and large (upper inset). In the upper inset, the signals from the same residue but in different spectra were placed in smaller boxes.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) The figure shows the worm representation of the backbone structure of the mDvl1 PDZ domain. The thickness of the worm is proportional to the weighted sum (in Hz) of the
       <sup>
        1
       </sup>
       H and
       <sup>
        15
       </sup>
       N shifts upon binding by the Fz7 peptide (see A), and the increasing chemical-shift perturbation is shown (blue, low; red, high).
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) Ribbon diagram of the PDZ domain structure. The binding site of the Fz7 peptide identified from the chemical-shift perturbation studies is indicated.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Binding of the Fz C Terminus to Dvl PDZ Domain In Vitro
    </title>
    <p>
     To further characterize the binding properties of the C terminus of Frizzled proteins, we performed a yeast two-hybrid screen with the C-terminal domain of
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Fz2 as bait. By screening a library of 10
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
     clones, we isolated 6 clones that encoded
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Dishevelled (Dsh). Using the same two-hybrid assay, we confirmed that the C terminus of Fz2 and of Fz can bind to Dsh. Such binding was not affected by the deletion of the last five amino acids of either Fz or Fz2 (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). This finding is consistent with our previous observation that the C termini of Frizzled proteins bind to Dvl/Dsh through an internal sequence motif.
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 1
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        <strong>
         Detection of the Fz-Dvl Interaction in a Yeast Two-Hybrid System
        </strong>
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
    <p>
     To further demonstrate that the Fz7 peptide interacts with the mDvl1 PDZ domain, we conducted biotin pulldown assays. The N termini of both the Fz7 peptide and the Dpr/Frodo peptide were biotinylated, and after biotinylation the peptides were coupled to agarose beads immobilized with avidin. The Fz7- and Dpr/Frodo-coupled beads bound to the purified PDZ domain (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     ), and their binding affinities were similar. Furthermore, we found that the PDZ domain bound to Fz7 peptide-coupled beads can be eluted by the Dpr/Frodo peptide. This result indicated that the Fz7 peptide and the Dpr/Frodo peptide compete for the same site on the surface of the PDZ domain. It is consistent with those of the NMR spectroscopy studies.
    </p>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 3
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo Peptides and Their Binding to the PDZ Domain In Vitro
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) Biotinylated Fz7 or Dpr/Frodo peptide was coupled to the UltraLink Immobilized Monomeric Avidin, and the avidin-coupled peptides were then incubated with purified PDZ domain. After extensive washing, peptide-interacting proteins were resolved and visualized by SDS-PAGE. Besides those bound to the PDZ domain, some proteins that became detached from the avidin-immobilized beads were also observed. Lane 1, marker. Lane 2, PDZ domain. Lane 3, The PDZ domain and the avidin-agarose beads. Lane 4, The PDZ domain and beads coupled to the Fz7 peptide. Lane 5, the PDZ domain and beads coupled to the Dpr/Frodo peptide. Lane 6: the PDZ domain bound to the Fz7 peptide-coupled beads after elution by the Dpr/Frodo peptide. The experimental condition was similar to that used for the mixture depicted in lane 4, except that before SDS-PAGE, the beads were washed with a buffer that contained Dpr/Frodo peptide.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) Fluorescence spectra (labeled with different colors) of the PDZ domain in the presence of various concentrations of Dpr/Frodo peptides. Intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence of the PDZ domain was quenched by bound peptide.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C) Reciprocal plot of fluorescence data were fitted to a competitive inhibition model in which the Fz7 peptide disrupts the interaction between the Dpr/Frodo peptide and the PDZ domain. Extracted from the fitting, the binding affinity of <span id="3870913" source="intactdb" intactdbid="14636582" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="Q8R4A3" type="participant">Dpr/Frodo peptide</span> and the <span id="3870913" source="intactdb" intactdbid="14636582" annotator="elias" UNIPROT="P51141" type="participant">PDZ domain</span> was <span id="3870913" source="intactdb" intactdbid="14636582" annotator="elias" type="value">16.1 ± 0.7</span><span id="3870913" source="intactdb" intactdbid="14636582" annotator="elias" type="unit">μM</span>, and the affinity of the Fz7 peptide and the PDZ domain, extracted from the two apparent K
       <sub>
        I
       </sub>
       values at two concentrations (5.9 μM and 12.8 μM, respectively), was 9.5 ± 7.9 μM.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
    <p>
     The binding affinities between the PDZ domain and the Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides were also measured by using fluorescence spectroscopy. The binding of the Dpr/Frodo peptide quenched the intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence of the PDZ domain. By monitoring such changes in fluorescence intensity, we determined that the binding affinity between the Dpr/Frodo peptide and the PDZ domain was 16.1 ± 0.7 μM. However, the tryptophan residue within the Fz7 peptide prevented us from using this method to directly determine the binding affinity between this peptide and the PDZ domain. Nevertheless, we determined that the Fz7 peptide inhibits the binding of the Dpr/Frodo peptide to the PDZ domain in the manner of classical competitive inhibition (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3C
     </xref>
     ). The estimated inhibition constant, K
     <sub>
      I
     </sub>
     , which was equivalent to the mean binding affinity between the Fz7 peptide and the PDZ domain, was 9.5 ± 7.9 μM (K
     <sub>
      I
     </sub>
     values obtained from two independent measurements were 5.9 ± 0.5 μM and 12.8 ± 3.9 μM,
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3C
     </xref>
     ). Furthermore, by using the mutated Fz7 peptide Fz7W/G (GKTLQS
     <strong>
      G
     </strong>
     RRFYH), which does not have an intrinsic tryptophan, we conducted fluorescence spectroscopy analysis of the binding affinity between this mutated peptide and the PDZ domain. The measured affinity was 100 times weaker than that of wild-type (K
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     = 1.3 ± 0.4 mM, the mean of two independent measurements).
    </p>
    <p>
     The well-defined but relatively weak (K
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ∼10 μM) interaction between the Fz7 peptide and the mDvl1 PDZ domain suggests that other regions of Dvl are required for signal transduction between membrane-bound Fz and Dvl. Although the DEP domain of Dvl does not bind to the Fz7 peptide (data not shown), previous studies have indicated that the DEP domain plays a role in the membrane localization of the protein (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Wong et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Axelrod et al., 1998
     </xref>
     , 2001;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Rothbacher et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ;
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Boutros et al., 1998
     </xref>
     ). Therefore, signal transduction between Fz and Dvl may require the membrane-targeting function of the DEP domain to bring the two proteins into close proximity to one another. Indeed, it may be a common feature that multiple interactions are involved in a specific Dvl reorganization event. Another such example is the interaction between Dpr/Frodo and Dvl. Although deletion of the C-terminal residues of Frodo abolished interaction with Dvl, the DIX domain and adjacent Dvl sequence are also important to the Frodo-Dvl association (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Gloy et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ). The C-terminal residues of Dpr/Frodo bind to the Dvl PDZ domain (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Cheyette et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ), and, as we showed in this report, the binding affinity is relatively low (K
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ∼16 μM). However, all of these weak but specific interactions orchestrate the association event, and the disruption of any one of these weak interactions may cause the breakdown of binding.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Inhibition of the Canonical Wnt Pathway by Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo Peptides
    </title>
    <p>
     To further examine the role of the PDZ domain of Dvl in the canonical and noncanonical Wnt signaling pathways, we tested the effects of the PDZ binding peptides on Wnt signaling. Because mutations in the conserved KTXXXW motif of Fz abolish Fz activity in the canonical Wnt signaling pathway (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ), we coinjected peptides that contained various mutations in the KTXXXW motif and different activators of the canonical Wnt pathway into the animal-pole region of
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     embryos at the 8 cell stage (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). We then performed RT-PCR to analyze expression of the Wnt target gene
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     in ectodermal explants that were dissected from blastulae and cultured until they reached the early gastrula stage. Although the mutFz7 peptide had little effect on
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     expression induced by Wnt1 and Dvl, the Fz7 peptide inhibited
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     expression induced by Wnt1 and Dvl (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4A
     </xref>
     ). In addition, the Fz7 peptide did not block
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     expression induced by dominant-negative GSK3β and by β-catenin, but it reduced
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     expression induced by Xfz3 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4B
     </xref>
     ); these results indicate that the Fz7 peptide disrupts canonical Wnt signaling at the level of Dishevelled. These results are consistent with the notion that the binding of the internal sequence of Fz to the PDZ domain of Dvl is important for signaling in the canonical Wnt pathway. Furthermore, a separate experiment revealed that Dvl translocates to the membrane of ectodermal cells of
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     embryos when they are given injections of full-length
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Fz mRNA and Dvl mRNA (data not shown). However, coinjections of the C-terminal region of Fz into the ectodermal cells did not cause Dvl to localize to the membrane. Because full-length Fz, but not its C-terminal portion, is membrane bound, these results further indicate the direct interaction between Fz and Dvl.
    </p>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
     <label>
      Figure 4
     </label>     <caption>
      <strong>
       Effects of PDZ Binding Peptides on Canonical Wnt Signaling in
       <em>
        Xenopus
       </em>
       Embryos
      </strong>
      <p>
       (A) The Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides inhibited the canonical Wnt pathway. RT-PCR was conducted to analyze the expression of the
       <em>
        Xenopus
       </em>
       Wnt target gene
       <em>
        Siamois
       </em>
       in ectodermal explants. Synthetic mRNA corresponding to
       <em>
        Wnt1
       </em>
       (1 pg) and
       <em>
        Dvl
       </em>
       (500 ng) were injected alone or were coinjected with PDZ binding peptides (100 ng; corresponding concentration after injection, approximately 200 μM). Injections were administered to the animal-pole region at the 8 cell stage, and ectodermal explants were cultured until they reached the early gastrula stage, at which time they underwent RT-PCR analysis.
      </p>
      <p>
       (B) The Fz7 peptide had no effect on
       <em>
        Siamois
       </em>
       expression induced by dominant-negative GSK3β (dnGSK3β) or by β-catenin, but it blocked
       <em>
        Siamois
       </em>
       expression induced by Xfz3. RT-, whole-embryo sample analyzed in the absence of reverse transcription.
       <em>
        ODC (ornithine decarboxylase)
       </em>
       was used as a loading control.
      </p>
      <p>
       (C–G) Blockage of secondary axis formation by PDZ binding peptides. Ventro-vegetal injections of
       <em>
        Wnt1
       </em>
       mRNA (1 pg) and PDZ binding peptides (100 ng; corresponding concentration after injection, approximately 200 μM) were done at the 4 cell stage. Embryos that received injections were cultured until they reached the larval stage; at that point they were analyzed to determine whether any secondary axis was present. (C) A control embryo that received no injection. (D) An embryo that received an injection of
       <em>
        Wnt1
       </em>
       mRNA developed a complete secondary axis. (E) An embryo that received coinjections of the mutated Fz7 peptide, mutFz7, and
       <em>
        Wnt1
       </em>
       mRNA developed a secondary axis. (F and G) An embryo that received coinjections of
       <em>
        Wnt1
       </em>
       mRNA and either Fz7 (F) or Dpr/Frodo (G) peptide developed a partial secondary axis. (H–M) The Fz7 peptide differentially rescued the effect of Xfz7 and Xdd1 on elongation
       <em>
        of Xenopus
       </em>
       explants. The animal-pole region of embryos at the 4 cell stage received injections of 500 ng synthetic mRNA corresponding to
       <em>
        Xfz7
       </em>
       or
       <em>
        Xdd1
       </em>
       that were given alone or together with the Fz7 peptide. Ectodermal explants dissected at the early blastula stage were treated with activin and cultured until they reached the neurula stage. (H) Untreated explants from control embryos did not show elongation. (I) Activin-treated explants from control embryos exhibited extensive elongation. (J) Xfz7 blocked explant elongation induced by activin. (K) The coinjected Fz7 peptide rescued explant elongation. (L) Xdd1 blocked explant elongation to a similar degree as did Xfz7. (M) The coinjected Fz7 peptide did not rescue explant elongation.
      </p>
     </caption>
    </fig>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo Peptide-Mediated Inhibition of Wnt1-Induced Secondary Axis Formation
    </title>
    <p>
     We tested whether the peptides affect the well-known ability of Wnt to induce secondary axis formation.
     <em>
      Wnt1
     </em>
     mRNA injected into the ventro-vegetal region of
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     embryos at the 4 cell stage induced the formation of a complete secondary axis (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4C and 4D
     </xref>
     ). The peptide with a mutated KTXXXW motif (mutFz7) did not significantly block secondary axis formation (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4E
     </xref>
     ), whereas Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides substantially reduced the extent of secondary axis formation induced by Wnt1 (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 2
      </span>
     </a>
     ). This reduction resulted in embryos with a partial secondary axis or only a single axis (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4F and 4G
     </xref>
     ). Therefore, Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides specifically block signaling in the canonical Wnt pathway. Furthermore, the blockage of secondary axis formation by Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides did not result from defects in gastrulation because ventral injection of these peptides, either alone or with Wnt1, did not affect gastrulation movements (data not shown). Incomplete blockage of the Wnt signaling by both the Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo peptides is likely due to the relative weak interactions between these peptides and Dvl. Indeed, the result of our coinjection experiments using the Dpr/Frodo peptide is consistent with those of earlier experiments in which
     <em>
      Wnt8
     </em>
     mRNA and a small C-terminal fragment of Frodo (FrdC) were coinjected into
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     embryos (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Gloy et al., 2002
     </xref>
     ). The effect of the Fz7 peptide on canonical Wnt signaling is dose dependent. A higher concentration (200 μM) efficiently blocked Wnt1-induced secondary axis formation, whereas a low concentration (50 μM) had a weak effect (
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 2
      </span>
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
    <sec>
     <a>
      <img/>
     </a>
     <sec>
      <sec>
       <a>
        Table 2
       </a>
      </sec>
      <sec>
       <span>
        <strong>
         Effects of Fz7 and Dpr/Frodo Peptides on Secondary Axis Formation Induced by Wnt1
         <sup>
          a
         </sup>
        </strong>
       </span>
      </sec>
     </sec>
    </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Lack of Interference by the Fz7 Peptide with the DEP-Mediated Noncanonical Wnt Pathway
    </title>
    <p>
     Although the Fz7 peptide blocks canonical Wnt signaling, it is unclear whether it interferes with other Wnt pathways. The noncanonical Wnt pathway that involves the DEP domain is required for planar cell polarity in
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Axelrod, 2001
     </xref>
     ) and for convergent extension in
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Sokol, 1996
     </xref>
     ). Therefore, we conducted the
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     explant elongation assay to test whether the Fz7 peptide interferes with this noncanonical pathway. Ectodermal explants that were treated with activin at the blastula stage and cultured until they reached the neurula stage exhibited extensive elongation that mimics convergent extension (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figures 4H and 4I
     </xref>
     ). Gain of function by overexpression of full-length Xfz7 blocked elongation (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Djiane et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ) (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4J
     </xref>
     ), and this blockage was rescued by coinjection of the Fz7 peptide and Xfz7 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4K
     </xref>
     ). This result suggests that the Fz7 peptide disrupts the interaction between the Xfz7 receptor and the PDZ domain of Dvl and is consistent with the requirement of the PDZ and DEP domains in planar cell polarity signaling (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Boutros and Mlodzik, 1999
     </xref>
     ). A truncated Dvl protein, i.e., Xdd1 that lacked the PDZ domain, also blocked elongation of the ectodermal ex-plant (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4L
     </xref>
     ) (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Sokol, 1996
     </xref>
     ). However, coinjection of the Fz7 peptide did not rescue explant elongation blocked by Xdd1 (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 4M
     </xref>
     ). This result implies that the Fz7 peptide does not interfere with the DEP domain of Xdd1 and thus does not affect the noncanonical Wnt pathway. Together, these observations further suggest a specific interaction of the Fz7 peptide with the PDZ domain of Dvl.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Conclusion
   </title>
   <p>
    We have demonstrated that there is a direct interaction between Fz and Dvl. Specifically, the PDZ domain of mDvl1 interacts directly with the Fz conserved sequence that is C-terminal to the seventh transmembrane helix. This interaction is essential in the transduction of the Wnt signal from Fz to the downstream components of the pathway. Thus, our finding sheds light on the mechanism by which the receptor Fz communicates with the downstream component Dvl. Furthermore, our findings should be useful in designing pharmaceutical antagonists that modulate Wnt signaling in tumor cells.
   </p>
   <p>
    The interaction between Fz and Dvl is relatively weak; we therefore hypothesize that the membrane-targeting function of the Dvl DEP domain is required to ensure signal transduction. The weak interaction between Fz and Dvl could allow signaling from Fz to be mediated by cytoplasmic proteins, e.g., Dpr/Frodo. Indeed, the Dvl1 PDZ domain uses a single recognition site to interact with Fz and Dpr/Frodo. In addition, because of the weak interaction, the local physiological condition and the local environment, which includes the local concentrations of Dvl and its regulatory effectors, should play a considerable role in the mediation of the molecular recognition of Dvl (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Nooren and Thornton, 2003
    </xref>
    ). This possibility may serve as an explanation for the following discrepancy: despite the 90% amino acid identity between Dpr and Frodo (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Wharton, 2003
    </xref>
    ), Dpr negatively regulates Wnt signaling (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Cheyette et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ), whereas Frodo enhances Wnt signaling (
    <xref ref-type="bibr">
     Gloy et al., 2002
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Multiple homologs of Fz and Dvl are present in mammals. The differences in the sequences of the PDZ domains of Dvl1 homologs (
    <xref ref-type="fig">
     Figure 1
    </xref>
    ) and the C-terminal regions of Fz receptors suggest that the binding affinities of each in the Fz-Dvl complexes should differ. Further studies to fully investigate such differences will provide insight into the signaling pathways that involve Fz and Dvl.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Purification of the mDvl1 PDZ Domain
    </title>
    <p>
     The cDNA that encodes the mDvl1 PDZ domain (amino acids 247-341) was subcloned into the pET28a vector; the cDNA was inserted so that a region encoding a 6xHis tag was linked to the 5′ of the cDNA. The 6xHis-tagged protein was expressed in BL21(DE3)-RP
     <em>
      E. coli
     </em>
     cells. Site-directed mutagenesis was done to replace particular codons in the cDNA with those commonly used by bacteria. No change in peptide sequence was caused by these codon replacements. To improve the protein solubility and to prevent dimerization, Cys334 was replaced with alanine. No change in the
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-HSQC spectra after the mutation indicated that the structure of the altered PDZ domain remained the same as that of the wild-type protein.
    </p>
    <p>
     Transformed cells were grown in MOPS-containing medium with 1 gL
     <sup>
      −1 15
     </sup>
     NH
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     Cl as the source of
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N and 3 gL
     <sup>
      −1 13
     </sup>
     C
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     -glucose as the source of
     <sup>
      13
     </sup>
     C. Protein expression was induced by the addition of 1 mM isopropyl-1-thio-β-D-galactoside (IPTG) when the OD
     <sub>
      600
     </sub>
     of the cells was approximately 0.7; 6 hr after induction, the cells were resuspended in lysis buffer and sonicated, and the lysate was centrifuged. The supernatant was then transferred to a column of Ni-NTA beads, and the column was washed with 50 mM imidazole. The protein was eluted by 200 mM imidazole in 20 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.5) and 300 mM NaCl. The PDZ domain was further purified by chromatography using a Superdex 75-pg column (Amersham Pharmacia) and was eluted by 100 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.5).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     NMR Spectroscopy and Structure Calculation
    </title>
    <p>
     NMR experiments were performed with a Varian INOVA 600 MHz NMR spectrometer at 25°C. Samples consisted of the PDZ domain (0.8–1.5 mM) in 100 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.5), 10% D
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O, and 0.5 mM EDTA. HNCACB and CBCA(CO)NH were performed to determine the backbone assignment. Side-chain proton and carbon resonances were assigned on the basis of the results of the HCCH-TOCSY and HCCH-COSY experiments. The
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     J
     <sub>
      HN-Hα
     </sub>
     coupling constant was measured by J-HMQC.NOE connections were assigned on the basis of three-dimensional
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
     N-edited NOESY and
     <sup>
      13
     </sup>
     C-edited NOESY. NMR spectra were processed with NMRpipe (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Delaglio et al., 1995
     </xref>
     ) software and analyzed by XEASY (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Xia et al., 1993
     </xref>
     ). Integrated NOE peaks were calibrated and converted to distance constraints with the program CALIBA (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Guntert et al., 1991
     </xref>
     ). A total of 1124 meaningful distance constraints were derived. In addition, 44 dihedral angle restraints and 20 distance restraints from hydrogen bonds obtained from NMR experiments were added. The program DYANA (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Guntert et al., 1997
     </xref>
     ) was used for the final structural calculation. Twenty structures with the lowest target functions were selected from a total of 320 calculated structures (see
     <a>
      Supplemental Data
     </a>
     at
     <a>
      http://www.molecule.org/cgi/content/full/12/5/1251/DC1
     </a>
     ).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Yeast Two-Hybrid System
    </title>
    <p>
     For this study, the MATCHMAKER two-hybrid system (Clontech, Inc.) was used. In brief, in the screening experiments, pGBT9 was used as the bait plasmid to express the
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Fz2 C terminus fused to the Gal4 DNA binding domain. A
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     imaginal disc library was used as prey. In the mating assay, the full-length
     <em>
      Drosophila
     </em>
     Dsh clone, which was isolated in the screen, was used as prey; the cytoplasmic C-terminal sequences of Fz and Fz2 and their deletion constructs were used as bait (see
     <a>
      <span>
       Table 1
      </span>
     </a>
     ). β-Gal activity was determined by colony-lift filter assays in which X-Gal served as the substrate.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Peptide Synthesis and Purification
    </title>
    <p>
     Peptides were chemically synthesized by the Hartwell Center for Bioinformatics &amp; Biotechnology at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital. Amino groups were attached to the N terminus of each peptide; carboxylate groups, to the C terminus. Peptides were purified by reverse-phase high-performance liquid chromatography and lyophilized.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Biotin Pull-Down Experiment
    </title>
    <p>
     UltraLink Immobilized Monomeric Avidin was obtained from Pierce (Pierce Biotechnology, Inc.), and the pull-down experiments were conducted in accordance with a standard protocol provided by the manufacturer. PBS was used as buffer throughout the experiments. In brief, for each pull-down experiment, 100 μl of avidin-conjugated beads were incubated with 200 pmol of biotinylated peptide, either Fz7 or Dpr/Frodo, for 2 hr at room temperature. The peptide-charged beads were then incubated with 25 pmol of purified PDZ domain at 4°C for 2 hr. After the beads were washed at least 5 times with buffer, they underwent SDS-PAGE. When the Dpr/Frodo peptide was used to compete with the Fz7 peptide (lane 6,
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3A
     </xref>
     ), the Fz7 peptide-coupled beads that were bound by PDZ were subjected to an additional 5 washes with buffer that contained 0.5 mM Dpr/Frodo peptide.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     Fluorescence Spectroscopy
    </title>
    <p>
     A Jobin-Yvon Fluorolog-3 spectrofluorometer (Jobin-Yvon, Inc.) was used to obtain the fluorescence measurements of the interaction between the PDZ domain of mDvl1 and the Dpr/Frodo peptide. Titration experiments were performed at 10°C in a phosphate buffer (0.1 M potassium phosphate; 0.5 mM EDTA [pH 7.5]). The peptide ligand (2 mM) was injected into the 2.0 ml sample cell that contained either the PDZ domain (10 μM) or the mixture of the PDZ domain (10 μM) and the Fz7 peptide (10 μM or 50 μM). The excitation wavelength was 290 nm (slit width, 5 nm), and the fluorescence emissions from 320 nm to 370 nm (slit width, 5 nm) were recorded (
     <xref ref-type="fig">
      Figure 3B
     </xref>
     ) during the titration of Dpr/Frodo, whose concentrations ranged from 2 μM to 90 μM. The fluorescence data were analyzed by the ORIGIN program (Microcal). Fitting was performed to extract the maximum fluorescence intensity quenching (F
     <sub>
      max
     </sub>
     ), the binding affinity of the Dpr/Frodo peptide and the PDZ domain (K
     <sub>
      d
     </sub>
     ), and the inhibition constant (K
     <sub>
      I
     </sub>
     ) of Fz7 in its disruption of the interaction between the PDZ domain and the Dpr/Frodo peptide. The KI value was calculated from a reciprocal plot of fluorescence intensity quenching (ΔF) against the concentration of the Dpr/Frodo peptide for three sets of titration data.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     Embryos and Microinjections of mRNA and Peptides
    </title>
    <p>
     <em>
      Xenopus
     </em>
     eggs were obtained from females that had received injections of 500 IU of human chorionic gonadotropin (Sigma) and had been artificially fertilized. Synthesis and microinjection of capped mRNAs were done as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). To assess secondary axis formation, the mRNAs were injected into the ventro-vegetal blastomere of 4 cell–stage embryos, and the embryos were then cultured until they reached the larval stage. For explant elongation assay, ectodermal explants from control and treated embryos at the early gastrula stage were dissected and treated with activin (a gift from J.C. Smith). The explants were then cultured until they reached the neurula stage.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec>
    <title>
     RT-PCR
    </title>
    <p>
     Animal-cap explants from control and treated embryos at the blastula stage were dissected and then cultured until they reached the early gastrula stage. Extraction of RNA, RT-PCR, and primers for
     <em>
      Siamois
     </em>
     and
     <em>
      ODC
     </em>
     were as described (
     <xref ref-type="bibr">
      Umbhauer et al., 2000
     </xref>
     ). The RT-PCR results were analyzed by using a phosphoimager system (BioRad).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Supplementary Material
   </title>
   <sec>
    <title>
     supplemental material
    </title>
    <sec>
     <a>
      Click here to view.
     </a>
     <sup>
      (36K, doc)
     </sup>
    </sec>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
