<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2010.10.059
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Characterization of GmCaMK1, a member of a soybean calmodulin-binding receptor-like kinase family
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaM
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      calmodulin
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaMBD
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      CaM-binding domain
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaMBP
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      CaM-binding protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaMK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      calmodulin-binding kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaMRLK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      CaM-binding RLK
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CBL
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      calcineurin B-like protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CCaMK
     </span>
     ,
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CDPK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      calcium-dependent protein kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CIPK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      CBL-interacting protein kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CML
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      calmodulin-like protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CRK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      CDPK-related kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      GmCaMK1
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      Glycine max CaM-binding RLK
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      GST
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      glutathione S-transferase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      HRP
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      horseradish peroxidase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      ITC
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      isothermal titration calorimetry
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      MALDI
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Q-tof
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      quantitative time-of-flight
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      RLK
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      receptor-like kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      qPCR
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      quantitative real-time PCR
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      Calcium
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Calmodulin
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Signal transduction
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CaM-binding protein
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      Receptor-like kinase
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <em>
      Glycine max
     </em>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    1. Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    is a central second messenger in all eurkaryotes, and intracellular [Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ] fluxes have been observed in response to numerous stimuli
    <a>
     [1]
    </a>
    . Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    signals are perceived and interpreted by Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -binding proteins (Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    sensors), many of which bind Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    through the conserved EF-hand motif
    <a>
     [2]
    </a>
    . In plants several large families of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    sensors have been studied, including: calmodulin (CaM) and calmodulin-like proteins (CMLs), calcium-dependent protein kinases (CDPKs), and calcineurin B-like proteins (CBLs)
    <a>
     [3]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [4]
    </a>
    . CDPKs and CBLs (via their corresponding CBL-interacting protein kinase family [CIPKs]) possess catalytic activity, while CaM acts via regulation of many CaM-binding target proteins of diverse function
    <a>
     [5]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [6]
    </a>
    . CaM is an archetypal and ubiquitous eukaryotic Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -sensor, and in plants participates in coordinating developmental processes, abiotic and biotic stress response, and the formation of microbial symbioses
    <a>
     [4]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [7]
    </a>
    . Although considerable progress has been made in the identification of plant CaM targets, the role of CaM-binding protein kinases (CaMKs) are poorly understood. In contrast, there has been extensive analysis of CaMKs in animals
    <a>
     [8]
    </a>
    . To date, plant CaMKs identified include kinases that share some sequence homology to CDPK-related kinases (CRKs), the chimeric Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    and Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM-depedent protein kinase (CCaMK), and CaM-binding receptor-like kinases (RLKs)
    <a>
     [9]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [10]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Amongst plant CaM-binding kinases, CCaMK is the most thoroughly studied
    <a>
     [11]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [12]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [14]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [15]
    </a>
    and a large body of evidence has demonstrated that CCaMK is critical for both rhizobial nodule formation and mycorrhizal fungal associations
    <a>
     [13]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [14]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [15]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [16]
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     [17]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [18]
    </a>
    . Given the importance of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    signals and CaM-binding CCaMK in nodule formation, we screened expressed soybean nodule cDNA using
    <sup>
     35
    </sup>
    S-CaM as a probe to identify nodule-expressed CaM-binding proteins (CaMBPs). We isolated a CaM-binding RLK (CaMRLK),
    <em>
     Glycine max
    </em>
    CaM-binding RLK (GmCaMK1), which is a homolog of the recently identified CRLK1 of
    <em>
     Arabidopsis thaliana
    </em>
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . Here we present the biochemical characterization of GmCaMK1 and demonstrate that this family of CaMRLKs is conserved in soybean,
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    , and
    <em>
     Medicago truncatula
    </em>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    2. Materials and methods
   </title>
   <title>
    2.1. Plant growth conditions
   </title>
   <p>
    <em>
     G. max
    </em>
    L. cv. Djakal or cv. Boyer seeds were sown in Waikerie river sand, inoculated with
    <em>
     Bradyrhizobium japonicum
    </em>
    USDA 110 one-day after planting, and fertilized twice weekly with nutrient solution lacking nitrogen
    <a>
     [20]
    </a>
    . Plants were grown in a glasshouse (24–28 °C) under long day conditions (16/8 h day/night).
    <em>
     A. thaliana
    </em>
    (ecotype Col-0) seeds were grown in soil in a growth chamber under long day (16/8 h) conditions at 22 °C and supplemented weekly with 1 g/l 20–20–20 fertilizer.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.2. Preparation and screening of soybean nodule cDNA library
   </title>
   <p>
    We prepared a cDNA expression library from soybean nodules (
    <em>
     G. max
    </em>
    L. cv. Boyer) at various developmental stages using the UniZapII kit (Stratagene) according to manufacturer’s instructions. This nodule cDNA library was then screened for CaMBPs using
    <sup>
     35
    </sup>
    S-methionine labeled CaM (in all cases recombinant petunia CaM81 – a conserved plant CaM with 100% amino acid identity to
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    CaM2) in the presence of 1 mM Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    as previously described
    <a>
     [21]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.3. Cloning and expression of GmCaMK1
   </title>
   <p>
    Serial truncations of
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    were subcloned from the
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    clone isolated from the cDNA library screen and expressed as glutathione S-transferase (GST)-fusion proteins in the pGEX4T3 vector (Amersham) using
    <em>
     Escherichia coli
    </em>
    BL21 pLysS cells grown in LB media at 37 °C.
    <a>
     Supplementary Table 1
    </a>
    lists the relevant PCR primers used for subcloning procedures. Recombinant proteins used in kinase assays were purified to near-homogeneity (
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 3
    </a>
    ) by glutathione-agarose affinity chromatography and/or Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependent CaM-agarose affinity chromatography or phenyl-sepharose chromatography (in the case of CaM).
   </p>
   <p>
    A full length
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    cDNA was obtained from the SoyBase database (clone Gm_c1065-5498), from which a fragment encoding residues 29-431 was amplified by PCR, subcloned into a pET21 vector, expressed in
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    BL21 pLysS cells, and purified by Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependent CaM-agarose affinity chromatography as described
    <a>
     [22]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.4. CaM-binding assays
   </title>
   <p>
    CaM-binding overlay assays were performed as described previously (
    <a>
     [22]
    </a>
    . Briefly, proteins were either separated by SDS–PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose or purified proteins were blotted directly onto nitrocellulose (spot blot assays) according to figure legends. Membranes were blocked in 25 mM Tris–Cl, pH 7.5 with 5% (w/v) skim milk powder at 4 °C overnight, probed with either
    <sup>
     35
    </sup>
    S-methionine CaM81 (150 nM) or horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated CaM (HRP::CaM, 25–100 nM as indicated in figure legends) in 25 mM Tris–Cl, pH 7.5, 1% milk and either 1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    or 5 mM EGTA for 60 min. HRP::CaM conjugation and bioluminescent overlay assays were performed as described
    <a>
     [23]
    </a>
    . Membranes were washed in buffer without milk and imaged using chemiluminescence reagents with either X-ray film (Kodak MR-1) or a Typhoon phosphorimager (GE).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.5. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC)
   </title>
   <p>
    ITC was performed using a VP-ITC calorimeter (Microcal, LLC, Northampton, MA) at 30 °C in CaM-binding buffer (25 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.5, 1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ). A 26mer peptide (364-KRPSMRDIVQVLTRILKSRHQRNHHH-389) containing the CaM-binding domain (CaMBD) of GmCaMK1 was synthesized (GenScript) and used for binding analysis with CaM. CaM (114 μM) was titrated into the cell containing 14.5 μM CaMBD peptide in 49 injections of 6 μl each with a 300-s equilibration interval between injections. Using Origin 7.0 software (OriginLab Corp., Northampton, MA), the best fit for the ITC binding isotherm was obtained with the two sets of sites model, following removal of the initial injection point and subtraction of the heat of dilution as determined from the final 20 injections of the isotherm post-saturation of both binding sites. Amino acid analysis (Advanced Protein Technology Centre, Toronto) was used to quantify peptide and CaM concentrations for ITC samples.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.6. Non-dissociating PAGE
   </title>
   <p>
    CaM-binding peptide shift gels were carried out as described previously
    <a>
     [22]
    </a>
    . Briefly, CaM was incubated with GmCaMK1 CaMBD peptide at varying molar ratios in 25 mM Tris–Cl, pH 7.5, 0.1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (or 2 mM EGTA) for 30 min at 25 °C, separated by non-dissociating 12.5% acrylamide PAGE (ND-PAGE) in the presence of 0.1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (or 2 mM EGTA) at 25 mA and 25 °C, then stained with Coomassie brilliant blue R-250.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.7. Mass spectrometry analysis of CaM–peptide complex
   </title>
   <p>
    For all mass spectrometry analyses, CaM and GmCaMK1 peptide were combined in 25 mM Tris–Cl, 1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , pH 7.5 to a final concentration of 75 μM (sample ∼50 μl). For denaturing matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization (MALDI) mass spectrometry, re-crystallized sinapinic acid (Sigma) was freshly prepared at a concentration of 10 mg/ml in 70% acetonitrile, 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid, 10 mM diammonium citrate. One microliter of this solution was applied to each sample spot on the MALDI target and allowed to air dry. Samples were mixed 1:1 with matrix solution prepared previously and 1 μl was applied to a target position. The spots were allowed to air dry. Each sample was washed on the target with 1.5 μl of ice cold 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid for 5 s. The wash was removed and discarded. Spectra were acquired and analyzed on a Voyager DePro (Applied Biosystems Corporation) using Data Explorer Version 5.1 software (Applied Biosystems Corporation). Spectra were acquired in positive-ion linear mode. Two hundred laser shots were averaged per spectrum.
   </p>
   <p>
    For non-denaturing quantitative time-of-flight (Q-tof), the sample was diluted to a volume of 2 ml in 10 mM ammonium acetate pH 6.8 + 1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    . The sample was filtered through a Vivaspin 500 3000 MWCO PES cartridge (Sartorius part #VS0192) to a final volume of 50 μl. The filtered sample was introduced by static nanoelectrospray to a Waters Q-tof Ultima Global mass spectrometer operating in positive ion mode. The instrument had been calibrated using a solution of NaI in the range of 50–3000
    <em>
     m
    </em>
    /
    <em>
     z
    </em>
    . Data was processed using Waters MassLynx 4.0 software and the charge series was manually assigned. Identification of protein–peptide complex by mass spectrometry was conducted at the PFD Facility (Queen’s University).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.8. Mutant analysis of the GmCaMK1 CaMBD
   </title>
   <p>
    Peptides (corresponding to GmCaMK1 K364-H389) featuring single amino acid substitutions (at V372, L375, R377, or K380) were synthesized (GenScript) and used in spot blot CaM-binding overlays as described above (see Section
    <a>
     2.4
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.9. CaMBD analysis of CaMK family members
   </title>
   <p>
    Based on sequence alignment with GmCaMK1, the CaMBD region of soybean CaMKs (GmCaMK1-5),
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    (AtCRLK2), and
    <em>
     M. truncatula
    </em>
    (MtCaMK) were synthesized (GenScript) and used in spot blot CaM-binding overlays as described above (see Section
    <a>
     2.4
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    2.10. RNA extraction and quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR)
   </title>
   <p>
    Plant material was collected from 10 individual soybean plants at either 15 days (young nodules) or 36 days (start of flowering) post-germination and pooled for RNA extractions. Nodules were collected from the root crown area. Main roots consisted of tissue collected from the root crown stripped of nodules. Lateral roots consisted of tissue collected within 5 cm from lateral root tips. RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen) and treated with DNase (Ambion). cDNA synthesis was carried out with 1.25 μg of total RNA using an oligo(dT)20 primer with Superscript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen). cDNA was diluted 10-fold and 2 μl used for qPCR with a 1× SYBR Green Master Mix (Bio-Rad) on a Bio-Rad iCycler.
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    was amplified using a forward (5′-CCTAGTTCTGTTGTCTCGCAGAA-3′) and reverse (5′-CGGGCAAGAAAGGTAACTTTCTA-3′) primer designed to amplify a portion of the 3′ untranslated region. Relative transcript levels were determined by the comparative C
    <sub>
     t
    </sub>
    method
    <a>
     [24]
    </a>
    using
    <em>
     cons6
    </em>
    as the reference gene
    <a>
     [25]
    </a>
    . qPCR reactions were done in triplicate and results presented are representative of two independent RNA isolations.
   </p>
   <title>
    2.11.
    <em>
     In vitro
    </em>
    kinase phosphorylation assays
   </title>
   <p>
    Autophosphorylation assays were carried out in kinase buffer (25 mM Tris–Cl, pH 7.5, 3 mM Mg-acetate, 3 mM MnCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) supplemented with either 1 mM CaCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    /1 μg CaM or 2 mM EGTA. One microgram of recombinant kinase (G3 or 29-431) was used for all reactions. Reactions were initiated with the addition of 100 μM ATP with 2 μCi [γ-
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]ATP and carried out at 30 °C for 10 min (final reaction volume 30 μl). Assay linearity was validated in a 0–20 min time-course experiment (data not shown). Reactions were stopped by addition of 3× Laemli loading buffer and heating to 95 °C for 5 min. Proteins were separated by SDS–PAGE and imaged with a Typhoon phosphorimager. Semi-quantification of phosphorylated proteins was performed with ImageQuant software (GE). Purified proteins used in assays are shown in
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 3
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    2.12. Identification of autophosphorylation sites by mass spectrometry
   </title>
   <p>
    Autophosphorylation reactions were carried out as above, with the exception of the addition of [γ-
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]ATP. Identification of phosphorylated residues by mass spectrometry was conducted at The Advanced Protein Technology Centre of The Hospital for Sick Children (Toronto, Canada).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    3. Results
   </title>
   <title>
    3.1. Identification and cloning of GmCaMK1
   </title>
   <p>
    Screening the soybean nodule cDNA library for CaMBPs, we isolated a cDNA encoding a putative CaM-binding kinase, termed GmCaMK1, comprised of 431 residues with a predicted MW of 49 kDa and a single transmembrane (TM) domain predicted near the N-terminus. Database analysis suggested that orthologs of GmCaMK1 are represented broadly across plant taxa (
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 1
    </a>
    ), often as part of a multi-member family. Putative orthologs of GmCaMK1 examined in
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     M. truncatula
    </em>
    are highly conserved and are all predicted to possess an N-terminal TM domain, all 12 subdomains of a conserved ser/thr kinase domain, and a CaMBD. GmCaMK1 is part of a putative 5-member family in soybean as shown in
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 2
    </a>
    . Recombinant GmCaMK1 bound CaM in a Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependent manner (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    C), and we delineated the CaMBD to a region near the C-terminus (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Mapping and Ca2+-dependence of GmCaMK1 CaMBD. (A) Schematic representation of ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Mapping and Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         -dependence of GmCaMK1 CaMBD. (A) Schematic representation of recombinant fusion proteins used in CaM-binding assays. (B) Anti-GST Western blot (left panel) and HRP::CaM overlay (right panel) of purified GmCaMK1 truncation proteins. CaM-binding overlay was probed with 75 nM HRP::CaM in the presence of 1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         . (C) Spot blot of purified G4 protein (∼1 μg) probed with HRP::CaM in the presence of 1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         (left) or 2 mM EGTA (right). Pure HRP was spotted as a positive control for chemiluminescence. For all Western blots and overlays, 1 μg of protein was loaded into each well. All data are representative from at least three independent replicated experiments.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (927 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    3.2. Mapping of a single, high affinity, Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependent CaMBD
   </title>
   <p>
    Removal of a 20-residue region (a.a. 368–387) of GmCaMK1 was found to eliminate CaMBD completely as G3 bound CaM and G2 did not (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    A and B). ITC analysis of CaM binding to the GmCaMK1 CaMBD 26mer peptide (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    ) demonstrated that this domain binds CaM with high affinity, with a high pM to low nM
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). The binding curve of peptide into CaM titrations modeled best to a two-site interaction, where each site showed a stoichiometry of approximately 0.5:1 (peptide:CaM) molar ratio, with exothermic binding to the higher affinity site (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    0.331 nM) driven enthalpically, and endothermic binding to the lower affinity site (
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    11.6 nM) driven entropically. Values obtained from ITC analysis are summarized in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC). (A) Calorimetric titration of 114&amp;#956;M CaM ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC). (A) Calorimetric titration of 114 μM CaM into 14.5 μM CaMBD peptide in 6 μl aliquot injections. (B) Two-site model of least-squares fitted titration data. Molar ratios show the ratio of CaM to CaMBD peptide. Data are best representatives of three independent titrations.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (210 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         ITC values. Values obtained from ITC analysis shown in
         <a>
          Fig. 2
         </a>
         . Shown are
         <em>
          N
         </em>
         (number of sites),
         <em>
          K
         </em>
         (binding constant in M
         <sup>
          −1
         </sup>
         ),
         <em>
          K
         </em>
         <sub>
          d
         </sub>
         (dissociation constant obtained from reciprocal of
         <em>
          K
         </em>
         , in nM), Δ
         <em>
          H
         </em>
         (heat change in cal/mol), Δ
         <em>
          S
         </em>
         (entropy change in cal/mol/deg), and
         <em>
          T
         </em>
         (temperature in °C).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Value
          </th>
          <th>
           Site 1
          </th>
          <th>
           Site 2
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            N
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           0.417 ± 0.002
          </td>
          <td>
           0.499 ± 0.003
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           3.02E9 ± 7.31E8
          </td>
          <td>
           8.63E7 ± 1.96E7
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
          </td>
          <td>
           331 pM (267, 437)
          </td>
          <td>
           11.6 nM (9.44, 15.0)
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Δ
           <em>
            H
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           −2.087E4 ± 158
          </td>
          <td>
           8762 ± 150
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Δ
           <em>
            S
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           −25.5
          </td>
          <td>
           65.2
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <em>
            T
           </em>
          </td>
          <td>
           30
          </td>
          <td>
           30
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    ND-PAGE showed that CaM forms a 1:1 molar ratio complex with the CaMBD peptide, and does so only in the presence of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    B). The 1:1 molar ratio of the CaM–peptide complex was further corroborated by non-denaturing mass spectrometry, in which the 1:1 complex (approximately 20.1 kDa) and no larger complexes were detected (
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Characterization of the CaMBD of GmCaMK1. (A) A wild-type 26mer peptide was used ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         Characterization of the CaMBD of GmCaMK1. (A) A wild-type 26mer peptide was used in CaM-binding assays, with the modeled CaMBD boxed. Residues identified as critical for CaM-binding are indicated with *. (B) Non-dissociating PAGE showing 1:1 binding of CaM to CaMBD peptide in the presence of 0.1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         (top panel) and lack of binding in the presence of 2 mM EGTA (lower panel). (C) Spot blot of 26mer mutant peptides, probed with 75 nM HRP::CaM in the presence of 1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         (CaM-binding) or stained with Ponceau S (protein stain). (D) Helical wheel model of 20-residue CaMBD region (outlined in (A)), with hydrophobic residues shaded. A dashed line shows the predicted hydrophobic and hydrophilic faces of the amphipathic CaMBD. All data are representative from at least three independent replicated experiments.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (320 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Mass spectrometry analysis of CaM&amp;ndash;peptide complex. (A) CaM&amp;ndash;peptide complex ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         Mass spectrometry analysis of CaM–peptide complex. (A) CaM–peptide complex analyzed by denaturing MALDI mass spectrometry. Peptide peaks were 3246 (mass + 1 hydrogen) and 6492 (2 mass + 1 hydrogen). CaM peaks were 16 721 (mass + 1 hydrogen) and 8359 (mass + 2 hydrogen). (B) CaM–peptide complex analyzed by non-denaturing Q-tof mass spectrometry, showing a 1:1 molar ratio (predicted mass approximately 20.07 kDa).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (176 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    We examined the CaMBD to determine residues critical for CaM-binding. Within the CaMBD substitution of either V372 or L375 to Glu prevented CaM-binding, whereas a neutral substitution of V372 to Ile did not interfere with binding (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    C). Both V372 and L375 fit to the hydrophobic face of the amphipathic helical wheel modeled using a 20 residue region of the CaMBD (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    D). Substitution of either R377 or K380 to Ala was found to reduce CaM-binding without disrupting the interaction completely, while substitution of R377 to Glu was shown to result in a greater reduction of CaM-binding (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    C) relative to substitution of R377 to Ala.
   </p>
   <title>
    3.3. Expression profiling of GmCaMK1
   </title>
   <p>
    Analysis of
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    expression by qPCR revealed expression broadly across tissues, with strongest levels observed in main and lateral roots, and developing (15 days post-germination) nodules (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). Nodules and leaves showed the greatest relative decrease in expression during maturation (15–36 day plants).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) profile of GmCaMK1. Tissue-based gene expression ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         Quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) profile of GmCaMK1. Tissue-based gene expression profile of
         <em>
          GmCaMK1
         </em>
         at 15 vs. 36 days post-germination, as measured relative to the reference gene
         <em>
          cons6
         </em>
         transcript levels
         <a>
          [23]
         </a>
         . Values are shown ±S.D. and represent means from triplicate runs of two independent RNA isolations. Transcript levels were significantly different between all tissues at 15 days except leaf and stem. Likewise, transcript levels were significantly different between all tissues at 36 days except flower and main root. Finally, all individual tissues varied significantly in expression between 15 and 36 days except for lateral roots. All pairwise comparisons were analyzed by two-tailed
         <em>
          t
         </em>
         -test.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (114 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    3.4. Phosphorylation activity of GmCaMK1
   </title>
   <p>
    All recombinant GmCaMK1 fragments containing the kinase domain displayed
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    autophosphorylation activity. Activity was observed using soluble bacterial extracts of GST-fusions G4 and G3, as well as the untagged protein corresponding to residues 29-431. We were unable to test G2 (lacking the CaMBD) for activity, as this protein was not expressed in the soluble fraction of
    <em>
     E. coli
    </em>
    extracts. Autophosphorylation activity was dependent upon the presence of divalent cations Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    or Mn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    (data not shown). Purified G3 and 29-431 proteins were used for autophosphorylation assays and phosphorylation-site mapping by mass spectrometry (purified proteins used in assays shown in
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 3
    </a>
    ). Autophosphorylation activity was not affected by the presence of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM (
    <a>
     Fig. 6
    </a>
    A and B,
    <em>
     t
    </em>
    -test,
    <em>
     P
    </em>
    &gt; 0.05). Substrate phosphorylation assays showed that fragment G3 was capable of weakly phosphorylating myelin basic protein or histone III, but this activity was not affected by the presence of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM (data not shown).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Kinase activity of GmCaMK1. (A) Autophosphorylation of G3 recombinant protein ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 6.
        <p>
         Kinase activity of GmCaMK1. (A) Autophosphorylation of G3 recombinant protein (see
         <a>
          Fig. 1
         </a>
         A) in the presence of 2 mM EGTA or 1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         and 1 μg CaM. (B) Quantification (mean ± S.D.,
         <em>
          n
         </em>
         = 8) of autophosphorylation activity presented in (A), by area of
         <sup>
          32
         </sup>
         P-protein band as measured with ImageQuant (GE). Values shown in (B) are not significantly different (two-tailed
         <em>
          t
         </em>
         -test,
         <em>
          P
         </em>
         -value &gt;0.05).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (183 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    3.5. GmCaMK1 is part of a conserved family of CaMRLKs across plant taxa
   </title>
   <p>
    We demonstrated that a functional CaMBD is conserved among four of the five members of the GmCaMK family (
    <a>
     Fig. 7
    </a>
    ). We corroborated the CaM-binding of
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    homolog CRLK1
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    , which shares high sequence similarity (72% a.a. identity) with GmCaMK1. We also demonstrated CaM-binding for
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    CRLK2 and the single predicted family member from
    <em>
     M. truncatula
    </em>
    (MtCaMK) (
    <a>
     Fig. 7
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Conservation of the GmCaMK1 CaMBD. (A) Alignment of the 26mer CaMBD region ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 7.
        <p>
         Conservation of the GmCaMK1 CaMBD. (A) Alignment of the 26mer CaMBD region peptide of GmCaMK1 with the GmCaMK family of soybean, the AtCRLK family of
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         , and MtCaMK of
         <em>
          M. truncatula
         </em>
         . (B) Spot blot of peptides from panel A probed with 50 nM HRP::CaM in the presence of 1 mM CaCl
         <sub>
          2
         </sub>
         or stained with Ponceau S (protein stain).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (453 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    4. Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    The CaM-binding kinases of plants represent a growing and diverse group of CaMBPs. Several distinct CaMRLKs have been previously identified in plants, including CRCK1
    <a>
     [26]
    </a>
    , CBRLK1
    <a>
     [27]
    </a>
    , and AtCaMRLK
    <a>
     [28]
    </a>
    from
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    and SRK from
    <em>
     Brassica oleracea
    </em>
    <a>
     [10]
    </a>
    . Physiological data regarding these CaMRLKs is limited, though recent evidence has indicated a role for CBRLK1 in the negative regulation of plant defense responses
    <a>
     [29]
    </a>
    . GmCaMK1, isolated in the present study, appears to be unrelated to these previously described CaMKs, but putative orthologs of GmCaMK1 are highly conserved across plant taxa (
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 1
    </a>
    ), including CRLK1 of
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . GmCaMKs form a 5-member family in soybean, of which only GmCaMK5 is predicted to be a cytosolic protein (lacking the N-terminal TM domain) (
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 2
    </a>
    ); interestingly GmCaMK5 is also the only member of the family to lack a functional CaMBD at the conserved C-terminal region (
    <a>
     Fig. 7
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependence and high affinity of CaM/GmCaMK1 interaction is reminiscent of that described for other plant CaMBPs
    <a>
     [30]
    </a>
    and well within the physiological levels of CaM
    <a>
     [31]
    </a>
    . The GmCaMK1 CaMBD binds Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM with low nM affinity (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). In accordance with the two-site interaction indicated by our ITC titration results (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    ), we speculate that the N- and C-terminal lobes of CaM bind to the GmCaMK1 CaMBD separately. Although the affinities of the two sites differ sufficiently for the exothermic site to dominate initial binding, both affinities are relatively high (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ), and it is evident from the raw isotherm that some binding to the second site occurs prior to saturation of the higher affinity site. The 0.5:1 CaM:peptide molar ratio determined for each of the two individual interaction sites gives the interaction an overall 1:1 ratio, with each lobe binding the CaMBD. This stoichiometry is consistent with both our ND-PAGE and non-denaturing mass spectrometry results, which both confirm an unambiguous 1:1 molar ratio for the overall CaM–peptide interaction (Figs.
    <a>
     3
    </a>
    B and
    <a>
     4
    </a>
    ). Differential binding of N- and C-terminal lobes of CaM to the CaMBD of animal CaMKII has been previously studied
    <a>
     [32]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The CaMBD of GmCaMK1 is predicted as a putative IQ-like motif, which is a class of CaM-binding motifs that are sometimes capable of binding Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -free CaM (apoCaM)
    <a>
     [33]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [34]
    </a>
    , though this was not the case for GmCaMK1 (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    ) nor it’s orthologs. Interestingly, while V372 was found to be critical for CaM-binding (as predicted for an IQ-like motif), L375 was also found to be required, despite modeling that suggested a L375E substitution would not disrupt CaM-binding
    <a>
     [35]
    </a>
    . The importance of these residues, coupled with a lack of apoCaM–GmCaMK1 interaction suggests that this CaMBD is a non-canonical IQ-like motif, and is part of a growing number of uncategorized CaM-binding motifs
    <a>
     [36]
    </a>
    . Interestingly, R377 is predicted to be a conserved residue important for CaM-binding within the consensus IQ-like motif: [I,L,V]QxxxR[G,x]xxx[R,K]
    <a>
     [37]
    </a>
    . Substitution of either this residue or another basic residue (K380) to an uncharged residue (A) interferes with CaM-binding but does not eliminate it. Substitution of R377 to an acidic residue (E) has a greater impact on the interaction, but again does not completely prevent it (
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    C). It is likely these basic residues are involved in electrostatic interactions with CaM, while the hydrophobic residues examined (V372, L375) are interacting directly with the hydrophobic clefts on CaM. Of additional interest in the CaMBD is the presence of a hydrophobic residue (I378) at the semi-conserved G of the IQ-like motif, as the charge and size of this residue has been recently shown to affect the affinity and Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependence of CaM-binding by IQ-like motifs
    <a>
     [37]
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Phosphorylation assays revealed that recombinant GmCaMK1 protein is an active protein kinase, which could autophosphorylate independent of CaM-binding (
    <a>
     Fig. 6
    </a>
    ). The lack of effect of CaM on
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    kinase activity is interesting, as the CaMBD appears to overlap with kinase subdomain XI (
    <a>
     Supplementary Fig. 1
    </a>
    ). This CaM-independent kinase activity is consistent with several other studies on plant CaMRLKs
    <a>
     [27]
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     [28]
    </a>
    . It remains possible that Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM may regulate GmCaMK1 activity
    <em>
     in vivo
    </em>
    , as the recombinant proteins in our study lacked the N-terminal TM domain and this may have interfered with proper regulation of activity. Alternatively, CaM may control other, non-catalytic properties of GmCaMK1, such as interaction with substrates, though it is unknown at present what its targets may be. While the role of CaM-binding to many plant RLKs is presently unclear, recent work has demonstrated that CaM-binding regulates the intracellular trafficking of the EGF receptor, a CaM-binding receptor-kinase in animals
    <a>
     [38]
    </a>
    . What role CaM may have on GmCaMK1 remains an interesting avenue for further investigation.
   </p>
   <p>
    The
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    homolog to GmCaMK1, CRLK1, is an important component of cold stress-response in
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    , as shown recently
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . Loss of function
    <em>
     crlk1
    </em>
    mutant
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    show reduced survival of cold treatment, while overexpression of wild-type
    <em>
     CRLK1
    </em>
    confers improved cold tolerance. CLRK1 is a positive regulator of cold responses, as
    <em>
     crlk1
    </em>
    plants show slower induction of CBF-(cold binding factors) regulated COR (cold-regulated) genes
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    , and appears to act via regulation of MEKK1
    <a>
     [39]
    </a>
    . Interestingly, CRLK1 and GmCaMK1 have several important divergent properties. CaMBD affinity differs between the two orthologs, with the CaMBD of GmCaMK1 having an affinity for CaM of approximately 0.338–11.6 nM (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ) and the CaMBD of CRLK1 an affinity of 25 nM (as determined by bound/unbound
    <sup>
     35
    </sup>
    S-CaM assay)
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . CRLK1 also possesses a second, N-terminal CaMBD with a
    <em>
     K
    </em>
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of 160 nM; this CaMBD is not conserved in GmCaMK1, as shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    B. No function has been assigned to this non-conserved N-terminal CaMBD of CRLK1, and the lack of this CaMBD in GmCaMK1 may explain differential regulation by CaM in different species. Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    /CaM appears to upregulate the
    <em>
     in vitro
    </em>
    kinase activity of CRLK1
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    an effect not observed for GmCaMK1 (
    <a>
     Fig. 6
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Several potential autophosphorylation sites on GmCaMK1 were identified by mass spectrometry, summarized in
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    . One putative GmCaMK1 autophosphorylation site is in the activation loop of kinase subdomains VII and VIII. Autophosphorylation sites were not mapped for CRLK1, but it will be interesting to determine whether such sites are conserved among GmCaMK1 orthologs. Though CRLK1 appears to have a role in cold stress signaling, it is possible that this kinase (or related family members) has other function(s). Our analysis of
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    expression by qPCR matches expression data from the recently published soybean transcriptome atlas
    <a>
     [40]
    </a>
    . These data demonstrated significant enrichment of
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    transcripts in root and young nodules (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ), and suggests that GmCaMK1 may function during Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    signaling in these tissues. In contrast,
    <em>
     CRLK1
    </em>
    transcript expression is not as dominant in roots throughout development compared to
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    <a>
     [19]
    </a>
    . The difference between
    <em>
     GmCaMK1
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     CRLK1
    </em>
    in expression patterns and biochemical properties suggests that GmCaMK1 and its family members may play divergent, species-specific roles. Moreover, as GmCaMK5 lacks both a conserved transmembrane domain and the conserved C-terminal CaMBD (
    <a>
     Fig. 7
    </a>
    ), our data suggest the potential for complex Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    -dependent and independent regulation of this kinase family in soybean. Given the many RLKs in plants (i.e. over 600 members in
    <em>
     Arabidopsis
    </em>
    <a>
     [41]
    </a>
    ), it is important to characterize the roles of CaMRLKs to further elucidate the complex signaling pathways of plants.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 2.
        </span>
        <p>
         Identification of GmCaMK1 autophosphorylation sites. Autophosphorylation reactions were carried out using G3 and 29-431 proteins as described in Section
         <a>
          2.10
         </a>
         . Phosphopeptides were identified by LC-MS/MS (APTC, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Canada). Phosphopeptides are grouped by unique sequence. Potential Ser/Thr phosphorylation sites are underlined.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Peptide
          </th>
          <th>
           Sequence
          </th>
          <th>
           No. phosphate groups
          </th>
          <th>
           Location (a.a.)
          </th>
          <th>
           Actual peptide mass (AMU)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            A
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            YNF
            <span>
             TT
            </span>
            LIGQGAFGPVYK
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           111–129
          </td>
          <td>
           2127.01
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           2
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            A
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            YNF
            <span>
             TT
            </span>
            LIGQGAFGPVYK
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           111–129
          </td>
          <td>
           2127.01
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           3
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            A
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            YNF
            <span>
             TT
            </span>
            LIGQGAFGPVYK
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           111–129
          </td>
          <td>
           2127.01
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           4
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            FGYLDPEYI
            <span>
             SS
            </span>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            F
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            K
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           272–289
          </td>
          <td>
           2061.89
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           5
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            FGYLDPEYI
            <span>
             SS
            </span>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            F
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            K
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           272–289
          </td>
          <td>
           2061.90
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           6
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            FGYLDPEYI
            <span>
             SS
            </span>
            G
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            F
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            K
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           272–289
          </td>
          <td>
           2061.89
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           7
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            L
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            A
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            ADEV
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            IDVDQLE
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            K
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           392–410
          </td>
          <td>
           2099.95
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           8
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            L
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            A
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            ADEV
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            IDVDQLE
            <span>
             T
            </span>
            K
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           392–410
          </td>
          <td>
           2099.95
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           9
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            REE
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            ID
            <span>
             ST
            </span>
            ADIYDL
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           417–431
          </td>
          <td>
           1705.71
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           10
          </td>
          <td>
           <tt>
            REE
            <span>
             S
            </span>
            ID
            <span>
             ST
            </span>
            ADIYDL
           </tt>
          </td>
          <td>
           1
          </td>
          <td>
           417–431
          </td>
          <td>
           1705.71
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    <a>
    </a>
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Protein sequence alignment of GmCaMK1 with putative orthologs. Sequence ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Supplementary Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Protein sequence alignment of GmCaMK1 with putative orthologs. Sequence alignment of GmCaMK1 (Glyma13g36140) with predicted orthologs from
         <em>
          M. truncatula
         </em>
         (MtCaMK, Medtr2g096390.1),
         <em>
          Arabidopsis
         </em>
         (CRLK1, At5g54590), and
         <em>
          Oryza sativa
         </em>
         (
         <a>
          BAD03013.1
         </a>
         ). The delineated CaMBD is indicated, as are the predicted transmembrane domain (TM) and the 12 subdomains of the ser/thr kinase domain. Putative orthologs were identified by protein BLAST (BLASTP) alignment using the NCBI protein database.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (867 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The predicted GmCaMK family of soybean. Family members were identified sequence ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Supplementary Fig. 2.
        <p>
         The predicted GmCaMK family of soybean. Family members were identified sequence homology to GmCaMK1 protein sequence using the
         <em>
          Glycine max
         </em>
         proteome database at Phytozome (
         <a>
          http://www.phytozome.net/soybean.php
         </a>
         ). Percent amino acid identity to GmCaMK1 (Glyma13g36140) are as follows: GmCaMK2 (Glyma12g34410) 97%, GmCaMK3 (Glyma06g41510) 84%, GmCaMK4 (Glyma12g16650) 84%, GmCaMK5 (Glyma19g04870) 62%.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (767 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Representative SDS&amp;ndash;PAGE of purified recombinant proteins used in ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0014579310008902-fx3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Supplementary Fig. 3.
        <p>
         Representative SDS–PAGE of purified recombinant proteins used in autophosphorylation assays. Proteins used in all assays were purified by GSH-agarose and/or CaM-agarose affinity chromatography, as outlined in Section
         <a>
          2.3
         </a>
         . Proteins were separated by SDS–PAGE and stained with Coomassie brilliant blue R-250 for total protein. Arrows indicate the expected size of each recombinant GmCaMK1 protein.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (81 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Supplementary Table 1.
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>
       Primers used in PCR-based subcloning of reactions. Added restriction sites and gateway recombination sites are underlined and stop codons bolded.
      </p>
      <p>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with DOC files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file ( K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [1]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.R. McAinsh, J.K. Pittman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Shaping the calcium signature
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New Phytol., 181 (2009), pp. 275–294
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [2]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.L. Gifford, M.P. Walsh, H.J. Vogel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structures and metal-ion-binding properties of the Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         -binding helix-loop-helix EF-hand motifs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 405 (2007), pp. 199–222
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [3]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V.S. Reddy, A.S.N. Reddy
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proteomics of calcium-signaling components in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Phytochemistry, 65 (2004), pp. 1745–1776
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [4]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T.A. DeFalco, K.W. Bender, W.A. Snedden
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Breaking the code: Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         sensors in plant signalling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. J., 425 (2010), pp. 27–40
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [5]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Yang, B.W. Poovaiah
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Calcium/calmodulin-mediated signal network in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Plant Sci., 8 (2003), pp. 505–512
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [6]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Bouche, A. Yellin, W.A. Snedden, H. Fromm
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant-specific calmodulin-binding proteins
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Annu. Rev. Plant Biol., 56 (2005), pp. 435–466
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [7]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.F. Harper, A. Harmon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plants, symbiosis and parasites: a calcium signalling connection
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 6 (2005), pp. 555–566
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [8]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.T. Swulius, W.M.N. Waxham
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         /calmodulin-dependent protein kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell. Mol. Life Sci., 65 (2008), pp. 2637–2657
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [9]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Zhang, Y.T. Lu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Calmodulin-binding protein kinases in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Plant Sci., 8 (2003), pp. 123–127
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [10]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V. Vanoosthuyse, G. Tichtinsky, C. Dumas, T. Gaude, J.M. Cock
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Interaction of calmodulin, a sorting nexin and kinase-associated protein phosphatase with the
         <em>
          Brassica oleracea
         </em>
         S locus receptor kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Physiol., 133 (2003), pp. 919–929
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [11]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Takezawa, S. Ramachandiran, V. Paranjape, B.W. Poovaiah
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dual regulation of a chimeric plant serine/threonine kinase by calcium and calcium/calmodulin
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 271 (1996), pp. 8126–8132
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [12]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Ramachandiran, D. Takezawa, W. Wang, B.W. Poovaiah
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional domains of plant chimeric calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase: regulation by autoinhibitory and visinin-like domains
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biochem., 121 (1997), pp. 984–990
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [13]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J. Levy, C. Bres, R. Geurts, B. Chalhoub, O. Kulikova, G. Duc, E.P. Journet, J.M. Ane, E. Lauber, T. Bisseling, J. Denarie, C. Rosenberg, F. Debelle
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A putative Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase required for bacterial and fungal symbioses
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 303 (2004), pp. 1361–1364
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [14]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.M. Mitra, C.A. Gleason, A. Edwards, J. Hadfield, J.A. Downie, G.E.D. Oldroyd, S.R. Long
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         /calmodulin-dependent protein kinase required for symbiotic nodule development: gene identification by transcript-based cloning
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 101 (2004), pp. 4701–4705
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [15]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Tirichine, H. Imaizumi-Anraku, S. Yoshida, Y. Murakami, L.H. Madsen, H. Miwa, T. Nakagawa, N. Sandal, A.S. Albrektsen, M. Kawaguchi, A. Downie, S. Sato, S. Tabata, H. Kouchi, M. Parniske, S. Kawasaki, J. Stougaard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Deregulation of a Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         /calmodulin-dependent kinase leads to spontaneous nodule development
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 441 (2006), pp. 1153–1156
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [16]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        O. Godfroy, F. Debelle, T. Timmers, C. Rosenberg
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A rice calcium- and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase restores nodulation to a legume mutant
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Plant–Microbe Interact., 19 (2006), pp. 495–501
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [17]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Chen, M. Gao, J. Liu, H. Zhu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Fungal symbiosis in rice requires an ortholog of a legume common symbiosis gene encoding a Ca
         <sup>
          2+
         </sup>
         /calmodulin-dependent kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Physiol., 145 (2007), pp. 1619–1628
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [18]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Chen, J. Ane, H. Zhu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         OsIPD3, an ortholog of the
         <em>
          Medicago truncatula
         </em>
         DMI3 interacting protein IPD3, is required for mycorrhizal symbiosis in rice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         New Phytol., 180 (2008), pp. 311–315
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [19]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Yang, S. Chaudhuri, L. Yang, L. Du, B. Poovaiah
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A calcium/calmodulin-regulated member of the receptor-like kinase family confers cold tolerance in plants
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 285 (2010), pp. 7119–7126
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         [20]
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D.F. Herridge, M.B. Peoples
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Ureide assay for measuring nitrogen fixation by nodulated soybean calibrated by 15N methods
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Plant Physiol., 93 (1990), pp. 495–503
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>