<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.str.2009.03.017
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Distinct Binding Modes of Two Epitopes in Gab2 that Interact with the SH3C Domain of Grb2
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Author Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      PROTEINS
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      SIGNALING
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Gab (Grb2-associated binder) proteins are a family of large multisite docking (LMD) proteins (
    <a>
     Gu and Neel, 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Liu and Rohrschneider, 2002
    </a>
    ). They display compositional similarity to other LMD proteins, such as those of the IRS and p130Cas families (
    <a>
     Defilippi et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     O'Neill et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sesti et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Thirone et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). LMD proteins function as scaffolds in the assembly of large multiprotein complexes and may serve as signal integration and processing platforms for several signaling pathways.
   </p>
   <p>
    Gab proteins are important for the signal transmission of cell surface receptors that regulate developmental processes, cell growth, and immune cell signaling. Gab1 is a crucial facilitator of signals from the HGF receptor c-Met (
    <a>
     Sachs et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sakkab et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Schaeper et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weidner et al., 1996
    </a>
    ), but also mediates signals of EGFR, FGFR, and PDGFR (
    <a>
     Kallin et al., 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lamothe et al., 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Schaeper et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). It contains an N-terminal PH domain as the only readily recognizable protein fold, but also a unique Met-binding region (
    <a>
     Lock et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lock et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Weidner et al., 1996
    </a>
    ) and numerous tyrosines, which, upon phosphorylation, serve as docking sites for SH2 domains of such signaling proteins as PI3 kinase, SHP2, and CRKL. In addition, several SH3 domain docking motifs have been identified on Gab1. Targeted disruption of
    <em>
     gab1
    </em>
    leads to multiple developmental defects in mice, reminiscent of defects in
    <em>
     c-met
    </em>
    receptor knockouts (
    <a>
     Itoh et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Rosario and Birchmeier, 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Sachs et al., 2000
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Gab2 is structurally similar to Gab1 and is implicated in the signaling of cytokine, T and B cell, and growth factor receptors (
    <a>
     Gu et al., 1998
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Linnekin et al., 1992
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Liu et al., 2001
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nishida et al., 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Nishida et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wickrema et al., 1999
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Yamasaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Zhao et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). The mouse knockout phenotype of
    <em>
     gab2
    </em>
    is more subtle than that of
    <em>
     gab1
    </em>
    , with no obvious developmental defects (
    <a>
     Gu et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Nishida et al., 2002
    </a>
    ), but a reduction in the number and responsiveness of mast cells (
    <a>
     Gonzalez-Espinosa et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Gu et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Nishida et al., 2002
    </a>
    ), as well as defects in phagocytosis (
    <a>
     Gu et al., 2003
    </a>
    ) and in osteoclastogenesis (
    <a>
     Wada et al., 2005
    </a>
    ). Subsequent studies have also shown defects in the cytokine responsiveness of hematopoietic progenitor cells in
    <em>
     gab2
    </em>
    <sup>
     (−/−)
    </sup>
    mice (
    <a>
     Zhang et al., 2007
    </a>
    ), as well as postnatal deaths due to heart failure, which results from impaired neuregulin-1/ErB signaling, in a cardiomyocyte-specific double knockout of
    <em>
     gab1
    </em>
    and
    <em>
     gab2
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Nakaoka et al., 2007
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The role of Gab3 is less well defined. Gab3-deficient mice exhibit normal development and hematopoiesis (
    <a>
     Bourgin et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Seiffert et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Gab4 has been deposited as a DNA sequence, but remains virtually uncharacterized so far.
   </p>
   <p>
    Gab family proteins, in particular Gab2, have been implicated in the development of human cancers of the breast (
    <a>
     Bennett et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Bentires-Alj et al., 2006b
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Brummer et al., 2006
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Daly et al., 2002
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Ke et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yuan et al., 2007
    </a>
    ) and CML (
    <a>
     Sattler et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Subsets of breast cancers overexpress the EGF receptor family protein ErbB2 (Her2, Neu) or Gab2 (
    <a>
     Bentires-Alj et al., 2006a
    </a>
    ), which appear together in a disease-driving multiprotein complex. ErbB2 overexpression typically correlates with poor prognosis for patients and hormone therapy resistance (
    <a>
     Menard et al., 2003
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Complex formation of ErbB2 with Gab2 is mediated by the small adaptor Grb2, which docks with its SH2 onto pTyr residues of ErbB2 (
    <a>
     Dankort et al., 2001
    </a>
    ) and recruits Gab2 via an SH3 domain-mediated interaction. The functional significance of the ErbB2-Grb2-Gab2 complex in breast cancers is believed to come from the activation of the Ras-MAPK and PI3K-Akt pathways, which leads, for example, to the down-regulation of the cell cycle inhibitor p27Kip1 (
    <a>
     Janes et al., 1994
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Lim et al., 2000
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Moasser et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Yang et al., 2000
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Several studies have reported the binding of Grb2 to atypical SH3-binding motifs in Gab1 and Gab2 via the C-terminal Grb2 SH3 domain (SH3C) (
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lock et al., 2000
    </a>
    ), but the molecular details of this interaction were not known. In the current study, the binding sites for the Grb2SH3C in Gab2 were analyzed by peptide array overlay blots, isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC), and protein crystallography. This revealed striking differences in the composition and conformation of the two SH3C-binding epitopes of Gab2. It also elucidated the similarity of interactions in one of the Grb2SH3C-Gab2 peptide complexes with interactions of the SH3C domain from the Grb2 relative Mona/Gads binding to the adaptor protein SLP-76 or the S/T-kinase HPK1.
   </p>
   <p>
    This new high-resolution structural information will facilitate the testing of different point mutants that eliminate the interaction of Gab2 and Grb2 for biological effects. It may also allow the development of small molecules that can selectively disrupt Gab family complexes and could serve as useful research tools or even as therapeutic compounds for cancer treatments.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Gab2 Contains Two Distinct Grb2SH3C Binding Regions that Share a Core Consensus RxxK Motif
   </title>
   <p>
    Earlier work had suggested the presence of two Grb2SH3C binding sites in Gab1 and 2 (
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2001
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lock et al., 2000
    </a>
    ), and subsequent studies with the SH3C domain of the Grb2 family adaptor Mona/Gads pointed to the motif R/KxxK as core binding residues (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Five of these motifs occur in human Gab2 and, hence, other Grb2SH3C binding sites could exist. Therefore, Gab2 was synthesized as a spot array of overlapping 30 amino acid (aa) peptides, sliding 3 aa with each following peptide. This array was probed with GST-Grb2SH3C fusion protein, or GST alone as a control for nonspecific tag binding. As shown in
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    , two regions in Gab2, designated Gab2a and Gab2b, were detected. Both of these contain, as expected, RxxK motifs. To define further the binding sites, peptide arrays with step-wise truncations of Gab2a or Gab2b were synthesized and probed with GST-Grb2SH3C. This showed that the core binding regions are 7 to 8 aa in length (Gab2a: PPP
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    PP
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    , Gab2b: PPVN
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    NL
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    ; see
    <a>
     Figures S1 and S2
    </a>
    available online). Permutation arrays in which single positions are exchanged for all 20 naturally occurring amino acids were further used to pinpoint positions that are partially or highly restricted with respect to amino acids that allow binding with similar strength to that of the wild-type motif (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    ). This delineated a pPp
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    Pp
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    pxxxe motif in Gab2a and a Pxvx
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    xx
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    P motif in Gab2b (highly restricted positions in capital letters, moderately restricted positions in lower case letters, and marginally or nonrestricted positions designated as x).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Grb2SH3C Domain Overlay Blot of&amp;nbsp;Gab2 Synthesized as Peptide Array Detects Two ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (264 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Peptide Permutation Arrays of the&amp;nbsp;Grb2SH3C Binding Gab2a and Gab2b Epitopes ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (482 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Peptide arrays only allow a semiquantitative analysis. Hence, ITC of GST-Grb2SH3C with selected peptides was conducted, to confirm binding in solution and to quantify the effects of different peptide lengths and mutations. The ITC results are summarized in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    . Starting with 27 aa peptides, suitable ITC conditions were established, and these peptides were then compared to successively shorter peptides. This indicated that the motif required for optimal Grb2SH3C binding is confined to regions of approximately 12 and 15 aa, respectively. Unexpectedly, the deletion of a Glu residue in Gab2a, which appeared to be potentially important based on the peptide permutation array results (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    ), had no negative effect on SH3C binding. Overall, the affinities of Gab2a-derived peptides were approximately 10-fold lower than those of Gab2b peptides. Gab2b contains two RxxK motifs (aa 515 to 518 and 521 to 524). Double Ala mutation of either motif showed that only the first one is essential for Grb2SH3C binding.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         Isothermal titration calorimetric measurements of Grb2SH3C interactions with wild-type and mutant peptides derived from Gab2 and p27Kip1
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           <img/>
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Interestingly, the human cell cycle regulator p27Kip1 contains a region similar to Gab2a (PP
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    PP
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    ) and binds with slightly higher affinity than does the Gab2a to Grb2SH3C (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). In contrast to the Gab2a region, p27Kip1 contains two tyrosines (Y88/Y89) N-terminal of the RxxK motif. These residues are targets of several tyrosine kinases, including oncogenic Src and Abl (
    <a>
     Chu et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Grimmler et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Kardinal et al., 2006
    </a>
    ). ITC analyses showed that tyrosine phosphorylation reduces binding of Grb2SH3C and Mona/Gads SH3C to this epitope considerably (M.L. and S.F., unpublished data).
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystallization Screens of the Grb2SH3C Domain with Different Peptides
   </title>
   <p>
    For structural analysis, the Grb2SH3C domain was cleaved from its GST-tag, purified by FPLC, concentrated, mixed with short Gab2a, Gab2b, or p27Kip1-derived binding peptides retaining full binding affinity (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ), and screened for crystal formation by extensive sparse matrix sampling using automated facilities. Crystals were obtained rapidly with a wide variety of precipitant mixtures, and all crystals analyzed diffracted to high resolution, but none of these contained an SH3C-peptide complex. Instead, it was apparent that autoassociation of the SH3C, driven by a proline (P212, located in the C-terminal overhang of the SH3), promoted crystal packing. P212 was invariably found occupying a hydrophobic groove in the surface of adjacent domains (stacking against Y209) and as a result, incoming peptides were potentially excluded. This was likely the result of intracrystal stabilization of transient self-associations due to the high Grb2SH3C concentration. Since P212 was not expected to play a major role in Gab2 peptide binding, a P212A mutated SH3C was generated, and three C-terminal residues were also deleted. The expressed, cleaved, and purified SH3C was tested for functionality by ITC (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Subsequently, the P212A-SH3C was used in extensive crystallization screens. Crystals were first obtained with P212A-SH3C and the Gab2b peptide. X-ray diffraction data were collected to 1.58 Å resolution (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A; for further details on all structures, see
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). Later, crystals appeared in the mixture of P212A-SH3C with Gab2a peptide and these diffracted to 1.7 Å (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). Electron density maps of the peptides are shown in
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    .
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Stereo Views of Three Newly Solved SH3C Domain-Peptide ComplexesElectrostatic ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1119 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Structures of Native and Complexed Grb2SH3C
   </title>
   <p>
    The X-ray atomic structures of the Grb2SH3C alone or in complex with peptide ligands display the typical β-barrel SH3 domain architecture repeatedly seen before. The domain is composed of five β strands and a 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix and forms a typical RxxK binding platform where a focal area of negative potential is flanked by predominantly hydrophobic surfaces. Both the RT and n-Src loops show a degree of C
    <sub>
     α
    </sub>
    positional flexibility in response to peptide binding. In the structures of Grb2SH3C in complex with either Gab2a or Gab2b, the two loops move closer to each other relative to the unbound conformation by up to 1.4 Å, which reflects closure of the binding groove around the peptide.
   </p>
   <p>
    Noticeable individual residue relocations are mostly evident in the Grb2SH3C-Gab2b structure, and include Met46
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    moving closer to the C terminus of Gab2b, and Pro48
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    shifting downward and away from the peptide, thereby displacing the Phe47
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    C
    <sub>
     α
    </sub>
    by 0.6 Å in its wake. Phe7
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    moves closer to the peptide in both Gab2a and Gab2b, whereas Pro33
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    is respectively pushed away.
   </p>
   <p>
    For clarity, the peptide residues described hereafter will be denoted by their relative positions with respect to the arginine of the RxxK motif. Hence, the residue type will be followed by a number, n, indicating the number of residues away from the RxxK arginine, either on its N-terminal side, designated as -n, or C-terminal side, denoted as +n.
   </p>
   <title>
    Structure of the Grb2SH3C-Gab2b Complex
   </title>
   <p>
    Gab2b binding has a hybrid hydrophobic-hydrophilic nature, which encompasses a focal area of high electrostatic potential heavily complemented by multiple stabilizing hydrophobic interactions. Lacking the stereochemical constrains of a poly-proline helix, the Gab2b peptide adopts an extended conformation that allows maximum use of the available electrostatic potential in both the peptide and the SH3 domain. In agreement with typical RxxK motifs seen before (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Kaneko et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), hydrophobic docking provides accessory interactions that further stabilize the incoming peptide. Both Pro(−4) and Pro(−5) (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A) associate with the hydrophobic groove of Tyr51
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    and Phe7
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    stacking against the respective side chain rings. A second hydrophobic determinant emerges as Val(−2) positions itself in a hydrophobic patch over Pro48
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    effectively pushing the peptide upward in the direction of the RT loop. This shift obliges the RxxK arginine to twist its side chain and offer two alternative atoms, N
    <sub>
     η
    </sub>
    and N
    <sub>
     ɛ
    </sub>
    , to Glu16
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    as H-bonding partners. The RxxK arginine marks also the beginning of a 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix that excludes Asn(+1) and Leu(+2) from the binding interface but secures the RxxK lysine in its optimal position for H-bonding through its N
    <sub>
     ζ
    </sub>
    atom with Glu13
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    and Glu16
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    . As an additional stabilizing element, the aliphatic portion of the RxxK lysine stacks against Trp35
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    , a feature that appears conserved in all known RxxK-containing structures. Binding is completed with a C-terminal site of hydrophobic interactions involving Pro(+4), which lies adjacent to Met46
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    and over the aliphatic portion of Asp32
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Comparison of Grb2SH3C-Gab2b and Other Typical RxxK Motifs
   </title>
   <p>
    Gab2b exhibits the canonical RxxK motif and adopts a relatively extended conformation on the surface of Grb2SH3C much in the fashion of SLP-76 and HPK1 binding to Mona/Gads SH3C (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A–4D) (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) as well as UBPY binding to the STAM2 SH3 domain (
    <a>
     Kaneko et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). All these structures display extensive similarity in the architecture of the H-bonding interface defined by the invariant residues of the RxxK motif. In either case, binding is dominated by electrostatic interactions, in contrast to traditional poly-proline peptides that effect predominantly hydrophobic interactions. Specifically, the RxxK arginine involves both a primary and a secondary side chain amine in hydrogen bonds with invariant SH3 domain glutamates, while the RxxK lysine remains firmly docked C-terminally, constrained by several proximal SH3 glutamates. A gamut of accessory interactions, of mainly hydrophobic nature, supplement binding. Invariant points of docking involve Pro(−4), which rests in the first N-terminal hydrophobic groove of the SH3 binding platform and Val(−2) at the adjacent groove. The relative spacing between key motif residues is maintained via the 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix present in all these structures.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Similarity of the Grb2SH3C-Gab2b Complex with Mona/GadsSH3C in Complex with ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (508 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    Structure of Grb2SH3C-Gab2a
   </title>
   <p>
    In contrast to Gab2b, Gab2a uses predominantly its poly-proline type II (PPII) helical conformation to dock onto the Grb2SH3C domain (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B). Pro(−2) is the first site of hydrophobic docking and rests in the groove formed by Phe7
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    and Tyr51
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    followed by Pro(+1), which stacks against Trp35
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    . The latter also offers its side chain as a hydrophobic platform against which the aliphatic portion of the RxxK lysine stacks. Significantly, it is the poly-proline conformation of the polypeptide chain that restricts plasticity and hinders the RxxK lysine from forming optimal H-bonds at its canonical resting position (as seen for Gab2b), a fact that is reflected in the elevated thermal motion of this side chain in the crystal structure as will be discussed further later. The residue that dominates the electrostatic contribution to binding is the RxxK arginine, which forms stable H-bonds with the domain at the site of Glu16
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    where the domain surface shows the highest electronegative potential. Additionally, Glu12
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    stacks over the RxxK arginine side chain, effectively clamping the incoming peptide in place, an action that is seen again in the case of a novel SH3 binding motif, RxxxxK, described further below.
   </p>
   <p>
    Subsequent ITC analyses of mutant Gab2a peptides confirmed the importance of the RxxK motif in Gab2a also for solution phase binding (
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    ). Replacing the PPII helix-embedded arginine by an alanine virtually abolished peptide binding to the Grb2SH3C domain. However, its replacement by a leucine led merely to a minimal reduction in affinity, again highlighting the surprising versatility that SH3C domains display in accommodating different peptides. Replacing the lysine with alanine also led to a dramatic loss of binding affinity, although a weak interaction was still detectable.
   </p>
   <title>
    Comparison of Grb2SH3C in Complex with Gab2a or Gab2b
   </title>
   <p>
    Upon superposition of the available Grb2SH3C structures, either bound to Gab2 peptides or in their unbound conformation, structurally conserved features emerge indicating a level of positional invariance with respect to the binding site. The most notable residue in the domain is Glu16
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    , which persists as the single residue with the maximum electrostatic interactions with docking residues and the minimal positional deviation (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    A and 5B). The rigid nature of the location forces atoms bearing a δ
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    charge into positions of defined stereochemistry. Thus, in both complexes the arginine of the RxxK motif contributes two electropositive atoms, either two N
    <sub>
     η
    </sub>
    atoms or an N
    <sub>
     η
    </sub>
    and an N
    <sub>
     ɛ
    </sub>
    atom. In the native structure, two water molecules fulfill the charge requirements of Glu16
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    by positioning themselves on sites that superimpose perfectly with the RxxK arginine atoms that will ultimately bind there. An additional water molecule further facilitates the stability of the H-bond network by occupying a structurally conserved position between one N
    <sub>
     η
    </sub>
    atom and the domain backbone at Asp10
    <sub>
     Grb2
    </sub>
    . This invariant water molecule could possibly be a good candidate position to be targeted for the selective disruption of SH3C binding. The final site of electrochemical conservation is focused on the position generally occupied by the N
    <sub>
     ζ
    </sub>
    atom contributed by the lysine of the RxxK motif. That same site is occupied by a water molecule in the native form of the domain and is indicative of the electrochemical requirements at this site.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Interaction Details and Peptide Temperature Factors in the Newly Solved ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (476 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Given the relative novelty of the peptide docking mode observed in the Grb2SH3C-Gab2a complex, we also analyzed another potentially similar interaction within the focus of our research, aiming to obtain a clearer view of the stereochemistry responsible for such arrangements.
   </p>
   <title>
    The Putative Phosphatase HD-PTP (PTPN23) Binds to the SH3C Domain of the Grb2-Relative Mona/Gads via an RxxxxK Motif
   </title>
   <p>
    In an effort to detect new SH3 domain-binding partners of Grb2 family adaptors, the SH3C domain of the Mona/Gads expressed as a GST-fusion protein was utilized to affinity purify candidate proteins from human Jurkat T cells (for details, see
    <a>
     Lewitzky, 2005
    </a>
    ). The same GST-SH3C, preblocked with an SLP-76-derived peptide, was used for comparison to detect proteins that bind nonspecifically or distant from the previously identified Mona/GadsSH3C peptide binding groove (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Mass spectrometric (MS) analysis of peptides generated by tryptic digest of bands detected by MS-compatible gel surface silver staining (
    <a>
     Shevchenko et al., 1996
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A) led to the identification of several proteins, including HDP-PTP (PTPN23, PTP-TD14), USP8 (UBPY), c-Cbl, dynamin II, CMS/CD2AP, and SLP-76 (
    <a>
     Lewitzky, 2005
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Mona/GadsSH3C Binding Proteins Identified from Human Jurkat T Cells(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (383 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    HD-PTP is a phosphatase-like protein with an N-terminal Bro1 domain, a peculiar His- and Pro-rich region that may form a complex hand-like structure (
    <a>
     Toyooka et al., 2000
    </a>
    ), followed by a potential catalytic domain and a C-terminal PEST region (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B). HD-PTP remains largely unstudied but was recently reported to play roles in endothelial cell migration and endosomal sorting (
    <a>
     Castiglioni et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Doyotte et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). So far, we and others have failed to detect any catalytic activity of HD-PTP (T.T. et al., unpublished data), so HD-PTP may in fact function as a LMD protein, just like the Gab, IRS, and p130Cas family proteins.
   </p>
   <p>
    To identify potential binding sites of Mona/GadsSH3C in HD-PTP, a peptide array of the entire HD-PTP sequence was probed with GST-Mona/GadsSH3C, and a single candidate-binding region, which directly precedes the His- and Pro-rich region, was identified (
    <a>
     Figure S4
    </a>
    ). The site was further mapped to aa 717–725 (PP
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    PTAP
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    P) (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    ). Strikingly, this epitope lacks a traditional RxxK motif bearing a more extended RxxxxK motif. Analysis of Ala- or Gly-substituted point mutant HD-PTP peptides by ITC confirmed the Arg and Lys residues in the RxxxxK motif as the most important residues for binding (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ). Three additional prolines also significantly contribute to high-affinity binding of the HD-PTP peptide to the SH3C domain according to ITC, delineating a Px
    <strong>
     <span>
      R
     </span>
    </strong>
    Pxxx
    <strong>
     <span>
      K
     </span>
    </strong>
    P motif. Further analyses showed that the Lys cannot be replaced by Arg or His without severely impairing peptide binding. ITC analysis of sequentially truncated peptides indicated that a 14 aa peptide fully retained high-affinity binding, but that further truncations gradually weakened the interaction. The measured K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    of approximately 170 nM for the 14-mer peptide represents a remarkably high affinity. Many SH3 domains interact at micromolar affinities with peptides corresponding to relevant epitopes in their biologically important partner proteins. However, we were so far unable to detect a complex of HD-PTP and Mona/Gads in Jurkat cells. This could be indicative of a transient complex formation, which has been previously observed for some SH3 domain interactions. Further analyses of resting and stimulated primary T cells and other cell types coexpressing Mona/Gads and HD-PTP are clearly needed. Interestingly, in vitro binding of full-length HD-PTP from Jurkat lysates to the Grb2SH3C domain, as well as 20 other SH3 domains tested, was not detectable, which is suggestive of a highly selective interaction between Mona/GadsSH3C and the HD-PTP epitope (
    <a>
     Tsirka, 2008
    </a>
    ). ITC analysis of a potential interaction between Grb2SH3C and HD-PTP peptides also indicated only minimal binding (
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    To define the molecular details of this novel interaction, the Mona/GadsSH3C was purified for crystallographic screening as described before (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    ), concentrated and mixed with the 14 aa HD-PTP peptide. Crystals were rapidly obtained and diffracted to 1.9 Å resolution, revealing a unique SH3 domain interaction (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    C).
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystal Structure of Mona/GadsSH3C in Complex with an HD-PTP-Derived Peptide and Comparison with other Mona/GadsSH3C Complexes
   </title>
   <p>
    The Mona/Gads SH3C domain itself retains all the characteristics previously reported (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). The HD-PTP peptide is present in a semi-extended conformation with an N-terminal PPII helix containing the RxxxxK arginine and a fully extended C-terminal region where the RxxxxK lysine resides. The peptide retains the N-terminal invariant hydrophobic anchor at Pro(−2), which stacks within the Tyr12
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    , Tyr56
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    groove. This is supplemented by the Pro(+1) hydrophobic interactions with Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    8.8 Å away (the normal pitch of a PPII helix). Peptide backbone anchoring is completed with Pro(+6) and Leu(+8) both hydrophobically attaching the C-terminal portion of the peptide beyond the region of high negative potential on the SH3 surface. Both the RxxxxK arginine and RxxxxK lysine approach the electronegative glutamate and aspartate-rich region of Mona/Gads SH3C in a fashion similar to the Gab2a interaction with Grb2SH3C. The arginine and lysine further complement the motif's potency by hydrophobic stacking of their aliphatic side chains against Leu17
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    and Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    , respectively, very much in the manner of Gab2a docking. The RxxxxK lysine N
    <sub>
     ζ
    </sub>
    is fully engaged by one aspartate and two glutamate residues, with one glutamate also being the H-bonding partner of the RxxxxK arginine N
    <sub>
     η
    </sub>
    atoms.
   </p>
   <p>
    It is interesting to note that there are three residues on the binding surface of this SH3 domain that respond to the presence of the HD-PTP peptide by repositioning their side chains. In response to the N-terminal portion of the peptide, both Tyr12
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    and Tyr52
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    shift their phenoxyl rings by about 0.8 Å toward the center of the binding site.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Even more impressively, Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    shifts its side chain (using N
    <sub>
     ɛ
    </sub>
    as a reference) by 1.9 Å relative to the SLP-76 structure (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). There appears to be a clear correlation between the position of this SH3 domain side chain and the RxxK lysine. As the latter shifts further C-terminally, depending on the stereochemical restrictions imposed by the peptide's secondary structure, Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    responds by altering its relative position to maintain a reasonable hydrophobic fit at a distance of just over 3 Å away. This becomes obvious through alignment of all three available Mona/GadsSH3C complexes with SLP-76, HPK1, and HD-PTP, respectively. Taking the SLP-76 complex to be position zero (where no strict secondary structure restrictions prevail within the peptide), we observe a shift in Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    of 0.8 Å upon binding to HPK1 where the aliphatic portion of its RxxK lysine is pushed further away because of the PPII helix preceding the RxxK motif. A further 1.1 Å displacement of Trp40
    <sub>
     MONA
    </sub>
    is effected in response to the HD-PTP RxxxxK lysine, which, because of the direct interference of the PPII helix with the RxxK motif, is displaced even further.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    The biophysical analyses in this study highlight once again the great versatility of SH3 domains to accommodate short linear motifs located on the surfaces of proteins despite their sometimes highly variable secondary structures. Two central residues, an arginine and a lysine, which can vary in their relative positions to each other, appear to be the only strictly conserved feature of the Grb2 family SH3C domain interactions known to this date. Even more surprisingly, according to our ITC analysis of mutant peptides, in certain sequence contexts the arginine of the Rx
    <sub>
     n
    </sub>
    K (n = 2 or 4) core motif may even be replaced by a leucine residue with little loss of binding affinity, although biologically relevant examples of this have not yet been reported. Consequently, it seems likely that simple amino acid motif searches will be of little use in order to detect novel biological signaling partners for these domains.
   </p>
   <p>
    The relative degree of thermal motion of the peptide atoms in their respective crystalline lattices provides interesting insight into the contribution of the poly-proline helix. To study the effects of the presence and position of the poly-proline helix on the binding characteristics, we can examine the Rx
    <sub>
     n
    </sub>
    K motifs outside the context of a poly-proline helix (Gab2a on Grb2SH3C), embedded within a poly-proline helix (Gab2b on Grb2SH3C), or adjacent to one (HD-PTP on Mona/Gads SH3C). The relative magnitudes of the mean square atomic displacements (&lt;u
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    &gt;) of the peptide residues in these models (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    D–5F), which are proportional to the temperature factors (B = &lt; u
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    &gt; 8π
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    /3), clearly indicate that the presence of a poly-proline helix severely compromises the binding potential of the Rx
    <sub>
     n
    </sub>
    K motif and shifts the focus of the attachment to the poly-proline region of the peptide where the least atomic motion is encountered due to its inherent stability. This appears to be correlated with the compromised strength of binding in the case of Mona/Gads-HD-PTP and Grb2SH3C-Gab2a when compared to Mona/Gads-SLP-76 (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    ) and Grb2SH3C-Gab2b, respectively.
   </p>
   <p>
    What remains to be addressed is whether each of the two Grb2SH3C domain binding sites structurally characterized here has a distinct biological role, or whether they act together to enhance the stability of a multiprotein complex. The latter is indirectly supported by the results of one of our previous studies (
    <a>
     Feller et al., 2002
    </a>
    ) in which the
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    homolog of the mammalian Gab proteins, Dos, was point mutated in either one or both of its DrkSH3C binding sites. Each single mutation had a moderate effect on the development of the R7 photoreceptor cells, while the double mutation completely abolished R7 development, indicating a concerted interaction of both SH3 binding motifs. Similar functional studies of the related epitopes in the mammalian Gab1 and Gab2 proteins using mouse “knock in” technology are still lacking, although expression of a mutant mouse lacking both Grb2SH3C binding sites and suffering from developmental defects in placenta, liver, and palatal shelf has been recently reported (
    <a>
     Schaeper et al., 2007
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    On the basis of sequence comparisons of well-studied metazoan species (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    ), it seems possible that a ‘Gab − 2x Grb2’ module, which provides a solid link between membrane receptors and multiple intracellular signaling pathways, is present not only in complex chordates but also in simple metazoans like the starlet sea anemone
    <em>
     Nematostella vectensis
    </em>
    . Although it is difficult to provide conclusive evidence without functional studies in more of these highly diverse organisms, the conservation of a “Gab-like protein” with an N-terminal PH domain, two RxxK motifs, in combination with the presence of protein sequences that correspond to a Grb2SH3C-like domain, supports the notion of an early appearance of this signaling module.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Sequence Alignments of Grb2 or Gab Family Proteins from Diverse, Selected ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0969212609001877-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1868 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    However, while the distinct composition and, presumably, conformation of the two SH3 binding motifs in the Gab-like proteins seems to be present in rather diverse branches of the animal kingdom and may therefore represent the “module archetype,” the Gab2a-like motif seems to have been lost or replaced on various occasions. It is, for example, absent from human Gab4 and
    <em>
     C. elegans
    </em>
    Soc1, which appear to rely solely on a Gab2b-like motif. Moreover,
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    Dos has two functional binding sites that resemble the human Gab2b motif. Conceivably, such alterations of the basic modular architecture could serve to vary binding strengths, thereby fine-tuning the assembly and disassembly of multiprotein signaling machines according to the requirements of the specific organism.
   </p>
   <p>
    Our determination of the molecular details of the Grb2SH3C-Gab2 interactions could form the basis for the development of inhibitory molecules that can selectively disrupt Grb2-Gab2 complexes in cultured cells and potentially even in vivo. However, since multiple receptors rely on the Grb2 complexes with Gab1 or Gab2 for transmission of their signals, it is conceivable that some undesired effects may result from blocking this interaction. On the other hand, many receptor functions are truly essential only during embryonic or postnatal development and their inhibition in mature individuals (i.e., most cancer patients) may be compensated through redundancies in the signaling networks of normal cells. Cancer cells have sometimes lost this redundancy and are thus pathway addicted, opening a therapeutic window.
   </p>
   <p>
    Protein-protein interaction inhibitors have recently become a focus for medicinal chemists interested in developing cancer therapeutics (
    <a>
     Arkin and Wells, 2004
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Wells and McClendon, 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     White et al., 2008
    </a>
    ). Examples of compounds with in vivo activity in murine cancer models include nutlins (
    <a>
     Vassilev, 2007
    </a>
    ), polyphenylureas (
    <a>
     Schimmer et al., 2004
    </a>
    ), ABT-737 (
    <a>
     Oltersdorf et al., 2005
    </a>
    ), and C90 (
    <a>
     Giubellino et al., 2007
    </a>
    ). The latter inhibits interactions of the Grb2 SH2 domain, blocking growth factor-induced cell motility and angiogenesis.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    Small molecule inhibitors that bind to SH3 domains or SH3 domain interacting motifs are currently not in advanced stages of development, but some early successes with both conventional and
    <em>
     in silico
    </em>
    screens have been reported (
    <a>
     Atatreh et al., 2008
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Betzi et al., 2007
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Feller and Lewitzky, 2006
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Feller et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). First in vivo studies of SH3 domain interaction blockers with peptide derivatives show a modest bioactivity (
    <a>
     Gril et al., 2007
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Hashimoto et al., 2006
    </a>
    ) that is unlikely to suffice to move these agents forward to clinical studies, but encourages further exploration. Small molecule Grb2SH3C inhibitors based on the Rx
    <sub>
     n
    </sub>
    K core motif would possibly only affect a small subset of SH3 domains in mammals, and there may even be opportunities to “fine tune” inhibitors for preferential binding to a specific SH3 domain. The SH3 domains of the Stam proteins, Mona/GadsSH3C and Grb2SH3C, share only approximately 50% amino acid identity, leaving some room to explore whether SH3 sequence variability could be utilized to generate more selective inhibitors. SH3 domain inhibitor molecules generated by these means may not only be useful as agents for monotherapy, but could be particularly interesting when combined with more conventional small molecule inhibitors for receptor kinases that rely on Gab proteins as key signaling mediators.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Cloning, Expression, and Purification of Proteins
   </title>
   <p>
    The pGEX-vector wild-type human Grb2SH3C has been described elsewhere (
    <a>
     Pendergast et al., 1993
    </a>
    ). The P212A-Grb2SH3C construct encodes human Grb2 aa 159 to 214. The PCR primers used were 5′-aagttctgtttcagggcccgACATACGTCCAGGCCCTCTTTGAC-3′ (fwd), and 5′-atggtctagaaagctttaGTTCACGGCGGTGACATAATTGCG-3′ (rev). The reverse primer incorporates the P212A mutation. Both primers contain 15 bp tags for In-Fusion cloning into pOPINJ (
    <a>
     Berrow et al., 2007
    </a>
    ), which adds an N-terminal 6xHis-GST tag with a 3C protease cleavage site to the construct.
   </p>
   <p>
    For protein expression, bacteria were grown in terrific broth with 100 μg/ml ampicillin. Expression was induced at OD
    <sub>
     600
    </sub>
    0.8 with 0.05 mM IPTG overnight at 18°C, and bacteria were then sedimented by centrifugation. To generate protein for ITC and peptide array overlay blots, chilled bacterial pellets were lysed in cold TPE (1% [v/v] Triton X-100, PBS [pH 7.4], 100 mM EDTA, 10 μg/ml aprotinin, 0.7 μg/ml pepstatin A, 0.5 μg/ml leupeptin, and 5 μg/ml antipain) and sonicated, and the lysate was clarified by centrifugation at 20,000 × g for 1 hr at 4°C. GST-fusion protein was purified by coincubating with GSH-sepharose beads overnight at 4°C on a nutator. Beads were then washed extensively with 50 mM TrisHCl (pH 7.5), 100 mM EDTA, and 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20. Bound GST-fusion protein was eluted with 100 mM GSH pH-adjusted to approximately pH 7.5 with TrisHCl (pH 8.8), and the eluate was dialyzed against 5 mM TrisHCl (pH 7.5). The integrity of the dialyzed protein was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie Blue staining, and the protein concentration was assayed by the Bradford method. Purified GST-SH3 fusion protein was snap frozen in aliquots and stored at −80°C until further use in ITC or peptide array blots. Purification of the Mona/GadsSH3C has been described elsewhere (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    For crystallization experiments and some ITC measurements, expressed GST-SH3 fusions proteins were purified in the absence of detergent and the GST tags were removed. Chilled bacterial pellets were dissolved in 50 mM HEPES (pH 7.5) with 50 mM NaCl, 0.2 mM PMSF, and 1 × Complete™ protease inhibitors (Roche), were sonicated, and were centrifuged. Cleared lysates were incubated with GSH-sepharose as before; washed extensively with PBS (wild-type SH3C) or 50 mM TrisHCl (pH 7.0), 150 mM NaCl, and 1 mM EDTA (P212A mutant), and then cleaved with thrombin (GE Healthcare) in PBS (wild-type SH3C) or 3C protease (PreScission protease, GE Healthcare) in 50 mM TrisHCl (pH 7.0), 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, and 1 mM DTT (P212A mutant) to remove the GST-tag. SH3C protein was eluted, the solution was cleared by centrifugation for 10 min at 20,000 × g, and the SH3 domain was further purified by size exclusion FPLC on a HiLoad™ 16/60 Superdex™ S75 column equilibrated with 50 mM HEPES (pH 7.5) and 150 mM NaCl. Purified protein was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie Blue staining and then was concentrated (Vivaspin VS0611; Vivascience). Its concentration was quantified by UV absorption at 280 nm.
   </p>
   <title>
    Isolation and Identification of Putative Mona/Gads SH3C Binding Partners by Affinity Chromatography and Mass Spectrometry
   </title>
   <p>
    Jurkat T cells were grown in RPMI 1640 medium with 10% FBS and antibiotics. For generation of protein extracts, cells were pelleted by centrifugation and washed once with chilled PBS. Resulting cell pellets were kept on ice for 20 min and then lysed in 2 volumes of chilled RIPA buffer (20 mM TrisHCl [pH 7.5], 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% SDS, and 100 mM NaCl) supplemented with 1 × Complete™ (Roche). The lysate was nutated for 30 min in the cold and centrifuged for 30 min at 10,000 × g at 2°C; the supernatant was snap frozen. To isolate Mona/GadsSH3C binding proteins for MS analyses, 10 mg of protein extract were precleared twice for 2 hr each with 50 μg of GST immobilized on 20 μl of GSH beads, after which a further round of preclearing with GSH beads for 2 hr followed. Proteins remaining in the precleared supernatant were subjected to precipitation with 100 μg of GST-Mona/GadsSH3C overnight, followed by 3 high stringency washes with RIPA buffer containing 1 M NaCl. Precipitates were then size-separated by SDS-PAGE. As a control, a second sample was run in parallel, in which the known binding groove of Mona/GadsSH3C had been blocked by preincubation with a 50-fold molar excess of a SLP-76-derived peptide (PAPSIDRSTKPPL-amide). Surface staining of gel bands was done as described elsewhere (
    <a>
     Shevchenko et al., 1996
    </a>
    ). Bands cut from stained gels were sent to a specialist company for tryptic digest, MS, and bioinformatic analyses (Protana, Odense, Denmark).
   </p>
   <title>
    Peptide Synthesis for ITC and Crystallography
   </title>
   <p>
    C-terminally amidated peptides were synthesized using 9-fluorenylmethyloxycarbonyl for temporary α-amino group protection, cleaved from the resin, deprotected, freeze-dried, purified on a C8 RP column (Perkin Elmer Series 200 system), and analyzed for purity and mass on an Agilent 1100 LC-MS.
   </p>
   <title>
    Synthesis of Peptide Arrays
   </title>
   <p>
    Arrays were synthesized on a Multipep Synthesizer (Intavis Bioanalytical Instruments, Cologne, Germany) on derivatized cellulose (amino–Peg500 UC540, acid-hardened, loading 400 nmol/cm
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    ; Intavis). After peptides were spot-assembled and deprotected, membranes were washed extensively with dichlormethane, N-methylpyrolidone, and ethanol.
   </p>
   <title>
    Peptide Array SH3 Domain Overlay Blots
   </title>
   <p>
    Air-dried array membranes were wetted in ethanol for 10 s and washed twice for 10 min with TBST (20 mM TrisHCl [pH 7.5], 100 mM NaCl, and 0.1% [v/v] Tween 20) before blocking overnight at 4°C in TBST with 5% (w/v) dry skimmed milk and 0.1% (w/v) sodium azide. Membranes were first incubated overnight with 2.7 μg/ml GST in blocking buffer at 4°C to detect nonspecific tag binding, if any. After 3 × 10 min washes with TBST, an anti-GST mouse mAb (2C8-1-4; gift of Elisabeth Kremmer, Munich), or self-made rabbit polyclonal anti-GST—when undesirable background resulting from the mAb appeared—was added in blocking buffer overnight at 4°C. The membrane was washed as before with TBST and HRP-coupled secondary antibody in TBST was then added for 1 hr at room temperature. After TBST washes, bound GST was detected by ECL. To probe membranes subsequently with GST-Grb2SH3C, they were incubated as before with 3.3 μg/ml GST-Grb2-SH3 for epitope scanning arrays or with 20 μg/ml for permutation arrays. HD-PTP peptide arrays were probed with 1.25 μg/ml GST-Mona/GadsSH3C.
   </p>
   <title>
    Isothermal Titration Calorimetry
   </title>
   <p>
    ITC was performed with a VP-ITC MicroCalorimeter (MicroCal, Northampton, MA). Peptides were dissolved at 1 mM in ITC buffer (25 mM HEPES [pH 7.5, adjusted with potassium hydroxide], 100 mM potassium acetate, and 5 mM magnesium acetate), clarified by centrifugation for 10 min at 20,000 × g prior to use, degassed (ThermoVac; MicroCal), and titrated from a syringe (300 μl total volume) into a sample chamber holding 1.43 ml of clarified and degassed 0.1 mM GST-Grb2SH3C, or FPLC-purified Grb2SH3C in ITC buffer. Upon reaching the equilibrium temperature of 30°C, peptide solutions were titrated into the sample chamber by 28 injections of 10 μl each. Resulting peaks of measured deviations from the equilibrium temperature were integrated to yield the quantity of heat generated. Data were obtained using χ2 minimization on a model assuming a single set of sites to calculate the binding affinity K
    <sub>
     d
    </sub>
    . All steps of the data analysis were performed using ORIGIN (V5.0) software provided by the manufacturer. ITC using the GST-Mona/GadsSH3C has been previously described (
    <a>
     Harkiolaki et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Lewitzky et al., 2004
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    Crystallization Screens, Data Collection, Phasing, and Refinement
   </title>
   <p>
    Crystallization screens were conducted with the wild-type Grb2SH3C domain or the Grb2SH3C P212A mutant by mixing with peptides corresponding to Gab2a, Gab2b, or the Gab2a-related epitope in p27Kip1. Crystals were generated by the sitting drop vapor diffusion method at 21°C. Further details of crystals obtained, X-ray diffraction and model building are summarized in
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    Coordinates have been deposited in the PDB with accession codes 2VVK, 2VWF, 2W02, and 2W10.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Six Figures and Two Tables.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (815 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Arkin and Wells, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.R. Arkin, J.A. Wells
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Small-molecule inhibitors of protein-protein interactions: progressing towards the dream
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Drug Discov., 3 (2004), pp. 301–317
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Atatreh et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N. Atatreh, C. Stojkoski, P. Smith, G.W. Booker, C. Dive, A.D. Frenkel, S. Freeman, R.A. Bryce
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         In silico screening and biological evaluation of inhibitors of Src-SH3 domain interaction with a proline-rich ligand
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 18 (2008), pp. 1217–1222
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bennett et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.L. Bennett, T. Brummer, A. Jeanes, A.S. Yap, R.J. Daly
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab2 and Src co-operate in human mammary epithelial cells to promote growth factor independence and disruption of acinar morphogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 27 (2008), pp. 2693–2704
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bentires-Alj et al., 2006a
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Bentires-Alj, S.G. Gil, R. Chan, Z.C. Wang, Y. Wang, N. Imanaka, L.N. Harris, A. Richardson, B.G. Neel, H. Gu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A role for the scaffolding adapter GAB2 in breast cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Med., 12 (2006), pp. 114–121
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bentires-Alj et al., 2006b
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Bentires-Alj, M.I. Kontaridis, B.G. Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Stops along the RAS pathway in human genetic disease
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Med., 12 (2006), pp. 283–285
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Berrow et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        N.S. Berrow, D. Alderton, S. Sainsbury, J. Nettleship, R. Assenberg, N. Rahman, D.I. Stuart, R.J. Owens
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A versatile ligation-independent cloning method suitable for high-throughput expression screening applications
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nucleic Acids Res., 35 (2007), p. e45
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Betzi et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Betzi, A. Restouin, S. Opi, S.T. Arold, I. Parrot, F. Guerlesquin, X. Morelli, Y. Collette
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein protein interaction inhibition (2P2I) combining high throughput and virtual screening: Application to the HIV-1 Nef protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 104 (2007), pp. 19256–19261
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Bourgin et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Bourgin, R.P. Bourette, S. Arnaud, Y. Liu, L.R. Rohrschneider, G. Mouchiroud
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Induced expression and association of the Mona/Gads adapter and Gab3 scaffolding protein during monocyte/macrophage differentiation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 22 (2002), pp. 3744–3756
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Brummer et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Brummer, D. Schramek, V.M. Hayes, H.L. Bennett, C.E. Caldon, E.A. Musgrove, R.J. Daly
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Increased proliferation and altered growth factor dependence of human mammary epithelial cells overexpressing the Gab2 docking protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 281 (2006), pp. 626–637
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Castiglioni et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Castiglioni, J.A. Maier, M. Mariotti
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The tyrosine phosphatase HD-PTP: A novel player in endothelial migration
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 364 (2007), pp. 534–539
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Chu et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        I. Chu, J. Sun, A. Arnaout, H. Kahn, W. Hanna, S. Narod, P. Sun, C.K. Tan, L. Hengst, J. Slingerland
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         p27 phosphorylation by Src regulates inhibition of cyclin E-Cdk2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 128 (2007), pp. 281–294
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Daly et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.J. Daly, H. Gu, J. Parmar, S. Malaney, R.J. Lyons, R. Kairouz, D.R. Head, S.M. Henshall, B.G. Neel, R.L. Sutherland
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The docking protein Gab2 is overexpressed and estrogen regulated in human breast cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 21 (2002), pp. 5175–5181
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Dankort et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Dankort, B. Maslikowski, N. Warner, N. Kanno, H. Kim, Z. Wang, M.F. Moran, R.G. Oshima, R.D. Cardiff, W.J. Muller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Grb2 and Shc adapter proteins play distinct roles in Neu (ErbB-2)-induced mammary tumorigenesis: implications for human breast cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 21 (2001), pp. 1540–1551
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Defilippi et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P. Defilippi, P. Di Stefano, S. Cabodi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         p130Cas: a versatile scaffold in signaling networks
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Cell Biol., 16 (2006), pp. 257–263
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Doyotte et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Doyotte, A. Mironov, E. McKenzie, P. Woodman
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Bro1-related protein HD-PTP/PTPN23 is required for endosomal cargo sorting and multivesicular body morphogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 105 (2008), pp. 6308–6313
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feller and Lewitzky, 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.M. Feller, M. Lewitzky
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Potential disease targets for drugs that disrupt protein–protein interactions of Grb2 and Crk family adaptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Pharm. Des., 12 (2006), pp. 529–548
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feller et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.M. Feller, G. Tuchscherer, J. Voss
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         High affinity molecules disrupting GRB2 protein complexes as a therapeutic strategy for chronic myelogenous leukaemia
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Leuk. Lymphoma, 44 (2003), pp. 411–427
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Feller et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.M. Feller, H. Wecklein, M. Lewitzky, E. Kibler, T. Raabe
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3 domain-mediated binding of the Drk protein to Dos is an important step in signaling of
         <em>
          Drosophila
         </em>
         receptor tyrosine kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mech. Dev., 116 (2002), pp. 129–139
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Giubellino et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Giubellino, Y. Gao, S. Lee, M.J. Lee, J.R. Vasselli, S. Medepalli, J.B. Trepel, T.R. Burke Jr., D.P. Bottaro
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Inhibition of tumor metastasis by a growth factor receptor bound protein 2 Src homology 2 domain-binding antagonist
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 67 (2007), pp. 6012–6016
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gonzalez-Espinosa et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Gonzalez-Espinosa, S. Odom, A. Olivera, J.P. Hobson, M.E. Martinez, A. Oliveira-Dos-Santos, L. Barra, S. Spiegel, J.M. Penninger, J. Rivera
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Preferential signaling and induction of allergy-promoting lymphokines upon weak stimulation of the high affinity IgE receptor on mast cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Exp. Med., 197 (2003), pp. 1453–1465
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gril et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Gril, M. Vidal, F. Assayag, M.F. Poupon, W.Q. Liu, C. Garbay
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Grb2-SH3 ligand inhibits the growth of HER2+ cancer cells and has antitumor effects in human cancer xenografts alone and in combination with docetaxel
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Int. J. Cancer, 121 (2007), pp. 407–415
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Grimmler et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Grimmler, Y. Wang, T. Mund, Z. Cilensek, E.M. Keidel, M.B. Waddell, H. Jakel, M. Kullmann, R.W. Kriwacki, L. Hengst
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cdk-inhibitory activity and stability of p27Kip1 are directly regulated by oncogenic tyrosine kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 128 (2007), pp. 269–280
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gu and Neel, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Gu, B.G. Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The “Gab” in signal transduction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Cell Biol., 13 (2003), pp. 122–130
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gu et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Gu, J.C. Pratt, S.J. Burakoff, B.G. Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cloning of p97/Gab2, the major SHP2-binding protein in hematopoietic cells, reveals a novel pathway for cytokine-induced gene activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell, 2 (1998), pp. 729–740
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gu et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Gu, K. Saito, L.D. Klaman, J. Shen, T. Fleming, Y. Wang, J.C. Pratt, G. Lin, B. Lim, J.P. Kinet, B.G. Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Essential role for Gab2 in the allergic response
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 412 (2001), pp. 186–190
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Gu et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Gu, R.J. Botelho, M. Yu, S. Grinstein, B.G. Neel
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Critical role for scaffolding adapter Gab2 in Fc gamma R-mediated phagocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 161 (2003), pp. 1151–1161
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Harkiolaki et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Harkiolaki, M. Lewitzky, R.J. Gilbert, E.Y. Jones, R.P. Bourette, G. Mouchiroud, H. Sondermann, I. Moarefi, S.M. Feller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural basis for SH3 domain-mediated high-affinity binding between Mona/Gads and SLP-76
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 22 (2003), pp. 2571–2582
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hashimoto et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Hashimoto, M. Hirose, A. Hashimoto, M. Morishige, A. Yamada, H. Hosaka, K. Akagi, E. Ogawa, C. Oneyama, T. Agatsuma,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Targeting AMAP1 and cortactin binding bearing an atypical src homology 3/proline interface for prevention of breast cancer invasion and metastasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 103 (2006), pp. 7036–7041
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Itoh et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Itoh, Y. Yoshida, K. Nishida, M. Narimatsu, M. Hibi, T. Hirano
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role of Gab1 in heart, placenta, and skin development and growth factor- and cytokine-induced extracellular signal-regulated kinase mitogen-activated protein kinase activation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 20 (2000), pp. 3695–3704
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Janes et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.W. Janes, R.J. Daly, A. deFazio, R.L. Sutherland
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Activation of the Ras signalling pathway in human breast cancer cells overexpressing erbB-2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 9 (1994), pp. 3601–3608
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kallin et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Kallin, J.B. Demoulin, K. Nishida, T. Hirano, L. Ronnstrand, C.H. Heldin
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab1 contributes to cytoskeletal reorganization and chemotaxis in response to platelet-derived growth factor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 17897–17904
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kaneko et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Kaneko, T. Kumasaka, T. Ganbe, T. Sato, K. Miyazawa, N. Kitamura, N. Tanaka
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Structural insight into modest binding of a non-PXXP ligand to the signal transducing adaptor molecule-2 Src homology 3 domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 48162–48168
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Kardinal et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Kardinal, M. Dangers, A. Kardinal, A. Koch, D.T. Brandt, T. Tamura, K. Welte
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tyrosine phosphorylation modulates binding preference to cyclin-dependent kinases and subcellular localization of p27Kip1 in the acute promyelocytic leukemia cell line NB4
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Blood, 107 (2006), pp. 1133–1140
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ke et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Ke, D. Wu, F. Princen, T. Nguyen, Y. Pang, J. Lesperance, W.J. Muller, R.G. Oshima, G.S. Feng
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role of Gab2 in mammary tumorigenesis and metastasis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 26 (2007), pp. 4951–4960
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lamothe et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Lamothe, M. Yamada, U. Schaeper, W. Birchmeier, I. Lax, J. Schlessinger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The docking protein Gab1 is an essential component of an indirect mechanism for fibroblast growth factor stimulation of the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt antiapoptotic pathway
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 24 (2004), pp. 5657–5666
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lewitzky, 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Lewitzky, M. (2005) Signalling through small SH2/SH3 adaptor proteins of the Grb2 family. D.Phil. Thesis, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lewitzky et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Lewitzky, M. Harkiolaki, M.C. Domart, E.Y. Jones, S.M. Feller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mona/Gads SH3C binding to hematopoietic progenitor kinase 1 (HPK1) combines an atypical SH3 binding motif, R/KXXK, with a classical PXXP motif embedded in a polyproline type II (PPII) helix
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 279 (2004), pp. 28724–28732
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lewitzky et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Lewitzky, C. Kardinal, N.H. Gehring, E.K. Schmidt, B. Konkol, M. Eulitz, W. Birchmeier, U. Schaeper, S.M. Feller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The C-terminal SH3 domain of the adapter protein Grb2 binds with high affinity to sequences in Gab1 and SLP-76 which lack the SH3-typical P-x-x-P core motif
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 20 (2001), pp. 1052–1062
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lim et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.J. Lim, G. Lopez-Berestein, M.C. Hung, R. Lupu, A.M. Tari
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Grb2 downregulation leads to Akt inactivation in heregulin-stimulated and ErbB2-overexpressing breast cancer cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 19 (2000), pp. 6271–6276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref39'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Linnekin et al., 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Linnekin, G. Evans, D. Michiel, W.L. Farrar
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Characterization of a 97-kDa phosphotyrosylprotein regulated by multiple cytokines
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 267 (1992), pp. 23993–23998
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref40'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu and Rohrschneider, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Liu, L.R. Rohrschneider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The gift of Gab
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FEBS Lett., 515 (2002), pp. 1–7
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref41'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Liu et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Liu, B. Jenkins, J.L. Shin, L.R. Rohrschneider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Scaffolding protein Gab2 mediates differentiation signaling downstream of Fms receptor tyrosine kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 21 (2001), pp. 3047–3056
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref42'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lock et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.S. Lock, I. Royal, M.A. Naujokas, M. Park
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification of an atypical Grb2 carboxyl-terminal SH3 domain binding site in Gab docking proteins reveals Grb2-dependent and -independent recruitment of Gab1 to receptor tyrosine kinases
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 275 (2000), pp. 31536–31545
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref43'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lock et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.S. Lock, C.R. Maroun, M.A. Naujokas, M. Park
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distinct recruitment and function of Gab1 and Gab2 in Met receptor-mediated epithelial morphogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Biol. Cell, 13 (2002), pp. 2132–2146
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref44'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lock et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.S. Lock, M.M. Frigault, C. Saucier, M. Park
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Grb2-independent recruitment of Gab1 requires the C-terminal lobe and structural integrity of the Met receptor kinase domain
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 30083–30090
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref45'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Menard et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Menard, S.M. Pupa, M. Campiglio, E. Tagliabue
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biologic and therapeutic role of HER2 in cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogene, 22 (2003), pp. 6570–6578
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref46'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Moasser et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M.M. Moasser, A. Basso, S.D. Averbuch, N. Rosen
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The tyrosine kinase inhibitor ZD1839 (“Iressa”) inhibits HER2-driven signaling and suppresses the growth of HER2-overexpressing tumor cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 61 (2001), pp. 7184–7188
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref47'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nakaoka et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Nakaoka, K. Nishida, M. Narimatsu, A. Kamiya, T. Minami, H. Sawa, K. Okawa, Y. Fujio, T. Koyama, M. Maeda,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab family proteins are essential for postnatal maintenance of cardiac function via neuregulin-1/ErbB signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Clin. Invest., 117 (2007), pp. 1771–1781
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref48'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nishida et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Nishida, Y. Yoshida, M. Itoh, T. Fukada, T. Ohtani, T. Shirogane, T. Atsumi, M. Takahashi-Tezuka, K. Ishihara, M. Hibi, T. Hirano
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab-family adapter proteins act downstream of cytokine and growth factor receptors and T- and B-cell antigen receptors
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Blood, 93 (1999), pp. 1809–1816
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref49'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Nishida et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Nishida, L. Wang, E. Morii, S.J. Park, M. Narimatsu, S. Itoh, S. Yamasaki, M. Fujishima, K. Ishihara, M. Hibi,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Requirement of Gab2 for mast cell development and KitL/c-Kit signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Blood, 99 (2002), pp. 1866–1869
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref50'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         O'Neill et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.M. O'Neill, S.J. Fashena, E.A. Golemis
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Integrin signalling: a new Cas(t) of characters enters the stage
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Cell Biol., 10 (2000), pp. 111–119
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref51'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Oltersdorf et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Oltersdorf, S.W. Elmore, A.R. Shoemaker, R.C. Armstrong, D.J. Augeri, B.A. Belli, M. Bruncko, T.L. Deckwerth, J. Dinges, P.J. Hajduk,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         An inhibitor of Bcl-2 family proteins induces regression of solid tumours
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 435 (2005), pp. 677–681
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref52'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pendergast et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.M. Pendergast, L.A. Quilliam, L.D. Cripe, C.H. Bassing, Z. Dai, N. Li, A. Batzer, K.M. Rabun, C.J. Der, J. Schlessinger,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         BCR-ABL-induced oncogenesis is mediated by direct interaction with the SH2 domain of the GRB-2 adaptor protein
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cell, 75 (1993), pp. 175–185
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref53'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rosario and Birchmeier, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Rosario, W. Birchmeier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         How to make tubes: signaling by the Met receptor tyrosine kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Cell Biol., 13 (2003), pp. 328–335
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref54'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sachs et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Sachs, H. Brohmann, D. Zechner, T. Muller, J. Hulsken, I. Walther, U. Schaeper, C. Birchmeier, W. Birchmeier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Essential role of Gab1 for signaling by the c-Met receptor in vivo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 150 (2000), pp. 1375–1384
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref55'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sakkab et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Sakkab, M. Lewitzky, G. Posern, U. Schaeper, M. Sachs, W. Birchmeier, S.M. Feller
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Signaling of hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor (HGF) to the small GTPase Rap1 via the large docking protein Gab1 and the adapter protein CRKL
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 275 (2000), pp. 10772–10778
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref56'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sattler et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Sattler, M.G. Mohi, Y.B. Pride, L.R. Quinnan, N.A. Malouf, K. Podar, F. Gesbert, H. Iwasaki, S. Li, R.A. Van Etten,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Critical role for Gab2 in transformation by BCR/ABL
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 1 (2002), pp. 479–492
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref57'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schaeper et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        U. Schaeper, R. Vogel, J. Chmielowiec, J. Huelsken, M. Rosario, W. Birchmeier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distinct requirements for Gab1 in Met and EGF receptor signaling in vivo
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 104 (2007), pp. 15376–15381
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref58'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Schimmer et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.D. Schimmer, K. Welsh, C. Pinilla, Z. Wang, M. Krajewska, M.J. Bonneau, I.M. Pedersen, S. Kitada, F.L. Scott, B. Bailly-Maitre,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Small-molecule antagonists of apoptosis suppressor XIAP exhibit broad antitumor activity
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Cell, 5 (2004), pp. 25–35
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref59'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Seiffert et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Seiffert, J.M. Custodio, I. Wolf, M. Harkey, Y. Liu, J.N. Blattman, P.D. Greenberg, L.R. Rohrschneider
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab3-deficient mice exhibit normal development and hematopoiesis and are immunocompetent
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 23 (2003), pp. 2415–2424
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref60'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sesti et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G. Sesti, M. Federici, M.L. Hribal, D. Lauro, P. Sbraccia, R. Lauro
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Defects of the insulin receptor substrate (IRS) system in human metabolic disorders
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         FASEB J., 15 (2001), pp. 2099–2111
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref61'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Shevchenko et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Shevchenko, M. Wilm, O. Vorm, M. Mann
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mass spectrometric sequencing of proteins silver-stained polyacrylamide gels
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anal. Chem., 68 (1996), pp. 850–858
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref62'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Thirone et al., 2006
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.C. Thirone, C. Huang, A. Klip
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tissue-specific roles of IRS proteins in insulin signaling and glucose transport
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Endocrinol. Metab., 17 (2006), pp. 72–78
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref63'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Toyooka et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Toyooka, M. Ouchida, Y. Jitsumori, K. Tsukuda, A. Sakai, A. Nakamura, N. Shimizu, K. Shimizu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         HD-PTP: A novel protein tyrosine phosphatase gene on human chromosome 3p21.3
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 278 (2000), pp. 671–678
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref64'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Tsirka, 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Tsirka, T. (2008) Characterisation of the interactions mediated by C-terminal Src homology 3 domains of the Grb2 family adaptors. M.Sc. Thesis, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref65'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Vassilev, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.T. Vassilev
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         MDM2 inhibitors for cancer therapy
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Trends Mol. Med., 13 (2007), pp. 23–31
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref66'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wada et al., 2005
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Wada, T. Nakashima, A.J. Oliveira-dos-Santos, J. Gasser, H. Hara, G. Schett, J.M. Penninger
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The molecular scaffold Gab2 is a crucial component of RANK signaling and osteoclastogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Med., 11 (2005), pp. 394–399
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref67'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Weidner et al., 1996
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K.M. Weidner, S. Di Cesare, M. Sachs, V. Brinkmann, J. Behrens, W. Birchmeier
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Interaction between Gab1 and the c-Met receptor tyrosine kinase is responsible for epithelial morphogenesis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 384 (1996), pp. 173–176
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref68'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wells and McClendon, 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.A. Wells, C.L. McClendon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Reaching for high-hanging fruit in drug discovery at protein-protein interfaces
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 450 (2007), pp. 1001–1009
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref69'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         White et al., 2008
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.W. White, A.D. Westwell, G. Brahemi
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Protein-protein interactions as targets for small-molecule therapeutics in cancer
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Expert Rev. Mol. Med., 10 (2008), p. e8
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref70'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wickrema et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Wickrema, S. Uddin, A. Sharma, F. Chen, Y. Alsayed, S. Ahmad, S.T. Sawyer, G. Krystal, T. Yi, K. Nishada,
        <em>
         et al.
        </em>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Engagement of Gab1 and Gab2 in erythropoietin signaling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 24469–24474
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref71'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yamasaki et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Yamasaki, K. Nishida, M. Sakuma, D. Berry, C.J. McGlade, T. Hirano, T. Saito
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gads/Grb2-mediated association with LAT is critical for the inhibitory function of Gab2 in T cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Cell. Biol., 23 (2003), pp. 2515–2529
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref72'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yang et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.Y. Yang, B.P. Zhou, M.C. Hung, M.H. Lee
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Oncogenic signals of HER-2/neu in regulating the stability of the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p27
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 275 (2000), pp. 24735–24739
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref73'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yuan et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Yuan, L. Qin, D. Liu, R.C. Wu, P. Mussi, S. Zhou, Z. Songyang, J. Xu
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genetic screening reveals an essential role of p27kip1 in restriction of breast cancer progression
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cancer Res., 67 (2007), pp. 8032–8042
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref74'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhang et al., 2007
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Zhang, E. Diaz-Flores, G. Li, Z. Wang, Z. Kang, E. Haviernikova, S. Rowe, C.-K. Qu, W. Tse, K.M. Shannon, K.D. Bunting
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Abnormal hematopoiesis in Gab2 mutant mice
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Blood, 110 (2007), pp. 116–124
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref75'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Zhao et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Zhao, D.H. Yu, R. Shen, G.S. Feng
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Gab2, a new pleckstrin homology domain-containing adapter protein, acts to uncouple signaling from ERK kinase to Elk-1
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 274 (1999), pp. 19649–19654
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref76'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>