<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2005.10.021
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    TTP Specifically Regulates the Internalization of the Transferrin Receptor
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    Clathrin-coated pits (CCP), responsible for a major modality of internalization of plasma membrane (PM) receptors, are assembled from a basic hardware of clathrin, and clathrin adaptors. Clathrin adaptors are scaffold organizers that simultaneously bind to clathrin, lipids, and to endocytic signals present in cargo molecules (
    <a>
     Conner and Schmid, 2003b
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Sorkin, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Traub, 2003
    </a>
    ). Clathrin molecules are thus recruited to the PM and polymerize into a polygonal lattice, which progresses to a deeply invaginated pit. A fully invaginated CCP then constricts and is pinched off the PM, giving rise to a clathrin-coated vesicle (CCV), through the action of the GTPase dynamin (
    <a>
     Orth and McNiven, 2003
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Praefcke and McMahon, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Song and Schmid, 2003
    </a>
    ). Many other “accessory” proteins are thought to contribute to the spatial/temporal regulation of endocytosis (
    <a>
     Slepnev and De Camilli, 2000
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    There is good biochemical evidence that endocytosis of different cargoes, through CCP, is differentially controlled. The epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), the transferrin receptor (TfR), and the low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLR) are all internalized through saturable pathways, which however are not competitive (
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wiley, 1988
    </a>
    ). In part, this differential control is achieved via cargo-specific adaptors. The heterotetrameric complex AP-2 had been long thought to be the major clathrin adaptor. However, the notion of the “centrality” of AP-2 has been challenged, since its functional ablation had far more dramatic effects on TfR than on EGFR internalization (
    <a>
     Hinrichsen et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Motley et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). Similarly, overexpression of AAK1 (adaptor-associated kinase 1), which probably operates by functionally sequestering AP-2, inhibited endocytosis of the TfR and of the LRP (low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein), but not of the EGFR (
    <a>
     Conner and Schmid, 2003a
    </a>
    ). Thus, molecules other than AP-2 might serve as adaptors. These include ARH, disabled-2, and possibly Numb (
    <a>
     Sorkin, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Traub, 2003
    </a>
    ). Ubiquitin binding endocytic proteins, such as epsin, might also function as adaptors, due to their ability to bind to ubiquitinated cargo molecules, lipids and clathrin (
    <a>
     Wang and Struhl, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wendland, 2002
    </a>
    ). Thus, “cocktails” of adaptors, which may vary in different cells and for various cargoes, seem to be involved in optimal coupling of receptors to clathrin.
   </p>
   <p>
    The relevance and impact of these alternative adaptor mechanisms, is far from being clear. For instance, the functional ablation of AP-2 diminishes the density of CCP by more than 90% (
    <a>
     Motley et al., 2003
    </a>
    ). This suggests that while alternate adaptors can sustain internalization in the absence of AP-2, the process might still require AP-2, under physiological conditions. The notion is further supported by findings that in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    the putative adaptor function of Numb is clearly exerted upstream of AP-2 (
    <a>
     Berdnik et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). The extent to which CCP are biochemically and functionally heterogeneous in the same cell is also unclear. The adaptors alone are unlikely to account completely, on the basis of present knowledge, for the mechanism of specific cargo selection. This role might be exerted, at least in part, by “accessory” endocytic proteins, as shown for instance by findings that tyrosine phosphorylation of eps15, but not eps15 itself, is required for EGFR, but not for TfR, internalization (
    <a>
     Confalonieri et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). Here we describe an endocytic “accessory” protein, TTP, which is involved in the control of internalization of the TfR, but not of the EGFR or of the LDLR. TTP might represent one of the long sought for rate-limiting molecules that allow cargo-specific control of clathrin-mediated endocytosis.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Identification and Characterization of TTP
   </title>
   <p>
    In the course of a screening to identify EH-interacting proteins, we cloned a cDNA [corresponding to a previously described cDNA, named SH3BP4 (
    <a>
     Dunlevy et al., 1999
    </a>
    ), GenBank acc. NM 014521; the sequence of our cDNA is deposited with the accession number DQ232895] predicting a protein of 963 amino acids (107.5 KDa). The predicted protein displays, from N- to C terminus, a putative clathrin binding site, a SH3 domain, three NPF (asparagine-proline-phenylalanine) repeats, responsible for the interaction with the EH domain, a putative AP-2 binding site (WXXF), and a short coiled-coil region (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    A). We named this protein TTP (
    <span>
     T
    </span>
    ransferrin receptor
    <span>
     T
    </span>
    rafficking
    <span>
     P
    </span>
    rotein) for reasons that will become subsequently clear. Anti-TTP polyclonal antibodies (Ab) specifically identified a ∼103 KDa band that: i) was recognized by two Ab directed against different epitopes, ii) was enriched in immunoprecipitation-immunoblot experiments, iii) was competed by the immunizing antigen, iv) comigrated with a HA-tagged version of the protein (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    B), and v) was abolished by specific RNA interference (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Interaction of TTP with Endocytic Proteins and Its Localization in Endocytic ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig1" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (966 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    As predicted from its signatures, TTP could be coimmunoprecipitated with either eps15 or clathrin or AP-2 (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    C). In addition, TTP eluted from size columns as a complex of at least 500 KDa (not shown), suggesting that it might be involved in multiple protein:protein interactions. In these complexes, TTP might be present as a dimer/multimer, as show by coimmunoprecipitation of FLAG-tagged and HA-tagged TTP, expressed in HeLa cells (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    D).
   </p>
   <p>
    By indirect immunofluorescence (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E), endogenous TTP displayed a punctate staining, with reinforcement of the signal at the periphery of the cell and at the PM. These signals were strongly reduced upon knockdown (KD) of the protein confirming their specificity (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    E). Some nuclear staining was also detected, which however was scarcely sensitive to KD, thus probably representing nonspecific staining.
   </p>
   <p>
    By quantitative immunoelectron microscopy (immuno-EM), we characterized the subcellular distribution of TTP (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F,
    <a>
     Table S1
    </a>
    ). Analysis of TTP-specific signals (obtained by comparing TTP-KD to control cells) revealed that TTP is roughly equally partitioned between CCP, CCV and the “linear” PM. When the signals were corrected for the extension of these organelles, TTP was ∼30-fold enriched in CCP and CCV, with respect to the linear PM (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    F). Little, if any, TTP was detected in the Golgi apparatus and, more importantly, in endosomes. By confocal microscopy, we were also unable to detect significant colocalization of TTP with the endosomal marker EEA1, or with the TfR in the endosomal compartment (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Data
    </a>
    available with this article online). These results indicate that TTP is highly enriched in CCP and remains associated with endocytic organelles for a limited phase of their biogenesis. Finally, there was intense nuclear staining, which was again scarcely sensitive to KD. While we cannot exclude that a minor fraction of TTP is localized to the nucleus, the sum of our data argues against a major nuclear localization. In this regard, it is of note that ectopically expressed TTP did not show appreciable nuclear localization (see
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <p>
    We further characterized, by immuno-EM, TTP-containing CCP and CCV (
    <a>
     Figure 1
    </a>
    G). Surprisingly, while we could easily colocalize TTP in TfR- containing CCP/CCV, we did not detect any TTP staining in EGFR-containing organelles. A mutant TTP, devoid of the SH3 domain (TTPΔSH3), while still associated with the PM (see
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A), could not be localized to TfR-CCP/CCV. In addition, while the isolated TTP-SH3 domain localized to TfR-containing organelles (but not to EGFR-containing ones), a mutant SH3, harboring a W→A substitution (SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    ), did not localize to CCP/CCV. We concluded that TTP specifically localizes to TfR-CCP/CCV, through interactions mediated by its SH3 domain. TTP might be additionally directed to the PM by regions other than the SH3 (see TTPΔSH3,
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    A), which were not further investigated; one obvious possibility is that NPF-mediated interactions, with EH-containing proteins can contribute to the localization of TTP at the PM.
   </p>
   <p>
    Finally, we used total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy (TIRF) to examine the colocalization of TTP with clathrin and various receptors. There was good colocalization of TTP with TfR (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    A) and clathrin (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    B), but little if any colocalization with the EGFR (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    C) or the LDLR (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    D). We also detected good triple TTP/TfR/clathrin colocalization (
    <a>
     Figure 2
    </a>
    E). Of note, in panel E (which represents cells not stimulated with EGF) almost all clathrin dots colocalized with TTP. When experiments were performed in the presence of EGF, clathrin dots were readily detectable, which colocalized with EGFR but not with TTP (data not shown).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Colocalization of TTP with Receptors and ClathrinHeLa cells were transfected ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig2" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1589 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <title>
    The Perturbation of TTP Selectively Affects TfR Internalization
   </title>
   <p>
    The above results suggest a specific role for TTP in a subset of clathrin-dependent endocytic reactions. To test this hypothesis, we performed RNA interference (KD). A specific siRNA decreased TTP levels by more than 80% in HeLa cells (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A). This resulted in a significant decrease in endocytosis of the TfR, but not of the EGFR of the LDLR, (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B, 3C,
    <a>
     S2
    </a>
    , and
    <a>
     S3
    </a>
    ). We then performed overexpression experiments. A 3- to 5-fold overexpression of TTP (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    A) resulted in a strong reduction of TfR endocytosis, while leaving endocytosis of the EGFR or of the LDLR unperturbed (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B, 3C, and
    <a>
     S4
    </a>
    ). Kinetic assays performed with
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-Tf or
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-EGF (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    D and 3E) confirmed the specificity of the effects for TfR internalization, with ∼3-fold decrease in the internalization rate constant (Ke) for this receptor (
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Perturbation of TTP Specifically Alters the Internalization of TfR(A) IB, with ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig3" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (801 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    These results are compatible with the possibility that TTP is part of the machinery that selectively controls the internalization of TfR. If so, then surface molecules known to compete with TfR for internalization, such as LAMP-1 (
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), might also be affected by the KD of TTP. Indeed, in TTP-KD cells there was a significant reduction of LAMP-1 internalization, which was comparable to that observed for the TfR (
    <a>
     Figure S6
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The reduction in the internalization rate of TfR resulted in an increase in the steady-state levels of surface TfR but not of the EGFR (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    F). Finally, neither the overexpression of TTP, nor its KD, affected the kinetics of recycling of the TfR (
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    G). Consistently with this latter finding, TTP did not show appreciable colocalization with Rab11, which marks recycling endosomes (
    <a>
     Figure S1
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <title>
    The Effects of TTP on Endocytosis Depend on Its SH3 and Are Rescued by Dynamin
   </title>
   <p>
    Since the SH3 domain of TTP dictates the localization of the holoprotein in TfR-containing pits, we investigated whether the TTP-exerted inhibition of TfR endocytosis is also dependent on an intact SH3 domain. The expression of an isolated TTP-SH3 inhibited TfR endocytosis almost as efficiently as full length TTP, while leaving internalization of the EGFR unperturbed (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A and 4B). In addition, the TTPΔSH3 mutant, and the mutated SH3, SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    , did not interfere with TfR endocytosis (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    A, 4B, and
    <a>
     S7
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="The Biological Activity of TTP Depends on its SH3 and Is Reversed by Dynamin(A) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr4.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr4.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr4.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr4.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig4" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1215 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Clues as to the molecular mechanism of action of TTP derived from EM analysis. In TTP-overexpressing cells, a significant proportion of CCP displayed an aberrant morphology, consisting of elongated pits joined to the PM by “long necks” (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). These structures closely resembled those induced by the dominant negative mutant of dynamin, DynK44A (
    <a>
     Damke et al., 1994
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). However, the effect of TTP was more selective than that of DynK44A, since TTP-induced “long neck” structures contained frequently the TfR, but not the EGFR (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    D). In addition, while the DynK44A mutant interfered with caveolar endocytosis, giving rise to the typical “grape-shaped” clusters of caveolae (
    <a>
     Henley et al., 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C), such structures could not be observed in TTP transfectants (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). Thus, ultrastructural studies confirmed the specificity of TTP for TfR endocytosis.
   </p>
   <p>
    The similarity between the “long necks” induced by TTP and DynK44A suggested that excess TTP might directly or indirectly interfere with the function of dynamin. If so, then the effect of TTP should be rescued by overexpression of dynamin. Indeed, upon overexpression of dynamin II in HeLa cells, the TTP-induced (and the TTP-SH3-induced) block in TfR internalization was reverted (
    <a>
     Figures 4
    </a>
    E and 4F).
   </p>
   <title>
    Functional Ablation of TTP Causes Reduction in Loading and Size of TfR-CCV
   </title>
   <p>
    At variance with its condition of overexpression, the KD of TTP KD did not result in significant formation of aberrant CCP (
    <a>
     Figure 4
    </a>
    C). This indicates that TTP overexpression or its ablation cause inhibition of TfR internalization through mechanisms that must be divergent, at least in part.
   </p>
   <p>
    To gain insights into this issue, we investigated, by immuno-EM, alterations induced by the TTP-KD in the internalization of the TfR. The ablation of TTP caused an increase in the total PM staining for TfR, consistent with the saturation binding assays in
    <a>
     Figure 3
    </a>
    F, but also a significant redistribution of the TfR, which appeared less concentrated in CCP (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    A). In addition, the number of TfR-CCP/CCV was reduced by ∼2- to 3-fold in TTP-KD cells, while the distribution of the EGFR was unchanged (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    B). Next, we analyzed 100 CCP and 100 CCV, immunogold labeled with Ab to TfR or EGFR, and counted the number of gold particles per organelle. There was a clear decrease in TfR loading, but not in EGFR loading, in TTP KD cells (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    C). In addition, the average diameter of TfR-CCV, but not of EGFR-CCV was reduced, by ∼40%, in TTP KD cells (
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    D). It is of note that the total number of CCP and CCV per cell was comparable between TTP-KD and control cells, indicating that the effects in TfR-containing pits were not due to major alterations in the mechanism of formation of these organelle (see legend to
    <a>
     Figure 5
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Knockdown of TTP Specifically Alters Loading and Size of TfR-Containing ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig5" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1259 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    There is controversy as to whether TfR and EGFR are internalized through the same coated pit, an issue that is distinct from the differential regulation of their internalization (
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1998
    </a>
    ). Earlier studies [see (
    <a>
     Lamaze et al., 1993
    </a>
    ) and references within] favored the “same pit” scenario, while more recent findings (
    <a>
     Stang et al., 2004
    </a>
    ) argued a “separate pits” (at least in part) picture. The resolution of this issue is, obviously, relevant to our findings, which are more immediately reconcilable with the latter possibility. Thus, we performed double immuno-EM analysis with anti-EGFR and anti-TfR Ab. We analyzed 100 CCV and found that 11 contained both receptors, while 56 and 33 contained TfR or EGFR alone, respectively (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    E, left, and
    <a>
     S8
    </a>
    ). In another experiment, we isolated vesicles and subjected them to double immuno-EM analysis, with results comparable to the previous method (
    <a>
     Figures 5
    </a>
    E, right/top, and
    <a>
     S8
    </a>
    ). In addition we analyzed, by TIRF, the colocalization of EGFR, TfR, and LDLR, on the cell surface. The three receptors exhibited varying degrees of colocalization, which did not exceed ∼10%–30% (
    <a>
     Figure S8
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    The sum of our results, therefore, favors the possibility that EGFR and TfR are internalized, by and large, through separate pits, and that TTP controls cargo loading in TfR-CCP.
   </p>
   <title>
    TTP Interacts with Dynamin
   </title>
   <p>
    Many endocytic SH3-containing proteins interact with the proline-rich region (PRD) of dynamin. In addition, overexpression of dynamin rescued the block by TTP on TfR endocytosis. Thus, we analyzed whether TTP interacts with dynamin. By TIRF, we found good colocalization between TTP and dynamin (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    A). In addition, TTP and dynamin could be coimmunoprecipitated from mouse brain lysates or HeLa cell lysates (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    B). In pull down experiments, GST-TTP-SH3 was able to bind to dynamin II, while GST-SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    (carrying the W→A mutation) did not bind (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C). Finally, GST-TTP-SH3 could directly bind to dynamin purified from rat brain, while GST-TTP-SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    did not (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    C). Thus, TTP and dynamin interact directly through the SH3 of TTP.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="TTP Interacts with Dynamin via Its SH3(A) Colocalization between TTP (red) and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr6.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr6.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr6.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr6.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig6" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (541 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Functional assays further confirmed the TTP:dynamin interaction. We performed an in vitro assay of liposome-stimulated dynamin GTPase activity. Both purified TTP and TTP-SH3, but not TTP-SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    , inhibited the GTPase activity of dynamin. The extent of inhibition was comparable to that exerted by endophilin or its isolated SH3, both known inhibitors of the dynamin GTPase (
    <a>
     Simpson et al., 1999
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 6
    </a>
    D). It is to be cautioned that the effect of SH3-containing proteins on the GTPase activity of dynamin can vary, as a function of protein concentrations and experimental conditions (
    <a>
     Yoshida et al., 2004
    </a>
    ). Thus, a minimalistic interpretation of our results is that the effect of TTP on dynamin function confirms their direct interaction. However, together with the biological data, our findings also suggest that TTP might act, at least in part, by controlling the GTPase activity of dynamin.
   </p>
   <title>
    TfR and Dynamin Compete for Binding to TTP
   </title>
   <p>
    As shown in
    <a>
     Figure 7 [ protein] [ kd]
    </a>
    A, TTP and the TfR could be coimmunoprecipitated. The interaction was mediated by the SH3 of TTP, as shown by lack of coimmunoprecipitation between the TfR and the HA-TTPΔSH3 mutant, or the HA-SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    mutant, whereas the HA-SH3 protein (isolated TTP-SH3) was able to interact in vivo with the TfR (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    B). Finally, there was no coimmunoprecipitation between TTP and the EGFR (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    B).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Regulation of the TTP:Dynamin Interaction(A) HeLa lysates were IP/IB with the ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr7.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr7.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr7.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr7.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig7" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (613 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    It is of note that the intracytoplasmic portion of TfR does not display a “canonical” binding consensus for SH3 domains. However, some SH3s have been shown to bind to noncanonical consensi [see for instance (
    <a>
     Mongiovi et al., 1999
    </a>
    )]. This seems to be the case also for TTP, as shown by experiments in which the isolated GST-TTP-SH3 could bind to the pure, recombinantly produced, intracellular fragment of the TfR (TfRcyt,
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    C). We concluded that the binding of TTP to the TfR is direct and mediated by the TTP-SH3.
   </p>
   <p>
    Since both dynamin and the TfR interacted with the SH3 of TTP, we sought to understand whether a hierarchy of interactions exists. We determined the kinetic parameters of the TTP:TfR and TTP:dynamin interactions, by plasmon surface resonance. In order to do this, we used pure TfRcyt, and the proline-rich-region (PRD) of dynamin II, which is known to bind to SH3-containing proteins (
    <a>
     Okamoto et al., 1997
    </a>
    ). The PRD displayed a 10-fold higher binding affinity to TTP-SH3, than TfRcyt (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    D). In addition, dynamin and TfR competed for the same binding site on the SH3 of TTP, as shown by in vitro binding experiments, in which the PRD could efficiently displace the binding of TfRcyt to the TTP-SH3 (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    E).
   </p>
   <title>
    Regulation of the TTP:Dynamin Interaction by Tyrosine Phosphorylation
   </title>
   <p>
    A possible paradox emerged from the previous set of results. TTP is localized only in TfR-CCP, however dynamin is present in all CCP, which would apparently negate the possibility of a specific localization of TTP.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    We sought for insights into this issue, by employing the EGFR model. We reasoned that, in the case of RTKs, tyrosine phosphorylation of TTP and/or dynamin, might prevent their interaction, thus excluding TTP from RTK-containing pits. Indeed, active EGFRs tyrosine-phosphorylate dynamin, in a process that seems to be important in the activation of the fission activity of dynamin (
    <a>
     Ahn et al., 2002
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <p>
    We used GST-TTP-SH3 to pull down dynamin from lysates of cells treated or not with EGF. While total dynamin could be readily recovered, tyrosine phosphorylated dynamin could not (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F, GST-TTP-SH3 lanes). As a further control, we eluted from GST-TTP-SH3 all bound proteins and immunoprecipitated them with anti-dynamin (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F, lanes TTP-SH3/IP Dyn). Also in this case, no pTyr-containing dynamin could be recovered. Conversely, an isolated SH3 from endophilin, used as a control, was able to interact with both unphosphorylated and tyrosine-phosphorylated dynamin (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    F).
   </p>
   <p>
    We tested whether TTP is a substrate for the EGFR kinase. EGF stimulation induced tyrosine phosphorylation of TTP with a rapid and sustained kinetic (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    G). Tyrosine-phosphorylated TTP could not interact with dynamin. As shown in
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H, the PRD of dynamin was able to pull down Flag-TTP from cellular lysates, albeit no pTyr-containing band migrating in the region of TTP could be detected (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H, lanes PRD). We eluted the material bound to the PRD and immunoprecipitated it with an anti-Flag (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H, lanes PRD/IP Flag). In these immunoprecipitates, TTP was present at levels comparable to those obtained in the direct anti-Flag immunoprecipitation (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H, upper panel), however, no pTyr-containing TTP could be detected (
    <a>
     Figure 7
    </a>
    H, lower panel). Thus, EGFR-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of either dynamin or TTP might prevent their interaction in vivo, providing a possible explanation for the exclusion of TTP from EGFR-containing CCP.
   </p>
   <p>
    Such a mechanism could in principle be extended to other RTKs, and also to caveolar internalization, in which activation of tyrosine kinases is required (
    <a>
     Pelkmans et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). It remains to be established whether in other cases, such that of the LDLR which is unaffected by perturbation of TTP, similar mechanisms of TTP-exclusion are at play. We note that the tyrosine kinase inhibitor genistein profoundly affected the internalization of LDLR, but not of the TfR (
    <a>
     Figure S9
    </a>
    ). Thus, the possibility that TTP is also excluded from LDLR-CCP through a kinase-dependent mechanism, while warranting further investigation, is plausible.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Discussion
   </title>
   <p>
    Studies of the kinetics of internalization of different PM receptors predicted the existence of cargo-specific (and rate-limiting) molecular machinery in clathrin-mediated internalization (
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1997
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Warren et al., 1998
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Wiley, 1988
    </a>
    ). A share-a-ware mechanism, in which different adaptors concur to the formulation of different “cocktails” specific for individual cargoes (or group of cargoes) has recently emerged as one possible molecular explanation (
    <a>
     Sorkin, 2004
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Traub, 2003
    </a>
    ). Yet some specific (or quasi-specific) components must exist to account for the observed rate-limitedness of the process. Here, we identify TTP as one such component, selectively involved in the regulation of TfR internalization. The specificity of TTP appears rather tight as its perturbation did not apparently exert any effect on EGFR and LDLR internalization, and the protein localized specifically in TfR-CCP.
   </p>
   <p>
    The specificity of TTP function is also supported by evolutionary arguments. TTP is present in all vertebrates (
    <a>
     Figure S10
    </a>
    ,
    <a>
     Table S2
    </a>
    ), but absent in lower organisms (yeast, nematode,
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    ), and seems to have coevolved with the TfR, since also this receptor, while present in vertebrate genomes, is apparently absent in lower species (
    <a>
     Figure S10
    </a>
    ). This is interesting since Tf is present in
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    (
    <a>
     Yoshiga et al., 1999
    </a>
    ), in the absence of its cognate receptor. In
    <em>
     Drosophila
    </em>
    , Tf has been implicated in the general immune response to bacterial infections (
    <a>
     Yoshiga et al., 1999
    </a>
    ). It is not known whether and how Tf is endocytosed by insect cells. However, the remarkable evolutionary coincidence between the appearance of an efficient transport system (the TfR) and of its regulatory software (TTP), argues in favor of the concept that cargo-specific mechanisms of receptor internalization might have been selected during evolution to optimize the process. This concept is further strengthened by the observation that TTP-insensitive receptors, such as the EGFR or the LDLR, are present in fly and nematode, where TTP is absent (
    <a>
     Figure S10
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    How does TTP work? In the simplest scenario (“adaptor,”
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    A), TTP could function as a TfR-specific adaptor, since it can simultaneously bind to the receptor and to clathrin. Such a function should be exerted somehow in synergy with AP-2. Both functional depletion of AP-2 (
    <a>
     Hinrichsen et al., 2003
    </a>
    and
    <a>
     Motley et al., 2003
    </a>
    ) and TTP (this paper) have rather profound effects on TfR endocytosis, arguing against their redundancy. However, the two molecules can synergize either in parallel, through some kind of avidity mechanism, or acting in series, in a fashion reminiscent of the Numb/AP-2 concerted action (
    <a>
     Berdnik et al., 2002
    </a>
    ) (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    A). In this latter case there should be physical association between TTP and AP-2. Indeed, we showed coimmunoprecipitation between TTP and AP-2, although it remains to be established whether the interaction is direct or indirect.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Working Models for TTP Function(A) &amp;ldquo;Adaptor model;&amp;rdquo; TTP functions by linking TfR ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr8.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr8.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr8.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0092867405011086-gr8.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <fig id="fig8" position="float">
       </fig>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (271 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    An adaptor function, however, cannot be the sole one for TTP. In the “adaptor” hypothesis (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    A), the phenotypes of TTP overexpression and functional ablation are predicted to be similar. Conversely, overexpression of TTP blocked the budding of TfR-CCP giving rise to a “long neck” phenotype, whereas the TTP-KD caused reduction in loading and size of TfR-CCV. In addition, we report biological and biochemical evidence compatible with the possibility that the action of TTP is exerted, at least in part, through the regulation of dynamin in TfR-CCP. Thus, any modeling of the function of TTP should take into account its interaction with dynamin as well. We note that, since TTP is present in the cell at least as a dimer, its interactions with the TfR and dynamin need not to be mutually exclusive. TTP might then act as a “scaffold coordinator” (
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    B) that connects the hardware of the pit to the fission machinery. Under this scenario, TTP might act as an adaptor to facilitate TfR recruitment into a forming pit (possibly in synergy with AP-2), and, at the same time, it would bind to dynamin allowing or facilitating its recruitment to the pit.
   </p>
   <p>
    An interesting twist of the previous situation is depicted as the “vesicle loading hypothesis” in
    <a>
     Figure 8
    </a>
    C. According to this possibility, TTP would not only participate to the recruitment of dynamin, but also keep its GTPase activity inhibited. As the TfR accumulates in the pit it might reach a critical threshold concentration able to displace the TTP:dynamin interaction (the TfR has a 10-fold lower affinity than dynamin for the SH3 of TTP). This would in turn allow fission of the CCV, which would be therefore coordinated with its optimal filling. It is of note that this latter hypothesis readily accounts for the observed biological phenotypes, in that it predicts inhibition of fission by overexpression of TTP, and premature vesicle release, associated with reduced cargo loading and size, by functional ablation of TTP.
   </p>
   <p>
    The understanding of the function of TTP is far from being complete. Why is TTP specifically localized in TfR-CCP, at least among the receptors analyzed here? The K
    <sub>
     D
    </sub>
    of the TTP:TfR interaction is in the high μM range, and thus unlikely to account alone for the specific localization. In the “vesicle loading hypothesis”, actually, the interaction with TfR is seen as a tool to displace TTP from the interaction with dynamin, rather than as an exclusive/primary determinant for its localization. An alternative possibility is that TTP is capable “in principle” of localizing to every pit, but it is actively excluded from some. In this study, we present evidence as to how this can be achieved. The TTP:dynamin interaction, for instance, is sensitive to tyrosine phosphorylation. Thus, TTP might be excluded from CCP in which sufficient tyrosine kinase activity is present. We realize that dynamin is unlikely to be the sole molecule capable of localizing TTP to a pit; after all TTP interacts with several other endocytic proteins. We note that also the TTP:dynamin interaction displays a rather modest affinity. Thus, the possibility exists that TTP is localized to pits through multiple interactions, by a mechanism involving avidity. Under this scenario, the resolution of a single interaction (e.g., with dynamin) might be sufficient to release TTP from a pit. It also remains to be established whether tyrosine phosphorylation of TTP might affect its interaction with other endocytic proteins.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
    It also unclear how tyrosine phosphorylation prevents the TTP:dynamin interaction. In the simplest scenario, direct phosphorylation of the TTP-SH3 or of the dynamin-PRD might account for the effect. We have not mapped yet the pTyr site(s) in TTP. In dynamin, however, two Tyr (aa 231 and 597), outside the PRD, are known to be indirect substrates (via src) of the EGFR kinase (
    <a>
     Ahn et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Thus, one would have to invoke conformational changes, induced by tyrosine phosphorylation of dynamin, as responsible for the diminished interaction of the latter with TTP. We note, however, that mutagenesis of Tyr 231/597, reduces tyrosine phosphorylation of dynamin by ∼80% (
    <a>
     Ahn et al., 2002
    </a>
    ). Thus the existence of additional sites cannot be ruled out.
   </p>
   <p>
    Finally, if TTP is a regulator of dynamin selectively acting in TfR-CCP, are there comparable mechanisms in other pits? We can only speculate here. However, we have reported that tyrosine phosphorylation of eps15 is specifically required for EGFR, but not for TfR, internalization (
    <a>
     Confalonieri et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). In the nematode system, we have shown that eps15 performs an “optimizing” function on clathrin endocytosis, and that this correlates with genetic and physical interaction with dynamin (
    <a>
     Salcini et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). Thus eps15 (or phospho-eps15) is a candidate “TTP-like” regulator of EGFR internalization. The experimental verification of the above models and hypotheses warrants further investigations and should help defining the molecular framework of cargo-specific regulation of internalization.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Experimental Procedures
   </title>
   <title>
    Reagents
   </title>
   <p>
    EGF was from Intergen; Rhodamine-EGF, Rhodamine-TF, DiI-LDL, Texas Red-Tf, Alexa 488-Tf, Texas Red-EGF complex, EGF-biotin, and Streptavidin-Alexa-488 from Molecular Probes;
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-EGF from Amersham Biosciences,
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-Tf from PerkimElmer. Ab were: anti-HRP (P7899, Sigma), anti-HA (16B12, Babco, or sc-805, Santa Cruz), anti-EGFR (sc-03, Santa Cruz), anti-FLAG (M2, Sigma), anti-clathrin (X22, Affinity Bioreagents), anti-pTyr (4G10, Upstate), anti vinculin (hvin-1, Santa Cruz), affinity-purified anti-TfR (13-6800, Zimed, and 5E9C11 clone, ATCC Rockville, MD), anti-TTP (177 and 153 raised against residue 114-164 and 944-960 of human TTP, respectively), anti-eps15 (3T,
    <a>
     Confalonieri et al., 2000
    </a>
    ), anti-DynaminI/II (Santa Cruz), anti-LDLR (C7, Santa Cruz), anti-LAMP1 (BD Pharmigen). Secondary Ab were: Cy3- (Amersham), or Alexa 488- or 568 or 405-conjugated (Molecular Probes), or rabbit anti-mouse (ZO412, DAKO-Botany). [α-
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]GTP was from Amersham. ProteinA-gold was from Utrecht University, Tf-HRP was from Pierce.
   </p>
   <title>
    Plasmids and Oligos
   </title>
   <p>
    The full-length human TTP cDNA was cloned from a human placenta cDNA library, using a partial clone [ehb10, (
    <a>
     Salcini et al., 1997
    </a>
    )] as a probe, and was used to generate, by recombinant PCR, the different plasmids used in the study. In the TTPΔSH3 mutant, aa 51–139 were removed; the SH3 construct encompassed aa 50–139. The SH3
    <sup>
     ∗
    </sup>
    construct harbored a W92→A substitution. The PRD region of dynamin (aa 740–870) was PCR-cloned starting from pcR3-DynaminII. TfRcyt was amplified by PCR from a human fibroblast library. All constructs were sequence verified. Details are available upon request.
   </p>
   <title>
    Transfections and Protein Studies
   </title>
   <p>
    HeLa cells were used in all shown experiments. Transfections were performed using LipofectAMINE
    <sup>
     T
    </sup>
    or OligofectAMINE
    <sup>
     T
    </sup>
    (Invitrogen).
   </p>
   <p>
    Two different siRNAs (Dharmacon, Inc.) were used for TTP KD, with comparable results. Target sequences were AGACAAACATCGTGTGCAA (shown in all experiments) and AAACCTCTATCATCTTGGA (siRNA2,
    <a>
     Figure S3
    </a>
    ). The control siRNA (ctr-siRNA) was a scrambled oligo.
   </p>
   <p>
    For biochemical experiments, cells were serum starved, and then stimulated with EGF 100 ng/ml, 37°C. Lysis, immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting were performed as described (
    <a>
     Fazioli et al., 1992
    </a>
    ). HeLa cells were used as source of lysates, unless otherwise indicated.
   </p>
   <title>
    Liposomes, Dynamin Purification, and GTPase Assay
   </title>
   <p>
    Liposomes composed of brain lipid extract (type 1, Folch fraction 1; Sigma-Aldrich) were prepared as described (
    <a>
     Takei et al., 1999
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Dynamin was affinity purified from rat brain cytosol using the amphiphysin 1–SH3. This material, as assessed by SDS-PAGE, yielded 90%–95% dynamin, and 5%–10% synaptojanin. Synaptojanin was immunodepleted using a monoclonal Ab.
   </p>
   <p>
    GTPase assays were performed in a buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 5 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , 1 mM DTT and 0.1% BSA in a final volume of 20 μl. Assays contained 0.5–1 μg Dynamin, 0.02 mg/ml liposomes, and SH3-domains (2–10 μg). Reactions were initiated by the addition of 250 μM GTP containing 0.1 μCi [α-
    <sup>
     32
    </sup>
    P]GTP. 1.5 μl aliquots were removed at each time point and spotted onto cellulose polyethyleneimine thin layer chromatography plates with fluorescent indicator (Sigma), and run in 1 M LiCl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , 2 M formic acid (1:1). Quantization of GTP and GDP at each time point was performed on a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics). Rates of GTP hydrolysis were calculated from a minimum of five time points and expressed as the percent of GDP/GTP+GDP.
   </p>
   <title>
    Internalization Studies and Imaging Procedures
   </title>
   <p>
    Internalization assays of fluorochrome-conjugated ligands were performed as described (
    <a>
     Haglund et al., 2003
    </a>
    ), using fluorochrome-conjugated EGF (1 μg/ml), or Tf (50 μg/ml), or LDL (10 μg/ml), at 37°C for 15 min. Internalization of LAMP-1 was monitored with anti-LAMP-1 Ab (2 μg/ml, 16 hr at 37°C). Quantization was performed on at least two experiments, in duplicate, on at least 100 cells/condition. Cells were scored as “noninternalizing” when, by visual expression, they showed &lt;80% of the staining, compared to controls. In all shown experiments SD was less than 15% of the mean. In RNA interference experiments (
    <a>
     Figures 3
    </a>
    B and 3C) only cells showing clearly decreased TTP levels were scored. In all shown experiments (unless otherwise indicated) cells were subjected to acid wash (0.5 M NaCl, 0.5 M acetic acid [pH 2.5], 5 min on ice) before fixation.
   </p>
   <p>
    Internalization of
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I -labeled ligands was as described (
    <a>
     Haglund et al., 2003
    </a>
    ), in the presence of
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-EGF 1.5 ng/ml, or Tf 2 μg/ml (0.4 μg/ml
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-Tf plus 1.6 μg/ml cold Tf). The rate of internalization is expressed as internalized/surface-bound radioactivity. Nonspecific binding was measured in the presence of a 100-200-fold excess of cold ligands, and was less than ∼5% of the total counts. Additional details are in the legend to
    <a>
     Figure S5
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Saturation binding assays with
    <sup>
     125
    </sup>
    I-labeled ligands were performed as described in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    TfR recycling was measured as described (
    <a>
     Ren et al., 1998
    </a>
    ), with modifications described in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    . For each time point Tf recycling is expressed as the ratio of medium + bound (recycled) / internalized + medium + bound (total).
   </p>
   <p>
    Indirect IF was performed with the appropriate primary/secondary Ab, and analyzed under an AX-70 Provis (Olympus) fluorescence microscope equipped with a b/w cooled CCD camera (Hamamatsu c5985), or with a Leica TCS SP2 AOBS confocal microscope equipped with 405 nm, 488 nm, 543, and 633 laser lines.
   </p>
   <p>
    Total internal reflection fluorescence (TIRF) imaging of cells was performed with an Olympus Biosystem TIRF workstation based on Cell^R Imaging System. Additional details are in the
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <title>
    Electron Microscopy and Immunoelectron Microscopy
   </title>
   <p>
    For epon embedding, samples were fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer (pH 7.2), 10 min at RT, postfixed with 1% OsO4 in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer (pH 7.2), 10 min, en bloc stained with 1% uranyl acetate in H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O, dehydrated and processed for Epon embedding (Polybed 812, Polysciences, Inc.). For immunogold labeling, samples were fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde/0.2% glutaraldehyde in PBS, for 2 hr at RT, and processed for ultrathin cryosectioning as described (
    <a>
     Confalonieri et al., 2000
    </a>
    ). Double immunogold labeling was performed as described (
    <a>
     Slot et al., 1991
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    For Tf-HRP uptake, cells were serum starved for 18 hr, incubated with Tf-HRP (Pierce, Rockford, Illinois, USA), 30 μg/ml, 15 min, 37°C, washed and processed for immunogold labeling with rabbit anti-HRP. In all immuno-EM experiments in which internalization of the EGFR was studied, starved cells were incubated with EGF 100 ng/ml 1 hr at 0°C, followed by 2 min at 37°C.
   </p>
   <p>
    Isolation of vesicles and whole-mount immunolabeling was as published (
    <a>
     Metzler et al., 2001
    </a>
    ). A detailed protocol is in
    <a>
     Supplemental Experimental Procedures
    </a>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Morphometric analyses were performed either on selected cell profiles, observing microscopy fields at 13,000X, or on systematically sampled micrographs, depending on the target. Sections were examined with a Philips CM10 or a FEI TECNAI G2 electron microscope. Each experiment was repeated at least three times. For immunogold labeling, the optimal concentration of the Ab was assessed by the background/signal ratio. The nuclear gold labeling density was used as background reference (
    <a>
     Rabouille, 1999
    </a>
    ) for known nonnuclear antigens (EGFR, TfR, Tf-HRP). For TTP labeling, background was assessed by determining the label density in TTP-siRNA cell sections. PM, CCP, and CCV perimeters were determined by the point intersection method (
    <a>
     Rabouille, 1999
    </a>
    ). CCP and CCV were clearly identifiable by morphological criteria, including ordered electron density and thickness of the coat (20-22 nm).
   </p>
   <p>
    To facilitate the observation in the rather low magnifications used in the shown micrographs, the darkness, but not the size or the contrast, of the gold particles has been increased by digital processing.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
   <div>
    <dl>
     <dd>
      <span>
      </span>
      <a>
       <img/>
      </a>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <p>
       <a>
        Document S1. Supplemental Experimental Procedures, Supplemental References, Ten Figures, and Two Tables.
       </a>
      </p>
     </dd>
     <dd>
      <div>
       <a>
        Help with PDF files
       </a>
      </div>
      <div>
       <a>
        Options
       </a>
       <div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Download file (1112 K)
        </a>
       </li>
      </ul>
     </dd>
    </dl>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <p>
   </p>
   <p>
    The GenBank accession number for the cloned cDNA sequence reported in this paper is DQ232895.
   </p>
   <p>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    References
   </title>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ahn et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Ahn, J. Kim, C.L. Lucaveche, M.C. Reedy, L.M. Luttrell, R.J. Lefkowitz, Y. Daaka
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Src-dependent tyrosine phosphorylation regulates dynamin self-assembly and ligand-induced endocytosis of the epidermal growth factor receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 277 (2002), pp. 26642–26651
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref1'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Berdnik et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        D. Berdnik, T. Torok, M. Gonzalez-Gaitan, J.A. Knoblich
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The endocytic protein alpha-Adaptin is required for numb-mediated asymmetric cell division in Drosophila
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dev. Cell, 3 (2002), pp. 221–231
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref2'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Confalonieri et al., 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S. Confalonieri, A.E. Salcini, C. Puri, C. Tacchetti, P.P. Di Fiore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Tyrosine phosphorylation of Eps15 is required for ligand-regulated, but not constitutive, endocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 150 (2000), pp. 905–912
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref3'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Conner and Schmid, 2003a
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.D. Conner, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Differential requirements for AP-2 in clathrin-mediated endocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 162 (2003), pp. 773–779
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref4'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Conner and Schmid, 2003b
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        S.D. Conner, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Regulated portals of entry into the cell
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nature, 422 (2003), pp. 37–44
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref5'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Damke et al., 1994
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H. Damke, T. Baba, D.E. Warnock, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Induction of mutant dynamin specifically blocks endocytic coated vesicle formation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 127 (1994), pp. 915–934
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref6'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Dunlevy et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.R. Dunlevy, B.L. Berryhill, J.P. Vergnes, N. SundarRaj, J.R. Hassell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cloning, chromosomal localization, and characterization of cDNA from a novel gene, SH3BP4, expressed by human corneal fibroblasts
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genomics, 62 (1999), pp. 519–524
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref7'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Fazioli et al., 1992
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Fazioli, D.P. Bottaro, L. Minichiello, A. Auricchio, W.T. Wong, O. Segatto, P.P. Di Fiore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Identification and biochemical characterization of novel putative substrates for the epidermal growth factor receptor kinase
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 267 (1992), pp. 5155–5161
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref8'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Haglund et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Haglund, S. Sigismund, S. Polo, I. Szymkiewicz, P.P. Di Fiore, I. Dikic
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Multiple monoubiquitination of RTKs is sufficient for their endocytosis and degradation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 5 (2003), pp. 461–466
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref9'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Henley et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.R. Henley, E.W. Krueger, B.J. Oswald, M.A. McNiven
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dynamin-mediated internalization of caveolae
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 141 (1998), pp. 85–99
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref10'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Hinrichsen et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Hinrichsen, J. Harborth, L. Andrees, K. Weber, E.J. Ungewickell
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Effect of clathrin heavy chain- and alpha -adaptin specific small interfering RNAs on endocytic accessory proteins and receptor trafficking in HeLa cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J Biol Chem., 278 (2003), pp. 45160–45170
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref11'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Lamaze et al., 1993
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Lamaze, T. Baba, T.E. Redelmeier, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Recruitment of epidermal growth factor and transferrin receptors into coated pits in vitro: differing biochemical requirements
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Biol. Cell, 4 (1993), pp. 715–727
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref12'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Metzler et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Metzler, V. Legendre-Guillemin, L. Gan, V. Chopra, A. Kwok, P.S. McPherson, M.R. Hayden
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         HIP1 functions in clathrin-mediated endocytosis through binding to clathrin and adaptor protein 2
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 276 (2001), pp. 39271–39276
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref13'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Mongiovi et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.M. Mongiovi, P.R. Romano, S. Panni, M. Mendoza, W.T. Wong, A. Musacchio, G. Cesareni, P.P. Di Fiore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A novel peptide-SH3 interaction
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 18 (1999), pp. 5300–5309
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref14'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Motley et al., 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Motley, N.A. Bright, M.N. Seaman, M.S. Robinson
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Clathrin-mediated endocytosis in AP-2-depleted cells
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 162 (2003), pp. 909–918
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref15'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Okamoto et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        P.M. Okamoto, J.S. Herskovits, R.B. Vallee
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Role of the basic, proline-rich region of dynamin in Src homology 3 domain binding and endocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 11629–11635
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref16'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Orth and McNiven, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.D. Orth, M.A. McNiven
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Dynamin at the actin-membrane interface
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Cell Biol., 15 (2003), pp. 31–39
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref17'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Pelkmans et al., 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L. Pelkmans, D. Puntener, A. Helenius
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Local actin polymerization and dynamin recruitment in SV40-induced internalization of caveolae
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Science, 296 (2002), pp. 535–539
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref18'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Praefcke and McMahon, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        G.J. Praefcke, H.T. McMahon
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The dynamin superfamily: universal membrane tubulation and fission molecules?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 5 (2004), pp. 133–147
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref19'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Rabouille, 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        C. Rabouille
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Quantitative aspects of immunogold labeling in embedded and nonembedded sections
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Methods Mol. Biol., 117 (1999), pp. 125–144
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref20'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <ol>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Ren et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        M. Ren, G. Xu, J. Zeng, C. De Lemos-Chiarandini, M. Adesnik, D.D. Sabatini
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Hydrolysis of GTP on rab11 is required for the direct delivery of transferrin from the pericentriolar recycling compartment to the cell surface but not from sorting endosomes
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 95 (1998), pp. 6187–6192
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref21'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Salcini et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.E. Salcini, S. Confalonieri, M. Doria, E. Santolini, E. Tassi, O. Minenkova, G. Cesareni, P.G. Pelicci, P.P. Di Fiore
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Binding specificity and in vivo targets of the EH domain, a novel protein-protein interaction module
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Genes Dev., 11 (1997), pp. 2239–2249
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref22'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Salcini et al., 2001
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A.E. Salcini, M.A. Hilliard, A. Croce, S. Arbucci, P. Luzzi, C. Tacchetti, L. Daniell, P. De Camilli, P.G. Pelicci, P.P. Di Fiore, P. Bazzicalupo
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The Eps15 C. elegans homologue EHS-1 is implicated in synaptic vesicle recycling
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 3 (2001), pp. 755–760
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref23'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Simpson et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        F. Simpson, N.K. Hussain, B. Qualmann, R.B. Kelly, B.K. Kay, P.S. McPherson, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         SH3-domain-containing proteins function at distinct steps in clathrin-coated vesicle formation
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 1 (1999), pp. 119–124
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref24'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Slepnev and De Camilli, 2000
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        V.I. Slepnev, P. De Camilli
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Accessory factors in clathrin-dependent synaptic vesicle endocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Neurosci., 1 (2000), pp. 161–172
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref25'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Slot et al., 1991
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        J.W. Slot, H.J. Geuze, S. Gigengack, D.E. James, G.E. Lienhard
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Translocation of the glucose transporter GLUT4 in cardiac myocytes of the rat
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 88 (1991), pp. 7815–7819
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref26'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Song and Schmid, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B.D. Song, S.L. Schmid
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         A molecular motor or a regulator? Dynamin's in a class of its own
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Biochemistry, 42 (2003), pp. 1369–1376
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref27'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Sorkin, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        A. Sorkin
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cargo recognition during clathrin-mediated endocytosis: a team effort
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Curr. Opin. Cell Biol., 16 (2004), pp. 392–399
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref28'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Stang et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        E. Stang, F.D. Blystad, M. Kazazic, V. Bertelsen, T. Brodahl, C. Raiborg, H. Stenmark, I.H. Madshus
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Cbl-dependent ubiquitination is required for progression of EGF receptors into clathrin-coated pits
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Mol. Biol. Cell, 15 (2004), pp. 3591–3604
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref29'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Takei et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        K. Takei, V.I. Slepnev, V. Haucke, P. De Camilli
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Functional partnership between amphiphysin and dynamin in clathrin-mediated endocytosis
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Cell Biol., 1 (1999), pp. 33–39
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref30'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Traub, 2003
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        L.M. Traub
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Sorting it out: AP-2 and alternate clathrin adaptors in endocytic cargo selection
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 163 (2003), pp. 203–208
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref31'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wang and Struhl, 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        W. Wang, G. Struhl
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Drosophila Epsin mediates a select endocytic pathway that DSL ligands must enter to activate Notch
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Development, 131 (2004), pp. 5367–5380
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref32'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Warren et al., 1997
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.A. Warren, F.A. Green, C.A. Enns
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Saturation of the endocytic pathway for the transferrin receptor does not affect the endocytosis of the epidermal growth factor receptor
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 272 (1997), pp. 2116–2121
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref33'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Warren et al., 1998
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        R.A. Warren, F.A. Green, P.E. Stenberg, C.A. Enns
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Distinct saturable pathways for the endocytosis of different tyrosine motifs
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Biol. Chem., 273 (1998), pp. 17056–17063
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref34'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wendland, 2002
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        B. Wendland
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Epsins: adaptors in endocytosis?
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol., 3 (2002), pp. 971–977
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref35'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Wiley, 1988
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        H.S. Wiley
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Anomalous binding of epidermal growth factor to A431 cells is due to the effect of high receptor densities and a saturable endocytic system
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         J. Cell Biol., 107 (1988), pp. 801–810
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref36'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yoshida et al., 2004
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        Y. Yoshida, M. Kinuta, T. Abe, S. Liang, K. Araki, O. Cremona, G. Di Paolo, Y. Moriyama, T. Yasuda, P. De Camilli, K. Takei
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         The stimulatory action of amphiphysin on dynamin function is dependent on lipid bilayer curvature
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         EMBO J., 23 (2004), pp. 3483–3491
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref37'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
     <li>
      <ul>
       <li>
        <a>
         Yoshiga et al., 1999
        </a>
       </li>
       <li>
        T. Yoshiga, T. Georgieva, B.C. Dunkov, N. Harizanova, K. Ralchev, J.H. Law
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Drosophila melanogaster transferrin. Cloning, deduced protein sequence, expression during the life cycle, gene localization and up-regulation on bacterial infection
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <p>
         Eur. J. Biochem., 260 (1999), pp. 414–420
        </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <img/>
       </li>
      </ul>
      <script>
       myMap['bibsbref38'] = new Array();
      </script>
     </li>
    </ol>
   </div>
   <p>
    Copyright © 2005 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>
