<article>
 <front>
  <article-meta>
   <article-id>
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2009.02.061
   </article-id>
  </article-meta>
  <title-group>
   <article-title>
    Novel Insights into the Mechanisms of CIN85 SH3 Domains Binding to Cbl Proteins: Solution-Based Investigations and In Vivo Implications
   </article-title>
  </title-group>
 </front>
 <body>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Abbreviations
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      ITC
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      isothermal titration calorimetry
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      CS
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      chemical shift
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      NOESY
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      nuclear Overhauser enhancement spectroscopy
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      HSQC
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      heteronuclear single quantum coherence
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      1D
     </span>
     ,
     <span>
      one-dimensional
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Keywords
   </title>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <span>
      ubiquitination
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      NMR spectroscopy
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      isothermal titration calorimetry
     </span>
     ;
    </li>
    <li>
     <span>
      chemical shifts
     </span>
    </li>
   </ul>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Introduction
   </title>
   <p>
    The 85-kDa human Cbl-interacting protein CIN85, also known as SETA, Ruk, or SH3KBP1, is an important adaptor protein.
    <a>
     <sup>
      1
     </sup>
    </a>
    It is well known to play a key role in down-regulation of receptor tyrosine kinases and to facilitate endocytosis by interacting with endophilin-associated Cbl proteins.
    <sup>
     <a>
      2
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      3
     </a>
    </sup>
    However, CIN85 has also been implicated in other cellular processes such as apoptosis, via association with the p85 subunit of PI3K and AIP1/Alix,
    <sup>
     <a>
      4
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      5
     </a>
    </sup>
    as well as adhesion and cytoskeletal rearrangement, via interaction with p130Cas, cortactin, and ASAP1.
    <sup>
     <a>
      6
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      7
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      8
     </a>
    </sup>
    CIN85 is involved in additional important physiological processes such as regulation of cellular stress response via interaction with MEKK4,
    <a>
     <sup>
      9
     </sup>
    </a>
    cross-linking of F-actin into bundles,
    <a>
     <sup>
      10
     </sup>
    </a>
    and several others.
    <sup>
     <a>
      1
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      11
     </a>
     ,
     <a>
      12
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      13
     </a>
    </sup>
    In addition, CIN85 is implicated in infectious diseases via interaction with infected cell protein 0 from herpes simplex virus,
    <a>
     <sup>
      14
     </sup>
    </a>
    development of glomerulosclerosis in a diseased mouse model,
    <a>
     <sup>
      15
     </sup>
    </a>
    and breast cancer cell invasion via interaction with AMAP1.
    <a>
     <sup>
      16
     </sup>
    </a>
   </p>
   <p>
    CIN85 interacts with binding partners through its three SH3 domains (via atypical proline-rich motifs based on the sequence PXXXPR, where X is any amino acid), a proline-rich region, and a serine-rich region
    <sup>
     <a>
      10
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      17
     </a>
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    a). The importance of the CIN85 SH3 domains in clustering Cbl proteins has also been reported.
    <a>
     <sup>
      17
     </sup>
    </a>
    Although there are several isoforms of CIN85, little is known about their roles in promoting or rescuing activity or in competing with full-length functions
    <sup>
     <a>
      5
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      18
     </a>
    </sup>
    (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    a). Nonetheless, the full-length protein and the isoform lacking the first SH3 domain show distinct functions.
    <a>
     <sup>
      19
     </sup>
    </a>
    CIN85 lacking the first two SH3 domains competes with the intact protein for binding to the p85α subunit of PI3K.
    <a>
     <sup>
      5
     </sup>
    </a>
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Domain organization and isoforms of CIN85. (a) Domain organization of CIN85 and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr1.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr1.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr1.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr1.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 1.
        <p>
         Domain organization and isoforms of CIN85. (a) Domain organization of CIN85 and its natural isoforms. (b) Ribbon representation of the structural model of CIN85AB fragment showing the four prolines located in the linker. (c) Sequence alignment of the SH3 domains CIN85A and CIN85B. Arrows highlight binding site residues. Blue, conserved; red, nonconserved.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (603 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    The SH3 domain is one of the best-characterized interacting modules involved in protein–protein associations.
    <sup>
     <a>
      20
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      21
     </a>
    </sup>
    It binds primarily to proline-rich sequences that generally adopt a PPII helix conformation. Binding of peptides containing proline-rich sequences to SH3 domains can occur in two opposing orientations. The stoichiometry of binding is 1:1, with notable exception of the tandem SH3 domains of p47phox, where a single peptide binds to both SH3 domains.
    <sup>
     <a>
      22
     </a>
     and
     <a>
      23
     </a>
    </sup>
    Recent studies have reported novel binding features of CIN85 SH3 domains. In one of these studies that explored the molecular mechanism of the interaction of CIN85 with the p85α subunit of PI3K, it was proposed that the proline-rich motif from the p85α monomer simultaneously binds to both N-terminal SH3 domain A (referred to as CIN85A) and N-terminal SH3 domain B (referred to as CIN85B).
    <a>
     <sup>
      24
     </sup>
    </a>
    Taking into account the long linker between CIN85A and CIN85B (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    b), such complex formation is plausible. Recently, it was reported that binding of CIN85A to a peptide from Cbl-b results in heterotrimer complex formation between two SH3 domains and one peptide.
    <a>
     <sup>
      25
     </sup>
    </a>
    Since the CIN85 SH3 domains are selective for proline-rich motifs of type PXXXPR, it is possible that CIN85B may also form a heterotrimeric complex of the form described for CIN85A.
   </p>
   <p>
    Taking into account the large number of interacting proteins with CIN85 via its SH3 domains, the existence of several of its isoforms with deletion of one to all SH3 domains, and the recent new binding mode revealed by its SH3 domains, further detailed studies of the CIN85 protein—particularly its SH3 domains—are important. Hence, to explore the structural implications and to understand the functional role of complex formation between CIN85 SH3 domains and proline-rich peptides from c-Cbl and Cbl-b proteins (referred to as Cbl and Cbl-b, respectively), we have initiated a detailed investigation of high-resolution structures and interactions in solution of CIN85A and CIN85B, in isolation and in the context of a CIN85A–linker–CIN85B fragment (referred to as CIN85AB). We report the solution structure of CIN85B. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) and NMR spectroscopic experiments demonstrate that both domains, in isolation or as part of CIN85AB, form heterodimeric complexes with both peptides. An unusual curved chemical shift(s) (CS) change for several residues in CIN85A was observed upon titration with Cbl-b. This reveals the existence of more than one complex with CIN85A in isolated form or in the CIN85AB form. Here we report that the mechanisms of binding of CIN85A and CIN85B to both peptides are different and independent of CIN85AB. This suggests that the SH3 domains of CIN85 have evolved to incorporate different modes of recognition for cognate ligands, providing a level of specificity to achieve its multifunctional capability.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <title>
    Results
   </title>
   <title>
    Solution structure of CIN85B and the absence of intramolecular interaction with CIN85A within the CIN85AB fragment
   </title>
   <p>
    The structure of CIN85A was recently reported in complex with Cbl-b.
    <a>
     <sup>
      25
     </sup>
    </a>
    It was shown that there are no substantial structural changes between the apo form and the complex form of CIN85A.
    <a>
     <sup>
      26
     </sup>
    </a>
    The structure calculation of CIN85B reported here is based on excellent-quality three-dimensional
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N- and
    <sup>
     13
    </sup>
    C-resolved heteronuclear nuclear Overhauser enhancement spectroscopy (NOESY) spectra of a monomeric protein supported by a rotational correlation time of 6.92 ns at a concentration of ∼ 0.7 mM. The family of structures shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    a indicates a highly defined structure, supported by a root mean square deviation (rmsd) of 0.27 Å for backbone atoms (see
    <a>
     Table S1 in Supplementary Materials
    </a>
    ). The only regions of disorder are the N- and C-termini, which extend beyond the SH3 domain. The solution structure of CIN85B maintains a typical SH3 fold consisting of five β-strands organized in an antiparallel β-barrel structure, with a short 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix between the last two β-strands, and two characteristic loops, namely, the RT loop (between β1 and β2) and the n-Src loop (between β2 and β3), as shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    b. Sequence alignment of CIN85A and CIN85B shows about 47% identity. The residues in the binding pocket are highly conserved, but some notable differences are apparent (
    <a>
     Fig. 1
    </a>
    c, blue and red arrows). Structural alignment of CIN85B with the crystal structure of CIN85A in complex with Cbl-b shows significant differences in the RT and n-Src loop regions and an overall rmsd of 3 Å.
    <a>
     <sup>
      25
     </sup>
    </a>
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Solution structure of CIN85B. (a) Superposition of the 27 best structures. (b) ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr2.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr2.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr2.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr2.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 2.
        <p>
         Solution structure of CIN85B. (a) Superposition of the 27 best structures. (b) Secondary structure representation and labeling of the best structure. (c) Overlaid
         <sup>
          1
         </sup>
         H–
         <sup>
          15
         </sup>
         N HSQC spectra of isolated CIN85A (black), CIN85B (red), and CIN85AB (blue) fragments. (d) Mapping of the amino acids of CIN85A with small to substantial CS changes in their resonances in CIN85AB.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (828 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    Backbone assignment of polypeptides provides a direct assessment of the existence of any intramolecular interactions between CIN85A and CIN85B within CIN85AB. Overlay of the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H–
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N heteronuclear single quantum coherence (HSQC) spectra of the isolated domains with that of CIN85AB shows a reasonable match (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    c). CIN85A has about 20 (small to substantial) unmatched resonances. Far better matching is observed between CIN85B and CIN85AB. Unmatched resonances of CIN85A were mapped over the whole domain surface (
    <a>
     Fig. 2
    </a>
    d). This suggests that no specific intermolecular or intramolecular interaction exists. Thus, these data rule out the possibility of an interaction of the SH3 domains with the PXXP motif (PEKPLHEVP), which is present in the linker region (see
    <a>
     Fig. 1b
    </a>
    ). Such CS changes may be directly related to the removal of the C-terminal His-tag
    <a>
     <sup>
      27
     </sup>
    </a>
    and/or the presence of the linker. To control for this, we expressed and purified a new construct without the His-tag (CIN85A_new). The overlay of the
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H–
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N HSQC spectra of the new construct with CIN85AB revealed a very good match, with almost all its resonances within CIN85AB (see
    <a>
     Fig. S1 in Supplementary Materials
    </a>
    ). This demonstrates that the presence of the His-tag in the construct of CIN85A can affect the CS of a small number resonances of CIN85A within the CIN85AB polypeptide. These observations, along with additional evidence provided below, suggest that CIN85A and CIN85B do not interact within the CIN85AB fragment.
   </p>
   <title>
    CIN85A and CIN85B form 1:1 complexes with Cbl and Cbl-b peptides
   </title>
   <p>
    ITC analysis is summarized in
    <a>
     Table 1
    </a>
    , and use example of typical ITC data for the interaction of the domains with Cbl peptide is shown in
    <a>
     Fig. 3
    </a>
    . Clearly, the interaction stoichiometry
    <em>
     n
    </em>
    shows that CIN85A
    <a>
     <sup>
      29
     </sup>
    </a>
    and CIN85B form heterodimeric complexes with both peptides.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 1.
        </span>
        <p>
         ITC binding parameters of CIN85A, CIN85B, and CIN85AB with Cbl and Cbl-b peptides
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           Protein–peptide
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            n
           </em>
          </th>
          <th>
           <em>
            K
           </em>
           <sub>
            d
           </sub>
           (μM)
          </th>
          <th>
           Δ
           <em>
            H
           </em>
           <sub>
            obs
           </sub>
           (kJ/mol)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85A–Cbl
          </td>
          <td>
           0.84 ± 0.05
          </td>
          <td>
           31.31 ± 5.78
          </td>
          <td>
           − 14.29 ± 2.05
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85B–Cbl
          </td>
          <td>
           0.92 ± 0.02
          </td>
          <td>
           4.93 ± 0.55
          </td>
          <td>
           − 36.59 ± 1.13
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85AB–Cbl
          </td>
          <td>
           1.80 ± 0.26
          </td>
          <td>
           27.09 ± 4.24
          </td>
          <td>
           − 48.17 ± 5.70
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85A–Cbl-b
          </td>
          <td>
           0.89 ± 0.17
          </td>
          <td>
           9.87 ± 3.80
          </td>
          <td>
           − 7.43 ± 1.09
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85B–Cbl-b
          </td>
          <td>
           0.80 ± 0.11
          </td>
          <td>
           7.06 ± 1.68
          </td>
          <td>
           − 38.22 ± 7.16
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85AB–Cbl-b⁎
          </td>
          <td>
           2.12 ± 0.05
          </td>
          <td>
           12.65 ± 1.30
          </td>
          <td>
           − 30.67 ± 0.93
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85A–Cbl-b(F)
          </td>
          <td>
           0.83 ± 0.12
          </td>
          <td>
           25.90 ± 5.87
          </td>
          <td>
           − 12.76 ± 3.00
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85B–Cbl-b(F)⁎
          </td>
          <td>
           0.94 ± 0.02
          </td>
          <td>
           6.22 ± 0.64
          </td>
          <td>
           − 31.56 ± 2.17
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85AB–Cbl-b(F)
          </td>
          <td>
           1.97 ± 0.21
          </td>
          <td>
           33.07 ± 8.65
          </td>
          <td>
           − 38.03 ± 7.76
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85A–Cbl-b(E)
          </td>
          <td>
           0.81 ± 0.08
          </td>
          <td>
           8.46 ± 2.01
          </td>
          <td>
           − 11.11 ± 5.85
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85B–Cbl-b(E)⁎
          </td>
          <td>
           0.86 ± 0.03
          </td>
          <td>
           6.14 ± 0.87
          </td>
          <td>
           − 29.65 ± 1.19
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           CIN85AB–Cbl-b(E)
          </td>
          <td>
           2.04 ± 0.04
          </td>
          <td>
           21.66 ± 3.43
          </td>
          <td>
           − 34.18 ± 2.23
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <p>
       </p>
       <p>
        All titrations were carried out two or three times to estimate the errors as standard deviations, except for titrations with (⁎), where the errors were estimated as confidence intervals at the 68.3% level.
        <a>
         <sup>
          28
         </sup>
        </a>
       </p>
       <p>
       </p>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="ITC measurements of the proteins with Cbl peptide. (a) ITC data titration with ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr3.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr3.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr3.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr3.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 3.
        <p>
         ITC measurements of the proteins with Cbl peptide. (a) ITC data titration with the best-fitting line for CIN85A. (b) ITC data titration with the best-fitting line for CIN85B. (c) ITC data titration with the best-fitting line for CIN85AB. The insets show the raw data of each titration.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (429 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    CIN85A and CIN85B titrations with peptides were monitored with
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H–
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N HSQC spectra. Most of the residues in the binding site are in a fast-exchange regime. The combined backbone
    <sup>
     1
    </sup>
    H and
    <sup>
     15
    </sup>
    N CS changes between apo and saturated complexes are plotted against the domain sequences in
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    a. For both domains, there are three major groups of residues with substantial CS changes above the 〈Δδ
    <sub>
     tot
    </sub>
    〉 threshold. These include residues in the RT loop (8–19 and 108–117 for CIN85A and CIN85B, respectively), at the n-Src loop and β3 (32–39 and 128–138, respectively), and near β4 and the 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix (48–53 and 145–154, respectively). Upon binding of the peptides, several residues of CIN85B show highly perturbed CS. CIN85A, on the other hand, shows low CS perturbations, except for Asp16 at the RT loop and Asn51 at the 3
    <sub>
     10
    </sub>
    helix. These residues form hydrogen bonds with the peptides.
    <a>
     <sup>
      25
     </sup>
    </a>
    Residues with CS changes above a 〈Δδ
    <sub>
     tot
    </sub>
    〉 + 1σ threshold are mapped on the domain structures in
    <a>
     Fig. 4
    </a>
    b.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Combined 1H and 15N CS perturbations of the proteins with Cbl and wild-type and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4ab.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4ab.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4ab.jpg,1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4c.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4ab.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Combined 1H and 15N CS perturbations of the proteins with Cbl and wild-type and ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4c.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4c.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4ab.jpg,1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4c.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr4c.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 4.
        <p>
         Combined
         <sup>
          1
         </sup>
         H and
         <sup>
          15
         </sup>
         N CS perturbations of the proteins with Cbl and wild-type and mutant Cbl-b peptides. In all panels, the average CS perturbation of all amino acids 〈Δδ
         <sub>
          tot
         </sub>
         〉 is indicated by the first blue horizontal line; the 〈Δδ
         <sub>
          tot
         </sub>
         〉 + 1σ threshold is shown as the second blue horizontal line. (a) Wild-type Cbl and Cbl-b peptides. (b) Mapping of the amino acids at and above the 〈Δδ
         <sub>
          tot
         </sub>
         〉 + 1σ threshold on CIN85A and CIN85B structures for titration with the wild-type Cbl-b peptide. (c) Mutants of Cbl and Cbl-b peptides.
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (809 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    CIN85A and CIN85B binding to Cbl results in linear CS changes in amide and side-chain signals (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). For CIN85B binding to Cbl-b, similar CS changes were observed. Surprisingly, CIN85A binding to Cbl-b reveals highly curved and slightly curved CS changes for Phe8, His14, Gly35, Trp36, Asp50, and Asn51. As an illustration of such striking curved CS changes, we show the titrations of the Trp36 side chain in CIN85A (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ). Interestingly in CIN85B, while the Trp135 side-chain titration with Cbl peptide shows linear CS changes, we observed a double signal set at intermediate concentrations (0.17–0.57 Eq) (
    <a>
     Fig. 5
    </a>
    ).
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dt>
       <a>
        <img/>
        <noscript>
         &lt;img class="figure large" border="0" alt="Spectral perturbations of N&amp;#949; (NE) of conserved Trp residues from the SH3 domains ..." src="http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr5.jpg" data-thumbEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr5.sml" data-imgEIDs="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr5.jpg" data-fullEID="1-s2.0-S0022283609002411-gr5.jpg"&gt;
        </noscript>
       </a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
       <div>
        Fig. 5.
        <p>
         Spectral perturbations of Nε (NE) of conserved Trp residues from the SH3 domains of CIN85. Trp36 (W36NE) and Trp135 (W135NE) are found in CIN85A and CIN85B respectively. Top two rows: Left - W36 binding to Cbl and Cbl-b (titration performed up to 2.8 and 2.5 equivalents respectively). Right - W135 on binding to Cbl and Cbl-b (1.6 and 2.4 eq. respectively). Middle row: Trp36 (blue arrow) and Trp135 (black arrow) of CIN85AB on binding to Cbl and Cbl-b (4.5 and 4.3 eq. respectively). Bottom two rows: Left - W36 on binding to Cbl-b(F) and Cbl-b(E) (up to 3.1 and 2.8 eq. respectively). Right - W135 on binding to Cbl-b(F) and Cbl-b(E) (both titrations up to 1.7 Eq.).
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Figure options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download full-size image
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download high-quality image (1421 K)
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <a>
          Download as PowerPoint slide
         </a>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p>
    To verify further the stoichiometry of the complexes formed by CIN85A and CIN85B with both peptides in solution, we have determined the rotational correlation times (τ
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    ) of the apo and complex forms of these domains using NMR relaxation (
    <a>
     Table 2
    </a>
    ). The τ
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    values of the apo domains (∼ 6–7 ns) increase in the complexes (∼ 8.8–9.0 ns). Note that the CIN85A construct is 10 residues shorter than the CIN85B construct, which may account for the lower τ
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    values. Taking into account the anisotropic nature of the complexes due to the disordered termini of both the domains and/or the peptides,
    <a>
     <sup>
      30
     </sup>
    </a>
    τ
    <sub>
     c
    </sub>
    values provide strong additional evidence that the CIN85A and CIN85B complexes are monomeric species binding with a 1:1 stoichiometry.
   </p>
   <div>
    <div>
     <dl>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <span>
         Table 2.
        </span>
        <p>
         Rotational correlation time (ns) for the apo and complex forms of separate CIN85A CIN85B, and within CIN85AB [i.e., CIN85AB(A) or CIN85AB(B)]
        </p>
       </div>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <table>
        <colgroup>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
         <col>
         </col>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
         <tr>
          <th>
           State form
          </th>
          <th>
           CIN85A
          </th>
          <th>
           CIN85B
          </th>
          <th>
           CIN85AB(A)
          </th>
          <th>
           CIN85AB(B)
          </th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Apo
          </td>
          <td>
           6.25 ± 0.27
          </td>
          <td>
           6.92 ± 0.20
          </td>
          <td>
           6.81 ± 0.76
          </td>
          <td>
           7. 33 ± 0.87
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Complex with Cbl
          </td>
          <td>
           8.75 ± 0.24
          </td>
          <td>
           9.10 ± 0.22
          </td>
          <td>
           8.50 ± 0.47
          </td>
          <td>
           8.79 ± 0.56
          </td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
          <td>
           Complex with Cbl-b
          </td>
          <td>
           8.55 ± 0.21
          </td>
          <td>
           8.95 ± 0.24
          </td>
          <td>
           8.31 ± 0.39
          </td>
          <td>
           8.58 ± 0.54
          </td>
         </tr>
        </tbody>
       </table>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <a>
        Full-size table
       </a>
      </dd>
      <dd>
       <div>
        <a>
         Table options
        </a>
        <div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <ul>
        <li>
         <a>
          View in workspace
         </a>
        </li>
        <li>
         <div>
          <a>
           Download as CSV
          </a>
         </div>
        </li>
       </ul>
      </dd>
     </dl>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </body>
</article>